.
Okay, so let's start the class.
Since I think this is the last lecture and also the last week of the teaching week.
For this course, our exam is almost the beginning.
The first day is Friday, the study week, next week Friday, but our course will be Saturday,
Saturday afternoon.
So I hope for most of you, it should be your first exam paper.
And then also because most of you are new students from the August patch.
So perhaps I may briefly mention also some exams, things you need to take note, which
particularly during your first exam such as forgetting to bring the matriculation card
and forgetting to bring some of the calculated one.
So these are things you need to take note other than preparing for the exams.
So let's see what I have today.
I will finish the last small part of chapter 3, which is the eigen space, eigen decommission
method applying to spectrum estimation.
I know this is a difficult part, so I will try to narrow down some scope after finishing
this lecture.
But it's quite useful, the techniques you learn.
So anyway, every year the scope of the exam may vary somewhat.
Also some of the fundamental ones, they always require you to burn and memorize whether it
could eventually appear in the exam paper or not because you cannot say, oh, this is
very basic and very fundamental.
Even not in the exam paper, you should learn it well.
So don't realize too much on past year exam paper.
You can refer that as a reference, but the important one is to understand the basics,
techniques, basic knowledge and how to apply and so on.
So later in conjunction with the quiz, the one we just took last week, I will also briefly
discuss some of that.
So anyway, regarding this chapter 3, I will not go through the early part, but more on
this icon analysis method.
So here the starting point is you need to have some linear algebraic magic knowledge
of words, such as how to get icon value, how to get the icon vector, and so on.
So I think the determinant solved the polynomial equation and being able to handle some solving
a system of equation which I always fear is quite fundamental as an engineering student,
including those perhaps considered in the computer science or computer technology area.
Still less, you are more in coding, but still I fear quite useful like this, particularly
those aiming to do research in certain states in the future.
So that part I will not go into detail because you should try your best to learn from how
to do that.
And also, you know, whether the two vectors are also going to know or the subspace also
going to know, we start with two vector also going to know.
And I can think about you do the inner product and then the inner product in that way is
no projection.
If in the 2D plane, you think about 90 degrees.
So these two vectors are also going to know.
So that's one way.
And then we also introduce orthogonal matrix, Hermitian matrix.
So these are in both complexes.
I later will talk a little bit, then you need to have a good understanding of complex number,
conjugate, and so on.
And then similar to eigenvalue, there is another very important one.
Not just for this course, but for you, say, you are applying to other related topic.
I believe most of you are taking the 6407, the machine learning one.
I know some of the content there, singular value, the eigenvalue, the commodation subspace.
I think it should be also important there.
Even that's the signal learning.
Okay.
So yeah.
And then the very important one is why we need all these orthogonal and subspace.
Because when you apply to, you know, our course here, as I emphasize many times, basically,
considering signal and noise.
And then it could be random, could be deterministic, but for noise, we always assume random.
And in this eigen-decommodation, eigenanalysis method using eigen-decommodation.
So it's very important to see our setting here is after working on this auto-correlation
magic from the major signal, then we can decompose.
Of course, with some assumption.
For example, the noise, there will be following the white noise distribution.
The signal will be harmonics, in this case, a sideways-related harmonic.
But it could be random signal also.
For example, the phase, it could be like following a uniform distribution.
And so therefore, the one important result here is you can decompose from a major data,
which is X into, you know, the major data is signal and noise.
So you can decompose into two subspace, just based on the singular value decomposition.
So therefore, from here, you can see you get the larger eigenvalue.
And for square matrix, and then for the positive semi-definite matrix, and the matrix being
square like in our case here, X.
So the singular value and eigenvalue, they are more or less the same, because they are
all positive.
And except for singular value, we can raise to square.
For eigenvalue, you just keep it as you calculate.
So therefore, you can see here, if you're learning this eigenvalue from high to low,
so those small least, they're all equal because there's a lot of noise.
They will be in the noise subspace and those larger ones in the signal subspace.
And the important one is, we already know also, you know, so in terms of subspace, you
can also consider there are also, you know, because I mean every, because a space is explained
by several vectors.
So each vector in this subspace must be also going to pose a vector, generate the other
subspace.
Where two subspace, one is signal.
And then the other is noise.
So this is a very important property.
And yeah, so based on that, we follow the discussion about a shield signal, you see here, cosine
and then, but it's not totally like the deterministic cosine.
So if the phase could be uniformly distributed.
So we get the model and then again do the decomposition and then analyze and see the,
yeah, get this.
So here we also follow the important result about the signal space and noise subspace.
And then based on that, I think we will quickly go through some of the methods which are very
popular and useful here.
Let me see.
So the first one is, I think some researchers in doing this, piece of raincoat harmonic
decomposition.
I think in show is PhD.
So it's very nice name.
Those are doing PhD here.
So therefore here is what we're doing here is we look at one of them, UN, yeah, only
one is normalized.
I can make the corresponding to the smallest eigenvalue.
And as we just mentioned, it will corresponding to the noise of Rx.
Rx is the major data you have.
They will form the auto correlation matrix from here and then divide this.
So this is, yeah, this is the vector to the, it's a column, a transport.
And then following the uncertainty, we have this.
So therefore this vector, it will be, yeah, it will be doing an inner product.
So it only when F equal to Fk, which is the, you know, for those corresponding to the signal,
then it will be equal to zero.
But otherwise it will not be equal to zero.
So therefore in this case, you can see this one, you can expand it into this, which is
a polynomial.
And then for the polynomial, we have always you can convert along the unit circle.
I will later talk about this.
This is very useful.
You can think about one is evaluate along the unit circle, while the other is a Pj,
a polynomial over the whole complex plane.
So therefore if this is all equal to N, then we all know we can always have the NP, zeroes,
which located along the unit circle.
So that, yeah, so therefore once we have this vector available, the frequency, it can be
obtained from all these loads.
So ideally it will be located along the unit circle.
But in practice, you may not exactly get at that location due to some small perturbation
and noise and so on.
So therefore the idea here is even if we, if it is zero because you take the inverse,
it will be infinity large.
But in general, you will expect this value very small.
So you want to divide a very small number.
You will see as a function of f.
Of course it's only on those selected frequency which corresponding to the signal because
we have the source signal having those specific frequency.
So therefore this is one of the quite early methods, 1973, which is many years ago.
And then the idea is very useful but in practice it is not a sadmiot because it's very sensitive
to noise.
So that's one of the methods to start with.
And then you can also see the example here.
We have given the autocorrelation value, which you did just for the quiz, the related one.
So assume this is for process, it contains a single sine wave in white noise.
This is our assumption here.
And then we have to determine the frequency of the sinusoid and the value of the additive
noise.
So what you do here is since these are given, so we form the autocorrelation matrix in this
case, we're given this.
So it's easy.
And then now we solve the eigenvalue problem.
So given a matrix, square matrix, you should be able to follow based on this definition,
polynomial, explaining, so lay equal to zero.
And in this case, you can get three eigenvalues here.
And then you rank it according to the, to the, they're all positive, but you rank according
to the largest value.
Actually this one is the largest, this is second.
This is the smallest one.
So yeah, so therefore the one corresponding to the noise will be here.
This eigenvalue also give the noise value.
And then to get the eigenvector, we already know you're applying this eigenvalue.
And this matrix will become singular and then you solve this and then normalize the vector.
So therefore you will get this.
And so in this case, this is second order polynomial.
And you can get, you can get the two rules here.
And it happened to be a pair of the complex value along the unicycle.
So based on the relationship, this one should be always expressed 2 pi f1.
So f1 here to be 1 over 8.
And this is the digital frequency.
It's defined from 0 to half.
So we get this frequency here.
And then you can extend to a more practical method.
This music, music is not our playing music, it's multiple signal classification algorithm.
Just take the first few, later become music.
This is also very well known.
It's developing from the PSD method.
And it happened to be this is part of the PSD thesis.
And yeah, this method is very well known in the Ray signal processing in the filter area.
Because doing signal processing more or less at least know what this means.
So therefore the one here is we, you know, the approach is similar.
You're visiting this, but now you're right as not just one vector.
You have several vectors, which is if you look at our definition, this is corresponding
to the noise subspace, you see, all the signal after NP, NP plus 1 after NP will be 1 here.
So again, ideally, you see, given to this also, the ability, if you evaluate at that
signal frequency in total, 1 after NP, this 1 over this 0 at the total source frequency,
it should be equal to infinity large.
So therefore, again, the way to do is to know when you get the spectrum, you don't
know the exact, because we only measure the signal.
And then from both, based on the measure data, we try to identify.
So therefore, in this case, your project is a continued function of F from say 0 to 1
over 2, but thankfully.
And after that, you will see some peak value, which is, could be very large, but may not
reach infinity, because we can't measure infinity large.
And yeah, based on this.
So again, this measure, as I mentioned, initially is part of the PhD work, which improved the
PhD measure here.
Again you can look at the autocorrelation matrix, but now this time, we make it more
complicated, it's complex.
And so you see here.
So this is what I say Hermitian matrix.
If it's real, it will be symmetry, but this is not this conjugate, you see here.
So compact 2J, then conjugate, it will be just change the sign, similarly here.
But for real, it will be equal.
The real part must be equal.
And then again, step one is solve the rules of this polynomial.
Then from here, in this case, we get the three eigenvalues, and one is a larger one.
The other two corresponding to noise, they are the same here.
So this one is a bit more complicated.
There's a single complex exponential.
This one corresponding to the signal.
And the other corresponding to noise subspace.
So I will say this is a little bit more challenging question.
And last year, one of the exam paper question, modified from this kind of example.
But it turns out to be, there are always a few students, very good.
They can solve and even get the perfect solution.
I worked with you doing the quiz about there.
I should say many students found this kind of question not so easy.
So anyway, how to solve that is, you see, you follow the similar step.
This one is more complicated because for the noise, you have one eigenvalue, you need
to solve two eigenvectors.
So you need to fix.
It can always be easy to solve one.
But once you fix this one, you have to find a way to solve the other one and also make
these two orthogonal.
So it's quite challenging, I will say.
So anyway, this year I will make the question easier, not to include this part.
So I will later talk about that.
So once you get this vector, you're plugging.
And then again, even this part, you will take quite some effort to simplify into this equation
with respect to, you see, the sine cosine.
And then after that, you'll need to, that was right last year's exam paper, give a so-called
hint to the trigonometric identity.
Then you can plug in and then translate into a polynomial equation, then solve it and find
the f in this case equal to 1 over 4.
But once you file, it's easy to plug in to solve.
But if you do not know this, it may take some effort to even calculate that.
OK?
So in this case, again, I won't go into the detail because it takes a lot of effort to
work out.
And then I can value the smaller 1 equal to 1.
So the value in this case is equal to 1.
That's what we already know.
And then, need to make good use of this Euler's formula.
This is a very famous Euler's formula, which for signaling system, we always emphasize
students should get this, know how this comes from and how to apply, how to change from
complex exponential to relating the sine cosine.
Of course, your real part, imaginary part.
OK?
So, yeah, later I will also talk about some notation because in the book, sometimes some
notation are not quite consistent.
So you should base on the given problem and should be able to easily identify where is
the input signal and the measure data.
So it can be y-ang or the x-ang and plus w-ang.
But sometimes we make the x of n as a measure data and the signal is s of n and so on.
And noise usually we use w, sometimes we use d.
And also auto correlation matrix, we can denote this instead of you know r of x.
And then another method is eigenvector method, which are quite similar.
First you can see introducing, there we go, waiting here.
And then there is another quite famous minimum norm method, which somewhat related to signal
estimation, the parameter estimation in the statistical signal processing.
And so they are all similar in the same year as you can see, all try to minimize the denominator
and five peaks.
So I think I will not go into detail.
And then you can see, you can consider doing some simulation and then see the noisy data.
We get, yeah, this is the first PSD method.
You can see the estimation is not very, it's very sensitive.
Music is better, the other method, they all looks better.
So okay, I think that's end the lectures here.
And any questions you would like to ask before we, yeah, so my plan is I will next try to
go through some statistics about the Simon Wang, because problem is already finished,
it's back, so he won't be here.
And he also say he will not upload the solution to the end student, because like last year
they upload, but then some students this year just copy from those, which are different
from the new question, maybe similar, but different.
During the quiz here, also I see some students very few, even copy from last year's quiz
question, which are totally related, but not the same.
So I always emphasize you can learn from past year paper, past year, but try to understand.
Usually we will, not yours exactly the same.
So anyway, it may be related, but sometimes the change may be quite subtle also.
So yeah, and then I, depending on how much time I take, based on my experience, I may
spend say maybe just less than one hour.
And I won't take a break in the middle or try my best to give you some reviews and tips.
First goes through my part, since this is part of my lecture.
So I will talk a little bit on the quiz and how the students performed and compared to
last year and so on.
So this is first.
And after that, as you all, I don't know other lecturers, some, I heard some lecturers
they don't give the scope just to review everything, but my style usually will narrow
down some scope, particularly courses like this one and 7402.
Too much.
So I see which one you need to review during the coming weeks.
There are less than two weeks because our paper is the first one, I believe.
Most of you may be some pick the Friday, some paper on Friday.
And then after that, I will give some time for consultations either perhaps some of you
will have common questions to share with others.
We will try to answer or if not, then maybe I will stay back for individuals, for those
who have questions to discuss and so on.
So that's my plan for the evening, this being the last lectures.
So we will be more flexible.
Does anyone have any questions from you or anyone have some questions to ask for the
quiz?
Last year, it took me quite some effort to mark because I happen to have the two courses.
The two quizzes are very close to each other and they all have a lot more students this
year.
So anyway, I managed to finish this one.
It looks like home.
So let me just...
You know this year we are doing at least...
I don't know whether for both the CA1, which is the assignment by Pro Wen, I think the thing
we call CA1, CA2, CA2 is the quiz.
I only talked average mark first.
So this is 2024.
And this year, I think CA1 usually assignment is slightly higher, about 75 average mark.
And then for the quiz, it's about 73.
Actually, it should be higher because we have a few students that did not apply leave and
did not come.
So they cannot get the make-up, so become zero for these components.
And so this is...
This year, the average.
Last year, CA1 only 73.4 and the quiz is even lower, 68.7.
So you'll see here we have improvement about four plus marks where the CA1 is still also
better but the difference not that big.
So I hope this year the students learn these calls like this.
I hope they get better understanding, better quality on the students' side.
And we do hope they will do better in the final exams also.
So this is the comparing to last year.
And then comparing to these two, CA1, if you look at the distribution, you'll see because
we are looking like at ring-damp signal.
So if you see, the average is here, 75 this year.
So quite a good Gaussian distribution in the sense of about...
The majority is near the center and then there are fewer to both sides.
But on the other hand, for CA2, it's not that case.
So even so, the average is a bit lower.
Then there are quite a large number of students at higher grades.
You see, I think I don't get the exact number but quite a lot of you even get A plus grade
which is 85 and above much more than the CA1.
And then also if you're counting A and A minor, A minor is 75.
So probably about two-thirds of the students achieve A minor and above.
But then because the problem is...
So that's what we call like long tail.
There are a number of students, not that many but there are quite some students much lower
than this.
I say a few students not even coming for the quiz.
And where the assignment every student somebody and the lowest grade for CA1 also higher than
this CA2.
Other than the few students who did not come, there are also quite a small number of students
which get relatively low because they maybe did not understand the question well or some
of them did not remember what the formula or the basic or did wrongly.
So there are various reasons I try to find out.
So anyway I think overall as I said the majority of the students did a good understanding and
did a good work for the quiz for the last week.
So we already released the result in grades.
So I think you can see what you have done.
I hope you remember what you have done because we have too many papers.
We are not written you the quiz paper.
So that's overall picture and any questions?
If you strongly fear you will not get good grades which we try to be fair actually later
you will see at least on my side I did mark quite easy going.
I usually give partial mark even the results are not correct.
And the same for the final exam paper.
So I think I want to also highlight here is even during the final exam you some question
you may not remember correctly.
So try your best to write down something unless it's totally wrong.
It's relevant as I say if you copy from last year's question which are not relevant but
like this you will try your best and you know write partially correct or related you will
get some partial mark.
Don't leave the answer just totally blank like some students did for the quiz.
So that's about most of you new students for this and you are taking this paper is likely
the first paper.
And then also we still keep the three hours and then I will say the three hours is long
enough most of the student finish in probably two hours but you can just spend your time
doing checking.
Don't worry about not enough time because we are considering cutting down to two and
half hours probably maybe next year or so but not finalize.
So that's some something so that's the overall one and then you know in media question I
would like to let me start with showing the quiz paper first.
So this is the one you are taking.
So first even after the quiz anyone find some typo errors in this question one sub question
A. Actually I apologize for making this typo error here.
So that's my fault but that will not happen in the exam paper we have quite a few other
colleagues to check.
So this one should be M also in the case of two it will be two but for example in this
case we have M equal to four and one of the solutions.
So the power should be M but then the whole class only two students correct correctility
using M equal to like four then it will change the end so the correct formula should be up
to M but anyway let me just go through that because initially I thought I will give you
the hint and most of I mean all of you should be able to follow it just a change of variable
you see we have we can do change of variable in normal variable but in random variable
is the same you see here so here I try to make a guess of time to explain about random
variable also if X is a random variable then X square also a random variable also this
random variable it will be you know whatever random value X can be positive negative this
sum is always at least greater or equal to equal to zero.
So therefore if you new this is a new random variable we call it Y okay alright okay so
so see here the given formula here you know the result what I ask is a value of X square
I think so therefore it's easier you look at this call it Y first okay make a call it
Y okay so and then then you can find this formula actually the beginning of thinking
about whether I should give this a hint but then I thought it would be easier to give so
if you're putting this formula value of Y will be equal to E of Y square yeah right
Y is because you call it X or call it Y it doesn't matter what the formula here the relationship
is always work for any of the so-called random variable so therefore you you need to evaluate
that and then after that you'll need to now we use this relationship you see E of you
know Y Y is equal to X power 2 even for random variable Y power 2 will be X power 2 then
raise power 2 okay right and then now you'll need to subtract E of X power 2 then raise
power 2 and for random variable they also follow the normal operation X power 2 then
raise power 2 you become X power 4 okay and then what you will be doing here this one
is the same your your evaluate X power 2 and because zero mean this is the this one will
be the value of value of X alright so that's how it's power 2 then now if you go back to
the to the to the moment there because we are dealing with zero mean so therefore the
the value should be equal to E force moment because it's zero mean so so you have that
and then subtract E here we already the formula give you all the moment 2 and 4 and and so
on raise power 2 so so they want the if I hope some students also not really sure the
meaning this one being one multiplied by 3 5 all the way up to depending on the value
M you see so in our case here and is equal to 4 equal to 4 and you will be E of X of
4 so the so by the way it should be the correct one if I say raise sigma power n it will be
one multiplied by 3 because 2 multiplied by you see up to yeah one three and the final
one is n minus one 4 minus 1 equal to 3 so you so you stop here and then it should be sigma
power 4 then you subtract this one is X squared just like the valiant and we go to 2 then they
will be no problem is sigma power 2 good power 2 so everyone know this part so so therefore
you will be 3 sigma power 4 minus sigma power 4 because it raise power 2 raise the power 2 is
equal to so the if I did not make a make a mistake it will be correct one will be 2 sigma
power 4 but of course the maturity of of student took my stay as the correct thing so the so
the result is 3 sigma power 2 minus if you remember I think most of you did that so anyway it's a
way to compensate I also every student as long you took this one you got you got full mark for this
first first subject even if you some student even do not so by right this if you my mistake you
took my mistake you will get this answer but if you big a few student big wrongly I will I keep all
the students like because you see it's a sub question 20 mark so you'll get this okay so you
don't it's my fault I shouldn't make this kind of typo typo errors here okay so this is the
the at the first one so what you do here is just the thing about random variable in the same way as
you are dealing with you know better at least in applying this formula here because a random
variable you raise power 2 still random variable okay so I hope yeah so so this is in paper because
my my mistake this should be the majority of student get this and we'll consider consider
correct and even yeah so that's the first sub question so to hope the question the lesson to
learn here is how you know on my side will be more careful actually this is probably the first
mistake type of error I even I did even for even for quiz paper like that so anyway that's
should be settled but you are not penalized because it's my my mistake so this is first
the second the sub question be which is supposed to be also very easy one because means I think most
of the student can get the main correct but when it comes to variant I see many different answer
because this is this one no mistake on my side so if you do not do not get right you will get
some some of the top but even if you try to derive the barrier even down so long it over
since you are doing something following the at least the evaluator barrier of of of each of them
yeah then you will get some partial mark so so in in this case it one good lesson to learn is I
already emphasized many times variant of a random variable unless they're not random variable a
very random variable is always positive and cannot be zero so this is a very basic guideline so but
I still see some students get the negative value or some say the variant of jet equal to equal to
zero or negative so even if you do not get the correct correct answer you should check using the
very common sense and knowledge so I think the main is very easy because it will be it will be it
will be linear so means of jet will be equal to means of 2x minor is it mean is a mean is a linear
operation so you whatever you see negative you will also use this negative side here and then of
course a mean is a linear then you can put it out to multiply by mean of x sub minor 3 you also
take out then mean of y okay so this is zero mean like yeah zero then the results will be very easy
you know the the mean of y got a tool so it will be minor 3 multiplied by 2 minus 6 so again most of
the student this is a easy one so okay but then in terms of the variance there are many different
solutions I always see is very interesting there are different ways some Spain a quite long page
you know the if you look at the the first question so by right I try to give those basic in question
one but because the question subperson a and b are very easy so I thought I have a lot blank page
no use where the other question you need space so I move this subperson C actually belong to chapter
a tool but okay so therefore in terms of the very easy way to do here I think many students did
that is because you'll think no of the independent if the tool random variable x and y are independent
they're independent you don't need to worry about cross term I mean by definition very in is you
need to raise a power of 2 and then evaluate by it E and your n double is a cross term but because
because it is independent so the cost term in in that case and then one of the variable is zero
mean so so therefore our variant here you will be equal to the variance of of of the first part
which is 2x and then and don't forget when you talk about variant you will never keep the minus side
what you you will do is you can because minus one you'll take the power to become one so you can either
do it do it directly 3 y okay you can the easy way is you follow the the property and then also change
the minus side because you can basically something like you are squaring this a minus b then the cost term
could be at a negative side but but when you when you square the other one it will be positive so
therefore variant is a second order operation so therefore if you take the constant you must raise
a power of 2 so you need to raise power 2 then multiply by variant of x and then similarly 3 you
can take out but take the power of 2 and then y so there will be a very easy very easy solution
you don't need to start from the definition and so on so value of x equal to what one so it's 4
multiplied by 1 plus 9 and then variance of y we already know is equal to 3 so that's so
long sir current sir is still 4 plus 24 so it must be positive and 31 you are never be
negative and won't be other value and you don't need to go through the very long that
you may have derivation and even some still don't even deep by integration and so on which is not
okay there's a not not the correct way to do so that's the so these two very basic are is more
testing about basic knowledge about ring them variable mean and mean and value and for the
subsequent see which is we can refer to the lecture note and normally the post kind of
descriptive question mostly I based on you know the lecture notes so you win a filter then of
course you'll look at how we let's see where is paid in this one only ask to draw the product
green of the winner filter so that's the take also give you the good picture about how you
know defy the winner filter and also make it differ from the from the linear prediction one so so
see here the program it will be just the one here but you need to mark in decay you see it will be
input this is a major data you you have a signal plus noise coming in and then you go through this is
the optimal linear filter or the winner filter we are defy but the whole picture you need to
indicate this is the desirable signal we are going to match it's not as we call the S but just quite
deep and then you so that's the one here and then the main difference if you can read this page you
will be also also describe here because it's it cover the three for winner filter is you know it can
do all the this three three you know three processing filtering signal prediction and also
signal signal smoothing yeah so but actually this is also yeah only yeah only when we refer to to
refer to as you see you can sometimes also not very common you may want to have the
signal which can even be even be different from the from from the S so but anyway so the main
advantage will be comparing this one compare with the one step linear prediction filter so if you
think most of the students this write down something or not necessarily keep the question maybe just
putting down the words so would be consider consider correct it will be it will be better even if
for even for linear prediction you see here the winner filter to do linear prediction is cover the
one step prediction is a special case it's not not just one step you can predict several steps where
you know the linear prediction with one step you can only do one step next so so that's also
one of the one of the difference at DBO answer that will be considered considered considered
correct and also remember the block diagram okay so this is the sub question C and how about the
other sub question 2 so if a question 2 I I scan some of the good students through soon here so
I see here this is a yeah one of the very good good and clear answer so if you if you the
those students who can do the question to the two sub question correct then usually they will do the
the question one also mostly correct so they are at least they will be in the grade of a a plus so
more kind near near full mark so see here this is a of course this one you'll need to remember the
one formula which is given in the lecture note also you can see here this this so you'll see
here in the we talk about lattice filter then there's a there's a conversion you see from yeah if
you see from KM to AL you have to do step by step depending on on the order so so the so the
formula use I will be just this formula but if you cannot remember then you will be hard to guess
so so what you do like you see this this is one KM to AL and then if you are given AL will be use
another formula so then you can see here you see this is starting from a 0 may a 1 and then and
then you know step by step you will finally get get this and also because the for this there you can
handle actually in our lecture note here we only teach about FIR filter we are we are doing it for
FIR filter so that's that's a one when you get a for there will be there will be correct quite some
student get this correct but then say the filter is one over this edge of jet which is not there
I already highlight the filter is FIR filter even in the very beginning I say the notation you know
in the announcement FIR should know the meaning of FIR so that's the way that's this one example
this is another student this one also very good you write this formula and then again you see
the very similar so so in the end you'll get this so not much difficulty is just you know the way
and this student even better you write as a fractional number so just I keep it here is fine
because you take the ratio you will be the same as what other and then this one is is correct but
then spend so much time to try the all the different way but in the end get I get the same
result but probably it's good to start from the principle and then yeah is it here in the end
you also get the same but the text very long page so I select this I think the I think a detail
there's no trick you once you apply this formula I think everyone can everyone can do if you are
if you're careful enough either this way or you do it do it in doing this way okay so so I hope
this is not the problem and then come to the final sub question B for question for question 2 you see
here so so again this one I won't say is is a mistake but initially if I'm very strict you see I
state clearly is your heroes the Euler Walker equation to solve so I expect you know like
you come out with you know these four student they all apply this some using a 4x4 matrix some
reduce to you know this because the other body equal to zero so you can delete those
corresponding to zero so entire ways 4x2 also also 5 good and then you see here this one is 4x4
and then this one long one is yeah 2x2 so the ideal one is only need 2x2 equation you know this 2x2
square matrix you solve these two to value because minus on the autocorrelation minus one equal to
one so once you get it because the the ring them for j is a first order so and they update you just
recursive you can get the next value and so on so once you get there you will get the next value
and then from next value you'll get the other one you are you will be just reduced by by half but
then it turns out to be the easy way to do at least if for for many students they use this
motto and then because that's a first order and then easy way based on this Fourier jet transform
you'll get this and then just once you have this you can evaluate them equal to 0 because
autocorrelation always symmetry then this minus one you just try to test whether you know this
property or start from 0 1 2 and it's very easy every time you reduce by half but the but the first
one is you have to yeah you have to get this right you see so this but so initially I thought if
you do not use this because that's a requirement then I may deduct some mark or at least some small
but in the anger so many student majority using this way so I decide okay as long as you'll get
the answer correct you you do not apply these you'll be okay so I consider all correct that's why
I end up with so many a plus probably 16 student will get a plus or a at least a so many many
of them okay so so so that's why why in this because I also did not initially I did not realize
the very simple way because this is a simple first order and they can do it but just to be careful
if you the relationship are more complicated you may not be able to use this way you may really
need to solve this this equation if one or the higher or the or you are given the auto correlation
and then try to get this you will need to really solve this matrix equation usually 2 by 2 or and most
3 by 3 so you don't need to go by 4 by 4 they will be because indicate it happened to be two of them
are 0 then you can solve easily but if they are not 0 then it's very complicated okay you make a
use of the relationship is recursive so you can once you go up to that order then after that you can
do it recursively so that's yeah okay so yeah that's that's about the quiz and the solution yeah so
any any question anything you like to ask or you want to comment maybe to auto discuss for for this
before we yeah maybe the more important one is try to try to prepare for the safe final exam paper so
okay so let's see what I'm putting here some of them I prepared before but because some of the basic
concept and most of mostly I just based on my understanding and handwriting so I hope I
scan it so let's see here for this course what usually you can also see from the quiz and the
past past year exam paper so normally will be important as not necessarily just like maybe
all the quiz I can have a question totally on you know ranked available probability of math but in
the final exam paper normally will be more related to the say the statistical signal processing linear
prediction or spectrum estimation so most study should be like the chapter 2 and 3 but it may use
some of the techniques in the early part like the math and it will be one is linear algebraic like
the matrix solving equation and so and some derivation to like simplify the you know based on the
past solution if maybe complicated you can file way to simplify and try to find out the
solutions or in magic form if possible so that's one concept is very important like what I say very
basic concept like a mean variant you know those are fundamental you you won't tell other people
say the very equal to negative you know so this is something totally wrong so things like that
that was why I asked that question and hope you know like this maybe learning from this mistake
you'll get you are not make the same mistake or similar mistake before some block diagram that's
like this not not many but usually some sub sub question part and then some computation also not
everyone so basically it's all around that concepts and some formulas also need to remember
and then this one is I did it before I think this is one of the confusion and the difficult part
in in this you know random process and so on because quite often students ask why we have we
have two noise here and and then how are they related for example if we look at the random
process the simple one is a AR model and the first order the one you just did for the quiz so
you see here as I see the the relationship of this essay is you know we are trying to generate
this random process from for example from this from from this white noise and and like you can
also view from signal processing for the view of white noise goes through filter and then the
output will no longer why it become a no white you know like color noise process that kind of thing
and then I'll date the ones you generate is a random process you measure the data your data is
this random signal in another noise so you cannot say I compile this this this two noise they are
they are they're totally different you see so although it looks like you know you can if you
move this one to the right hand side you will be beta as n minus plus this so you may think about
why can I plus that we cannot because our exchange only depending on s n it is for it's not s n minus
one okay so you can think about this noise is more like the internal noise related to this
random process the this AR process generally from this from this white noise that's why we call
innovation representation process and then once you have this random process there you are you
try to measure this then you'll have the measurement noise you see okay so it's a measurement I think
those nowadays actually there are some students from cca but nowadays cca some students are not
from the control background for those having control background because actually I did my
undergraduate in the auto automation like like this very much related to cca so you you have the
space space space space you have the system noise you know like internal noise and ever
that you'll you'll have the measurement equation which is the measurement noise so you always get
used to two noise they are they're different they are even quite often to make the calculation
easier we say they are uncorrelated or independent because it's also true because it comes from
different process one is like the internal you know your state space is more though the
dynamic system like yeah I for the other cause I talk about common filter which is state space
representation where this one is a measurement noise okay so this is something I believe is a
very basic one it's not necessarily I mean most of the time the passable may teach a little
test a little bit there but at least conceptually these are the important one after learning this
part two of this course and then give some detailed steps simplify results so along your answer try
to not just jump to the solution also in the exams I assume it's very hard to memorize from some
you know yeah so you what you try to get for be should be your own work but try it always try to
derive something along the way and then in the end simplify some of the results some of the notation
which is do also need to need to take note about that sometimes we call it power spectral density
or PSD sometimes we call it power density spectrum they are basically the same yeah yeah then it
yeah it also depends on you see here we we're writing in the power spectrum in terms of frequency
sometimes we also extend it into into the jet I think it's some of the example I will give later
also nowadays I incorporate some of these into example in collection so just need to
sometimes we're writing this way to explicitly write along the unicycle to this sometimes just
because this is anyway those are constants so what the true variable is f is a frequency here
then similarly auto correlation sometimes it can be x and x then sometimes just because
autocorrelation you are the same x so you can write in this way cross correlation if dx is the
common one you have two but sometimes the major signal is x we just write as d and then this one I
fear is useful actually this revision every year I because I have taught this course for several
years so I fear these are fundamental whether it's for exams or not and and these are also useful if
you are for prone the part one because it's related to linear system a via although here we
unless the air process which you can consider as a filter but most of time we are focused more
via filter for like part one so so these are the very much relationship input output relationship
linear system here and then for deterministic you I guess you'll learn it better x and n
take j transform your v capital x of j and then this so improbable relationship is related by the
transfer function it's just all the one linear and then frequency response you'll evaluate j along
the unicircle you'll get this but however for random signal sometimes it's called stochastic you see
you will not directly apply the j transform of x instead of from input signal x of n you'll get
the autocorrelation okay then after that you'll take the j transform so that's why you know the power
spectrum density sometimes we say in jet that means it will be the j transform of this one only
when you evaluate along the unicircle it will become the power density spectrum is along the
frequency but otherwise it could be extended to the whole to the whole jet plane and similarly
why you also have this relationship and then different from the deterministic signal where
improbable relative just directly the transfer function is here you have the the spectrum in the
power spectrum in jet is improbable relative to the h of j multiplied by h z to the power minus one
so so that's the that's a that would be the difference between dealing with random signal and
deterministic one and then furthermore you'll evaluate you see jet along the unicircle you'll
get this power spectrum density vst and then similarly this one you'll evaluate so you see here
one of things is the jet your jet is always represented by this and jet to the power minus one
you will take the minus side here okay then this this is the complex so these two
they are assuming of course here dealing with the real coefficient then you can write combine this into
magnitude raise of power two and that's how sometimes we start from here you should be able to
go back to the edge of jet as called the spectrum factorization so you need to be familiar with this
okay these are the little bit of autocorrelation and cost correlation so here autocorrelation it
doesn't matter you can start with xn and then n minus n because it's symmetry so yeah so that's why
it's equal to m equal to minus n well cross correlation then is the order will be will be
important like m mean the dx n mean this argument is
this one plus m so you mean you you can consider is n subtract this n minus n you'll get n so
it's not equal to this this one you'll n start with minus n but cost correlation you don't have this
symmetry as m will not equal to minus m in general so I think some students raise this question about
why is so so make sure this is zero mean why saying stays in the little indom process and then this is
the autocorrelation and therefore the variant of this because it's a ring done why you know we
consider that is insane like a noise so you can also get the variant is it just equal to either e
of this yn power of 2 take the expectation you see so that's the definition of variant but
make sure this is zero mean not zero mean you will it will be different and then you can evaluate
also is the autocorrelation at m equal to zero then this is always for autocorrelation that give you
the largest value at zero okay some useful there's some firm pair I think this one I already this year
I put into the lecture note also so yeah so you can directly use that's why many students use this in
the in the quiz but don't forget there is this this is not one because many some students
make a mistake by replacing it one it's to be one minus a square where this one is a one one over
this if you're on one side so you see here this is this is a more corresponding to autocorrelation
where this is a more like like a one side one side series it's not the this one is not the
autocorrelation okay okay I think this one this one I know in this year's lecture note I
is more on those the dead tip signal processing so that's one of them another one is somehow
yeah very similar to but maybe some of them are similar so I just show it here is yeah probably
on different years so I think this one not okay because part of it are useful because I again I
try to relate relate DSP and ADSP here also so yeah so this one you know abaya filter you are all very
familiar abaya then our case here for ring them signal sometimes we we're dealing with you seek
to deal with MA moving average ring them process which you will be quite similar to this abaya filter
and then IR filter for filter you will have this and then you can see this is one over this and then
is also in ring them process we call it as AR process but then even this case the if you try to
evaluate the even impulse response which different from every filter you won't get a finite number you
will get to edge infinity there will be infinity many of them and then again you have a filter you
have both numerator denominator so in this case corresponding to the armor model which is here
and concept of causal and stable also very important so it should be no DSP so so again this is
similar to what I say early but I emphasize on deterministic signal and variable you know so
so these are more in the frequency response where ADSP you were yeah similar to what
yeah I say early for if the input is a wide noise then you can simplify into that in general if the
input no wide noise you have to have this part here okay yeah this is yeah you can make it more
granular or if you are evaluating along the unicycle you can use the eurofomula to change it to a
function of cosine omica here and filter you have a simple first order filter you want to evaluate
this is the same as your this is called edge jack you see although you have the available is a jack to
the negative power you can so you remember this is our filter and this one when you change the jack
to the power minus one you have to replace this into jack no jack to the power one which is one jack
okay today for if you're still using this you can yeah you can gain your entire with simple
one in cosine omica and then you can see one corresponding to this you know the linear system
in the filter give you here and the other is input if assume the input here is you know the
AR model then these two end up with a very similar expression you see yeah yeah yeah they can
you can sometimes you can simplify you know the results depending on that so that's about some
a decent notes I can yeah share with you the other than the lecture notes so so finally I will
go through this lecture note again I will not go to chapter one because that's as I say that's I mean
some of the relationship here like how to define a m or d or and so because they won anyway in the
later part we also use it so so only yeah those are if you use you can refer back but let me probably
uh
run through this and I will narrow down some of the some of the scope for the finite gen paper
so it's uh
okay I think the forward linear prediction you know these are very fundamental so I think this
should know how to yeah how to do it how to write the equations and the brog diagrams and yeah and
and also uh the difference between a prediction error filter and the linear prediction filter because
yeah so this tool will have some relation but there are difference this is the definition of the
mean square error if you are dealing with complexity or at least and then you lead to this we will
yeah I show how to get the optimal solution by taking the derivation so but the derivation
uh for this solution uh will not will not be required here for the final exams so
and this uh F. I. R. for all zero is it so latest filter this is for the
uh F. I. R. filter we actually for latest filter we only discussed this F. I. R. so you should
know the there are all the recursive equations and the the one you just did for the quiz is the
relationship between the K. M. and A. L. the one way to the other also uh yeah so they are
basically just two formulas one convert into another one yeah once you remember this
then you can yeah do it follow the examples and follow the follow the you know the quiz
question uh so this part is still uh required to uh to know or to memorize the formula and
similarly back rule linear prediction how's the relationship with uh forward and backward so
you can yeah yeah try to learn one and then just just compare the difference and then yeah so the
relationship of the coefficient will be here uh and then again the mean mean square uh one
it's actually the result is the same but you don't need to solve it to derive and this equation the one
like what we say early for the quiz these are the uh very very basic because this one also
related to the Euler-Walker equation so I think some students I think you can see those students
did write down these and then actually you can you you don't need this part because you if you
know this is symmetry for autocorrelation yeah then you already know this so the one here is
remember in angle zero you have this noise value other than that is a recursive for AR so here we
only need to know the AR and then the Euler-Walker equation there could be the one including this
noise and all you can simplify by not include that one in to the other equation so from basically
you're from one you can derive the other two okay so that's the one here solution of that you
yeah so
uh
yeah these are the example so uh and these two computational equation iteration this one
you can uh ignore like this for I will exclude this from from exam the levy's to being algorithm so
so yeah so no need to you can skip this part uh wiener filter the basic one is for all this
relationship and then the design of wiener filter is only the FIA filter part you will see how to
uh solve this either in several equations or you can uh yeah write into the magic form
and then you'll compute the inverse inverse matrix so that's that's the one uh linking the
wiener filter and then follow the example like usually we're dealing with uncorrelated
ring them processes so it will be much easier you don't need to consider the cost here
yeah then follow the simple example and you know this is what we already discussed uh early
okay yeah so
also continuity principle think this one you can you can skip this one here yeah and like this this
I have your wiener filter you can you can skip so no no need this part yeah including the example
this is a quite good example but very uh complicated you need to have a very good understanding okay
power spectrum uh basic concept about you know signal in noise uh whether early part or the later
on these are the motivation of course you don't need to remember these uh figure these are from the
many approach and so so yeah and uh no parametric method uh usually I will skip this whole
no parametric section so you don't you can yeah you can if you don't have time you can skip this
whole one parametric method we uh try to relate this into the uh the AR models and yeah so some
yeah basic definition for AR model you or yeah get the relationship and
and that's the rock diagram to try to yeah issue system-based PSPSE that's the basic step I think the
maybe go to know this and then the algorithm for AR parameter estimation so should know
how to convert from say one AR model and then from here to evaluate the power spectrum to do the
power spec PSD power spectrum density so just so again this is we already learned in the early part
so it's the same here just apply this so we will yeah this is also similar to the latest
uh filter it's the same relationship but uh we all yeah yeah I think this
optimal coefficient this is too formula or I will skip because too many formulas so you don't need to
memorize these two we're not we're not test these two uh this page okay yeah and
yeah these are the other quantities uh this one also can you can skip unconstrained least square
measure yeah but then how to evaluate the one uh this is very much uh similar to the later part
the icon measure you evaluate you'll get the power spectrum you will see the peak
frequency uh very close to this one to the peak this one selection of AR model order can skip
this formula yeah no need yeah these two yeah okay uh how spectrum yeah these are the basic
MA is quite easy because you can you don't need really to solve your once you know the MA model
you can directly use so this is the one uh related to the auto correlation
uh AR
AR model you know the expression of AR AR model and and then how to yeah so this one should be also
good to uh yeah at least know the relationship from AR model to AR model and the MA MA model
at least the expression simulation result because you don't need to you can skip all these
uh speech application you're not yeah here no need this part this one so the this year the
icon and energy method is you should know at least the some of the MA background and uh
uh how to solve icon value icon vector orthogonal uh some very basic definition
positive definite uh matrix and singular values here is for no square one is yeah the signal
how to uh start from the yeah we always follow this signal in noise which is a random uh
sequence and then the how to decompose into uh subspace and the singular value uh icon value
also uh signal and noise subspace I explained earlier the orthogonalities and uh how it
corresponding to the actual signal and noise so basic representation some property
yeah okay so these are more profitable so this year I I will skip the from this page on
PhD and music the actual computation because in the past two years you will see
one one sub question related to either music or PhD so it turns out to be not so easy so this year
it is already making a little bit easier so but then the early part the subspace one maybe
good to know the at least the meanings of of it and then the actual PhD and the music and all the other
you know the yeah all these icon vector methods so on yeah you can you can skip from this
PhD section on work so it's more like the understanding some of the
concepts and at least the why we can use this uh icon uh decomposition
analysis uh method uh up to yeah this okay I think uh I hope this help you to narrow down the
some of the some of the topic so probably uh maybe at least uh near half or at least one third it's not
no include into the final exam yeah of course the exam paper you my power set two questions
problem also two questions then we may have usually one two to three sub question so it
cover some of these the one I say it will be possible to be exam but not of course not all the content
so so you can try your best to yeah to to do the revision uh waiting the next two weeks about
two weeks time okay yeah so uh yeah I will stop here and then since we still have time I did not
take the break you know today so you can stay back if you have questions or if you have
questions to discuss with other students you can also raise your hands and to see
uh or your fear a little bit uh uh you prefer to later to discuss with me then it's also fine
and of course always you're welcome you can email me so yeah I actually quite a some student
already did that I uh I will yeah try my best uh yeah to see how I can help and a few students who
did not do well for the quiz because uh for this call only teeth half so it's uh I only do one quiz
as I can't help the those weaker students more for the other calls I 7402 uh actually I can
share you a little bit is uh I did one assignment and one quiz because all by me so a few students
who did not do well in the assignment I personally at least I emailed them and then they did better in
the in the quiz so I I compared but on nothing a few students I think probably they maybe did not
do all the same by themselves they look quite okay all right I didn't know that's why I told them
you're in assignment try not to try to do by yourself if you did not do well you'll get some
warning then you you prepare better increase and the final exam so usually it works better
because for the whole course but then this course unfortunately I only teeth half so I I can't I don't
have time to yeah so but anyway I still alert a few students really need help maybe they
came from different background like computers or not learning the related course
before so it's a big difficult to catch up but anyway as I say I already cut down some contents
and then I also prepare some related material in DSP filter spectrum and all those should be useful
and then causal filter stable filter which we also need here the concept okay so I think that's
overall I hope you yeah at least you'll learn something useful here and I hope that maybe useful
in your future study or or future project or some of you did you know PhD or going to do
PhD or you are currently doing your dissertation project and so on so yeah so anyway yeah it's
a good to to see you here staying to the last lecture of this semester I may see some of you
next semester if you are mostly or you're a new student you still need to take course away
we're offering a new course next semester I'm teaching even yeah a few weeks there so so perhaps
because next semester there will be this course will repeat but of course you'll I hope I don't
see you here again because unless one very few of you fair then you may repeat but
fortunately not so but then 7402 there's a not offering semester two because some of you
sticking the one but the only one one once per year but the next next next semester and teaching
another course more related to machine learning yeah there are also some
mass related equation and so on so anyway I hope maybe see you again by at least building the
exam because I'm the examiner invigilator so if not seeing you if you don't have a question
then I will see you at least in the exam hall so yeah anyway for SPM or ML student because
I think I still quite often in touch with you so I hope yeah okay all the best and good luck to all
of you and yeah so see you see you again yeah thanks for coming and for attending this course
so I very much appreciate okay good see you
you