All right, OK, let me know if it's too dim, right?
Because I tried to turn it on.
But it's like too bright to me, and people cannot see the
monitor, I think, I feel.
OK.
All right, so maybe we can start.
And I think I can, like usual, I can finish everything by
nine, so you guys can leave earlier, right?
And this is actually our last lecture.
And next week will be recess week.
I hope all of you know that we have no class next week.
But we do need you to work on the homework.
All right, so don't forget the homework.
And actually, by the end of today, you should know all of
the knowledge, concept, which you need for the homework.
All right, so I think there's one question that needs the
topic for today.
But after that, you should have all of the information.
So do try those questions.
And I do receive some kind of concerns or questions that
regarding those homework.
So as you see that I did make some change to the homework
for this time, comparing to last year.
So please stick to the version this year, right?
Because I removed some questions from last year.
And you don't have to do it, all right?
So stick to the version I uploaded recently, OK?
And all of you know that the deadline will be the end of
recess week, right?
So don't miss the deadline.
All right, so without further ado, let's proceed to today's
topic.
So pretty much starting from last week, we're focusing on
the applications that we can use, the multi-rate processing
that we learned before.
And we say that, I think we covered the first two topics
last week, including how can we design the fractional
amount of phase shifter, right?
Basically, if you want to do some rate change, but they're
not integer amount of change, you can actually use one kind
of up sampler followed by another down sampler to
realize those fractional change.
And also, we talk about filter banks, in which you want to do
different kind of processing for different kind of
spectrum, right?
Which is quite common for signal processing.
And we say that you can come up with some analysis filter
bank, and then followed by some processing.
And then you do a synthesis process to reconstruct the
original signal, all right?
So we're going to do a quick review and recap on those two
things.
And after that, we're going to proceed to the last topic,
which is the QMF, right?
So QMF stands for the quadrature mirror filters, which
is some kind of a realistic way in which you can use
non-ideal low-pass filter to also achieve some kind of
perfect reconstruction.
So if you remember, we talk about in the filter bank that
if we use ideal low-pass filter, you can perfectly
separate the spectrums into different kind of bands that
you want to process them accordingly.
But all of this band-pass filter, low-pass filter are
ideal.
In other words, you don't see any transition from the pass
band to the stop band, right?
But we say that we don't have such kind of ideal low-pass
filter in practice.
What happens if we still want to do perfect reconstruction?
So the QMF is one thing you can do smartly to use those
non-ideal filter as still without getting to the aliasing
problems, right?
So we're going to see how we can do them.
So here's a recap on what we talked about last week.
So we talked about this fractional phase shifter,
which means if you want to do some kind of a rate change,
but this rate change can be only represented as a
fractional number, right?
Something like k over i, in which case both k and i are
integers, and they are relatively
prime positive integers.
In other words, no common factors, right?
So if you want to do so, it's hard to use one upsampler or
downsampler to do it.
But in practice, you can do two, right?
You can first apply an upsampler, followed by a
low-pass filter, and then another downsampler to do it.
But you have to make sure the ratio here are actually
corresponding weight, right?
You are going to do the corresponding ratios.
So that's actually something we covered in the first part.
And then we see that, well, we can use the multi-weight
processing to implement a filter bank.
So basically, if we are talking about ideal low-pass
filter or band-pass filter, the most common way we use
filter banks is to separate the spectrum into different
kind of sections.
And of course, this section will be like
orthogonal to each other.
So one possible way is that we want to kind of segment the
frequency entire range into uniformly, let's say, n
different kind of sections, right?
So every section cover a range of frequency spectrums, and
you believe that they have different characteristics, and
you want to process them differently.
So in this case, your low-pass filter or band-pass filter
will be in the following way, right?
So here, the K stands for the K channel, right?
So basically, we are shifting the low-pass filter to the
corresponding specific bandwidth, right?
So in this case, we call the H0 as the prototype, which
itself is a low-pass filter, right?
So the others will be just shifted
to the conversion of the prototype.
And in this case, we can also work out the time domain
representation for all of these HKs.
So this is actually your frequency domain.
Okay, let me use a pointer, right?
So this is actually your frequency domain representation
of the shifting.
So it's going to be a shift in the omega domain, right?
So we say that the shift in the frequency domain will be
correspondingly a phase change in the time domain, right?
This is due to the DTFT property, all right?
So the change from the H0 to HK in the time domain will be
a multiplication of the E2 power of a phase shift, right?
Of course, this phase shift will be completely depends
on the K, right?
So the different K is going to be proportionally change
the phase, right, the amount of phase shift.
So again, this H0 is called a prototype, but it's going to
be an impulse response of the prototype, all right?
So once you have this H0 specified, you can derive all of
the other band-pass filter, right?
So this is actually the idea.
You only need to give the prototype, and you should be able
to derive all of this HK, either in the frequency domain
or in the time domain, right?
This is something you need to know, and these two formulas
perfectly give you the idea how to do it, all right?
So, and we say that, well, when we implement these filter
bands, right, so in general, there are two stages.
So every time when you trying to decompose the spectrum
into, let's say, N different sections, the decomposition
of the representation is called the analysis filter, right?
So what is this analysis filter?
The analysis filter will be able to represent the signal
in the corresponding frequency range, all right?
That's the purpose of analysis filter.
So if you look at all of this X0, X1, all the way to XM-1,
these are down-sampled version of the signal
in the corresponding frequency range, all right?
That's what the band pass filter is doing.
And then if you look at every branch, what they are doing
here is actually, first, you apply some kind of a phase
shift, remember, this phase shift coming from here, right?
Because the case channel will have the corresponding
phase shift, right?
So in this case, every channel, the phase shift
will be different, okay?
Here, it's going to be zero channel, first channel,
all the way to M-1 channel, right?
And followed by the prototype filter.
So after the phase shift, this will be always the prototype.
So here, the H0 are the same.
If you combine the two, it's going to give you the H0,
H1, H2, and all the way HM-1.
So together, these two is the corresponding band pass
or low pass filter, right?
And after that, we say that since we only capture
a small range of the spectrum, so one can actually
down-sample the signal such that you can process
the signal in a much lower rate, okay?
If you don't do this, you can still process the signal,
but we're talking about a very narrow band signal
and in relatively high frequency, sorry, high rate.
So you actually waste a lot of computational resource, right?
So it's not saying you cannot do it, but it's less efficient
if you don't do the down-sampling, right?
Remember, when we do down-sampling, normally you have
to kind of stretch the spectrum, right?
So if your spectrum itself is very narrow,
it's perfectly fine to do it,
and you won't have any aliasing, remember?
So this thing before that is some kind of anti-aliasing
filter, right, if you view this from the decimation process.
All right, it's because that we already separated
the spectrum into different sections.
So naturally, the signal here, here, and here,
these are already band-limited.
So it's okay for you to directly do down-sampling, right?
And you should be aliasing-free if this D is actually
some number that proportional to this number of channels.
I mean, your D cannot be too large, of course, all right?
So this is actually the analysis process.
Now, after you do whatever you want,
so basically from this XK to the Y here,
this process is the processing you are doing
for that specific frequency range, right?
You can do different processing,
but basically the processing will make the X
change that into Y, right?
So for every channel, you can do specific processing
to whatever you wanna realize, and after that,
you should be able to recover the original signal, right?
So this synthesis process is like merging different
kind of sections of the spectrum into one, all right?
So this is what the synthesis filter band is doing.
So how they do it?
Well, you have to first convert the rate
back to the original rate, right?
So here, the down sampling D is always coupled
with this up sampling D, all right?
It's always the same, otherwise you go to different rate.
Okay, and followed by that, remember,
just like the way we do interpolation, right?
When you do interpolation, you have to have
another low-pass filter after it.
So similarly, here is the same thing.
You need to have another G followed by the phase shift
to get it back to the original kind of position, right?
So this is some kind of, if you view that
from the interpolation perspective,
this is actually a low-pass filter,
which is something like the reconstruction filter, right?
But then if you view the role of this filtering,
it's going to shift that kind of signal
back to the corresponding location.
Remember, all of these channels are only covering
a specific range, right, just like a band-pass filter.
So once you process that, you have to move it back
to the corresponding location in the spectrum
and then merge them together.
So all of this phase shift here will be
one-to-one corresponding to the phase shift here.
So they must be matched, all right, to move them,
to shift them back to the corresponding location.
Otherwise, if you sum them up,
it's going to overwrite each other, all right?
So this phase shift is actually necessary.
And then followed by that is just a summation, right?
Just combine everything together.
So by using this kind of filter band, right,
if you design correctly, and suppose you don't do anything
from X to Y, the entire process is doing nothing, right?
Basically, you should be able to get back
to your original signal without any change, okay?
So that's actually a qualified filter band, okay?
If you somehow introduced artifacts,
that's a non-ideal design, right?
You may have some problems.
Maybe your D is too large, which sometimes happens, right?
But what I'm saying is that a perfect filter band
with all of these conditions satisfy,
and if you directly put the Y equal to X, okay,
means you did not process anything in the middle,
the whole process should be identical.
What you have in the input will be the same as your output,
right, this is actually the purpose of the filter band,
right, making sure the spectrums themselves
are orthogonal to each other, right?
This is actually the, but of course, in practice,
we do add some processing between X and Y, right?
Just like the way we process different spectrums
in different ways, right?
All right, so important thing is that here,
you need to increase the sampling rate
to recover the original rate.
So this D must match with the analysis filter, right?
They are the same upsampling, and this filter,
sorry, this kind of shifter, sorry, phase shift
will be correspondingly shift the baseband output
to the bandpass output specifically, right?
Every channel the shift is corresponding
to the shift you did before in analysis filter band, right?
So this is how the entire process looks like, okay?
So I wish you, everybody can kind of understand the process,
and also, you should do two things.
First one is in the block diagram,
you should know how to do them, right?
How to, let's say if I give you a specific
downsampling rate, I give you a specific number of channels,
you should be able to draw the block diagram,
and also, you should be able to write the analytical form,
right, how can you generate the final output
using a bunch of Y and the G, right?
So both the block diagram and the analytical form
are needed, you have to know how to do it, all right?
Okay, so I hope I already make it very clear, right?
Which means you may see some questions, okay?
So you better make sure you are familiar
with most of the formulations, okay?
I will probably not test you on the
so-called simplified version.
Remember last time we said that you can actually use
a DFT followed by FFT to speed it up.
I won't test you on that, because that's,
but you know that they can be speed up, all right?
You are able to speed up the whole filter bank
using FFT, but I will not ask you to write it down, right?
How can you do FFT, that's kind of too much, all right?
But these form, analytical form,
and also the block diagram, I need you to know, okay?
All right?
Okay, so any question before I move on to the QMF today?
Okay, great.
So we have one last topic that we left out last week,
which is also quite important,
which are talking about the realistic,
how do I say, practical cases, right?
So all of this, if you remember,
all of this filter bank idea, right?
All of this G and all of this H,
we say they are ideal low-pass filter, right?
So that's why you can have something like this, right?
So this kind of sharp transition always happen in the,
in practice, sorry, always not possible in practice,
or impossible in practice.
So, but we want to enjoy this kind of merits of filter bank
and we want to implement them in practice.
So the question is that if we don't have
these kind of ideal low-pass filter or band-pass filter,
how can we still construct some kind of filter bank
to perform like a spectrum-specific processing, right?
So we, I mean, people have come up with different methods
to kind of overcome the practical challenges
of using non-ideal filters.
So this QMF is one of the method, okay?
Not all, but one of the methods.
So these ideas called quadrature mirroring filter, okay?
So I will explain what does that mean, all right?
So basically you need to know, how should I say, two things.
First one is what does QMM trying to achieve?
Okay, why are we doing this?
The purpose of doing the QMF.
That's one thing I wish you to know.
The other thing is what kind of filter
will satisfy the condition of QMF?
Okay, so in other words, if I call this bunch of filter
R QMF, what do I mean, right?
So there must be some requirement or condition
that qualify a set of filter to be QMF.
So you need to know what they are, all right?
So these two things are something I mean,
I wish you to know, okay?
So first of all, let's consider that in practice, right?
So we just show that multirate filters
are very important, right?
We talk about computational aspect,
we can save the computational resource
if you go to lower rate.
We talk about filter banks,
which we can process every spectrum specifically.
But in practice, due to the non-idealness of the filter,
there's always aliasing.
And there'll be some kind of artifacts resulting
from this decimation or interpolation process, right?
And we want to make them, you know, minimize.
We want to suppress all of these artifacts, right?
So the question is like, how can we suppress this aliasing
even if we are using the non-ideal low-pass filter?
So once you're non-ideal, I'm talking about
a low-pass filter that looks like this.
In other words, from the passband to the stopband,
there is a transition period, okay?
The difference is that it's not like
vertical line directly goes down, right?
You are going to take some time to change
from the passband to the stopband, right?
This is what we mean by practical filters, okay?
So now, how can we come up with a practical solution
to solve the aliasing problem
by still utilizing the non-ideal filter, okay?
This is the approach.
I mean, one of the methods is called QMF, right?
It's called the quadrature mirror filters, QMF, okay?
So the basic building block of the QMF will be two channels.
They can be generalized to more channels,
but let's start by two channels.
In other words, we are talking about two branch,
like one filter cover half of the spectrum.
Remember, we say that filter band, you have n channels.
But here, let's simplify the thing first.
Let's talk about two channels, okay?
So if it's in two channel, right,
we are talking about, let's say, one passband filter,
sorry, one low-pass filter.
The other one will be the high-pass filter
because that's the only way the two can cover
the entire spectrum, right?
So here, you are going to have like two channels,
sorry, two filters covering the organo kind of spectrums.
And suppose we have the X0 and X1
to be the low-pass filter in the analysis filter band.
All right, so remember, there are two stages, right?
Analysis, synthesis.
So now let's imagine that the low-pass filter
that we use in the analysis are H0 and H1, right?
And of course, there will be two, you need another two,
correspondingly as the low-pass and high-pass
in the synthesis stage.
Let's call them G0 and G1, all right?
So as we described previously for the filter band, right,
you will have this kind of structure
where the signal well goes into each of the channel.
You first need some kind of a low-pass or high-pass,
followed by a down sampling.
Let's think about two, right?
I mean, don't make it too aggressive, but two.
And then process somehow, let's just skip that, right?
So like I mentioned, if you skip the processing,
you should, I mean, a good or perfect filter band
should be able to recover the original signal, right?
So let's do this.
Let's first assume that nothing happens
in the average channel, right?
Then after that, you need to directly perform
the interpolation, and the second stage
is called the synthesis stage, all right?
So this is like just the simplified version
of the filter band we talk about, only with two channels.
All right, but the difference is that here
the H and the G are no longer ideal, right?
We're talking about non-ideal filter, okay?
So let's think about, right,
if this is the filter band, what we have, right?
Suppose N equal to two, and also D equal to two.
What is the spectrum, right, frequency response,
let's say, after the analysis, all right?
So we have to do this one by one, right?
Let's think about what happened
after you performed the analysis filter, all right?
After you do analysis filter, input is actually X zero.
After that, you should have two output, right?
Remember, every channel should get output.
So can we derive the representation
of the output of the analysis filters?
In fact, we learned this, right?
Remember, we say that, well,
for both that summation and the interpolation,
I need you to know both the time domain
and the frequency domain relationship, remember?
We have a big table, remember we showed that?
So we can use the Z transform relationship, right,
to represent the X output, but of course,
if you have the Z transform, you can easily get the omega.
Just need to substitute the Z with the E to power of J omega,
right, and if you do so, this is the formula.
You can simply set D equal to two, right?
And if you say D equal to two, you should get the formula,
the kind of representation like this, okay?
I mean, I leave this to you to do it.
It's not very hard.
You just need to set D equal to two,
and then you need to change the Z to E to power of J omega,
all right, and you represent everything in omega domain.
This is the one you have, all right?
I mean, take some time to do it
if you don't feel like it's so easy,
but it should be very straightforward.
Because it's D equal to two, right?
You only have two terms, okay?
The only difference is that here,
the first channel, you have H zero.
The second channel, you have H one, right?
The formula should be the same,
but make sure you are denoting the low-pass filter
in different way, right, H one, H zero, okay?
So these two will be correspondingly the spectrum
of your output, right, in each channel, here and here, okay?
All right, so now, of course,
with the non-idealness of the low-pass filter, right,
it could have some aliasing.
So right now, we have no guarantee there's no aliasing,
unless you have ideal filter, right?
This is non-ideal filter, so it's possible
that there could be some aliasing components in the output.
Why, because we say that for the ideal filter,
you can actually use the low-pass filter
to get rid of the aliasing,
but that only when you have no transition kind of a period,
right, now with the transition,
you will have some aliasing,
and actually, the aliasing is the second term,
if you realize the first term is your ideal
down-sample signal, right?
The second term, oh, sorry, sorry, not yet, actually.
Oh, no, no, no, sorry, sorry, I always wanted to say it,
later, later, but anyway, due to the fact
that H zero and H one are non-ideal,
so there could be some aliasing components,
which is the, okay, which is the second term of the output,
so this term could give you some aliasing, all right?
So, and this is actually due to the consequence
of this non-zero transition band,
and this non-zero transition band
will end up with some overlaps, all right?
So now, how to represent aliasing,
we can actually use some kind of a, you know,
notation to separate the two, right?
So let's think about, okay, so let's think about that,
let's denote the, sorry, each channel of the output
after analysis as the XA zero and XA one,
so here the A stands for the analysis field stage, right?
Zero and a one stands for which channel, okay?
Let's use the subscript to denote
different stages of our processing.
Now we have to pass this to the second stage,
so the second stage will be the synthesis stage, right?
And every channel of the synthesis stage
is actually a interpolation, right?
Of course, with the non-ideal low-pass filter.
So in this case, you can represent
the interpolation process in the following, okay?
So where does this come from?
This come from the interpolation formula, right?
We talk about this in interpolation.
I always do remember, otherwise I can show you, right?
So you can actually go to our, what is that?
Lecture four, right?
If you go to our lecture four, we have this table.
Where is it?
Here, right.
So just now what I'm showing you is the decimation.
This is where the decimation come from,
which is actually the analysis part.
So if it's a synthesis part,
this will be the Z-transfer we need, right?
And you can tell that the only change that happens
is the signal itself, right?
The omega is actually multiplied by I time, right?
So here in our case, I is two.
That's why all of these omega will multiply by two times.
Make sense?
So in this case, you can now represent the final output
as a function of the X signal.
But here the S stands for the synthesis stage, right?
X zero and X one, okay?
But of course, later we can see that you can assume
the X A zero equal to S zero
because we are doing nothing in the middle, all right?
So if you go back to the stage, right?
So let me just denote what we're talking about here.
I need to make sure I can edit it, right?
So what I mean is this.
Here at this stage, this is our X A zero, right?
And this is my X A one, right?
So those are the output of the analysis filter
correspondingly channel zero, channel one, right?
And this input is denote as X S zero.
And this input is X S one, right?
So here the S denotes the input of the synthesis filters.
Okay?
Same convention, A stands for analysis,
S stands for synthesis,
but one is output, one is input, okay?
So in practice, these two may not be the same
because if you do something here,
it's going to process the A into S.
But here, let's assume that they are the same, right?
Because we want to analyze how to form the low-pass filter.
So let's assume nothing happened between the two stage, okay?
So that's why they say that, well,
let's assume that the A always equal to S, right?
Here the same, A equal to S.
So that means your X S zero will be equal to X A zero.
Here X S one will be equal to X A one,
which was just the one we just represented
in the previous slide, okay?
So now just substitute all of this,
you just need to substitute all of this X A zero,
X A one, sorry, into the equation here, right?
You should be able to get the complete representation
of your final output, because final output
is nothing but summing them together, right?
You just need to sum the first term
with the second term together,
you should be able to form the final signal representation
using the frequency spectrum, right?
Using the frequency representation, all right?
Okay, so feel free to derive it themselves,
because that's also a good practice for you
to get familiar with the interpolation and decimation.
Like I mentioned, you need to know what happened
if you perform interpolation or decimation.
You need to know both the time domain and frequency domain.
So this is a good example for you to practice, right?
And it's not very challenging, because D equal to two,
right, it's a very simple example.
Okay, but you should be able to get
the overall representation, all the way from the X
to the final reconstruction of X hat.
So here the X is your original input.
X hat is the final reconstruction, final output.
So like I mentioned just now for filter bank,
if nothing happened in the middle
between analysis and the synthesis, right,
and good filter bank should give you
the original signal as the output.
In other words, what we're trying to reach or achieve
is nothing but making the X hat equal to X, right?
Makes sense, because now I'm assuming
that nothing happened in the analysis
and the synthesis in the middle, where nothing happened.
So I want to make sure my filter bank
is just as good as the one we talked about last week,
which is using the ideal filter, right?
So right now, of course, the filter is not ideal,
but we still want to have a perfect reconstruction
of my original signal,
which is making your X hat equal to original X, right?
So how can we achieve this?
How can we achieve that, the original signal, like X?
Oh, actually not, right?
So let me see, let me see, okay, actually it's not.
Oh, actually, okay, they are looking
for something slightly worse, slightly weak, okay.
So what they're trying to do is that they want to make sure
the second term, which is the adiasing, to be zero.
Okay, so I was wrong.
Actually, they didn't really require this term
to be perfect with reconstruction,
but they wish to make sure the second term,
which is actually the adiasing, to be zero, okay?
So why this is true?
Because if you don't have the adiasing term, right,
only your baseband signal should survive
in these filter banks.
So the baseband signal will be corresponding
to the first term, right?
Remember, the baseband signal is actually your X omega,
but if we do have some adiasing,
or we have some kind of overlapping in the low-pass
and high-pass kind of spectrum,
there will be an adiasing coming from the next version.
So originally you have X omega,
but the signal is actually periodic.
You have another kind of spectrum,
which happens at shifted by pi, right?
So we want to make sure the adiasing doesn't happen.
So all of these components should be zero,
because we shouldn't see any adiasing generated
from the shifted version of the baseband, right?
So I hope you still remember
where the adiasing coming from, right?
If you review the lecture four,
we say that the adiasing coming from the fact
that you do have some overlapping,
so after you do all of this shrinking of your spectrum,
you have some overlapping,
not shrinking, stretching of the spectrum,
you have some overlapping coming
from the next kind of periodic periods, right?
Your baseband signal, which is actually X omega,
but your next shift will be X omega minus pi, right?
So if they have some signal overlap
with your current signal,
that one becomes the adiasing, all right?
So in that sense, what we're trying to do
is to make sure there's no contribution from this guy, right?
In other words, we want to make sure
all of these weights in front, sorry,
all of these weights in front, this guy must be zero, right?
So the weights in front describe how much energy
or how much concentration are coming from the,
you know, kind of the first duplicate, right?
The first shifted version.
So if you make this term to be zero,
it's basically saying that the reconstruction result
is actually adiasing-free.
You are able to eliminate the adiasing, right?
Make sense?
Okay, so now the question is like,
how can we make this term to be zero, right?
We understand our objective, right?
This is something we want to achieve,
but we need to understand
when this condition can be achieved, okay?
So of course, the good thing is that we have the choice,
right, we can choose our, you know, the four filters,
H zero, G zero, H one, and G one in whatever we would like,
but of course, they can never be ideal, okay?
So you can choose whatever non-ideal filter you like.
As long as you make this term to be zero, you are good.
You are done.
The job is done, right?
So by looking at this equation, right,
this is the objective.
What can you think about?
I mean, if you are going to pick the G zero, H zero,
and the G one, H one, what should be the choice
of these four filters
to make the entire contribution to be zero?
What do you think?
I mean, this is something we want to achieve, right?
So the whole idea of going through the analysis,
synthesis analysis is to understand
when we say these filters, eight is in three,
what do we mean, right?
And now we get this equation and say,
hey, if this term equal to zero,
we should be able to eliminate the contribution
from the second term, right?
But what kind of choice of H zero and G zero
can make this term to be zero?
Do you find some kind of a trivial way
or maybe easy way to get it to be zero?
So remember, you have the full control of the filters, right?
The only constraint is that your H zero must be low pass.
Your H one must be high pass, right?
Similarly, your G zero must be low pass.
Your G one must be high pass.
That's it.
Remember, they have to be complementary, right?
So one have to cover part of the spectrum,
the other have to cover the rest of the spectrum.
Other than that, you have full control of, say,
how can we relate G and H?
Okay, so what do you think is the easy condition
to make this term to be zero?
Any thoughts?
So this is actually equation, right?
You have how many variables?
You have four variables.
And you have one equation.
You cannot really work out the filter response exactly,
but you may have some relationship
between the H and G, right, through this equation.
Okay, so think about this case, right?
So if this is zero,
what's the immediate thing come to your mind?
Basically, you only have two terms,
the first term and the second term.
Basically, the first term will be the negative
of the second term, right?
Make sense?
You wanna cancel each other.
The only way to cancel each other,
unless they're both zero, right?
They can be both zero.
I mean, very unlikely they can be both zero.
I mean, there's one chance if the,
these two filters are complementary.
In other words, there's no overlap, right?
This is actually the ideal case.
If you have two kind of a spectrum
which are completely orthogonal,
but you may not have that.
But the general case is that the first term
were equal to the minus of the second term, all right?
Very straightforward.
And then, if this is the case, right,
you wanna make sure the first term
is equal to the minus of the second term.
And of course, your H zero cannot be H one, remember?
Because H zero and H one must cover a different spectrum.
They cannot be the same, right?
Otherwise, you are not doing a spec of filter banks.
The only choice you have is to make the H zero term
to be the same as the G one term.
And then, correspondingly, the G zero term
to be the same as the H one term,
to make them the same in a cross way, right?
Make sense?
I mean, there could be other choice,
but this is the easy option, right?
So if you somehow make the H zero to be the same as G one,
the G zero to be, let's say, minus H one.
So in the cross way, they're the same,
the two term will be cancel each other, right?
And then you can make the whole thing to be zero, right?
So this is like an easy way to come up with one solution.
So that means I can crossly make the G zero,
okay, this is actually coming from here,
the G zero equal to the H one,
but remember, here's the shifted version of H one,
so you do shift that by pi, all right?
So making the G zero to be the shifted version of the H one,
and making the G one to be the shifted version
and the minus of H zero.
So in the cross way, they are equal,
and of course, you need to have a minus sign
to cancel each other, right?
So this will be one condition,
or actually the condition for QMF.
QMF uses this condition, all right?
So this will be the condition that making the set of filters
the four filters to satisfy QMF kind of requirement,
all right, and then if that's true,
we assume H zero to be low pass,
of course, it can be the other way around,
but let's assume that the first channel is low pass,
and then H one will be the high pass, sorry,
sorry, H one is the low pass, H one will be the high pass,
right, and actually, we can set the H one
to be the mirror image high pass filter,
which is something like this, right?
So if you assume that your H zero
is like a non-ideal low pass filter,
in which case you do have a transition period
from here to here, you can assume
that your H one will be the opposite,
I mean, the mirrored version of it,
and of course, it's going to be the high pass, right,
because now the pass is actually
in the high frequency region, all right?
So this is the way you can construct the H one,
and of course, by using this formula, right,
you can assume that, let's say my H zero,
let's call it H zero is actually some kind of a prototype,
H, and the H one will be the mirrored version
of the H itself, so that's how you can make
the H zero and the H one to be the pairs, right,
and these two will form the pair of high pass and low pass,
all right, okay?
So, but of course, this is the spectrum, right,
we say that if you have the spectrum relationship,
you can also work out the time domain relationship,
how to do it, well, you do the inverse DTFT, right,
and inverse DTFT says that if you have a shift in the phase,
sorry, you have a delay in the phase,
it's in the frequency, it should be correspondingly
a phase shift in the time domain,
remember, you will have some E to power of minus J,
what is that, N pi, right, something like this,
so according to different Ns,
it's going to be one, minus one, one, minus one,
so that's why you get this term, right,
this term coming from the corresponding phase shift,
so remember that phase shift in one domain
will be the delay in the other domain, right,
vice versa, okay, that's how you get this,
and then this 10.6 is the time domain relationship
between the mirrored filters, H one and H zero,
so H one and H zero, they must be complementary,
so one is low pass, the other must be high pass,
and to make it kind of aliasing free,
they must be a kind of mirrored version,
you just flip them, so that even if,
even if there's some kind of transition function,
sorry, transition period,
they are kind of transition in a mirrored way, all right,
so even though there are some overlap,
but they're kind of like a mirrored version,
so as a consequence, right,
these two will have the mirror images symmetric
at the frequency pi over two, so this is always true,
when you do mirroring,
you have to make them symmetric at pi over two,
why, because the delay here is pi, right,
you're shifting pi, you will have the symmetric point,
which is at pi over two, all right,
so this will be the kind of visualization of the spectrum,
when you talk about this mirror image symmetry property,
right, okay, so this is the plot,
this is the frequency domain relationship,
this is the time domain relationship,
so make sure you know how you can get one from the other,
right, and of course, you know,
what kind of form of transition is up to you, right,
I mean, this is just some illustration,
your transition can be like a wider,
your transition can be shorter, it can be different form,
but they must be symmetric, all right,
that's the principle, okay, all right,
so this is what we need to impose, right,
and then, where is this constraint,
just now we talk about H, right,
now we can correspondingly talk about the G,
remember the G and H are related in this way, right,
this is actually the GH correlation,
so once you have the pair of H,
you can work out the pair of G,
so in this case, G zero will be equal to the prototype H,
G one will be the mirror version plus,
and also a sign change, right, so two things,
so your G zero will be equal to the H zero,
in other words, so because H zero equal to H, right,
so your G zero will be equal to H,
will be H equal to H zero,
your G one will be the symmetric version
of H plus a minus sign, so don't forget a minus sign,
all right, so that's how you can derive your G one, okay,
but even though we have four filters,
there's only one prototype H, so once you give me the H,
if you tell me this is actually a QMF,
I can derive all of the four filters,
so all of the four filters will only have one free filter,
which is H, okay, all of the four
will be varied version of my H.
What is H?
That's up to you, I mean, you can pick
your own low-pass filter H, but once you pick that,
if you want me to construct the QMF,
I have a fixed way to do it, right,
and then this equation tell me
how I can construct the G pairs, all right?
Questions, I hope this makes sense, all right?
If it doesn't, let me know, I can explain it again,
but basically, this is one way to construct a filter bank
with an ideal filter, right, in other words,
your filter may not have a sharp transition,
slow transition that also works, so correspondingly, right,
we can convert the frequency domain into time domain,
so in the time domain, similarly,
there's a phase shift, sorry,
there's a delay in the frequency,
you have a phase shift, also there's a minus one,
so observe the minus one here, right,
and note that there could be a scaling factor in overall,
but the scaling factor is actually not the critical one,
the critical one is that we wish to make sure
the aliasing components actually vanish, right,
so using the QMF will make sure the second term,
which is the aliasing term, will be completely canceled,
by the aliasing term,
aliasing actually corresponding to this term,
so the important thing is that this term
will be eliminated if we have QMF.
Original form may have some scaling,
but that doesn't matter, right,
the scaling will not change the waveform, right,
this term erased, that's the most important thing we need.
Okay?
Okay, so that's the first thing,
the other thing, well, is that,
so all of these aliasing coming from the decimation
in the analysis will be perfectly canceled,
and then this is due to the fact
that when you do interpolation, right,
there are also going to be some kind of a distortion,
so by doing the QMF,
these two distortions will be canceled each other,
so overall, in overall sense, there will be no aliasing,
all right, but if the question ask you,
if you use QMF, will there be aliasing,
not in the final stage, but in the channel-wise X,
that's possible, right, you will still have some aliasing
as in the XA, okay,
so this is actually a common mistake people make, right,
so what we have here is to guarantee this term to be zero,
and this term is the aliasing in the final X hat, all right,
so here, when we say cancel aliasing,
we're only in cancel aliasing in the final X hat,
but we cannot guarantee that the aliasing
in the after the analysis filter is canceled,
no, this is still there,
you will still have possibly some aliasing
in the output of analysis filter, right,
because analysis filter, you use line ideal filter,
so you could have some aliasing,
so QMF cannot happen preventing this guy,
the QMF cannot get this guy to be zero,
no, they're still not zero,
so there will be some aliasing
after analysis filter back, right,
but the QMF can make sure those aliasing term
will be canceled after the interpolation,
after the synthesis, okay,
this is what the QMF is doing,
so it's not true to say that if you do QMF,
the entire process have no aliasing,
so this is not true, only in the final reconstruction,
we can guarantee there's no aliasing,
all right, so that's a common mistake people make,
okay, good, so in some sense,
you want the two part to cancel each other, right,
interpolation give you some problems,
you know, decimation give you some problem,
but unfortunately they can cancel each other,
so you got no problem, right, in the end,
this is actually the beauty of QMF, all right,
okay, so that's what you need to know,
and let's see, right,
okay, okay, and then now we have all of this H,
H0, H1, G0, and G1, right,
and now if you put them together into your,
remember we have overall representation
from the X hat to X, right,
if you put them together,
you can work out the frequency spectrum
of the entire system, remember,
you can treat the entire filter bank as one system, right,
and if you work out the,
something like a frequency response of the H,
the entire thing is just like a,
you know, E to power of something,
so this term will possibly give you some phase change,
but phase change is okay,
as long as we don't have any areas in term, right,
so if you cancel areas in term,
the overall response will be just some, you know,
E to power of minus J omega K, right,
which is possibly some phase shift, all right,
so ideally we will have this to be kind of a,
like a phase shift,
and actually you can actually form a polyphase form, right,
to represent the H1, sorry, H0 and H1 specifically,
I mean, I won't really test on this, to be honest,
but you probably know this, right,
so we can do polyphase for filter bank
that we talked about last week,
right now we can also do a polyphase form for the QMF, right,
because QMF is nothing but a filter bank,
so it's the same thing,
if you can do polyphase to implement
the filter bank in general,
you can also do a polyphase filter,
a polyphase realization for QMF,
which would be something like this,
but I won't really test on this,
because polyphase is more for increasing the efficiency,
right, but it will give you the same result
as the original filter bank, right,
but this is just to say that you can,
it's perfectly fine to do the polyphase realization
of the QMF, which is even simpler case
than filter bank in general, right, okay?
So, what else do we have here?
So, okay, this is about a linear phase,
so if your H itself is a linear phase filter, right,
and your HR, so remember linear,
if it's a filter, it's a linear phase,
your phase term will have a linear relationship,
so you won't have additional kind of phase shift,
right, everything is linear,
and the real part will be a, you know,
kind of a filter length of N, right,
you can represent it using a FIR, basically,
and the overall transfer function of the two-channel QMF,
which use a linear phase FIR will be the following, right,
you can actually represent your entire system
of the QMF with a FIR design, right,
but I think that's more about, you know,
talking about how can you come up with a, you know,
kind of finite order of the FIR to represent a QMF,
which, yeah, it's good to know,
but again, I mean, I probably will not test on this,
and what else do we have?
If it's a delay of the N sample, right, of the,
huh, I don't even remember, I put this one in my slides,
okay, yes, delay of N minus one samples,
and a magnitude of the characteristics of this.
Okay, I think I want to test you guys on this, actually.
Let me look at what I have here.
Okay, I will not test you on the FIR,
so maybe I will just remove these slides, okay.
So the only thing you need to know is the condition, right,
so I will just remove the FIR things,
because it's kind of something I'm not gonna test you on,
so I will just remove the two.
So the only thing I need to know is that
when we say a system is a QMF, right,
how can you come up with the design?
So I could give you some kind of a, you know,
H function, H omega, and you need to tell me
what are the four filters, right,
and if I use a QMF to process my signal, right,
I could give you some signal as input,
so you need to tell me after this kind of a QMF
what is the output, right, and here I put nothing,
so here I put nothing in between, remember?
I say that, well, here in between we have no processing,
because I want to prove that,
what is the requirement of a QMF,
but in practice I could give you some processing in between.
Okay, so you need to tell me if there's a processing
in channel zero, channel one correspondingly, right,
what will be the corresponding X?
So how can you derive that?
You have to be very familiar
with all of this representation, right,
so after analysis, what's going to be
the Z domain representation,
what's going to be the omega representation,
and then, followed by the synthesis, right,
what will be the change after you go from the,
here the XS to the final X hat, right,
so if you know both of these two stages,
analysis plus synthesis, you should be able
to derive the output, even if there's
any processing in the middle, all right,
so this is something I wish you to know.
The other thing is the design of the four filters, right,
H0, H1, G0, and G1, what is the requirement
if you call them QMF, right,
you need to tell me exactly the requirement,
and also you need to tell me,
after the requirement is satisfied, right,
what's the overall frequency response,
or transfer function, all right,
so this is all you need to know.
So forget about FIR, so I will just leave that aside, okay,
but you have to be very clear
about the requirement, condition,
and also, analytically, what is the formulation,
what's the form to reconstruct the signal
from the beginning, all right,
so this is what I need you to know.
Okay, so all of them should be covered until,
so, size 12, right, so up here, up to here,
that's the things you need to know,
and be very familiar with, all right?
Okay, any questions?
So let's look at one example, right,
I think this is actually a good example to,
it's just a practice, right,
so I could give you something like this,
where I say, hey, I consider a two-channel QMF,
oh, by the way, later on, I'm going to talk about
possible extension to more channels, okay,
but you just need to know that,
even though all of these discussions,
what we talk about here is only for two channels,
in practice, you can always generalize to more channels,
okay, I'm going to tell you how to generalize,
but I will not give you a question like for more channels,
the reason is it's too complicated,
you have to write down many lines, right,
so I think two channels is good enough, all right,
so make sure you can derive the two channels,
so this could be one of the, you know,
example questions that you may see, right,
so I could give you a diagram like this,
so this is like a very standard analysis filter bank,
I could give you some kind of, maybe filters,
I could maybe give you one, right,
say, hey, I tell you this is my H0, okay,
okay, I may not give you others,
but you should be able to derive other filters
using the QMF condition, all right,
so, and then I could ask you to verify,
for example, what will be the output, right,
in the, let's say, first channel, second channel,
both in the frequency domain or in the time domain,
so you need to be able to convert the representation
from the frequency to the time, all right, just like this,
if this is my, you know, Z domain relationship,
I should be able to kind of form the output
in the time domain representation, all right,
how to do it, you can do inverse Z transform
or you can do inverse DTFT, right,
but bear in mind that the, if we have a minus sign here,
if you have a two here, what does that mean?
In time domain, right, so basically,
Z to the power minus one is nothing but delay
in the time domain, right, so you should correspondently
have a delay here, right, that's where they come from,
all right, so you can actually use this as an exercise,
but I will give you some other form of H for sure,
I won't give you the same, but some other form of H,
but how to derive the other filters,
it should be all covered here, right,
this is how you can derive it, and, sorry,
this is how you can relate your H to H zero and H one,
right, so you should be familiar with that,
both in omega domain and also in the time domain, okay?
I hope I simplified it a bit so you don't confuse,
like, we have too many things,
you don't know how to prepare,
but this is all you need to know, all right,
and there will be a question on this, I can guarantee you,
right, there will be one question,
not too many, but one, okay, one sub-question, all right?
Okay, good, so any questions so far for QMF?
Okay, two channels, I mean, you need to know two channels.
All right, so, after that, right,
I'm gonna quickly go through how we can,
I think, wait, I think this is not updated, I,
okay, let me double-check,
I should have updated this slide.
Why I'm opening slides that,
let me see, it's because I didn't update it,
I think I removed some of the components from the,
okay, maybe I should check this one,
okay, give me a second,
because I remember I removed some of the components,
I don't know why they comes back again.
Oh, okay, maybe I forgot to save that,
but anyway, so that's fine.
Okay, so, these parts, I'm not going to test on that,
even though I leave that here,
because it shows you that sometimes, right,
you don't limit yourself to only two channels,
okay, you can actually go for more channels,
all right, but I will not test on this part,
because the computation is so complicated.
But the idea here is that,
if you can decompose the frequency channel into two,
right, you can keep dividing.
So, for example, now I have, let's say,
half of my spectrum,
I already have analysis filter to extract,
let's say, zero to pi over two, right.
If I want to further divide that spectrum,
and I don't have ideal filter,
I can keep using my QMF to divide it, right.
So, that's how somehow you can progressively divide
the entire spectrum into, let's say,
smaller and smaller section.
So, basically, if you know how to design a QMF
for two channels, you should be able to further expand
the division progressively for every sub-channel, right.
So, that's how people use this to realize,
for example, wavelets, right,
if you think about wavelets, how you do that,
you are keep dividing the space into low and high,
you can do one more cycle, one more level,
to keep dividing the low channel
into low-low and high-high, right.
So, that's how you do it.
And same way for, practically, when you design it,
you are going to divide them into several bands,
and each band will be encoded separately
with different accuracy, right.
So, in practice, the only thing you need to make sure
is that every division, right, in every division,
the design of the filter must satisfy the QMM condition,
the way we talk about, right, they must be symmetric,
at the position of pi over two,
but then, when you divide it, this symmetric point
will be not necessarily the pi over two, right,
it could be pi over four, or maybe pi over eight,
that's how you can progressively kind of divide it,
and the synthesis will be the opposite, right.
So, in other words, if you have, let's say,
here, your channel one, channel two, three, and four,
in your analysis kind of design,
when you do a synthesis, they must be symmetric.
In other words, you have the first synthesis one and two,
and followed by the synthesis of that with three,
and that with four, all right.
So, basically, analysis kind of filter bank,
you need to keep dividing your signal
into different spectrum distribution.
In the synthesis part, they should be also
kind of synthesized in a progressive way, right.
In this case, I mean, one and two will be synthesized first,
and then followed by three, followed by four, right.
But every pair, right, the filters here,
every pair of the filter will be satisfying
the QMF condition, all right.
This is actually the principle of the,
how should I say, generalized the two channel
into more channels, right.
So, I mean, practice, this could be some design, right.
So, this is the QMF for two channels,
this is the QMF for three channels, right.
So, you are keep dividing the first channel,
or you can further divide it into like a third layer, right.
So, this is actually the case,
you are going to have four channels in the QMF design, right.
But every division, they must be satisfying
the symmetric property, right.
Okay, so I will not give you a test on that,
but you need to know how you can generalize
two channel QMF to higher amount of channels, right.
This is the way they generalize.
And for those of you who know wavelets,
or maybe even people talking about DCT, right,
that's actually the principle.
They don't directly go to like say eight channel,
but they do this progressively every time just by two, right.
That's the principle of the designing filter banks
in practice, right.
So, okay.
Okay, you know, this is for you to rate.
I'm not going to test you and say,
hey, come up with the relationship for,
you know, zero, zero, zero, one, and you know, one, zero.
That's kind of too complicated.
But you should know the philosophy, right.
And I just pretty much skip this part.
Feel free to rate it because it's a good practice
for you to apply the true two channel QMF
for more channels, right.
And similarly, if two channel QMF, sorry,
if a filter bank can be implemented using FFT, right,
you can also do a polyphase realization
for M channel QMF as well, right.
It's the same kind of philosophy.
And you can speed up the processing
using a similar way, right.
Okay, so I think that's all I need to cover, actually.
I will not give you any question on this part,
but you just need to make sure, you know,
any questions regarding, I mean, not even here, right.
I think I kind of deleted this part.
So you just need to make sure up to this point, right.
For two channel question, you know every relationship
for filter design, for signal representation,
and how can come up with a perfect signal reconstruction
without any aliasing, right.
That will be good enough for you.
Okay.
All right, so if no question, let's take a 15 minutes break.
So next part, I will do a summary, okay.
I will give a summary lecture.
And meanwhile, if you have any question, right,
feel free to ask me during some summary lecture
because I'm going to walk you through all the thing
I cover from lecture two to right now, right.
So if anything unclear to me,
feel free to ask.
All right, so I will see you resume again around 7.45, okay.
All right, great.
Thank you.
Okay.
All right.
So let's start.
By the way, I think there's one question I got in the middle
which is very, I think is very good.
So there's one student tell me that here,
if you remember, like we have a formula, right?
Describing the time domain relationship between the,
what is that?
Interpolation, right?
Where is the image?
So the student suggested that here is actually
should be coming from minus infinity,
which I agree, actually.
Because in the whole discussion here,
we did assume the causality of the filter, remember?
All of this discussion we talk about in downsampling,
upsampling, we assume that the low-pass filter is actually
ideal, right?
So it's very hard to reach kind of a practical filter,
which is ideal low-pass.
So in practice, they actually assume all of the signal
to be non-causality, right?
So if it's non-causality, it doesn't make sense to do the,
sorry, do the convolution only starting from zero.
They catch it from minus zero, sorry,
minus infinity, all right?
Which I agree.
But I just want to say that in actual exam,
I won't give you like a super long signal to do convolution
because that's very competitionally expensive.
So in the actual exam, right, you just need to know
that this is nothing but a convolution between the two.
So then in this case, you just need to convolve to signal,
make sure all of this overlapping part of the shift
are computed, that's it.
I mean, this is just the theoretical form, right?
Are you going to convolve covering the minus infinity
to infinity or not, right?
I think there was, I mean, the reason this note says zero
is because they somehow assume the system to be causal,
right, but we're not talking about practical case.
So it's perfectly possible to have non-causal system, right?
I just want to clarify this point.
But if it's causal system, you just need to go from zero,
right, because all of this minus part will not be there.
All right, but I think that's a reasonable question, right,
to say that we do have to convolve from zero in this case.
Okay?
So after that, I think I'm going to give you some summary.
But what I covered in, all of these things we're going
to test is all covered, right?
So whatever I haven't talked about, like AM channel QMF
is not going to be tested, all right?
So don't worry about that.
All right, so I'm going to walk you through whatever
we cover for this part one.
Okay, hopefully we'll give you some idea about the,
you know, how to prepare the exam, right?
And meanwhile, if you spot any question,
you can feel free to ask me, right?
Again, you know, you can ask a question any time.
You don't have to wait until the break, all right?
So if you remember, like all of this discussion
we talk about from lecture two is starting
from the sampling process, all right?
So you should be able to understand,
when we say sampling process, what we mean by converting
the analog signal to, you know, discrete signal, right?
So this is actually the sampling process.
And in sampling process, one of the important parameter
is the sampling rate, right, which is FS.
You have to specifying sampling rate always,
if you're talking about A to D system, right?
And the sampling rate is always one over
the sampling period, right?
So these two are equivalent parameters, right?
One is the reciprocal of the others.
And if we're talking about the discrete time domain signal,
this is the way we are representing them, right?
So you can representing them using the small f, sorry,
or you can representing them using the omega,
just different way to represent a frequency, right?
And this f and omega are the normalized frequency
in the hertz and the radians per seconds respectively.
So the units are different, but if you do a two pi ratio,
you can convert one to the other, right?
The only thing is the change of the units, right?
And now we see that, you know, some of you are,
should be familiar with the CTFT before,
but that was for analog signal.
So for this class, we'll be mainly talking about DTFT,
starting from DTFT, right,
because we are interested of discrete signal.
But you should know what's the relationship
between CTFT and DTFT.
So this figure shows a comparison, right?
Basically CTFT, of course there's ICTFT,
we'll be converting the analog domain,
and the DTFT will be converting signal in the frequency,
sorry, digital domain, right?
And the way you're converting the time domain
will be the sampling, or the other way, the interpolation.
And again, you know, there will be aliasing formulation,
the sampling theorem,
which is also something we talk about,
like how can we determine the critical rate
to avoid aliasing, right?
That kind of form the relationship
between the analog frequency
and also the digital frequency, right?
This is their relationship.
But of course, you need to make sure
this critical rate is satisfied,
otherwise you will have some aliasing, right,
in your actual spectrum.
So you need to know the relationship of the functions
and, you know, of the signal domains,
and normally we will use the I to stands for the inverse,
right, so basically you need to know
the pairs of the transform,
like how can you do inverse transformers as well,
so make sure you know the difference, right?
We're gonna do inverse, we're gonna do forward transform,
the base will be different,
and for DTFT, one is summation, one is integration.
Remember, only the time domain is discrete, right?
The spectrum of the discrete signal
will be still continuous.
So if you do inverse DTFT,
you have to make sure this kind of summation
becomes integration, all right?
So don't get that wrong.
So talking about the sampling theorem, right,
this is the theorem, I mean,
maybe one of the most important theory
in the signal processing is to tell you
how can you make sure that these signal,
after sampling, will be kind of aliasing-free, right?
So basically you need to assume
that your analog signal itself is band limited.
So what does the band limited means?
When you're looking at the spectrum of the signal,
the spectrum must be zero if the frequency
is beyond the upper limit of the frequency bands, right?
And only the number zero, when you have W,
is less than the WM.
So this WM is the band limit, right?
And your, I mean, if that's the case,
your analog signal will be uniquely determined
by its samples, where the sampling rate
will be larger than two M.
So if you have the sampling frequency
that is larger than two WM,
you will have reached the critical sampling.
In other words, those measures can be used
to uniquely recover the original analog signal, right?
So this is actually what the sampling theory
is talking about.
So this frequency, which is the two times
your kind of the band limits,
is referred as the Nyquist rate, or Nyquist condition.
I mean, this is Nyquist rate,
and if your sampling rate is larger than that,
this is called Nyquist condition.
You need to satisfy the Nyquist condition
to make sure this measure can be used
to perfectly reconstruct the original analog signal.
In other words, avoid aliasing in the sampled images.
Sorry, sampled signals, right?
And I think we didn't talk about folding frequency,
but actually Nyquist rate is the most important thing.
And the highest frequency,
which is the upper limit of your spectrum,
is usually called Nyquist frequency,
since it determines the minimum sampling frequency.
So basically, what you need to do is say,
if I want you to do sampling,
you need first look at the analog signal,
work out the spectrum of it,
and that's how you can determine the Wm.
So once you determine the Wm,
times two is going to give you the Nyquist rate.
And if your sampling rate is beyond that Nyquist rate,
that means it satisfies the Nyquist condition.
So this is basically what we mean
by kind of fully sampled or over-sampled.
If it's beyond the Nyquist rate,
that's over-sampled signals.
So sampling theory is very important,
and this is also relevant or related
to the up-sampling and down-sampling things,
like multi-rate processing,
because here, the only thing is that
the analog signal can be considered as infinitely large rate.
But of course, later, when we say multi-rate,
we're talking about finite rate
between two different discrete signals.
But the sampling process will be the bridge
to kind of connect the analog signal
to the discrete signal we are talking about.
So make sure you know the Nyquist rate,
Nyquist condition, and also how to make sure
there's no aliasing.
This is the important thing.
Yeah, so Nyquist rate is this guy.
The minimum sampling rate you need
to satisfy the aliasing-free condition.
So two times your band limits,
this is called Nyquist rate.
Now, after we talk about DTFT,
we say that, well, DTFT, because it gives you
still a continuous spectrum,
which is hard to store and process in digital device.
So in practice, people actually more prefer
to use DFT, discrete Fourier transform.
The difference will be that if you apply DFT,
you will have a discrete spectrum,
rather than a continuous spectrum.
And DFT is always a square transform.
In other words, if your input signal has endpoints,
your output DFT will also have endpoints.
That's why we always specify the DFT as an endpoint DFT.
And also these endpoints is corresponding
to how many inputs you have,
how many points in your input signal.
So you need to know the forward DFT
and also the inverse DFT.
So the analog form, sorry, the analytical form is this way,
is this form.
And for both of inverse and the forward transform,
they are summation, because nothing to do
with continuous signal anymore.
Both of the spectrum and the signal are discrete.
So you just need to do summation,
and the summation is always going from zero to N minus one.
So in the DFT, we have a very important concept,
it's called resolution.
I hope you understand what is the resolution
when we talk about DFT.
It's going to depend on two things.
First one is the sampling frequency,
and also the number of points.
So basically you can try to use a more point DFT
to increase, I mean, improve the frequency,
improve the resolution,
but the quantity will be decreased.
In other words, the smaller the quantity,
the better resolution you have.
This is what you are doing.
So to do so, you can try to do zero padding of your signals
and then use a larger N when you apply the DFT.
So this is how you can do it.
And you should be able to work out the resolution.
If I give you, for example,
I tell you that signal is sampled at a certain frequency,
so this will be the FT,
and I tell you that the DFT will have 1,025 points,
so this one becomes your N.
So you need to make sure you can work out the resolution
in a corresponding way,
which is the FS or FT divided by the number of points.
So make sure you know what we mean by resolution,
and you can extract the information
from the description of the question,
where to extract that frequency,
where to extract that point.
And also, this number is the smaller, the better,
the smaller, the higher frequency,
sorry, the higher resolution.
And the last but not least, DFT is often,
I mean, this DFT is good for analysis,
but in practical deployment,
people always do FFT, Fast Fourier Transform,
because these two are exactly the same.
It's going to give you some speed up
and give you the exact same result.
So in practice, all people will do FFT.
But when people write down the formulation,
they will do DFT, because they're easier.
So that's actually the, you know,
because DFT is more theoretical presentable,
this is actually the reason
why we love to use this for analysis.
And another aspect is that because this DFT itself,
it's a kind of n point DFT,
one can represent the entire transform as a matrix.
All right, and this matrix will always be square.
So it's like n by n matrix, right?
And this matrix is nothing but involving a base,
which is e to the power of j two pi divided by n,
times your, sorry, two power of i minus one
times j minus one.
So in other words, you can represent every element
of this matrix as this form, right?
And this form, let me use a pointer here.
This form will be nothing but exponential
of the base elements here.
So these base elements will be only depends on n, right?
The larger the n, the smaller the face.
But you just keep exponentially using the coordinates
of i and j to form the actual elements, right?
That's how you can form the entire DFT matrix if you want.
And why we want to use the repetition of the matrix
is because if you represent the DFT using the matrix,
the entire forward DFT can be easily represented
as a matrix multiplied by the input vector, right?
Your x will be your input vector, which is also n point.
And you multiply by this n by a matrix,
you will get another n dimensional signal.
And this signal will be the spectrum, right?
DFT spectrum.
So that's how you can easily get the spectrum from the x.
Right, so in this case, you can avoid writing
the entire summation, right?
That's why people usually use this matrix vector form.
All right, and same for inverse DFT, right?
The inverse DFT is another matrix.
And this matrix, in fact, is the direct inverse
of the forward DFT.
So these two are exactly the inverse of the matrix.
You can show that this matrix itself is always full rank.
So inverse always exists.
In fact, this matrix is orthogonal, right?
If you try every column of the matrix
are orthogonal to each other.
So it's actually orthonormal,
not only orthonormal matrix, right?
So if you have this, okay, no.
I mean, you have to scale it, right?
You have to do one over square root of n,
otherwise it's not orthonormal.
But orthogonal, all right?
A orthogonal matrix always have inverse
and this inverse becomes the inverse DTFT matrix, all right?
So this is why you can come up
with this easy representation of the DFT and inverse DFT.
Okay?
And actually the inverse DFT can be also easily computed
as the Hermitian transpose
due to the structure of your DFT.
So it makes the inversion even easier, right?
Okay?
But actually, don't worry too much about this.
Even if you don't know the matrix form, right?
If you know the analytic form, you should be okay.
I mean, because anyway, you just need to write
the summation instead of the matrix vector multiplication.
They are equivalent, right?
Okay?
And we also say that, well,
without talking, before talking about multi-rate, right?
Remember, without the multi-rate, rate change,
we can assume that the system we're talking about
is LTI system, which stands for linear
time-invariant system.
And for this kind of system,
we will have a so-called transfer function
to represent the entire system.
So what is this transfer function?
Transfer function is nothing but your
spectrum of Y divided by spectrum of X, right?
That's your transfer function.
So, depends on the transfer function,
you can actually categorize the system
into either, let's say,
you have two way to categorize the system.
One is look at the time domain of the transfer function,
which is the impulse response, right?
By looking at how many components you have
in the impulse response.
If you have finite impulse response,
this is called FIR system, all right?
So, you know that in the transfer function,
you should have only the numerator, right?
The denominator should be one, in this case.
And this can be implemented using
a non-recursive block diagram, right?
Because you don't have to pass your Y back to the system.
Remember, all of this denominator
are coming from the past Y outputs, right?
If it's only one, that means you don't have to use
the past time outputs, then there's no recursion
in your block diagram.
But there's another kind of transfer function,
which is the opposite of FIR,
means that you will have infinitely many impulse response,
it's called IIR, and the actual implementation
will be a recursive block diagram.
So that's the difference.
Categorize according to the time domain impulse response.
That's one way to categorize the system.
There's another way to categorize the system,
but instead, time domain, you should look
at the frequency response of your system, right?
So, you can actually kind of classify your shape
based on the magnitude function,
which is like the absolute value, right?
You can also categorize it in terms of the phase.
So, according to the magnitude,
we have learned basically low pass,
high pass, band pass, or band stop, right?
So, nothing to do with the phase, but the magnitude.
Depends on where are the pass band, where are the stop band.
You can actually have these four kind of filters, right?
So, basically these filters will also use them for later,
like filter banks.
But for all of these filters, you need to specify,
for example, here, what is the color frequency, right?
The color frequency will be important
to define, like low pass, high pass.
And for band pass, you need two.
You need WC1 and WC2 to determine where is this pass band,
right?
So, once you have those parameters,
you can specify the type of filters you are talking about.
All right?
And then, we talk about that in practice, right?
All of these so-called low pass filter are ideal filter,
because you are suddenly changed from pass band
to stop band without a set of kind of transition period.
Right?
But in practice, we never have this ideal filter.
So, in practice, if because you are implementing
the filters using, let's say, FIR,
you will end up with something like this, right?
In other words, from your pass band to stop band,
there will be a transition band,
which is coming from the pass band to stop band, right?
So, your transition band will be non-zero,
and you need two frequencies to specify
where is this transition band,
which are the omega P and omega S.
All right?
If it's ideal filter, that's going to be the same, right?
You've got zero kind of transition width.
All right?
And also, besides the transition,
there's another phenomenon that could appear
in the non-ideal filter.
That is the repose, right?
So, there could be some small kind of perturbations
from the ideal pass band.
For example, ideally, there should be one,
but in practice, there's always some values
alternating between one plus delta P
and one minus delta P, right?
So, this is actually the actual fluctuation you will have.
So, similarly for stop band,
you will also have some fluctuation here.
Ideal pass filter is always one, right, for pass band.
So, that's the difference.
You need to know the difference,
and also, when we design the filters,
you need to know what is the objective
when we design the filter, right?
So, basically, you need to somehow come up
with a realizable transfer function,
which is not arbitrary.
You have to use this kind of a numerator,
denominator fix to approximate a given frequency spectrum,
so some frequency response.
So, in other words, all of this so-called filter design
is about what is the best approximation
given a certain amount of orders, right,
certain amount of degree of freedoms.
So, and also, there could be FIR, there could be IRR.
So, for this course, I'm gonna limit you to FIR, right?
IRR, I think Lin is gonna talk about it in the second part.
But basically, you need to make sure
that your design kind of a function
will have a good approximation
of the objective, intended specification.
And by the problem is that, you know,
how can we come up with a realizable approximation, right?
So, we actually learned only one method for this class.
I removed the other two, but only one method
that is windowing approach, right?
So, windowing approach, the idea is to use
a low-pass filter, which is like a window,
to limit your filter design, right,
which is, oh, sorry, not actually a low-pass filter.
It's actually a limited window in the time domain
to constrain your number of impulse
from infinity now to a finite number of impulse, right?
So, in this case, coming from a windowing function,
you are going to talk about a spectrum,
which is something like a zinc function, right?
But of course, you can tell that this function itself
will be non-causal, right,
and there will be infinity non-range.
So, in this case, you actually need
to come up with a finite duration,
which is specified by the window,
and also, you should do some kind of a shift
to approximate the whole thing to a causal system, right?
So, these are two things you need to do
for your windowing kind of function,
but for the window function,
you need to understand what's the objective,
which is going to minimize the mean square errors
when we do approximation,
and you need to specify where the window is, right?
The lens, the shift, and that's going to determine
your specific windows that are going to apply, right?
But I think for windowing approach,
you just need to know the kind of the rough idea.
I probably will not test it on how
to exactly implement windows,
but you need to know what's the philosophy
of this windowing approach.
What's the objective, and what's the limitation, right?
These are something you need to know for a window approach.
But that will be the only approach
we learn for filter design, right?
And you don't have to consider other approaches.
For that one, I can promise, okay?
So now, after that, we say that,
well, you can actually represent a system
using a transfer function, using an impulse response,
but you can also use a graph or diagram
to represent your system, right?
The idea is that if you have this diagram,
it's easy for implementation in the end, right?
So give you some kind of easy to write down
the computational algorithm by simply inspection,
and also you can analyze the block diagram
to determine the relationship.
So basically, we're going to use the components like this,
including addition, multiplication, delay,
to implement some of the system we have learned, right?
And you may need to, first of all, like a given,
let's say if I give you a block diagram like this,
you need to tell me what exactly is the relationship
between the X and Y, right?
So you may have some question like this,
I give you a block diagram.
Of course, I will specify what are the building blocks,
for example, addition, multiplication,
the ratio will be given,
and amplification also, the ratio will be given,
but you need to come up with multiple equations.
For example, these are the equations
describing the key points, right, the W1, W2, W3.
And finally, I will ask you to write,
give me the, maybe the transfer function,
or the impulse response of the entire system.
So you need to know how can you link the X to Y,
or link the Y to X, right?
The way to do that is by first writing down
all of this intermediate equation, right,
describing the junction here,
and somehow trying to cancel the variables, right,
because all of this W1, W2, W3
are the intermediate variables.
So they shouldn't be there for your .xy transfer function.
So you need to, making use of this multiple equation,
and cancel them, right?
And eventually, you should give me something like this,
right, you should somehow end up with the only,
or direct relationship between X and Y, right?
So after that, you should be able to do a Y divided by X,
and that's how you can come up with the transfer function,
like the, in the Z transform, right?
So you may have some question like this, okay?
And one direction is that given the block diagram,
derive the transfer function, okay?
So I expect all of you can do it, all right?
So if you don't do, if you cannot do it,
refer to example, right,
because the way to solve that is always the same.
You look at the junctions,
you work out multiple equation, cancel each other,
only leave the X and Y in the final representation.
And that equation will be easily,
you can divide it and form the XZ, all right?
Okay, so if you're not familiar with that,
look at this example,
look at the example we have in the notes.
And I mean, this is pretty much what I expect you to know,
right, block diagram interpretation, right?
And then, you know, another important aspect is the phase,
right, we say that in practice,
we may not have like a zero phase filter
due to the fact that we're using FIR,
but we always wish the phase to be linear, right?
I think I showed some example in the lecture
that if the filter is not linear phase,
you can have some distortion,
and you can make the whole thing like time vary, okay?
So how to make sure that FIR is linear phase?
There are, remember there are two conditions for symmetric,
right, all symmetric, even symmetric for FIR, okay?
And also, depends on how many degree,
how many order you have, right?
Even M is even, M is odd,
we will have, you know, four type of filters
that could be linear phase, all right?
So in total, there are four types,
but they are either forming a even symmetric kind of FIR
or all symmetric FIR.
So either way, but these two conditions together
are equivalent to linear phase.
In other words, the linear phase could indicate
either way, right, either symmetric or anti-symmetric.
But together, you know, if you have either
the even symmetric or all symmetric,
it's going to be necessary and sufficient
to say that this FIR is linear phase, okay?
So I hope you can understand the relationship.
For example, if I say, hey, this filter,
I give you a FIR, I say this filter is linear phase.
You have to try both.
You have to try both the anti-symmetric and the symmetric
before making a conclusion, right?
So if either of them somehow give you the answer,
that should be a valid answer.
So I think that hopefully give you some idea, right?
But if you want, if you are going to check
whether an FIR is a linear phase or not, right,
as long as one of the conditions satisfy,
you can say that the FIR is a linear phase
because it's a necessary condition, right?
Sorry, it's a sufficient condition, okay?
All right, so basically there's only four types.
Just need to make sure what's how you can check
FIR is a linear phase, right?
And if I say it's a linear phase,
can you work out the equivalent condition
on the coefficients of the FIR?
These will be two kind of questions I may give, all right?
So like I said, right, depends on whether
it's a symmetric, anti-symmetric,
depends on the length, is order, even if you have four types
but basically I think the symmetric and anti-symmetric,
this is the most important thing, right?
Make sure you know how to write down the equation
for symmetric and anti-symmetric.
That's how you can form the bunch of equations
to solve the coefficients, right?
All right, and I think this is a table
that you could refer to.
I mean, it just tell you that if it's each type, right,
what is the corresponding kind of phase term?
But anyway, the phase term will be linear, right?
But of course, the form will be different.
It's optional, I mean, I won't really ask you
to memorize it but you should be aware
that there are four types, right?
Okay, now we talk about, we are moving
to kind of a party phase, right?
We say, well, FIR can be decomposed
into a party phase representation, right?
So party phase is one way to decompose direct FIR
into multiple branches, remember?
So every branch, they can have a party phase decomposition.
And if you have L branch in total, okay,
your HZ, I mean, your transfer function
can be represented as the summation,
of course, with time delay, over all the branches, right?
So this EM, well, EM will be the corresponding
transfer function for branches zero, branch one,
all the way to branch L minus one, right?
So the overall transfer function will be the summation
of the entire L branches of party phase, right?
So the idea of doing that is to reduce, basically,
the computational complexity for every branch, all right?
So, and then you should be able to derive
what is this EM, right, in every branch.
But most importantly, I think party phase
is linked to the multirate processing
because multirate processing, it give you a natural way
to decompose a signal into every branch.
Every branch can be further down-sampled
to the lower rate to save the computational resource, right?
And that's where we followed by talking about
the interpolation and down-sampling,
interpolation and decimation, right?
So we first say that, well, actually,
after all of this block diagram, right,
we're going from a single rate to multirate.
And multirate, the idea is to change the rate
either to higher rate or lower rate, okay?
So basically, there are two possible change.
If you want to go up, you are going to talk
about up-sampling and interpolation, all right?
So this is actually the interpolation system
where interpolation must have up-sampling
followed by a low-pass filter, okay, the order matters.
For interpolation, a low-pass filter
must be after the up-sampling, all right?
The reason, we already explained, right,
the reason is to kill all of these duplicates
when you do the up-sampling, right?
You only want to keep the baseband waveform,
not the duplicates.
So you will first do up-sampling,
which will give you duplicates and you kill them
by the follow-up reconstruction filter, right?
So this is actually the filter we're talking about.
And like I mentioned, you need to know exactly
the how to derive or determine this low-pass filter.
So low-pass filter will be, have a color frequency,
which depends on the rate of your up-sampling, right?
So if this is eye time of up-sampling,
your color frequency will be pi divided by.
So the more you up-sampled, the narrower your band will be,
which makes sense, right?
If you have a high number of up-sampling,
you have more duplicates.
So you have to cut the frequency more aggressively.
So this pi over eye will be smaller, right?
And of course, this one really doesn't matter
because you need to have some scale
to compensate the energy loss.
So ideally, you can make C equal to I,
but the change will only be the scale, right?
It doesn't really change the waveform.
But by doing so, your output spectrum
will have the following relationship.
So this is what I'm talking about
as the frequency relationship
between input and output of the interpolation, right?
So similarly, you should also kind of
be able to work out the time domain relationship, right?
So time domain relationship will be
the kind of the convolution of your H and the V.
Remember, the V here is after up-sampling, right?
And what happens with up-sampling?
Up-sampling will make the XK to be the, sorry,
well, make the VKI equal to XK.
So here, the I will affect the scaling of the function,
right, sorry, the scaling of the signal, right?
So in this case, you can substitute this X back to the V.
You can work out the entire time domain relationship
from the beginning to all the way the output, right?
So you can refer to the table I actually stated
in lecture five, which give you the four relationship,
like up-sampling, interpolation,
down-sampling, and decimation.
So for every pair, you need to know
both time domain and the frequency domain, right?
So this is something I need you to know.
Okay, this is by up-substituting the X
is going to give you the overall relationship.
So this will be the mathematic expression
for the time domain of interpolation, right?
And just now, this is the frequency response,
frequency relationship for the interpolation, right?
Okay, so these are the two pairs.
Now, same for decimation, right?
The decimation, the order will be the opposite.
You need to first apply the anti-aliasing filter,
which is a low-pass filter, before down-sampling, right?
The idea is to prevent aliasing,
and aliasing is prevented by cutting the frequency,
make sure there's no overlap.
So this anti-aliasing must be before down-sampling.
Because if you don't do that, the overlapping happens.
You will be not able to resolve the overlapping part.
So even if you do low-pass filter after that,
the overlapping already happens.
So aliasing is already distorting your signal.
So in this case, low-pass filter
must be before down-sampling.
But of course, this low-pass filter
will also depend on the down-sampling ratio, right?
So in this case, I'll give you some kind of visual example
what happened for the down-sampling, right?
If you, there are two ways to interpret this process.
So first way, one way to do that
is to directly view this process to the omega y, right?
So like I mentioned, you can view
the entire kind of down-sampling
as the stretching of the signal, right?
So initially, your signal is limited by pi over four, right?
But by up down-sampling by four times,
you are going to stretch the signal to four times
such that your baseband will be
stretching from pi over four to pi, right?
So here, maybe I will do a pen here.
So this is like pi here, right?
So one way to view that is by stretching your signal here
from pi over four to pi, right?
So the ratio of the stretching of the signal
is equal to the number, ratio of the down-sampling.
So this is one way to view it.
If you view so, you are directly converting omega x
to omega y, right?
That's the first way.
The other way is that stay in the omega x, right?
Don't change the omega, still doing the omega x.
But considering, you know, like a duplicate
all the way from your baseband,
the first duplicate, second duplicate, and third duplicate.
So you will form entirely four copy of your baseband,
depends on how many ratio you have,
to fill up the range from zero to two pi, right?
And then converting the omega from omega x to omega y.
But in this case, your omega must be amplified by four times
In this case, here originally is actually pi over two,
this origin is pi over two, right?
And after multiplication is going to change to two pi, right?
So the same, you're gonna end up with the
same kind of waveform, by either way.
So it depends on how you wanna view that.
Either way will be the valid way
to kind of view the change of the spectrum, right?
In this down-sampling process.
Okay, so this process is only down-sampling.
Anti-aliasing already happened in this low-pass filter, right?
So if you have originally some kind of larger bandwidth,
your low-pass filter will cut everything, right?
Cut everything beyond pi over four,
so this will be killed, right?
But what is the illustrating here?
This process is just down-sampling, right?
And depends on the ratio, the stretching will be different.
But if your original signal is band limited by pi over four,
you won't have any aliasing, because there's no overlap,
even if you stretch your signal, right?
So here, your low-pass filter will be
cutting off at pi over four.
Or in other words, pi over I, right?
Depends on your I, I mean, sorry, pi over D.
What D is, the cutoff frequency will be different.
Okay?
Does it make sense?
So you need to clearly indicate what happened
for low-pass and I-pass.
Okay, I will have one question on that.
So make sure at least you know how to sketch the difference
for down-sampling, for up-sampling,
for anti-aliasing filter, for reconstruction filter.
All right?
Okay?
Make sure you know this.
If anything's unclear, come and ask me.
I'm happy to explain to you, all right?
But you will have one sub-question on this.
I can guarantee, I mean, I already said the question,
so what I'm saying here is serious.
Okay, there will be one question, at least on this part.
Okay?
All right, so this is, okay, so overall,
you need to know the sketch, how things change
in the spectrum, as well as the mathematic representation.
So make sure you are familiar with all of this.
Basically four sets, what happened if it's only
up-sampling, what happened is up-sampling
plus reconstruction filter, so in total, interpolation.
And then only down-sampling, and also together
with the anti-aliasing, so in total, the decimation.
So for all of these four, you need to know
time domain plus frequency domain.
All right?
And then it makes your job easier, right,
to work out the mathematic form.
All right?
Now, when we talk about multi-rate, right,
I could give you some question like give you
a block diagram with multiple up-sampling,
down-sampling, low-pass filter.
Sometimes you need to simplify the block diagram, right?
When you say simplify, you have to maybe swap the order
of the up-sampling or maybe down-sampling of the filter.
So the most important property you need to know
is the so-called noble identity, right?
So what is noble identity?
It's basically the relationship, if you wanna change
the order between the down-sampling and the low-pass filter
or the down-up-sampling with the low-pass filter.
So if you swap the order, how will the low-pass filter
change, right?
This is actually told by the noble identity.
So make sure you know what's the conclusion
and also make sure how you can derive it, okay?
Let me just emphasize this, right?
You need to know how you derive the noble identity.
Okay, which shouldn't be very hard,
but make sure you try all of the derivation, okay?
And make yourself convinced that when you swap the order
between the two, there'll be an exponential term
on the low-pass filter, right?
Basically, other words, your only goal will be scaled by d,
right, if you change the order of the two.
So make sure you go through the derivation here, okay?
Not just memorize the result, but you need to derive
the whole thing here, okay?
Okay, so like I mentioned, this is also important.
You know what it means, right?
There will be one question on that for sure.
So if anything unclear, please ask me, okay?
And then filter bank, right?
Filter bank, like I mentioned,
you don't have to deal with the party face,
but you need to know that filter bank
will have two parts, right, which is the analysis part.
So this will be the analysis part,
and there will be a, maybe I changed the pointer, right?
there will be a synthesis part,
and in the middle, people can do whatever DSP they like
for every channel specifically, all right?
But what you need to know is that how to construct
a qualified analysis filter bank,
and also how to construct a synthesis filter bank, right?
So this is what you need to know.
And how can we divide the signal into different subbands
such that we can also combine them later
to restore the original signal
with the distortion minimized, right?
So this is actually the purpose of designing
the filter banks, to make sure the signal
can be perfect to reconstruct if possible, right?
So for filter bank, we talk about two scenario.
One is the ideal case, okay?
Ideal case means your low-pass filter
can be sharp transition directly from passband to stopband.
So we're talking about the filter bank like this,
low-pass filter like this.
So if the, under the ideal case,
you can treat every channel, the low-pass filter, sorry,
the filters to be shifted version
of the prototype low-pass filter, all right?
So in other words, you only need to specify
one prototype as your H zero.
Other filters in the channel one, channel two,
all the way to M minus one will be nothing
but a shifted version of your prototype.
So you just need to specify H zero.
Of course, this frequency shifted,
delay will be nothing but a phase change
in the time domain.
So correspondingly, you should be able
to work out the relationship in the impulse response, right?
From the prototype to the specific HK, all right?
So, but remember, this is the ideal case,
not for practical case, right?
But for ideal case, this is the way we can construct
a list of filters from H zero to HK, right?
And now, if we are using ideal low-pass filter, right,
the way we can construct the filter band is the following.
You need to do some kind of a phase shift
in the time domain, followed by the prototype filters,
followed by down-sampling, right?
The reason of doing down-sampling is to reduce the rate
to save the computational, I mean,
to improve the efficiency, right?
And by doing so, you can actually generate
the specific spectrum of the signal in a lower rate.
And then you can do DSP for every channels, right?
But after that, you need another synthesis filter
to combine them together to restore the original signal.
The way we form the synthesis process
is something symmetric compared to analysis filter, right?
Which is up-sampling first, followed by a low-pass filter,
followed by another kind of a phase shift,
but opposite way, right?
You wanna shift the signal back to the specific bandwidth
and sum them together.
So this phase shift will be exact opposite
of the analysis phase shift, right, if you compare the two.
All right, because one is to shift them
from the specific band to the base band.
Synthesis will be shifted back to the specific band, right?
So they are actually the opposite.
So by doing so, if you don't do anything in the middle,
between X and Y, you will be able to get this VN,
which is exactly the same as your XN.
Maybe with some scaling, but waveform is the same, all right?
But remember, this is your ideal low-pass filter case, okay?
So when you go to exam, please read the question.
Are we talking about ideal filter or practical filter?
Ideal filter, goal is this formulation, all right?
And you should be able to write every term, right?
How can you derive the G?
How can you determine the rate?
How do you do the phase shift correspondingly?
All right?
Okay.
And now, now talking about practical case,
this is where we need the QMF.
All right, so ideal filter band, nothing to do with QMF.
You just need to specify a prototype,
do a shift, you form the list of filters.
Now, for practical cases, doing that way
will always give you aliasing,
because you cannot have a clear cut
of the frequency channels, frequency band, right?
So there will be some transition band,
and how can we use a practical filters,
but still have a result which is aliasing-free?
This is what the QMF is doing, okay?
So clearly, QMF is to construct a filter band
using non-ideal filters to get aliasing-free result.
Okay, this is what QMF is doing.
Now, QMF, we will only be learning the two-channel case,
but we say that you can extend it to more channels
by progressively dividing the frequency bandwidth,
but just for calculation purpose,
let's stick to two-channel, right?
Now, for two-channel filter band,
you basically need to determine four filters, all right?
Here, the H0, here, the H1, G0, and the G1.
So just now, the student asked me, he said,
hey, why my homework?
I don't call them H0 and H1.
So I can call them anything, for the record.
I can call them A, B, C, D, right?
But you always need four channel, sorry, four filters
to form a two-channel QMF, right?
The name of the filter doesn't matter.
I can call them H, I can call them A, call them B, right?
But to fully determine a two-channel filter band,
you need four filters, that's for sure, okay?
But for QMF, these four filters are not completely free.
Okay, there are dependency over the four filters, okay?
This is actually the condition of QMF, all right?
So you need to know the condition of QMF,
and the condition is actually derived,
I mean, first is the following, right?
You only need one H to represent all of them
because one H will be able to determine
what is G0, what is G1, and what is H0, what is H1.
But just while we talk about that,
where does this equation come from?
It comes from the fact that the adiabatic term
must be zero, right?
We say that the contribution of the adiabatic term
is the quantity, and we wanna make that quantity to be zero.
That's how we end up with these four equations, okay?
But these four equations, you can tell that
all of these four filters will be all depends
on this H, so you only need one H.
They can determine all of the four filters, right?
That's what the QMF is talking about, okay?
But all of the four, you should be able to tell that
the H0 and H1 are symmetric, right?
So one is the mirror symmetric of the others,
and the center point is always pi over two, right?
You can actually easily tell from these two pairs.
So one is equal to H omega,
and the other one is H omega minus pi, right?
Consider the filters themselves are symmetric.
If you shift by pi, you will form a mirror symmetric
within zero to pi region, all right?
Now, G0 and G1, they will be kind of both symmetric
and plus or minus sign, right?
But minus sign itself will not affect the magnitude, right?
Magnitude is always larger than zero,
so you also have some kind of symmetric property
of the magnitude of G0 and G1, right?
This is actually what QMF is telling you, right?
But whatever, what is the H0, H omega?
You can determine the H omega,
and sometimes H omega will be provided by the question,
right, but once you know that,
you need to be able to derive all of the four filters
in this QMF, right, for two channels.
That's what this part is talking about, right?
And also, if you know the frequency relationship,
you should also be able to tell
the time domain relationship,
which is nothing but the phase shift,
which is J e to the power of minus J n pi, right,
in this case, all right?
So this is actually the H.
You can also work out the G.
So basically, if you have this QMF,
what you can do is using non-ideal filter.
Here, the H is non-ideal filter
to form a aliasing-free filter bank, right?
This is what the QMF is doing.
So I mean, the reason they can form an aliasing-free result
is not because there's no aliasing in the middle.
It's because the aliasing from the analysis filter
will be somehow canceled by the follow-up interpolation.
All right, so in other words,
it's just because we designed the filter
to perfectly cancel the two components.
That's why we can achieve the final aliasing-free,
but it doesn't mean that there's no aliasing
after, sorry, after the analysis filter.
So there will be aliasing after an analysis filter.
Okay, that's actually the fact.
But if you do so, the next stage will cancel
whatever error you have in the first stage
to achieve the final result, which is aliasing-free, okay?
And like I said, we only talk about two channels,
and the two channels will be LTI system, right,
because basically the upsampling, downsampling
can be canceled each other,
so it's going to be still a timing-variance system.
All right, so I think that's all I have for the summary.
Basically, everything I cover for my summary,
they will be tested.
If I didn't cover in my summary, maybe they are not, right?
But anyway, I should specify all of the things
in my lecture already, right,
what are the optional ones, what are compulsory ones.
So whenever I see optional, forget about it,
it won't be tested, but good for you to know, right?
So if that's the case, I will end the lecture today,
and I will stay here for some questions.
If you have any questions, I'm happy to take.
Okay, otherwise, I hope you have a good recess,
and also don't forget homework.
Okay, homework is due by the end of the recess,
so don't be late.
And also, by now, we should have all the knowledge
to solve every question, so you still feel confused
or unclear of the question you've come and asked me.
All right?
Okay, thank you so much, so have a nice recess.
All right, okay, thank you.
Thank you.
Okay.