All right, so before I start the lecture today, I wish to draw your attention to these two
announcements, which was made earlier last week.
As I mentioned last week, right, we have two CAs, Continuous Assessment for this course.
One will be conducted by me, the other one will be conducted by Prof Lin in the second
part.
But the forms are different.
I don't know why there were some students still raise the question.
I think I made them clear last time, but please read the announcements, if you're not very
clear about the two CAs.
Basically, I will give you homework, so homework is not a quiz, you will do that at home.
So you don't have to come here, you will have like more than three weeks time.
So the homework will be made available to you in week three.
So this is actually, okay, this is already week three, so actually, did I say week three
or week four?
Sorry, week four.
So it will be made available to you next week, next Friday.
The reason is like you need the knowledge, which we are going to learn starting from
next week to do the homework.
So even if I announce now, it doesn't really help, all right, but don't worry, you have
enough time to do it because the due date will be the Friday of the recess week.
In other words, you should have how many weeks, five, six, seven, right?
So even if you count the recess week, there should be four weeks to do it.
So you should have enough time, so you can use your textbook, you can even search online
if you want, right?
So but mainly those questions for you to, you know, like a checkpoint for you to fully,
make sure you fully understand all of those concepts we cover in this, in my part, all
right?
And you will find the questions under the assignment, right?
So I don't know how many of you have checked the NTU Learner site, but if you go to the
NTU Learner page, for the content, right, this is where you can find the slides, lecture
slides, and later I'm going to create an item under here.
I mean, this was the old one, I think, but anyway, I'll update, but this was the old
one.
You will be able to find the assignment.
So you can download the question there, and then you can also submit your answer sheets
there.
Okay, in other words, you don't have to give me the hard copy.
You do it, you can either type set it, like you can use Latex to type it or Word, or you
can just write it.
I mean, you can do handwritten submission, but if you choose to write to your answers
by hand, make sure those answers can be read, okay?
Because if I cannot understand your handwriting, I cannot give you marks, it's very fair, right?
So it's your choice, you can choose to type set it, like use Word, or maybe Latex to
do it, which is completely safe, because I can definitely read those type sets, you
know, answer sheets.
But if you choose to write it down on papers, and then you can scan it, right, you can take
a photo, scan it, submit, make sure those answers can be read, because, you know, I'm
not sure about everybody's handwriting, but if your handwriting is, like, terrible, like,
you have to make it clear, because if I don't understand it, I cannot give you marks, okay?
So it's your job to make the handwriting clear, all right?
So this is my, for my part, okay, my part, the CA is not a quiz, okay, it's a homework,
okay, I hope I clarified this already, right?
But for Puffling, you know, as, you know, sorry, let's go to the announcement, all right?
So if you look at the announcement, right, Puffling also make another announcement for,
so for his part, he's going to give you a quiz, okay?
It's also 20%, but he's going to give you a quiz, in other words, for his part, it's
going to be a close book quiz, which is conducted in the lecture, I mean, I don't know whether
it's in the lecture, but it's going to conduct it, you know, physically here, right?
So he's going to tell you more details, but the form is different, for my part is homework,
for Puffling's part is a quiz, okay, don't confuse, you know, don't get it confused,
because I do have some, some people ask me, you know, how many homeworks do I have?
Only one homework, that's for me, the quiz is from Puffling, all right?
My part will only focus on part one, I will not touch the part two, okay?
Not speak for Puffling, but I think he's going to focus on part two, right?
Because this is actually how we separate the scope, okay?
Is it clear?
Because I do receive some emails, keep asking me this, but if you are not clear,
you have any question, please ask me no, all right?
Because if you email me, I could get delayed, because I cannot, I may not reply you on time,
so don't complain, if there's a better way to do it, just ask me no, all right?
I can clarify any question you have.
Yes?
What do you mean by one?
You can do multiple submissions, but I will only grade your last submission.
Okay, so here's the thing, he's asking, the gentleman is asking, how many times,
how many opportunities I can submit, all right?
You can submit any multiple time as many as you want, okay?
I'll make it unlimited, but I'm only going to grade your last submission.
In other words, if I make my second submission, that's going to replace the first submission,
okay?
Is it clear?
I'm not going to grade both, okay?
It doesn't make sense.
So if you find that your answer is wrong, or you want to fix anything, as long as it's
before that line, you can do it, okay?
Is it clear?
All right?
Answer your question?
Okay, good.
Any other questions?
Okay, so I assume it's clear now, right?
Prof. Ming asked me to mention this clearly, because both of us keep receiving emails,
so I just want to make sure this is clear for everyone, all right?
Okay, good.
Okay, so, okay, then let's go to our lecture today, right?
So this is my second lecture, so let me first do a recap of what we covered last week.
I hope you still remember what we talked about last week, right?
So last week, I will call it a review, because if you have taken any digital signal processing
course in your undergraduate, these are pretty much not new to you, right?
You probably have already learned them, but consider we have a very diverse background,
and the students come from very diverse backgrounds, so it's better to kind of review that first,
make sure everybody have the same kind of a, you know, baseline, right, unless you're
going to keep asking questions.
So what we covered last week is starting from this, you know, signal representation, right?
We learned that, well, you can represent signal both in time and in frequency domain, and
we talked about how we can generate so-called discrete signal, right, or digital signal.
We don't really differentiate the two, but I think one of you asked me the question,
what's the difference?
So for this course, we don't really differentiate the two, they are just discretized, sampled,
but we learned the theorem of sampling, how you can sample analog signal to generate digital,
right, and what could be wrong, what is the requirement of the sampling rate, right?
So we covered the, what is Nyquist condition, I hope you still remember, right?
Nyquist condition says you have to have a minimum sampling rate in order to avoid any
distortion, in other words, aliasing, right?
So I wish you could understand what is aliasing now, I mean, basically here, right, basically,
so basically aliasing is the distortion we are interested of, and we wish to avoid, right,
and this is what the Nyquist condition is talking about, right, is tell you what is
the minimum sampling rate that you need to avoid aliasing, right, specifically, and we
also learned how to do the DTFT and DFT specifically to represent the signals, right, we talked
about why we are interested in all of these, you know, varied version of Fourier transforms,
right, is because we believe that frequency representations sometimes are more useful
than time domain representation, right, we talk about frequency analysis, we talk about,
later we're going to talk about low pass filter, you know, high pass filter, I mean,
when we say low and high, we're referring to frequency, not time domain, right, so I
hope now everybody should be familiar with at least how to use DTFT, how to use DFT, so I
give you a summary about the three kind of most important transforms we talk about, so
CFT I didn't talk more because I believe this is covered, pretty much covered in your, even
before digital, like analog signal processing, right, very fundamental, so, but the difference
is that CFT, in other words, continuous time Fourier transform, dealing with analog signal,
right, which, that's why we are not focusing on this because we're focusing on digital
signal, and it's going to give you continuous function in both time and frequency domains,
right, input, output, both of them are continuous time, right, this is CFT or you call it CTFT,
then what we learned and what we started with last week is actually DTFT, right, because
DTFT are specifically for discrete time signal, right, it's for digital signal, and that's
what why it's called DT, right, DT stands for discrete time, and it's going to take
discrete signal in time domain, but it still gives you continuous function in the frequency
domain, right, this is DTFT, so DTFT output, the transform domain is going to steal continuous
time, right, that's why you will need to do integration when you want to do inverse transform,
right, so, but then definitely we don't want to store continuous number, right, as the
spectrum, because the computer cannot store continuous number, that's why what we really
use most frequently for digital device is DTFT, because DTFT is going to deal with the
discrete signal in both time domain and frequency domain, right, so you can see the change,
we are gradually moving from CT to DT, right, but you need to know what's the difference,
how one can gradually evolve coming from the original CTFT, originally or progressively
to the DTFT that we want to really use in practice, all right, so use this as a checkpoint
for you to organize all of the knowledge we learned, and basically you need to have this
understanding on the time frequency representation, right, of the signal, that's what we focused
on, right, DTFT, and actually the two things we are really using is DTFT and FFT in digital
device, right, so one last thing is that we talk about frequency, and there are two frequencies,
okay, so first you can represent frequency in terms of either hertz or radian, right,
that's why you use F and omega correspondingly, I mean you can also convert them to a multiplied
two pi, right, just the different units, and we also say that one can use your sampling
frequency to normalize them, right, so you can convert them in the period, I mean in
the duration of one, in other words you can normalize them so that they don't really vary
in terms of scale, right, so be very careful whether we're talking about normalized frequency
or unnormalized frequency, but the difference is just dividing a sampling frequency, right,
but in the question they can give you either, right, they can give you normalized, they
can also give you unnormalized version, all right, so these are basically the important
things we learned last week, so last week if you remember, right, we ended with the introduction
of DFT, right, discrete Fourier transform, so I give you a quick recap, right, basically
you need to know these two equations, one is the forward transform, right, going from
time domain to frequency domain, and sometimes we also call it an analysis transform because
we're analyzing the signal to get the frequency components, so you can consider the frequency
spectrum as an analysis of the time domain signal, right, you want to see whether this
is kind of very strong in low frequency or very strong in high frequency, it's an analysis,
okay, so, but pay attention to that, DFT always is dealing with some finite number of points,
okay, you cannot have infinitely, okay, you can in theory, but it's going to be periodic,
right, but most likely we're talking about endpoint DFT, remember we say that you can
actually use a matrix, square matrix to represent a DFT and the size of the matrix is the size
is determined by how many points you have, for end points DFT you have to have an m
by n matrix, alright, so it's always endpoint, and the number of time samples, in other words
the length of your time domain signal, it's always equal to the number of samples in frequency
domain, so no matter how you do this transform, right, inverse transform, forward transform,
it doesn't change the number of points you have, okay, so that's why you're, if you
remember, right, your DFT matrix is always a square matrix, because dimension is no change,
it's still n dimension, right, so this is the second point, and you know, you can also
do this m samples using DFT, but they have to be within a DFT window, in other words,
you can have a longer, you know, longer size of signal, but when you do the DFT you have
to do some kind of windowing or truncation to make them within, right, so this is a common
way people dealing with maybe a relatively longer signal, right, so when you do inverse
DFT, right, again it's going to be endpoint, right, but if you compare the form of the
forward and inverse, you realize that there are two difference, one is the base, right,
forward transform you have to do minus sign in the exponential, inverse transform there's
no minus sign, that's the, basically the base function is actually the opposite, right,
another thing is the scaling, so for our subject we use the version that you don't scale in
the forward transform and you scale it back by multiply of 1 over n to scale it to original,
right, so this scaling factor 1 over n is just to ensure that you can't get back to
the original signal without any scaling ambiguity, okay, but you may find the so-called DFT in
other contexts they do 1 over n square root, square root n here and also here 1 over square
root of n, which is totally fine, it's the definition of where you scale it, right, but
you have to scale this n by getting rid of the scale and ambiguity, so don't be surprised
if you see some other DFT which have different scaling factor, right, but the form is always
the same, right, the base is always the same, okay, so I think just give a recap before
introducing FFT, okay, but any question about DFT before I move on to FFT, you can ask me now.
Is it clear for everyone? Okay, good, now, okay, I give you another illustration, right, so I also
get some questions, says, okay, you have taught about DTFT, you also show a figure, right, if you
remember, there was a figure explaining like how you can go from CFT to DTFT to DFT, right,
so some of you are asking like how exactly are the DFT spectrum related to DTFT, right, you can
consider DTFT as a sampled version, I'm talking about spectrum, not time domain, right, but frequency
spectrum, you can consider DFT spectrum is a sampled version of DTFT spectrum, right, so here's one
example, consider this is your original digital signal, time domain, right, original digital
signal, if you do directly doing the DTFT, remember DTFT gives you a continuous spectrum, right,
not discrete, but continuous spectrum, so this will be your DTFT spectrum, right, continuous,
and also some of you may observe that this is actually a periodic function, in other words,
the function is going to repeat itself in the 2 pi period, okay, you can derive this because it's
actually a theorem says that if you have a finite length signal in time domain, you do DTFT,
the spectrum is always periodic, and this can be proved, right, you can try yourself, but it's
always like that, okay, and then if you compare to the DFT spectrum, right, this is your DFT spectrum,
you realize that, okay, in principle we should only have, you know, 8 samples, right, but you can
actually do a periodic expanding of the signal, and you find that the points you have in the DFT
spectrum will be the sampled version of your DTFT, okay, it only depends on how many samples you have,
right, but it's going to be a sampled version in a uniform spacing of your DTFT spectrum, right,
so if you draw an envelope of these functions, you are going to get the same spectrum as your DTFT,
right, and this DFT actually, you can also make it periodic, right, in other words you can actually
plus a 2 pi, but normally we're only interested of the coefficients in the first 8 points,
in other words in one period, right, but mathematically you can actually repeating,
right, by just adding another 2 pi, okay, so you can consider DFT as a sampled version of DTFT,
all right, so I hope this illustration helped you to clarify, and other things like, I also
get some email asking about this concept, I think I may have, I may not explain this very clearly,
that's why I want to repeat again, right, so resolution, remember we say that for DFT there's
one, you know, quantity we use to describe of the spectrum, we call it resolution of the DFT,
right, and we say that for the definition of the resolution is actually your sampling frequency
divided by the number of points of your DFT, all right, you remember that was what I explained
last time, right, but okay, and also one more thing is that this FS only depends on your sampling,
in other words how do you convert analog time domain signal to digital signal,
right, in time domain, nothing to do with your DFT, okay, nothing to do with DFT is just like
how you sample that, the N has nothing to do with your sampling, it only depends on what DFT you
are using, okay, so I hope this is clear, right, so that's where the two numbers come from, right,
one come from the sampling process, one come from what DFT you are using, okay, so this was
what we were talking about, but some people are asking okay how can I interpret this resolution
or another question is like is this number the larger the better or smaller the better,
all right, so I think that's a very good question, I probably didn't get there clearly last time,
to answer the question we have to talk about what is the meaning of this number, right,
when you divide the FS over N what does that mean in the spectrum, right, so in fact this number,
if you look at the quantity, right, it defines how are like two samples in the frequency domain
apart from each other, okay, so remember for DFT you will get some spikes, right, some kind of
measure, but they are discretized, so this number tells you how far away two bars are away from
each other, okay, not in the normalized domain but in the actual frequency domain, so if I give you
two bars, right, you have this spacing, how does this, what does this spacing represent,
so this number tells you what, just like think about the image, right, you have two pixels,
you're also interested, what does this two pixel represent, right, maybe the pixel,
one pixel represent one meter or maybe one pixel represent like I said maybe 10 centimeter, right,
so if you think about this as the digital image, right, normally a high resolution image means
a single pixel will present fewer, I mean smaller length, right, if I give you an image
that a single pixel will represent let's say one micrometer, that's probably some
microscopy images which is a very high resolution image, inversely if your image like a single
pixel will represent like 100 meters, right, we're talking about a very low resolution image,
so you can tell that the spacing actually is inversely proportional to resolution, in other
words the larger the spacing the lower the resolution, okay, I don't know whether this
makes sense to you, right, so similarly this number is also the smaller the better, right,
if you have a smaller FS divided by N that means you have a better resolution in your DFT spectrum,
okay, so this is basically representing the spacing, so like I said, you know having this
number, right, having this resolution can represent a digital frequency by simply doing a k times
FS divided by N, in other words k here means the kth bar or the kth spikes in your DFT spectrum,
right, basically if I'm talking about the fifth spikes that means five times this spacing,
that's what the spikes represent in the frequency domain, right, so if you know the spacing, if
you know how many bars you can you can calculate what is the frequency range we're talking about,
right, so this is basically what the FS divided by N represents, okay, I hope this clarifies some
questions we have last time, if you're still confused you can ask me, right, but this is
important, it could be some of the questions you see in the final exam, so make sure you understand
what this resolution represents, and if not you can ask me now, okay, yes,
so it's it again,
which regards to the sampling frequency and the frequency samples, right,
sampling frequency and frequency samples,
I see, I see, okay, so his question is that well, looks like this resolution depends on two things,
right, sampling frequency and okay, the A is not number of samples, the A is how many points you
have for your DFT, okay, so A is nothing to do with sampling, like I mentioned, right, FS is
determined fully by the sampling process, the N has nothing to do with your sampling process,
it depends on what is your size of the transform, how many points you have for your DFT, all right,
remember DFT you always have to define, it's 8 point DFT or maybe 10 point DFT, that is the N,
all right, so back to your question, you're saying that there are two numbers,
drawn to the depend, decide the resolution, so how can I, what number should I play to increase
the resolution, right, that's basically your question, so it depends on which one you can control,
okay, so I give you one example, right, so right now I give you a sum-hold signal,
I give you a discreet signal, already discreet, if you want to increase the resolution,
can you change the FS?
No, because FS is, like I mentioned FS is already determined and 100% determined by the sampling,
okay, what is sampling, sampling is the process converting analog signal to discreet signal,
all right, that's the sampling, so if I already give you a discreet signal, that means I already
sampled for you, the sampling is happened, it's done, right, the FS is fixed, you cannot touch it,
so if I give you a discreet signal and if you want to increase the resolution, the only thing you
can do is just by increasing, sorry, increasing the N, right, so this is like, you cannot control
the FS, so you have no choice, you can only do the DM, so you can only do the N, right,
but sometimes if I give you an analog signal, I say hey, do something and give me a DFT spectrum,
and now you have the choice, you can choose to, well, I want to spend more commutational
resource to do a more frequent sampling, in other words, I'm actually increasing my,
oh, sorry, I want to, oh, sorry, I want to, let me see, yeah, I want to decrease my FS,
oh, yeah, I want to decrease my FS, so now you can choose, right, you want to play with N or
you want to play with FS, right, so you have two choice, but what that means you have to look at
the question, why, if the question gives you something already fixed FS, now you have no choice,
you have to do N, right, but in principle you can play with two, so I think this is the answer,
right, so, but then another question, you know, if I were you, I would ask, it's like, say,
how can I play with N, right, so if I give you a discrete signal, how can I actually increase the
N, exactly zero padding, right, we learned this last time, zero padding, so you still use that
discrete signal, right, but what you can do is you can actually make the signal like literally
longer by adding zero, all right, if I add zero I didn't change the nature of the signal, but
I can increase my number points of my DFT, right, that's where the zero padding comes from, right,
yes,
oh, you're saying that, okay, so your question is like, if I give you a discrete signal, right,
so I do zero padding, let's say I double the number of N, right, so I do DFT,
then I do IDFT, I get it back, right, so what will I get, it's going to give you a zero
padding version of the signal, no, no, no, okay, yes, exactly, okay, so that's a very good point,
so you're saying that, okay, she's saying that, okay, you talk about increasing N, right,
but what if I decrease N, okay, now the question is like, how exactly do you want to decrease the
N, right, you have several choices, one choice is that I can do sub-sampling, right, I can,
let's say I pick one point from every two points, so now you are doing another sampling, right,
later we're going to learn, maybe not this week, maybe next week, we're going to learn
multirate processing, so this is exactly what we mean by multirate processing, you further sample
the signal such that I'm going to decrease the rate, so this process is going to lose information,
right, because you only keep half of the signal, so yes, you cannot get it back, but what I want
to say is that DFT itself, it's a lossless process, but sub-sampling, yes, it's a lossy process,
I hope you can differentiate it too, right, so if I give you a signal, you don't touch the signal,
you just do DFT, you won't lose anything, the DFT is just changing the domain, you won't get
anything lost, and you can always get it back, because any DFT followed by the IDFT, you always
can get back to the original signal, right, no loss, but if you do any kind of a, you know,
truncation, sub-sampling, which you are going to destroy the signal itself, that process
introduce distortion, okay, that will give you some lossy, but the lossy part, it doesn't come
from the DFT, all right, so I hope this explains, okay, good points, but one thing I can ensure you
is zero padding is always safe, where you do zero padding, you got nothing to lose, you only increase
the resolution, and you can always get it back, okay, all right, good question, any other question
you want to ask? So my advice is that when you look, I mean, for example, if you go to exam,
right, or maybe even homework, I have given some question about the resolution, right,
first understand how do you compute the resolution, what determine the resolution,
the other thing is if you want to change the resolution, what can you do, right,
it's not always totally free, there's always some restriction, but make sure you know what can be
changed, and what cannot, right, this is very important, and I already show you one example,
right, so discrete signal, nothing, pretty much nothing you can do on the sampling process,
it's already sampled, right, okay, any other questions before I move on? Okay, good, so this
is the resolution, so basically the conclusion is that the smaller the better, right, so you want
to decrease this number to get a better resolution, then of course the wider the spacing, the poorer
the resolution, in other words, when I say wider the spacing means I'm increasing this one, right,
I mean increasing this quantity, I will get better poor resolution, just like when you do discrete
images, it's the same thing, right, so okay, I also get another question that says, well you see
that you want to, you can increase the resolution, but what is the sufficient resolution I should
expect, right, in other words, you know, I can keep increasing this end, I can keep zero padding,
I can make it better and better, you know, you know, more, how should I say, higher resolution,
but how can I know this resolution is good enough, right, is there a number that,
something like a nitrous rate, right, is there a number I have to ensure to have sufficient
resolution, all right, I mean the simple answer to that is I don't have a clear answer, you know,
there's nothing like say, you know, sufficient resolution, right, but I can show you one example,
kind of talk about how the resolution makes a difference in the image, sorry, in the signal
representation, right, so you can consider this example, originally, right, if this is your,
okay, we started from analog signal, right, analog signal means it's before sampling,
so before sampling, we're talking about a bi-level signal, in other words, the signal will be
kind of oscillating between one and minus one, right, in the period of two seconds, so in other
words, the frequency itself is actually 0.5, right, I mean this is actually the maximum frequency of
the signal, so the spectrum, if you do a, let me see, so this is your original signal, right,
so the spectrum should clearly define the spectrum of spikes, right, so basically what I wish to get
is the spectrum that can clearly show the spikes, right, so I can, now I can choose to
represent this using a DFT, right, so but I can do the DFT in the low-resolutional way,
or I can do the DFT in the high-resolutional way, right, depends on how many, you know,
ends you are going to use, right, so now this is actually so called high-resolutional DFT,
and normally we wish to see this pattern because the spectrum like this can actually show,
wait, wait, sorry, so I think this is wrong, okay, wait, wait, DFT, oh, I think what they're talking
about is that they want to have sufficient DFT such that when they get it back, right, they show
clearly the spikes, so basically they want to see the spikes such that the frequency is very clear
that what are the so-called harmonics of the signal, right, because this is a square wave,
so some of you may know that for a square wave you won't have like something like a signal,
so it's only like two spikes, you have multiple spikes, and some of the spikes are just multiple
of the base harmonics, right, but this is something like we wish to see because every
spike at the frequency actually clearly indicates the frequency, but if you have like a low resolution
and then you want to get it back from the DFT to DFT, you will have something like
not very sharp spikes, right, like this, so this is a case that you cannot resolve what exactly is
the frequency of those spikes due to the fact that when you do DFT, you don't have sufficient
spacing, right, I mean you don't have like a sufficient small spacing to describe what exactly
is the spikes, so it's all always about when you store that and later when you restore that from
the digital domain back to the analog domain, can you still resolve those specific spikes?
If yes, that means your DFT has sufficient, you know, resolution, if you get something like this
means that you probably need to increase your resolution such that those spikes can be further
resolved, right, but what exactly is the frequency, right, is a really hard, the resolution is really
hard to tell, depends on the signals, it also depends on your, I mean the waveform of the signal,
right, but I can, I mean here's one example to see that if you don't have sufficient resolution
and when you get it back to the analog domain, what could be wrong, right, you will have something
like this, like, you know, not very sharp spikes but something smooth which you cannot tell exactly
where the harmonics are, so this is just one example to visualize, right, the consequence of having
low resolution, right, okay, so actually what we haven't talked about last time if you remember
towards the end of the lecture, I say well there's something important called fast Fourier transform,
right, it's one of the most important, one of the most important invention in the signal processing
community last century, it's because, well, DFT is, you know, theoretically simple, right,
remember we had just this one line equation to describe the DFT, right, but it's not really
efficient enough for computation, right, because if, I hope you still remember, like, when you do
DFT you are doing a matrix multiplied by a vector, right, so for those of you who know
a linear algebra, you know that if you have an n-by-n matrix multiplied by an n-less vector,
you have to do n-square, number of multiplications, you have to do a row multiplier column,
another row multiplier column, so in total you have to do n-square, right, so n-square is not
already a very good complexity, right, so what FFT is trying to do is that they give you the same
result as DFT, okay, no approximation, it's the same result, but it's going to save you some
computation from n-square to n-log n, right, so that this is why FFT is amazing, because you
got nothing loose, you don't lose anything, but you gain the computational advantage, right,
that's why for most of the device you can think about, which have to do DFT, they are always
doing FFT, because it's a free lunch, you save the computation, and there's no compromise,
it's the same result, okay, then of course there are many people proposing algorithms
to speed up the frequency, a Fourier transform, right, so there are many, we're going to learn
one of them, we don't have to learn all, but one of them which is, I would say relatively easier to
understand, and also I will try to explain where the advantage come from, right, why we can save
this computational resource, so it's actually called RADX2 decimation method, okay, so later
you can tell why there's a two, right, why it's actually RADX2 decimation, because it's always
divide into two and solve everyone, you know, separately and merge, but they keep dividing,
right, so basically all of these principles are, all of these methods follow the divide
and conquer principle, okay, so you have a complicated problem, you cannot solve that
directly, you divide it into multiple simpler problems, and you solve each of them, right,
this is basically what divide and conquer means, okay, so the fundamental, right, I can mention
is to divide the, let's say endpoints, where you have a signal of endpoints, I can directly do
endpoint DFT, but I don't want to do it, that's too expensive, so the idea here is to divide
the endpoint into two and keep dividing that, okay, until you have a single point, okay, why,
because single point, I don't know how many of you realize that, but a single point signal,
if you do DFT is going to be itself, I'm talking about a single point signal, if you do DFT is
going to be itself, no change, all right, so you, so basically the principle is to keep dividing
the signal into two, such that we're going to end up with a single point, so to do so we have to
assume that the signal will have the length equal to two to power of something, because only that
you can keep dividing by two, right, to reach the single point, some of you may ask me, hey,
there will happen if my a is not equal to two to power of something, you do zero padding,
you do zero padding to make it two to power of something, right, so this is actually the assumption,
we assume that we are dealing with a signal with the length equal to two to power of something,
like two, four, eight, 16, 32, 64, 128, right, these numbers, and then we want to keep dividing that
into from n to n divided by two to n divided by four and divided by eight, right, so imagine this
is the original signal, you want to divide that into two and then for every signal, every section
you also divide it by two and then divide it, right, so kind of dividing into every single pieces,
okay, so why we're going to do this is because we believe that by doing so the processing time
for every small piece of the signal will be very cheap, okay, so this is actually the fundamental
principle, so let me show you how, right, so consider you have a signal xn, okay, and this of
course this xn is in the time domain, right, every time I use the lower case, I'm always use the
lower case to represent time domain just for convention, right, so here all the lower case x
and y, these are talking about the time domain, all right, upper case, I normally refer to frequency
domain, all right, because right now both of them are discrete, but we have to somehow differentiate
that, so I use the lower case for time, upper case for frequency, all right, so I started the ways
endpoint time domain, discrete time signal, okay, so what I'm doing now is I'm going to divide it
into the even index and all the index, okay, I'm not doing like I say first half, second half,
I'm doing that say number zero, number two, number four, number six goes to the zero even index
sample, all right, and all of the, all the index sample number one, number three, number five,
number seven goes to the z, okay, so now I'm going to divide x which is n length into y and z,
so each of the y and z will have n divided by two length, n divided by two points, okay,
is it clear for everyone, like, you know how to divide a sequence into odd number,
odd sequence, even, sorry, odd index, even index, all right, so if I do this, right, I'm going to
end up with two subsequence, y and n, so y equal to x2n, okay, z and equal to x2n plus one,
all right, and the correspondingly, the dft of the x by definition will be this, right, I'm just
using the definition of dfs, okay, but here I can divide this guy, xn, into the two subsequence,
right, remember this is your y, this is your z, so I'm going to separate the two, right, so separate
this guy into here and here, okay, how can I separate that, well because this summation
cover all the n, all the choice of n, so summation is nothing but summing n terms together, right,
I just separate the summation into two summation, so all the, all term summation goes to the second
term, all of the even term summation goes to the first term, so I'm going to have two, like how
should I say, a varied version of dft, okay, and in fact these two will be the correspondingly,
the dft of y and dft of z multiplied by a phase shift, right, a factor here, but this factor is
nothing but just a phase shift, you just multiply by e to the power of something, it doesn't change
the magnitude, only change the phase, all right, so by doing so originally I have to do a dft for
my n point signal, now I can only, I can just need to do an n divided by two point dft for y
and n divided by t point of z, and just sum them together, right, and if you realize that if the
dft complex is n square, okay, I make it divided by two, so every side I will save one over four,
so I will get only one over four ratio of complex, right, I got one over four, one over four, sum
together, I got one over two, so I already saved half of the commutation, if the dft is actually n
square, okay, I hope this makes sense, so think about the dft, right, the dft as we explained last
week is nothing but a matrix multiplier vector, right, if you do a matrix multiplier vector,
the number of multiplication you need to do is n square, right, I suppose we have four points,
right, if it's four points I have to do four square number of multiplication, which is 16,
if I do directly the dft, now I divided the four point into two point and two point, okay,
two point dft only need four operations, so I got four plus four is eight,
so I'm reducing 16 to eight, this is how I can save commutation,
make sense, okay, so I'm not finished, I'm just saying that where the saving come from,
saving come from here, right, as you can see just by one stage of division I already saved
something, I saved half, okay, but let's complete, right, so right now I can divide the original
dft into two parts, right, so this is my first part in terms of x, right, so my x can, I can
look at my first n divided by two number of spectrum in my dft and then the second n divided
by two spectrum, so the first n divided by two spectrum can be written as this, which is the
form I just explained, right, in principle I can also represent the second half with the same number,
same form, but remember y and z only have n divided by two points, right, so basically I can only
assign value of k all the way until n divided by two minus one, so how can I represent the second
half of my dft spectrum, I can use the periodic property, right, I can do k plus n divided by two,
it's going to be periodic, right, so by adding this I can make the y and z into the second period,
so this is how I can represent the second half of my original spectrum, dft spectrum,
so once I have the y and z I have no problem representing my original xk and this is how you
can do it, all right, okay, think about it, right, so this equation explains to you how or why I can
represent x in terms of mathematics using, not directly using the xk, but indirectly using the
dft of the y and z, okay, this is how I derive it, okay, what I'm doing is just follow definition,
separate the summation to two terms and just naturally end it up here, right, but the issue
here is that y and z are both n divided by two term, sorry, n divided by two points, all right,
so my job is to represent the entire n point x, right, xk, so I will use the y and z original
period to represent the xk for up to n divided by two minus one, the first half of the spectrum,
the second half of the spectrum I can do periodic extension of y and z to cover that,
right, mathematically it's the same, but I just use the second period to do it, all right, and for
simplicity I can even represent this phase shift as the wn which is equal to e to the power of
minus j two pi divided by n, just for simplicity, I just use a dummy variable to replace that,
such that I can re-represent this guy in a cleaner way, right, in this way, so you realize
that when I represent xk, I just need to have yk and zk plus or minus some phase shift, right,
of course this term the k will change, right, the k depends on which index you are talking about,
right, but once I have the y and z and some kind of multiplier, I have no problem representing
the original x, okay, so does it make sense for everyone, yes, which one, top one or bottom one,
both of them, okay, yes, it's all information,
you're right, so I didn't do anything else, right, like you mentioned, right, y and z,
originally the time domain are nothing but sub-sub-sampling of the time of the x, right,
so the only thing I do is kind of I extract a sub-sequence from x to be y,
matrix, right, sounds like 18 to 8, 16 to 8, is something like some information between
oh you mean matrix, oh the matrix itself,
let me clarify, when you say information, if I talk about the signal, no information missing,
okay, we have the differentiate, are you talking about the transform or the signal,
right, if it's a signal, nothing missed, because what I'm doing here is I'm separating the old
sequence out there as the y, sorry, even as the y, all as the z, right, so all the original
signal would be covered by either y or z, so nothing lose, okay, if your question is asking,
okay, I'm reducing a 16 by 16 matrix to 8 by 8 matrix, am I losing something,
yes, because you're making a smaller matrix, but remember DFT contains no information on the
signal, right, the transform itself is a transform, it's a it's a rule, right, you specify hey this
guy called DFT, the DFT itself has nothing to do with the signal, the result of DFT depends on the
signal, yes, with signal, yes, WNK only to do with N and K, okay, so very good question, so
there's a misunderstanding when I say DFT, right, DFT itself just referred to the matrix,
so DFT is fully determined by the N, okay, we're talking about the matrix,
if I'm talking about 8-point DFT, that matrix is fixed, nothing to do with the signal,
but if we're talking about the DFT over signal, we are multiplying the matrix with the vector,
that result depends on the signal. So they may be, it's a different like a matrix, different size
of matrix, but after they complete the function, it should be the same function as signal, is that
complete the function should be, you mean, so when you write down the matrix with all the signal you
need, and you just like simplify the matrix or something, and you write the same function as
Yes, yes, yes, but I think you made a very good point, I want to maybe, I don't know how many of
you have the similar question, right, when I learned this I have this question to be honest,
right, I didn't really differentiate very clearly, but I think it's better to mention this, let's go
back to the slides I talked about last week, since you know you have this question, what I'm talking
about is the matrix, the matrix I'm talking about is this guy, I hope you still remember, right,
this guy, so we started by this equation, okay, we started by this equation,
okay, so this is the definition, right, this is called the forward Fourier transform,
where how you can convert a time domain to frequent domain, right, but we say that because both of
x and n are n points, right, so instead you can either choose to write let's say n equations,
I mean you can write a equation because k has to be equal to 0, 1, 2, all the way to n minus 1,
we're saying that if you want to represent all the xk in one shot, you can use this matrix
vector form, all right, why this is true, because by definition, right, if I multiply a matrix with
a vector, I'm doing nothing but multiplying the first row with this vector and get the first
coefficient, right, so this is exactly the x0, xk equal to 0 case, right, equal to the
all the Fourier DFT, right, and this is k equal to 1, x1 equal to the DFT, so when I'm saying
that 16 point DFT, I'm only talking about this matrix, okay, this matrix is literally called
the DFT, discrete Fourier transform, and in mathematics, when we say a transform,
it always a matrix, you can always represent a linear transform, let's make it straight, okay,
linear transform as a matrix, all right, Laplace transform, right, cosine transform,
they're always a matrix, so the transform itself, if it's a linear, should have nothing to do with
the signal, it's a fix, it's a fixed one, if you look at this form, right, the coefficients in this
w, do you see anything to do with the signal, no, because wn, right, this guy is fully determined
by the n and the coefficient, nothing, anything to do with my x, no, nothing to do with my x,
so you can construct any size of the transform, whatever you want, let's say 16 point, 8 point,
16 or 8 just change the n, right, so what I'm saying is that instead of doing a 16 by 16
DFT directly, what I just talk about is by reducing the transform into 8 by 8 transform,
does it make sense?
I changed the factor, yes, but I didn't change the signal, right, the signal is,
you still preserve the signal, I don't touch the signal,
no, I changed the points, I changed the n point, remember n is the denominator,
the n is not fs, right, fs is the sampling frequency, sampling frequency only determining
the conversion between analog to discrete, now here what I, what I think I talk about
nothing to do with the sampling, just the points, number of points I have for my DFT, right,
is it clear, I mean I just want to make it clear, when I say transform I'm talking about
this guy, all right, you can apply a transform to a signal, time domain signal to get its
spectrum, right, this is called spectrum, this is called the time domain signal, this is called DFT,
right, yes,
you are using a symmetric property to do the computational, to gain the advantage,
yes, exactly, so her question is that, okay, what we're doing, so basically maybe I translated it
in another way, right, so why we can gain this, right, the result, the gain cannot come from
nowhere, right, why exactly we can gain the computational advantage, indeed the reason
is that when I do this computation, remember, if I'm doing this exactly, I need to compute,
let's say the first row multiplied by the column, right, second row multiplied by the column,
I have to do exactly n squared number of multiplication, but why, because I don't do
anything, I don't lose anything, right, why exactly by doing this massage of the equation,
I can save something suddenly, you're right, exactly, there's some symmetric property,
I don't know if you can tell, right, this matrix is actually symmetric,
why is it symmetric, I mean, along this diagonal elements, right, all of these numbers are same,
right, here's W n square, this is also W n square, so when I apply this row and later when I apply
this row, I'm doing some redundant computation, I'm doing sometimes the same multiplication
multiple times, right, and basically why FFT works is giving you a smarter way to avoid
the repeating computation, so this is exactly where the saving comes from, right, it's due
to the fact that this matrix is not a random matrix, right, if I give you a random matrix,
then no hope you can save it, you have to do exactly all the things, but this matrix is a
highly structured, and this structure tells you something to save the computation smartly, right,
all right, but I want to make it clear, right, so when I say changing from, you know, n point to
n divided by two points, DFT, I'm talking about shrinking the size of the matrix, right, it doesn't
mean I lose anything because I'm going to still, let's say, separate the input elements, right,
into like these two guys goes to Y, here, here goes to Z, right, I'm still processing every
single number in my input signal, I didn't lose anything, right, okay, makes sense, all right,
if you have any question I can answer because, you know, I know some of you are very familiar with
this, if I say too much, you probably think I'm just, you know, wasting time, right, but
if you find something you feel uncomfortable, you want me to repeat, I'm perfectly fine to explain,
right, actually I would rather you ask me than we settle this before moving on, okay,
okay, everybody's clear, like, is it better? Good, good, okay, so let's go back to our business,
right, so we end up here, so we're saying that by using this dividing and the conquer strategy,
we can, let's say, dividing the original n point DFT, okay, let me use the pointer,
original n point DFT, if you want to directly use that big matrix, you have to do n point,
right, into a smarter way to compute y and z separately, right, y and z themselves, the length
or number points are only half, okay, because of that doing them is much easier than doing x directly,
okay, so you can do this but you may not stop there because you can do the exact same thing to
y and z, right, if I can save for x, now why should I do DFT for y and z, I can still do
doing a dividing for them as well, right, exactly the same thing, I can go from n divided by 2 to
n divided by 4, then keep dividing until I reach a single point, so this equation only shows you
the step from n to n divided by 2, but I can keep doing this, okay, so what you will have is, okay,
let's, this is actually the, okay, let's forget about keep doing, right, just look at this step,
so I can show you the mathematical equation of this step, okay, so mathematically this is,
this is what happened, I can also use a diagram to show you the exactly the same procedure,
so this diagram is exactly the same as this equation, okay, the only difference is that I'm
representing y and z as the input signal here, okay, so imagine this is my y0, my y1, blah blah
all the way to y and n divided by, sorry, n divided by 2 minus 1, right, so I'm input them into the
system, okay, so let's say if I want to get x0, right, if I want to get x0, I should get x0 equal
to y0 plus w to the power of 0 times z0, right, so in the graph you can find that this guy equal
to y0, right, the directly go here, sum up with the z0 multiplied by wn to the power of 0 sum
together, so this branch is corresponding to the equation, the first equation with k equal to 0,
all right, and then exactly the x1 here and here we're corresponding to the first equation
with k equal to 1, right, I'm just representing the mathematical equation using this so-called
diagram, okay, so later you will learn that this diagram is called block diagram, okay, why we love
it is because this is very good for design, right, because eventually mathematical form is for us to
understand, right, but later you want to understand something for manufacture, right, you cannot show
them the equation, you have to show them, okay, how exactly the signal is passed into from stage
to stage, right, so this diagram show you the signal going from stage one to stage two, right,
this is called block diagram, and normally the block diagram will have some fundamental components
like summation, you know, multiplications, and these are very easy to implement, right, in the
circuit design, right, circuit, you know, desired, you know, how should I say, future design or
circuit design, right, but this diagram is the same representation, sorry, equivalent to representation
as the mathematical form, okay, all right, so why we want to do this, I mean, why we want to use the
diagram to represent this stage, because I want to keep doing that, right, I want to go from
this stage into the other stage, right, for example, I already decompose my x into your y and the z,
right, I can do the same thing for y by further dividing the y into, let's say, y2 and z2,
same for z, right, but basically you have to do them in the corresponding way, and then, you know,
I can further divide my y2 into, you know, original signal, right, so you can keep dividing the
m point to m divided by 2 and divided by 4 until you have a single length signal, okay,
then you cannot divide anymore, right, it's only one point, nothing to divide,
but the good thing is, if you have a one point signal, the DFT of that is equal to itself,
so you can do nothing, you just leave it, that signal originally is the spectrum of itself,
right, so this is how you can, all the way starting from time domain, but you have to reshuffle that,
remember, the order is not 0, 1, 2, 3, it's actually 0, 4, 2, 6, okay, so this is something
people normally make a mistake, all right, this is not in the original order, but you can keep
doing this 2-point FFT three times to reach your 8-point output, because 2 to the power of 3
equal to 8, right, if you want to reach 16-point, you have to do four stages, all right, but the
principle is that you do not do the transform directly, but you divide and conquer until you
cannot divide anymore, right, so when you design this, you have to go from the output all the way
to input, but when you apply that, of course, you go from input to output, right, this is how the
so-called butterfly form come from, this is called butterfly form, by the way, so you can do this
in the 2-point division, sometimes people also do 3-point division, right, but for this class,
let's stick to 2-point, I don't want to complicate the story, right, but basically this is how you
can save computation and you can somehow, later I will show you, right, so you can actually go from
n-square to n-log n, okay, so, okay, so if you do DFT directly, you got n-square, right, and then
every stage, you should have n number of operation, all right, why, because every stage, you have to
do one multiplication, right, this is minus one, this is multiple, sorry, this is multiplied by
one, this is multiplied by w to n, w to power of zero, right, so for every stage, you have to do
exactly n number of multiplication, okay, how many stage actually is log n stage, all right, so
suppose n is 8, right, log n equal to 3, so this is where the n-log n come from, right, every stage
you need n number of operation, you have log n number of stages, right, this is where the come
from, but we'll get there, right, but I use this slide to show you the example of 8-point, right,
so you can read this, but they show you the step-by-step division from 8-point all the way to
the 2-point FFT, okay, but I won't repeat this, but you can use this example as a practice, right,
to see whether you do truly understand the divide and conquer strategy of this 2-point, sorry,
radix 2-point FFT process, all right, but it's the same principle, right, this is, I really
showed you the 8-point, but you can go through this mathematics process to understand how exactly you
can go from 8-point FFT to 4-point FFT to gradually reduce it, okay, yes,
sorry, tell me about what? Symmetric, okay,
we are totally ignoring the, what, negative frequency, or negative frequency,
for DFT, it doesn't really matter, for DFT, it's always fixed length, right, because, and also,
even if you are careful of negative frequency, it's symmetric, it's periodic, you can just do
another period to cover the negative frequency if you want, right, so it really doesn't matter,
we only care about that endpoints, right, this is the principle of DFT, you have endpoint input,
you only care about endpoint output, you can cover any frequency by simply repeating the same
pattern, yes, okay, good, any other questions? Okay, good, so this is the derivation of FFT,
right, and also, this is one example to show you numerically, right, if I give you a time domain
signal as 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, right, 8-point, how I can use my, you know, butterfly diagram to
generate the output, okay, I mean, again, I won't go through this because you have to try this number
by number, but I will leave this as exercise for you, but it's a practice for you to experience,
right, how the numbers can gradually go from the input by doing every stage to reach the output,
okay, okay, I probably want to test you on those kind of tricky numbers in the exam, but
you need to know the principle, okay, even if I give you a question, the number will be
relatively simple, trust me, right, but you need to know the principle, right, how this division
is actually works, right, all right, so yeah, so you can complete this example by yourself,
by gradually going from, you know, original stage, stage 1, stage 2, and continuously with stage 4
to reach the final number, so number will be very ugly, but, you know, that's how the DFT
actually give you, right, the same result as the actual DFT numbers, okay, and also, right,
I also want to show you that if you look at the spectrum of this guy, right, in other words,
the plot of this guy, remember, these are not the real number, all right, if you, even if you have
a real input after DFT, very likely you will get a complex number, the reason is this DFT
measure itself is complex, okay, every time you see e2 part of something is very likely, it's a
complex number, right, so the result will also be a complex number, and normally if you want to
show the spectrum of a complex signal, complex spectrum, you have to show that in terms of
magnitude and phase, okay, there are only two ways to represent complex number, real plus
imaginary or magnitude versus phase, right, for signal processing, more likely we're doing
magnitude and phase plot, right, the reason is magnitude is more important than phase, right,
so we want to know the magnitude and the phase separately, so if you recall last time we said
that if I give you a real signal input, right, I cannot guarantee the output is real, it's very
likely unreal, complex, but one thing I can guarantee you is that the magnitude will be symmetric,
remember, that real signal, you get a DFT, you get a symmetric spectrum, right, so here's one
example, you will get a symmetric spectrum like this for magnitude, right, but for phase,
it will be very tricky, right, for phase, for example this one, right, in fact this is a linear
phase, but you will see that well the line goes up but suddenly comes down here, the reason is that
I already reached so-called some boundary, I have to do a truncation, sorry, a flip sign
to the negative one, right, but in fact this is actually a linear phase, so later we're going
to talk about linear phase, but I just want to show that linear phase may have this sudden jump
due to the the range stuff, right, later we're going to see this, all right, so okay, most
important thing I want you to, let's even memorize this, right, it's the actual advantage we have
in terms of computation, all right, but first of all how can we, okay, what can we use to describe
a computational complex of algorithm, okay, how many of you have learned this, I just
wondering, you know, how many of you can recognize what I'm writing here, okay, you know that,
right, how many others guys do you, have you learned this B.O. analysis in your undergraduate
study, okay, you have learned it, I see some people raising hand, okay, let me just explain,
since most of us do not know this, right, so we talk about like one algorithm, it's cheaper than the
other, or one algorithm is more expensive than other, right, we have to quantify the complexity,
okay, so there are many ways to come to quantify a complexity of an algorithm, the most commonly
used one is called B.O. analysis, all right, so let me define what is B.O. analysis, so let's
first start by defining the g function as the actual number of operation that I have to do
for this algorithm, right, so g n give you the exact number, for example, 10 times, 11 times,
that's the g n, right, but sometimes we don't care about the actual numbers, we care about
is this function upper bounded by something, or in other words, what's the worst case,
what's the worst case this function can be, right, because the actual number of operation
depends on the length of the signals, depends on your, maybe even the quantity of the signals,
right, but what we care about is that we want the algorithm don't be too bad, even if I have a
worst case, okay, so this is where the B.O. come from, the B.O. analysis provides you an upper bound
saying that the actual number of operations of my algorithm cannot be larger than another function
multiplied by a given constant, okay, if you can find another function f n
multiplied by some constant, the constant can up to you, right, just give a constant,
which can always surpass the worst case of my actual number of operations,
this f is called the B.O. f n, in other words, if I give you say, hey, I have an algorithm
that runs as a B.O. of f n, that means no matter how bad my algorithm runs,
the number of operations cannot exceed a fixed constant times f n function,
so I use this f n function to upper bound the worst case of my algorithm, okay, so
is it clear for everyone? So every time you see B.O., you're thinking about the worst case,
the worst case of my algorithm, it cannot be worse than that, right, so of course,
if my worst case is susceptible, that means my algorithm is susceptible, right, I want to make
sure my worst case upper bound is something reasonable or something controllable, okay,
that's why we always use this to describe an algorithm, okay, so let's analyze, for example,
DFT, right, so I remember I say that if I directly do DFT, okay, so I still have these slides here,
I directly do DFT, right, this is what I'm going to do, I'm going to multiply this matrix with my
vector, okay, so I have to do a certain number of multiplication and a certain number of addition,
right, these are something I have to do, for example, I have to multiply the first row with
the first column, so I have to do n number of multiplications and maybe n minus 1 number of
addition, right, so you can count exactly how many addition you have and how many
multiplication you have, right, in fact, this is the total amount of operation you need for
directly doing DFT, okay, so it's end up with 2n square minus n, okay, so this is actually my actual
amount of operations, but I probably only care about the worst case, remember, only the worst
case actually matters, right, so in fact, there are two terms, second order term, first order term,
the first order term will not affect my worst case, the worst case will be dominated by the highest
order in the GN, in other words, this kind of quality can be upper bounded by some constants
times the n square, because second order term grows much faster than the first order term,
right, so because of that, I can say that my DFT will have a big n square complexity,
so these terms matters, you want to have this function to be as slow as possible,
grows as slow as possible, so n square, that's upper bound for directly applying DFT, okay,
it's actually dominated by these two, right, these two multiply together, okay, then let's look at
FFT, right, so if I don't do the DFT directly, I do an indirect way to divide and conquer,
all right, so what I was doing just now, right, let's look at here, right, what I'm doing just now,
like this, is that I have to do, you know, a certain amount of stages, let's say k stages,
right, but every stage what I need to do, I need to do one, two, three, four, five,
exactly n number of addition, right, I have to do exactly n number of multiplication,
so that means every stage I need to have roughly two n number of operations,
right, then multiply by number of stages, this will be the total number of operation I need to do
for FFT, right, makes sense, okay, so for n point FFT, how many stages I have,
so imagine, let's say you have eight, right, I do one stage, I can break eight into four,
all right, I do another stage, I can break four into two, I do another stage, I can break two into
one, right, so what I'm doing here is I'm doing log n, so if say I have, let's say,
n point, eight points, right, I need two to power of three to get eight, right, so number of stages
exactly talking about how many division I have, right, I go from eight to four, that's one stage,
four to two, that's second stage, two to one is the third stage, so I need three stages,
so that number is equal to log n, makes sense, it's division, every time you just cut it by half,
right, half, half, half, rich one, you got log n, okay, so the number of stages will be log n,
right, so this is where, okay, this is where this term come from, so you need log n, of course,
we're talking about the base two, right, so log two n, this will be the number of stages, but every
stage I have n number of operations, so sum together I will get n times log n number of operations,
so this will be my upper bound, my big O analysis will be n times log n, okay, so tell me n square
and the log n, which is more expensive? Do you know how to, do you know, okay, first one,
do you know what is the log function, okay, log, how does the log function look like,
okay, so let me just, okay, my drawing is terrible, but I won't have to show you this, right, but,
you know, forgive me my, you know, my terrible drawing, but basically, no, no, no, what is this,
okay, so this is my, this is my axis, right, so, you know, x and y, okay, what is linear function,
what is n, okay, n will be a straight line, right, like this, so this will be my n, okay,
what is log function, right, log function will be something like this, right, but the key here
is that log function will grow slower and slower, you cannot surpass the linear function,
makes sense, everybody agree, you know, basic math, right, so if I ask you, right, n versus log n,
which one grows faster, n, right, n is more expensive than log n, okay, now how about n square
versus n, sorry, n times log n, n square, right, because I just make it fear I just multiply
by n both sides, right, but because n grows faster than log n, so log n square will be faster than
n log n, makes sense, because of that, right, now what, what the FFT shows is that it's successfully
reducing the n square operation to n times log n operation, so it makes it grow slower, in other
words, the worst case becomes better, right, if you do FFT, makes sense, because the function
upper bound that number becomes growing slower, so you are making the worst case better,
you save commutation even if it's a worst case, all right, because of that, right,
this is where the values come from, right, so, so this is kind of better than n square,
so if you visualize the computational complex as the function of n, you will see that n square
eventually, that initially doesn't make a difference, but when n is large, right, the gain is huge,
you save a huge amount of commutation, right, comparing DFT with FFT, that's why everybody
use FFT, right, because we're not talking about like only a five point signal, we're talking
about the hundreds of points of signal, right, maybe a million point of signal, then doing FFT
is terrible, right, nobody doing that, so this is why in practice everybody will do FFT, but
when we analyze the process, we do FFT, because DFT is easy to analyze, right, but anyway,
both of them give you the same result, it doesn't make a difference, okay,
all right, it's better, because last week I just mentioned the advantage, but I didn't explain
where the advantage comes from, right, so I hope this one gives you a better idea, right,
why we have this advantage by doing the smarter way of dividing and conquering, okay,
any questions before I move on?
Yes, yes,
okay, so, okay, so her question is this, I guess you are seeing that do we have to memorize,
right, how how this function are, so, so the lady was asking like, okay, do we have to memorize
how these numbers are arranged, right, in principle you can derive it, if you know,
if you know how, if you know how this one is derived, okay, in principle you can derive it,
right, but memorizing that is not a very difficult job, I would say, okay, why,
I can tell you how I memorize it, I actually memorize it to be honest, right, but it's very
easy, right, for example, this is an eight point, eight point DFT, right, so FFT, so if it's eight
point, I have to do, you know, let's look at the first half and the second half, right,
so the first half will be always even number, even index, remember, why, because here is already
divided into even and odd, right, so all the even goes here, all the all the goes here, right,
so all of these numbers in the top half, upper half will be even, if you see any odd number here,
that means you're wrong, okay, and all the bottom half here will be odd number, you cannot have
any even there, so you consider every stage is like a reshuffle of the numbers, right,
so the first stage shuffle them into even and odd, all right, okay, so then what they're doing is
keep shuffling, okay, so here you are talking about zero, one, two, three, sorry, you know,
zero, two, four, six, right, but if you go one step back, you are picking the even number of the
even number, right, in other words, you are picking not zero, how to say, not zero, two, four, six,
but you're picking zero and four, because zero and four are the even subsequence of the even sequence,
I don't know if that makes sense, right, so you are picking, you are keep picking the even index
from the original sequence, right, so here it gives you all the even numbers, so here they
will say, well these two have to be step of four, instead of step of two, right, so it should be zero
and four, and then you know four and six, so four and six are the odd subsequence of the even sequence,
this is how I remember that, right, it's not very hard, but if you want that's how I memorize it,
otherwise you can always speak to the formula, right, but if you have no choice, you have,
you can think about it, right, but if you want to memorize how these are shuffled,
if they are keep picking the even and odd subsequence from the previous stage, right,
this is how I memorize it, okay, okay good, any other questions before we move on?
Okay, so I guess, so where are we, okay, so we're gonna take a break, maybe
let's come back around eight, right, shorter so we can finish earlier, right, so let's come back at eight,
all right, okay, thank you.
you
all right, okay, we can start, so as a promise, right, so I probably won't finish all the slides today,
some of them I probably will move to next week and also I will try to remove some of the components
because I think it's too much, all right, I will promise we, I will try to finish by let's say
9, 10 or something so that you can catch the bus, right, so give me a signal if I overrun time,
right, if I run out of time, give me a signal, but anyway, we talked about FFT, right,
there was something pretty much I didn't mention there clearly last time but it's important,
so that's why I was gonna spend time there, so, but all of these we talked about, right, FFT,
DFT, DTFT, these are something to do with signal, we're trying to represent the signal
in the way that they give you some, you know, features, right, useful information,
but another important aspect is the system, right, so signal is pretty much the data you have,
right, you want to process the data such that, or you want to represent a signal such that they
can be better analyzed, but we haven't talked about the system yet, so the system is actually
how you want to process the signal, how you want to, let's say, manipulate the signal, process
the signal such that they somehow satisfy your need, right, so now from now on the focus will be
the system, all right, so now we're going from signal to system, all right, so how the system
look like for, at least for this subject, we mentioned a little bit last week saying that we
have to say something constrained on the system, for example, we want to talk about LTI system,
if you still remember what this means, it means the system must be linear, all right, and the
system must be time invariant, okay, so this is always the assumption we make for this class,
right, so LTI system, and also, right, we will have multiple ways to represent the system,
just like we have multiple ways to represent the signal, right, we say the signal can be
representing time, in frequency, they can be discreet, they can be analog, so for system we
are also going to learn a few ways to represent a system, all right, so which is a better way to
represent depends on your task, right, so one way we can represent a system is called a transfer
function, okay, so transfer function is something to do with the frequency representation, so later
we'll get there, but transfer function, you can consider this as a, like a spectrum of the system,
right, like a filter, right, we talk about, for some of you have learned filter, right,
we call the filter like low pass, high pass, this is talking about the spectrum of the filter,
right, so the transfer function is always the same, like similarly, describing the system from the
frequency perspective, right, but based on the type of transfer function, okay, the transfer
function may have different types, right, but based on the types of the transfer function,
we can categorize the system in the following two ways, okay, the first one is to look at
what is the impulse response of a system, okay, so what is the impulse response, I hope,
some of you, all of you should know, right, or maybe, okay, so impulse function means I give
you a system, I inject an input signal, which is an impulse signal, okay, what is the output I have,
so this will be the impulse response of a system, right, so if the impulse response
have finite number of impulse functions, sorry, impulse in the response, right, so this is called
FIR, which literally means finite impulse response transfer function, okay, so we're counting the
number of impulse I have in my impulse response, if it's a finite number of impulse, that means it's
FIR, right, so you'll keep hearing the term FIR many times, because I'm going to focus on FIR
for my part, the filter design later, right, but there's another type, we call it the opposite
type, right, so if you have an impulse response, but you know, unfortunately, you have infinitely
many impulse, your impulse response, it means this is an IR filter, right, IR transfer function,
okay, so later we're going to learn that why, sometimes we also call FIR as a non-recursive
you know, function, IR is a recursive function, it's because later when we talk about the
difference equation, you'll see that IR, normally the right-hand side will also involve Y, okay,
Y means the output, so you have to represent the current time output using the past time output,
right, this is what we call it recursive, you have to recursively fill it back into your system to
implement an IR, but FIR, you don't have to, so FIR, you can just write the output as a function of X,
okay, so it's also called non-recursive, but this is by counting, right, by looking at how many
terms you have in the impulse, in the impulse response, this is one way to categorize the system
into FIR and IR, all right, but that's not the only way, it's not the only way to categorize,
you can also looking at the, you know, how the transfer function selects the frequency, right,
so I hope, I assume that some of you may already know this, right, for example, you can actually
look at the magnitude function of the, you know, transfer function, right, and for example, you
can actually, you may encounter some kind of transfer function in the way that they only maybe
allow certain frequency band to survive, right, in other words, if you look at the transfer function,
there will be one within, let's say here, low frequency range, right, so this is, this type
we call the low pass filter, in other words, that kind of system will only let the low frequency
component survive in the processing period, right, high frequency components will be killed
in the system, okay, you can have the opposite, which we call the high pass filter, means that they
kill the low frequency and they survive the high frequency, right, so it's exactly the opposite,
so it depends on which frequency will be passing through the system, you can actually categorize
them in the way by looking at the transfer function, and normally we call the frequency
that can survive as the pass band, right, in other words, if this is my transfer function,
the pass band will be here, right, can you see that, okay, here, it will be, this will be my pass band,
right, for this transfer function, the pass band will be the opposite, will be the
high frequency components, right, and of course, there will also be stop band, stop band means
all of this response will be zero, right, so the stop band for low pass will be the high pass components,
right, so all of these are looking at how, how the transfer function selects the frequency
components when it's processing the signal, right, so depends on the frequency, I mean,
there's also others, for example, they may not only look at the low frequency, they may look at
a specific range of the frequency, right, so this is, you can specify as a say omega c2 and omega c1,
this is the range, if they're only selecting a certain range, not too low, not too high,
this is called, this is called band pass filter, right, you can also make a band stop filter,
means that only the selected range will be killed, right, but very likely these four will be the
general cases you will be encounter, right, if you want to view the system from the frequency
selection perspective, right, I believe some of you, most of you should learn this, right,
even if you do the analog signal processing, but the frequency response can be a criteria to
categorize the digital filters, and all of these are talking about the magnitude, right, not the
phase, so just now I mentioned that you can actually look at the magnitude, you can have the phase,
but what I'm talking about is only look at the magnitude, all right, okay, so, you know,
the DTFT, right, so, okay, so when we say a system, right, normally we use a function for
some h to represent a system, the transfer function is normally used uppercase h to
represent a transfer function, in other words the spectrum of the impulse response,
but you can also do a DTFT to get it back to the impulse response, so in other words,
the impulse response can be obtained by a inverse DTFT of the transfer function, right,
that's how you can convert between the two, right, but basically impulse response
representing in the lower case is actually a time domain function, all right, transfer function
representing the uppercase, that's a frequency domain function, right, this is something you
must be very clear, and just now we are saying that for specifying the frequency, remember,
here we need to specify the frequency, for example, here we have to specify omega c
indicating what is the low pass we're talking about, what is the frequency range we're talking
about, right, sometimes we need two numbers, omega c1, omega c2 to represent a certain specific
range of the frequency, so all of these numbers, right, omega c, omega c1, omega c2, we call that
cutoff frequency, means the frequency that I go from surviving to killing, or in other words,
from passing to stop, right, that kind of a threshold we call the cutoff frequency,
okay, so these are some terms we usually use to describe the frequency behavior, right,
so just now I think one of you asked me, I think that gentleman asked me, say, hey,
all of you talk about, all of the things you talked about before, right, like anti-aliasing
filters, reconstruction filters, you are assuming a very ideal case, in other words, all of these
transitions are very sharp, right, suddenly you go from passband to stopband, so yes, all of the
so-called low pass filter, high pass filter showing up here, we call it ideal filter,
when I say ideal, I mean, I don't assume any transition, they can do a sudden transition
from stopband to passband, so this ideal case will have the magnitude of response equal to one,
exact one, in the passband and exactly zero to the stopband, so that's what we want, but not,
unfortunately, not always can be implementable, right, so that's something we're going to talk
about later, right, filter design, but ideal case, we always assume that they have a zero
phase everywhere, means the zero response is always, sorry, the phase response is always zero,
ideal case, I'm talking about ideal case, right, but this is useful in theory, because they make
things simple, okay, but bear in mind that if you see such kind of filters, like sharp transition,
exactly zero, exactly one, zero phase, it's not something practical, right, it's only called
ideal, okay, so like I said, ideal filter just like a brick wall, right, the frequency is actually,
you know, very sharp and very likely they are not causal, right, we talked about the causality
last time, if you remember, current signal cannot depend on future input, right, this is the causality
we're talking about, unfortunately, those ideal filters, they are not causal, there's another
reason like we, they will be never realizable in the finite length LTI system, because, you know,
causality, this is something we must have, you cannot see the future value, right, that's a
fundamental rule, so this is just to explain that, although all of these are ideal filters,
but of course, you know, they will have some ideal characteristics, for example, you can always do
DTFT, IDTFT to convert between transfer function and the impulse response, right, and all of this
we have learned, right, DTFT things, and the ideal filter can be represented in this way,
the magnitude can be one or zero, depends on, they are within the color frequency or outside the color
frequency, right, I won't really repeat, but basically these are some, you know, mathematical
theory for ideal filters and assuming the phase to be zero, right, mathematical way, this is what
just now the previous slide means, right, mathematically, likewise, this is actually low
pass filter, all of this is low pass filter, you can also do the same thing for a high pass filter
if you want, I won't really repeat, but you can explain or describe the magnitude of the high pass,
sorry, band stop filter, right, this is band stop filter in this way, and correspondingly you can
also compute the impulse response by simply a inverse DTFT, right, to get it back to the
impulse response, okay, but here is a summary of all of this ideal filter, let's make it specific,
ideal filter, they can be represented in the following way, okay, low pass, high pass, okay,
I won't repeat, but you can use this table as a summary of all of the four popular ideal filters
we have, band pass and band stop, all right, but bear in mind that all of them are not practical,
you cannot have them in practice, right, but they are mathematically simple and beautiful,
this is something we like it, so now talking about, you know, practical implementation, right,
we always start from the ideal filters, so ideal filter is something we can design,
we can start in ways, but then when you want to eventually develop something
realizable or practical, right, how can we do this, so or what compromise we have to make,
all right, so basically, right, we can never have this like a very sharp transition,
once you move to the practical, you know, filters, you have to do some so-called relaxation
to include a transition band between the pass band and stop band, right, so the big difference is
that in practice, you will never see a sharp transition from 0 to 1, what you will see in
practice is that when I move from pass band to stop band or maybe the other way around,
you have to have a certain range of the frequency to accommodate the transition from 1 to 0,
and the length, the range here is called transition band, right, when the transition band is 0,
that means it's ideal, right, but in practice, transition band will never be 0, it will be
something, we want to minimize it, but you cannot get 0, right, so this approximation,
well, permits the magnitude response to decay slowly, right, here's decay slowly from the maximum
to the minimum to 0, in other words, from the pass band to the stop band, right, so and also,
this is one one compromise we have to make, another compromise we have to make is that
even within the pass band and the stop band, you will not have exactly 1 and 0, okay, remember,
if you look at all of the function, right, very very very ideal, right, all of these are 1,
all of the stop band are 0, in practice, this never happens, right, what you will have is some
smaller deviation, right, kind of fluctuations around the 1, but they will never be 1, they will
be like up and down, up and down, right, so this is something we normally call it like a ripple,
or smaller fluctuations, and also we want to design the filter such that this deviation is
minimized, but never be 0, right, so these are the two major phenomena you will observe if you go from
ideal filter to the practical filter, transition band and the ripples, okay, so bear in mind that
when later when we talk about filter design, these are the two factors you have to bear in mind that
you want to use the limited resource to minimize the transition band and also minimize the ripple,
okay, so these are the two major kind of phenomena, right, and again this is actually magnitude, not
phase, remember we have two things, magnitude and phase, here we are talking about the magnitude,
okay, phase we'll also talk about separately, all right, okay, so okay, now phase, right,
so ideally we say that ideal kind of filters you are going to zero phase anywhere, right, no phase
change if you just apply that, they only preserve the signal phase, no change, but in practice again
this is not kind of practical, right, so what will actually happen is that there will be a
frequency shift property of the DTFT to impulse response of an ideal zero phase low pass filter,
right, so what you will arrive at is the following, right, so this will be the actual
impulse response, I mean if you directly do the inverse DTFT of this low pass filter,
right, you will get some kind of zinc function, if you don't do anything, right, remember last
week we also showed this zinc function, remember, like a kind of spread out from zero to infinity,
right, but if you don't do anything, right, this zinc function will give you a non-causal behavior,
in other words you'll get an impulse response from both paths and the filters, all right,
and also they give you infinitely long kind of an impulse response, so both of them will be
making the design to be unrealizable, so what you have to do is two things, you have the first
truncating the impulse response from infinitely long to finite number of terms, right, and also
you have to deal with the non-causality here by doing some shift, right, so the truncated
approximation may or may not exhibit the linear phase, depends on the value n we choose, all right,
so in practice even though we cannot make the phase to be zero, we wish the phase to be linear,
all right, so later we'll see that there's some trick or some rule to select the n such that
even if we make the compromise we can still land it at the linear phase filters, right,
so this is something we wish to achieve, but okay, here I just give you some kind of preview,
okay, we will have another lecture, I think maybe next week to talk about design, the actual design
of the filters, but here I just give you some idea like how, what exactly we need to do,
right, going from ideal phase, ideal filter to practical filters, okay, so I mean the principle
is that if you want to pass the input signal to a certain frequency range, for example here is the
low frequency range, you do not want to have a lot of distortion, right, basically you want
the signal to be undistorted both in magnitude and phase, right, such that your transfer function
should exhibit a unit magnitude response within the passband and also a linear phase response
in the band of interest, right, so this is something we wish to have, like no distortion in the
magnitude and only a linear phase in the band of interest, right, so to do so what we actually
need to do is that we need to make sure the zinc function is going to be like this, right, so basically
you kind of shift the major component to the past, this kind of will solve the non causality problem
and also you want to do the truncation which make the impulse response finite only within the window,
right, so these are two practical things we normally need to do to make an ideal low pass
filter to a practical kind of, I mean low pass filter, right, so but actually these major,
these two major steps also need to determine how much you have to shift and what is the
windowing function you are going to use, right, so this is actually something to do with the
filter design, but basically if you have a windowing function to truncate the approximation
and also doing a proper shift to make the, you know, filter causal, right, you will have something
like this, right, so for example this is a n, n equal to 13 point, you know, low pass zinc function,
this is n equal to 14 zinc function, so both of them because of this, you know, time shift and
also, you know, truncation they will become a linear phase FIR filter, remember what is FIR,
right, FIR is counting the number of response, right, in the time domain, if I have finite
number of response in the time domain that's FIR, so once I do truncation I can convert an IR into
FIR filter, right, because within the window the number of impulse or number of spikes are finite,
right, 13 or 14, this is FIR and also because all of these spikes are moved to the past,
this filter becomes causal, right, so by doing the shifting and truncation I can make originally a
non-causal, infinitely many kind of response into a causal and FIR filter, right, so this is what
we need for the actual implementation, right, but this is one example to show you that the
following doing this way will give you approximate transfer function which is not the same as the
ideal but good enough as the approximate, right, so we'll get to the actual design later, maybe
not today, right, maybe next week, but I just want to show you what's the gap between all of the
things we covered before, like ideal filters to the actual things can be designed, but basically
you have to get very in mind, you know, time shift and the truncation, these are two things you have
to do to overcome the non-causality and also the IR nature of the filters, right, so I'll also show
some simple filter examples, I mean not too much, so here's one example, right, I don't know if I
want to skip this because, okay, let me see, maybe I will skip this to the next time, right,
because next time I'm going to talk about design, so I will skip that, but I will get back to this
when I talk about the filter design, right, because I think these are two details, we don't have time
here, so I will skip here, but I will get back to this next week on the actual design, right,
but I want to directly go to the implementation part, right, so we talk about that, you know,
we want to implement the filters that can be realized in practice, what will be the actual
structure of the digital filters, so we have to, normally with the way we represent feasible
filters, we can use something we call it difference function, okay, like this, so what is the difference
function, so the difference function will be represented in terms of the output, the y, as a
function of both current time input or past time input plus possibly some past time output,
okay, let me explain why do we need my past time, right, so first of all, y always used to denote
the output, okay, for this course, I mean, for filter design, right, let's assume that y always
talking about the output of the system, all right, x refer to the input of the system,
okay, I use lowercase because both of them are in time domain,
all right, so the index of the signal represent time step, all right, so this n can be something
in the past or something in the future, right, so if, for example, if I'm care about the output of
time n, right, all the index with n minus some positive number, this should be the past time,
okay, makes sense, so I want to represent the output at the time step n,
suppose n goes to equal to 0, all right, so all the time step that is kind of smaller than
this time step will be the past time, okay, for example, if I'm care about my current time 0,
my time minus 1, minus 2, minus 3 will be the past time signal, all right, because of that,
I'm saying that here, even though this term involves some y, but all of this y are only the
past time output, why, because if you look at index, right, it always equal to n minus k,
and all the k here are positive number, so we are taking only the past value of the output,
okay, this is where the first term represent, they represent some past time output, they can,
we can use them to represent the current time output, okay, the first term, the second term x,
x means the input, right, but input can also involve current time input or past time input,
so how should I know, I should look at the index, right, so the index here also equal
to n minus k, but remember, be careful, here the k can be 0, right, if my k equal to 0,
it means I'm using exactly the current time input, so here the second term involves both the
current time input and the past time input, in other words, a general representation of our
futures, right, in terms of the difference function, difference equation will be representing the
current time output using the past time output together with current and the past time input,
this is a general expression for any kind of filters, okay, now what makes a difference for
IIR and FIR, remember there are two kind of filters, right, if you view the filter in terms of how
many spikes you have in the impulse response, IIR and FIR, these are two categories we're just saying,
right, so if you are talking about an IIR, it means this term, this term can be non-zero,
let me repeat, right, if you have a difference equation that do involve some contribution
from the past time output, it means this is an IIR, okay, so if you don't see this term,
for example here, right, if you see a difference function only representing the output using
the past time input or current time input, this is an IIR, okay, this is, this is, why,
how you can tell whether it's IIR from the difference equation, okay, all right, so this is
one thing we can, oh sorry, oops, what happened, okay, this is one thing, okay, this is one thing
you can use to tell, and also you can view the FIR as a special case of the IIR, why, because for
IIR if you let the decay, which is the coefficients, to be all zero, you can reduce the IIR representation
into an FIR, so in some way, in this perspective, you can actually view the FIR as a special case of
the IIR, right, makes sense, so this is how you can view it, right, so the actual implementation,
right, there will be correspondingly the design principle for FIR and the design principle for
IIR, right, and actually implementation depends on, you know, kind of either in software or hardware
form, right, depends on the applications, so now we have to talk about the structure, right,
so what is the, you know, so how can we kind of design this digital filter structure using,
for example, a certain principle to design, for example, FIR, right, so let's see what this
slide's talking about is a practical interest, okay, using an interconnect in the basic building,
so the first, okay, I don't even know what this talking about actually, but anyway,
so what I want to say is that, okay, like I mentioned, right, just now I explained FFT,
right, I'm saying that you can represent some filters in the mathematics form, right, if you
remember I showed you the mathematics form of FFT in the first place, later I'll show you another
block diagram, the butterfly diagram if you remember, right, to show equivalently what I
explained the mathematics form, so why people are interested in that diagram, I mean, of course,
sometimes it's simpler, right, for example, the FFT case, they keep showing how you can divide
the eight points all the way to one point, but also people like it is because showing this
diagram can also give you a straight forward way for filter design, because when you design the
filter, you are doing nothing but assembly of those components together, right, so by showing
the block diagram it's also the way to show how the filter is designed, right, so here's why we
need to learn equivalently, right, how can we use this block diagram to represent, let's say,
any filters in general, right, so we have already learned that you can represent a filter using
a transfer function, using an impulse ratio, but these are mathematics form, right, theoretically
they are good, but even if you know that it's not straightforward to design the filter,
so here we have to learn that, okay, you can actually use a diagram or you call it a block
diagram to represent the actual digital system that you want to design, okay, I think FFT is
one example, really that's one example you can use the diagram to represent it, but here I wish to
share with you the general way to represent the filter using the block, you know, block diagram,
right, so to do so normally we need to use some building blocks of the diagram, right, some of
them you have already saying in the FFT, for example this symbol means addition, you have two
input, you want to sum them together, you will use this kind of addition, kind of a block to indicate
you are doing adding two numbers, right, so normally the way is that if you write it like this, it
means the output equal to x plus w, right, so adding or addition is one of the commonly used
building blocks, another one is a multiplication, right, you want to multiply input with some number,
you will just write a triangle to say that y equal to a times x, okay, remember this triangle,
the direction matters, the input always go from the h and output go from the corner,
right, this is how it means, actually the orientation matters for the multiplications,
the last one may be a little bit new to you, right, you see this kind of block with z to
power of minus one, so this is actually called the delay time delay operator, okay, how many of
you have learned the z transform, I want to show you some of you learned z transform, right, so
for those who do not know z transform, so z is nothing but e to power of minus j omega, sorry j
omega, right, basically it's a simpler way to represent a Fourier transform basically, right,
but because of that we learned that, right, if you have a phase shift in the frequency domain,
it will be corresponding to a time delay in the time domain, remember we learned that, so
when you want to implement a time delay in the time domain, it will be equivalent to impose a
phase shift in the frequency domain, so that's why they will use a z to power of minus one to
indicate that I'm multiplying a e to power of minus j omega in the frequency domain,
which will be equivalently doing a delay of time by one in the time domain, okay, this is where the
z minus one come from, all right, but basically if you see a block with z to power of minus one,
it means all the signal will be delayed by one, right, it's very simple, so use these building
blocks, you can use them to represent, I would say the commonly seen filters for this subject,
and it's already good enough, right, like I mentioned, right, the advantage of using that is
it's easy to write down a computational algorithm by just looking at the diagram,
and also you can use this diagram to determine explicitly the relationship between the output
and input, which is easy for design, all right, so let me show you some, and let me show you the
principle of doing, I mean constructing the diagram, normally when you want to construct the diagram,
you have to first write down the expression for the output signal of each adder as a sum of the
input signal, right, so basically you have to develop a set of equations that relate
the input and output signal in terms of all internal signals, and then eventually you want to
eliminate the unwanted internal variable and obtain the expression, right, so these are basic
steps, so you can start from the mathematical relationship of the original signal, and you
break them down into multiple steps that can be represented using these modules, and eventually
that's how you can write down the diagram, right, this is how you can design it, but another way
you can, you can get for the question is that they can give you a diagram first, all right,
and they want to analyze the diagram and write down what is the relationship between the x and y,
okay, I would say this is the most common question you are seeing in an exam or in the homework or
quiz, right, so I mean, and this is actually very important, we have to learn how to do this,
all right, so let's look at this example, so as you can see this is a block diagram,
where you can tell that there's an input x and there's output y, right, so the entire process
here represents the system, basically the system processes the input and generate the output,
but of course it's not very easy to tell, for example, the transfer function directly from
this block diagram, because the block diagram only uses the fundamental building blocks, like
addition, multiplications, or maybe delay, right, so our job is to derive, let's say the transfer
function mathematically represent the filters from diagram here, okay, how to do it, so just
now I'm saying that we're saying that if you want to write the block diagram from the equation,
you have to divide the equation into multiple steps and make sure every step or every sub
equation are representable using the building blocks, now we're doing the opposite, right,
so we do have the block diagram, how can we get the equation, we have to first write down the simple
relationship at a certain portion of the diagram, so for example, I can start from this part, right,
I can tell that well this w1, even though this w1 is not the final input or final output, but
that's the signal I get here, right, I can tell that this w1 will be obtained by adding, let's say x
plus this branch, all right, remember this is a definition for summation, right, the addition operator
says the output equal to the first branch plus the second branch, the first branch will be x,
so I write x here, all right, the second branch you can tell that is equal to here, let's say this
is s2, right, you give a name, right, this is anywhere intermediate kind of a signal, say if
this is my s2, this branch equal to s2 multiplied by minus alpha, right, so the final w1 will be x
minus alpha times s2, right, so I complete the simple equation only considering this junction,
all right, so your step one is always write down the simple equation considering only let's say
one junction using those intermediate signal or variables, okay, you can do the same thing for
w2, right, w2 for example here equals to, so what is this, this is actually w1, right, w1 comes here,
become the first branch, now second branch equal to s1 multiplied by minus you know sigma, right,
so you can do them sum together, give you w2, all right, you do the same thing for this junction
and for this junction, you got w3 and you got w1, right, w, sorry, y, you got y, y is here,
this is coming from this junction, w3 coming from this junction, so you can use those key
junctions to write multiple but simple equations by considering the fundamental building blocks,
but make sure you cover all the building blocks, all right, if you don't cover all the building
blocks, you may miss some information, okay, now what's next, now you have four equations,
but of course none of this equation will tell you directly what is y over x, the transfer function,
right, so the second thing you do is to simplify them, okay, let's see how many variables we have,
we actually have w1, w2, w3, s1 and s2, right, so these are the so-called intermediate variables,
so our job is to cancel all of them and to only leave x and y in one equations because
that's how you can get the transfer function, so you can do some kind of simple trick, for example,
here you can easily tell that s1 here, right, how can I get s1, s1 will be getting from the
w2 multiplied by phase delay, right, so you can use the s1 equal to w1, w2 phase delay and also
s2 here is equal to w3 by phase delay, so these two will help you to kill two intermediate variables,
right, so eventually you are saved two and you will have w1, w2, w3, three intermediate variables
plus two, you know, input output variables, so now you can perfectly solve, let's say,
you know, how should I say, three unknowns with four equations which is definitely solvable,
so you can do all of this kind of cancellation, for example, you can starting from the second
equation to get rid of one of the, let's say, w3, right, also you can use the third equation to
get rid of some of them, so to come combine them, right, I won't go into detail, but I believe all
of you can know how to cancel variables, right, using multiple linear equations, but all of them,
by doing all of them, right, your job is to cancel or to kill w1, w2, w3 because all of them are
intermediate, you invented them, but you have to get rid of them, right, and only ways are there
constant in your final expression, okay, so your final expression will still keep the y and x
because they are the actual input and output, you can keep all of these very, the constant
which are introduced by the multiplication, right, and divide x, sorry, divide y with x,
so these will be your final transfer function, right, because transfer function is defined as
the final output spectrum divided by the final input spectrum, using the z-transform, right,
so these are, this is actually the overall transfer function, then you can derive from the equivalent
block diagram, all right, so let me just repeat, right, or let me just summarize what we have done,
so the question, what the question gave you is just a block diagram, right, the block diagram
uniquely determining what is the system, what is the filter, all right, so your job is to derive
the transfer function of the filter, so where do you start with, you start with the key conjunction
within the plug diagram, so very likely you can use the addition sign as the key junction, right,
so here we've got four addition signs, you can use them to formulate four simple equations
describing the relationship in that junction, plus there are also some kind of relationship
between, let's say, W2 and S1, W3 and S2, right, but here you actually have six equations with
how many unknown, right, W1, W2, W3, S1 and S2, so you have five intermediate variables,
you want to get rid of, you have six equations, you should be able to kill all of them, only leave
Y and X survive, right, so your job is to use all of this equation, get rid of the intermediate
variable, even though you can start with them, but you have to somehow remove them by cancellation,
right, you can do all sorts of cancellations you like, all the way until you only have the
constant or phase delay introduced by the block diagram to form your final transfer function,
so your job is to find the kind of a single line equation representing Y divided by X,
right, so this will be the final destination, so if you reach here you actually get the answer,
right, this is actually the transfer function, so this is one example, I hope you give you
how you can actually translate a block diagram to a mathematical expression of a transfer function,
but both of them are representing the same system, just two different ways, but you have to know
how you can go from one to the other, right, okay, so any question for this, I mean it's important
and I wish you can know, at least know the principle, step one, step two, step three, right,
so any question about this example, we're better clear now, all right, so okay one common question
is that, you know, you somehow get a fewer equation than you need, right, for example,
I only get the four, right, I find oh I have six, maybe five variables, intermediate variable,
but only have four, then you must miss something, okay, you will always have, let's say you have
n intermediate variable, you should always have n plus one equations, okay, if you somehow find
you got fewer, you keep finding, you must be able to find some more, all right, so the principle is
this, except for x and y, okay, all of these intermediate variables, let's say n, you have to
got n plus one equation, that's how you can solve it, all right, so check until you have n plus
one equation, then you can start to do this kind of elimination, cancellation of the intermediate
variables, right, otherwise you cannot get rid of all of them, okay, good, okay, great, so I mean
this is one of the important things I want to emphasize, of course, right, this is a general
way, right, general way we show that how you can go from a block diagram to get the actual
transfer function, well, there are some special type of block diagrams, so first of all, if I give
you a transfer function, there are actually many many ways to design the block diagram, so this
is not unique, block diagram is not unique, you can have multiple ways to design the block diagram
to represent the same transfer function, all right, and because of that, we sometimes, we don't want
to the structure of the block diagram to be arbitrary, to be random, we want the structure
of the diagram to be something compact, right, we want to minimize the design, so this is why we
need to ensure that the structure or the diagram is called, you know, canonical kind of structure,
okay, so what does that mean? Well, if you say a structure is canonical,
it means the number of delays in the block diagram will be exactly equal to the order
of the transfer function, okay, so first of all, what is the order of the transfer function, right,
here's one example, suppose this is my so-called difference equation, difference equation can be
easily transferred to a transfer function, right, by the way, but you can analyze the order also
from the difference equation, so this difference equation, remember difference equation, right
hand side got two parts, right, one coming from pass time output, one coming from the input,
right, you look at what's the highest order of each of the polynomial, okay, so this polynomial,
what is the highest order? One, right, so and this polynomial is also one, so in other words, the
order of this transfer function should be one, it's a first order transfer function, so the
canonical structure should also have only one delay function or delay block module in the diagram,
if you have a block diagram representing this transfer function with only one delay module,
that means that structure is canonical, okay, apparently this one is not because this one
you can find two delay module, right, that means this block diagram must be, what should I say,
redundant, so there will be some redundant structure in this block diagram, it can be
further simplified, right, so which means this structure is, we call the non-canonic, not kind
of minimized or not compact, right, because it used two delay to realize a first order difference
equation, right, so the reason we love canonical structures is because it gives you the minimum
cost when you actually pass this block diagram for implementation, right, you definitely want to
minimize the structure such that the implementation can lower the cost, right, this is the principle,
so I mean this is just some example for you to, for you to check, right, so you can't get something
like this, I mean, suppose this is your exam question, right, so say, hey, I kind of give you
this block diagram, right, so they want you to first determine the transform function and
want you to answer or to check, is this kind of block diagram canonical or not, all right,
so you can have something like this in the exam, so how should you do this, well you have to think
as yourself, right, how can I determine whether a block diagram is canonical or not, right,
the principle is to check or count how many delay I have and compare to the order of my
transform function, all right, is it hard to count the number of delays, it's not hard, right,
you can just say well I have how many, one, two, three, four, I have four delays, right, in the
blocks, the thing you do not know for sure is what's the order of the transfer function,
so the key here is you should always first compute the transfer function and that's how
you can compare, right, so how can we come compute the transfer function, we just learned this,
you start from the some key conjunction, junction in the block diagram for example here,
here and here can form the three junction maybe here as well, you can form a least of equation
using this junctions, right, and somehow cancel all of these intermediate variables to learn it
at a transfer function, okay, you have to get this first and this is how you can tell the order,
right, how to tell the order, well you look at the numerator and the denominator, so apparently
this for the both numerator and the denominator, these are second order, right, because the delay
got two, right, you got second order, polynomial, that means this is a second order kind of transfer
function, that means if this block got only two delays, that that's going to be a cononic,
right, apparently these doubles, so this is not a cononic function, a cononic structure because
it got more than needed in terms of number of delay blocks, okay, so always if you want to do
something, you think about do I have all the condition I need to make a decision, right,
to decide whether structure is cononic, I need to know two things, first one is how many delays
I have in the block, the second thing is what's the order of my transfer function, okay, the first
thing is easy to count, the second thing is you have to compute, right, so always compute the
transfer function, count your number of delay, compare the two, if they are equal, that means
it's cononic, if not equal, very likely you got more than needed in the block diagram,
that means it's actually non-cononic, right, so this is a common pipeline when you do the question
like this, okay, but of course you have to know how to compute the transfer function, right,
if you do not know how to do this, I cannot help you, all right, so you have to go back to the
process, right, example here, this example shows you how you can exactly compute the transfer
function from a given block diagram, right, and then this example tells you how you can link the
transfer function to the actual, you know, the property whether the block is, the block diagram
is cononic or not, right, okay, clear everybody, is it, makes sense for everyone, all right,
so make sure you can do this, okay, I say this twice means it's important and it could be
somewhere in the exam or, you know, homework or quiz, right, I hope you, you know what I mean,
right, so but you make sure you can do this and you know, make sure you know all of these definitions,
right, okay, so one last thing I want to cover, I finish this, I can end the lecture today, so
just now I say that, you know, if I give you a transfer function, let's say to represent a system,
right, you can get more than one block diagram, in fact you can get many, infinitely many block
diagrams if you want, right, but if I give you a block diagram, there should be a unique transfer
function, so it's one too many, right, the relationship is one too many, okay, because of that,
if I give you a block diagram, right, it's possible for you to find another block diagram,
which represent the same transfer function, makes sense, right, because it's one too many, right,
so these two block diagram, if they are representing the same transfer function, we call the two as
the equivalent structure of the equivalent block diagram, so the equivalent means even though they
look very different, but they are representing the same system or same filter, right, so that's why
we say that we define two digital filter structure to be the equivalent if they have the same transfer
function, right, so now the question is like, can I have a way to find an equivalent diagram if I
have one, okay, well I want to do this because sometimes one version is hard to implement,
I want to go for another version, right, maybe another version may be becomes easier, right,
so there are many ways to generate the equivalent structure by giving a block diagram, but we're
going to learn one, okay, not every method, but one method because it's simple, all right, so this
method is called a transpose operation, okay, so what does the transpose means, because if I give you
a filter like, sorry, a structure like this and I want to find let's say one specific equivalent
structure, I can actually do the following step to find the transpose of this block diagram,
so here's what I mean by transpose, right, so you have to first reverse all of the pass direction,
okay, so what is pass direction, if you see a line here, right, every kind of a signal have a path
and there's a direction indicating by this arrow, right, so this arrow means the signal goes down
through the multiplication, right, so the step one you have to do is make the direction reversed
for every path, okay, so if the original is like this, I have to go the other way around,
all right, so step one reverse all the pass direction, step two replace the pick off nodes,
so this is actually, this is actually a pick off node, means the signal will be branched into two
from one, all right, so replace all of the pick off nodes with an adder, so if here this is a pick
off node, make it an addition operator and vice versa, so if originally this is my addition,
I make it a pick off, okay, so just swap the pick off nodes with the addition, this is step two,
step three, interchange the input and output, so in other words this is going to be my y,
this is going to be my x, all right, makes sense, very simple, change the order, change the direction
of the path, replace pick off with addition, replace addition with pick off, swap the input
and output, right, so you can easily find something to call the transpose diagram, right, so why
we call the transpose, so I guess all of you know what is the transpose of a matrix, right,
you can flip the matrix and make it a transpose, this is like when you flip the diagram, make the
other diagram and by doing so, these two diagrams, even though they are different, they will be
equivalent, so they will give you exactly the same transfer function, okay, but we have to do this
in the correct way, right, so you have to exactly follow the three steps, if you miss anyone,
you will be wrong, so the answer will be wrong, but if you follow exactly all the steps, you will
get at least one equivalent representation and because of this is easy, so we just learned this,
but it's very useful, right, because it's very easy to get some alternative version, hopefully it's
going to be, how should I say, simpler, right, in the implementation, but I hope everybody knows,
right, how I can get from here to here, any question, ask now, right, so it makes sense for
everyone, like how I can go from the top, this is my original diagram, I want to find the equivalent,
this is how I end up with, so how can I go from here to the bottom one, I'm doing the three steps,
all right, so make sure you see the change, right, and make sure the change makes sense for you,
okay, but it's a very simple change, I mean it shouldn't be hard to understand, but if you do
this, you're well guaranteed to have an equivalent, I mean block diagram for any given one, all right,
so by doing so, right, I mean there are other methods for for equivalent, but they are either
very complicated or they may be based on some specific algorithm for structure, so we won't
learn it, right, and in fact, if I give you a diagram, there should be, by theory, infinitely
many number of equivalent structures, realizing the the same kind of transfer function, and you
cannot, it's impossible to develop all the equivalent realization, so we will just focus on the
common use structure for this course, so for any given kind of structure, you should be able to
apply that method to get equivalent, so you don't need to worry about other methods, right,
but there will be some special case which will be beyond the scope of this course, all right,
okay, so I will just leave this for next time maybe, because it's already not as a promise,
I'm going to end now, so there will be, you will see that there will be some slides removed from
these lectures, I will move them to the next lecture, right, so there will be update of the
slide, so don't be surprised if you see that, and I could have some updates for the next week,
so do check updated version once I make a change, and if you see some slides, I remove them,
means you don't need to worry about them, they won't be examined, they won't be taught,
you only focus on the content I cover in the lecture, it should be enough, okay,
okay, great, thank you, let's end today, I hope you can catch the bus, right, thank you, I'll see you next week.
Thank you, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye, bye
you