All right, so before I start the lecture today, I wish to draw your attention to these two
announcements, which was made earlier last week.
As I mentioned last week, we have two CAs, Continuous Assessment for this course.
One will be conducted by me, the other one will be conducted by Prof. Lin in the second
part.
But the forms are different.
I don't know why there were some students still raise the question.
I think I made them clear last time.
But please read the announcements, if you're not very clear about the two CAs.
Basically, I will give you homework.
So homework is not a quiz.
You will do that at home.
So you don't have to come here.
You will have more than three weeks' time.
So the homework will be made available to you in week three.
So this is actually, this is already week three.
So actually, did I say week three or week four?
Like week four, sorry, week four.
So it will be made available to you next week, next Friday.
The reason is like you need the knowledge, which we are going to learn starting from
next week to do the homework.
So even if I announce now, it doesn't really help.
All right.
But the one way you have enough time to do it, because the due date will be the Friday
of the recess week.
In other words, you should have how many weeks?
Five, six, seven.
So even if you count the recess week, there should be four weeks to do it.
So you should have enough time.
So you can use your textbook.
You can even search online if you want.
But mainly those questions for you, like a checkpoint for you to fully, make sure you
fully understand all of those concepts we cover in my part.
And you will find the questions under the assignment.
So I don't know how many of you have checked the NT Learner side.
If you go to the NT Learner page, for the content, this is where you can find the slides,
lecture slides.
And later I'm going to create an item under here.
I mean, this was the old one, I think.
But anyway, I'll update.
But this was the old one.
You will be able to find the assignment.
So you can download the question there.
And then you can also submit your answer sheets there.
In other words, you don't have to give me the hard copy.
You do it, you can either type set it, like you can use a late act to type it or a word.
Or you can just write it.
I mean, you can do handwritten submission.
But if you choose to write your answers by hand, make sure those answers can be read.
Because if I cannot understand your handwriting, I cannot give you marks.
It's very fair.
So it's your choice.
You can choose to type set it, like use words or maybe late act to do it, which is completely
safe because I can definitely read those typeset answer sheets.
But if you choose to write it down on papers, and then you can scan it, you can take a photo,
scan it, submit, make sure those answers can be read.
Because I'm not sure about everybody's handwriting.
But if your handwriting is terrible, you have to make it clear.
Because if I don't understand it, I cannot give you marks.
So it's your job to make the handwriting clear.
So this is for my part.
My part, the CA is not a quiz.
It's a homework.
I hope I clarified this already.
But for Puffling, let's go to the announcement.
So if you look at the announcement, Puffling also make another announcement.
So for his part, he's going to give you a quiz.
It's also 20%.
But he's going to give you a quiz.
In other words, for his part, it's going to be a close book quiz which is conducted in
the lecture.
I mean, I don't know whether it's in the lecture, but it's going to conduct it physically here.
So he's going to tell you more details.
But the forms is different.
For my part, it's homework.
For Puffling's part, it's a quiz.
Don't get me confused, because I do have some people ask me how many homeworks do I have?
Only one homework.
That's for me.
The quiz is from Puffling.
And my part will only focus on part one.
I will not touch the part two.
I don't speak for Puffling, but I think he's going to focus on part two, right?
Because this is actually how we separate the scope.
Is it clear?
Because I do receive some emails.
Keep asking me this.
But if you are not clear, you have any question, please ask me no.
Because if you email me, I could get delayed, because I may not reply you on time.
So don't complain.
If you have a better way to do it, just ask me no.
I can clarify any question you have.
Yes?
What do you mean by one?
You can do multiple submissions, but I will only grade your last submission.
Okay, so here's the thing.
He's asking, the gentleman is asking, how many times, how many opportunities I can submit?
All right.
You can submit multiple times as many as you want.
I'll make it unlimited.
But I'm only going to grade your last submission.
In other words, if I make my second submission, that's going to replace the first submission.
Okay, is it clear?
I'm not going to grade both.
Okay, doesn't make sense.
So if you find that your answer is wrong or you want to fix anything, as long as it's
before that line, you can do it.
Okay?
Is it clear?
All right, answer your question.
Okay, good.
Any other questions?
Okay, so I assume it's clear now, right?
Because Puffin asked me to mention this clearly, because both of us keep receiving emails.
I just want to make sure this is clear for everyone.
All right?
Okay, good.
Okay, so then let's go to our lecture today.
Right?
So this is my second lecture.
So let me first do a recap of what we covered last week.
I hope you still remember what we talked about last week.
Right?
So last week, I will quote us a review, because if you have taken any digital signal processing
course in your undergraduate, these are pretty much not new to you.
You probably have already learned them.
But consider we have a very diverse background.
Students come from very diverse backgrounds.
It's better to kind of review that first, make sure everybody have the same kind of a
baseline, right?
Unless you're going to keep asking questions.
So what we covered last week is starting from this signal representation.
Right?
We learned that, well, you can represent signal both in time and frequency domain.
When we talk about how we can generate so-called discrete signal, right?
Or digital signal, we don't really differentiate the two.
But I think one of you asked me the question, what's the difference?
So for this course, we don't really differentiate the two.
They are just discretized, sampled.
But we learned the theorem of sampling, how you can sample analog signal to generate digital.
Right?
And what could be wrong?
What is the requirement of the sampling rate?
Right?
So what is Nyquist condition?
I hope you still remember.
Right?
Nyquist condition says you have to have a minimum sampling rate in order to avoid any distortion.
In other words, adiasing.
Right?
So I wish you could understand what is adiasing now.
I mean, basically here, right?
Basically, adiasing is the distortion we are interested in.
And we wish to avoid.
Right?
And this is what the Nyquist condition is talking about.
It tells you what is the minimum sampling rate that you need to avoid adiasing.
Right?
Especially.
And we also learned how to do the DTFT and DTFT specifically to represent signals.
Right?
We talk about why we are interested in all of these, you know, varied version of Fourier
transforms.
Right?
It's because we believe that frequency representation sometimes are more useful than time domain
representation.
Right?
We talk about frequency analysis.
We talk about, later we are going to talk about low pass filter, you know, high pass
filter.
I mean, when we say low and high, we are referring to frequency, not time domain.
Right?
So I hope now everybody should be familiar with at least how to use DTFT, how to use
DTFT.
So I give you a summary about the three kind of most important transforms we talk about.
So CFT, I didn't talk more because I believe this is covered, pretty much covered in your,
even before digital, like analog signal processing.
Right?
Very fundamental.
So, but the difference is that CFT, in other words, continuous time Fourier transform,
dealing with analog signal.
Right?
Which, that's why we are not focusing on this because we are focusing on digital signal.
And it's going to give you continuous function in both time and frequency domains.
Right?
Input, output, both of them are continuous time.
So, CFT, or you call it CTFT.
Then what we learned and what we started with last week is actually DTFT.
Right?
Because DTFT are specifically for discrete time signal.
It's for digital signal.
And that's what why it's called DT.
Right?
DT stands for discrete time.
And it's going to take discrete signal in time domain.
But it still gives you continuous function in the frequency domain.
Right?
This is DTFT.
So, DTFT output, the transform domain is going to steal continuous time.
Right?
That's why you will need to do integration when you want to do inverse transform.
So, but then definitely we don't want to store continuous number.
Right?
As the spectrum because the computer cannot store continuous number.
That's why what we really use most frequently for digital device is DTFT.
Because DTFT is going to deal with the discrete signal in both time domain and frequency domain.
Right?
So, you can see the change.
We are gradually moving from CT to DT.
Right?
But you need to know what's the difference.
How one can gradually evolve coming from the original CTFT, original or progressively
to the DTFT that we want to really use in practice.
All right?
So, use this as a checkpoint for you to organize all of the knowledge we learned.
And basically you need to have this understanding on the time frequency representation of the
signal.
That's what we focused on.
Right?
DTFT.
And actually the two things we are really using is DTFT and FTFT in digital device.
Right?
So, one last thing is that we talk about frequency.
And there are two frequencies.
Okay?
First you can represent frequency in terms of either hertz or radian.
Right?
That's why you use F and omega correspondingly.
I mean you can also convert them by type multiply two pi.
Right?
Just the different units.
And we also say that one can use your sampling frequency to normalize them.
Right?
So, you can convert them in the period, I mean in the duration of one.
In other words, you can normalize them so that they don't really vary in terms of scale.
Right?
So, you have to be very careful whether we're talking about normalized frequency or unnormalized
frequency.
But the difference is just dividing the sampling frequency.
Right?
But in the question, they can give you either.
They can give you normalized.
They can also give you unnormalized version.
All right?
So, these are basically the important things we learned last week.
So last week, if you remember, right, we ended with the introduction of DTFT.
Right?
This is a portfolio transform.
So, I give you a quick recap.
Right?
So, basically, you need to know these two equations.
One is the forward transform, right?
Going from time domain to frequency domain.
And sometimes we also call it an analysis transform because we're analyzing the signal
to get the frequency components.
So, you can consider the frequency spectrum as an analysis of the time domain signal.
Right?
You want to see whether this kind of very strong in low frequency or very strong in high frequency.
It's an analysis.
Okay?
So, but pay attention to that.
DTFT always is dealing with some finite number of points.
Okay?
You cannot have infinitely.
You can in theory, but these are going to be periodic.
Right?
But most likely, we're talking about endpoint DFT.
Remember, we say that you can actually use a matrix, square matrix to represent a DFT.
And the size of the matrix is determined by how many points you have.
For endpoints, DFT, you have to have an end-by-end matrix.
All right?
So, it's always endpoint.
And the number of time samples, in other words, the length of your time domain signal,
it's always equal to the number of samples in frequency domain.
So, no matter how you do this transform, right?
Inverse transform, forward transform, it doesn't change the number of points you have.
Okay?
So, that's why your, if you remember, right?
So, if DFT matrix is always a square matrix, because dimension is no change.
It's still end dimension.
Right?
So, this is the second point.
And you know, you can also do this end samples using DFT, but they have to be within a DFT
window.
In other words, you can have a longer, you know, longer size of signal.
But when you do the DFT, you have to do some kind of windowing or truncation to make them
within.
Right?
So, a common way people dealing with maybe a relatively longer signal.
So, when you do inverse DFT, right?
Again, it's going to be endpoint.
Right?
But if you compare the form of the forward and inverse, you realize that there are two
difference.
One is the base.
Right?
Forward transform, you have to do minus sign in the exponential.
Inverse transform, there's no minus sign.
That's the, basically, the base function is actually the opposite.
Right?
And another thing is the scaling.
So, for our subject, we use the version that you don't scale in the forward transform and
you scale it back by multiplying of 1 over n to scale it to original.
Right?
So, this scaling factor 1 over n, it's just to ensure that you can get back to the original
signal without ending scaling ambiguity.
Okay?
But you may find the so-called DFT in other contexts.
They do 1 over n square root, square root n here and also here 1 over square root of
n, which is totally fine.
It's the definition of where you scale it.
Right?
But you have to scale this n by getting rid of the scale and ambiguity.
So don't be surprised if you see some other DFT which have different scaling factor.
Right?
But the form is always the same.
The base is always the same.
Okay?
So, I think just give a recap before introducing FFT.
Any question about DFT before I move on to FFT?
You can ask me now.
Is it clear for everyone?
Okay, good.
Now, okay, I give you another illustration.
Right?
So, I also get some questions.
It says, okay, you have taught about DFT.
You also show a figure, right?
If you remember, there was a figure explaining like how you can go from CFT to DFT to DFT.
Right?
So, some of you are asking like how exactly are the DFT spectrum related to DFT?
You can consider DFT as a sampled version.
I'm talking about spectrum, not time domain, right?
But frequency spectrum.
You can consider DFT spectrum is a sampled version of DFT spectrum.
Right?
So, here's one example.
Consider this is your original digital signal, time domain, right?
Original digital signal.
If you do directly doing the DFT, remember DFT give you a continuous spectrum, right?
Not discrete, but continuous spectrum.
So, this will be your DFT spectrum, right?
Continuous and also, some of you may observe that this is actually a periodic function.
In other words, the function is going to repeat itself in the 2 pi period.
Okay?
You can derive this because it's actually a theorem says that if you have a finite
length signal in time domain, you do DFT, the spectrum is always periodic.
And this can be proved, right?
You can try yourself, but it's always like that.
Okay?
And then, if you compare to the DFT spectrum, right?
This is your DFT spectrum.
You realize that, okay, in principle, we should only have, you know, 8 samples, right?
But you can actually do a periodic expanding of the signal.
And you find that the points you have in the DFT spectrum will be the sampled version
of your DTFT.
Okay?
It only depends on how many samples you have, right?
But it's going to be a sampled version in a uniform spacing of your DTFT spectrum, right?
So if you draw an envelope of these functions, you are going to get the same spectrum as
your DTFT, right?
And this DFT, actually, you can also make it periodic, right?
In other words, you can actually plus a 2 pi, but normally we are only interested of
the coefficients in the first 8 points.
In other words, in one period, right?
But mathematically, you can actually repeat it, right, by just adding another 2 pi.
Okay?
So you can consider DFT as a sampled version of DTFT.
All right?
So this illustration helps you to clarify.
And other things, like, I also get some email asking about this concept.
And I think I may have...
I may not explain this very clearly.
That's why I want to repeat again, right?
So resolution.
Remember, we say that for DFT, there is one quantity we use to describe of the spectrum.
We call it resolution of the DFT, right?
And we say that for the definition of the resolution is actually your sampling frequency
divided by the number of points of your DFT.
All right?
You remember that was what I explained last time, right?
But, okay, and also one more thing is that this FS only depends on your sampling.
In other words, how do you convert analog time domain signal to digital signal, right,
in time domain?
Nothing to do with your DFT.
Okay?
Nothing to do with DFT is just like how you sample that.
The N has nothing to do with your sampling.
It only depends on what DFT you are using.
Okay?
So I hope this is clear, right?
So that's where the two numbers come from, right?
One come from the sampling process.
One come from what DFT you are using.
Okay?
So this was what we're talking about.
But some people are asking, okay, how can I interpret this resolution?
Or another question is like, is this number the larger the better or smaller the better?
All right.
So I think that's a very good question.
I probably didn't get there clearly last time.
To answer the question, we have to talk about what is the meaning of this number, right?
When you divide it into FS over N, what does that mean in the spectrum?
Right?
So in fact, this number, if you look at the quantity, right, it defines how are like two
samples in a frequency domain apart from each other?
Okay?
So remember for DFT you will get some spikes, right?
Some kind of measure, but they are discretized.
So this number tells you how far away two bars are away from each other.
Okay?
Not in the normalized domain, but in the actual frequency domain.
So if I give you two bars, right, you have this spacing.
How does this, what does this spacing represent?
So this number tells you what, just like think about the image, right?
You have two pixels.
You're also interested, what does this two pixel represent?
Right?
Maybe the pixel, one pixel represents one meter.
Or maybe one pixel represents like I said, maybe 10 centimeter, right?
So if you think about this as the digital image, right?
Normally a high resolution image means a single pixel will present fewer, I mean smaller
length, right?
If I give you an image that a single pixel will represent, let's say, one micrometer,
that's probably some microscope images, which is a very high resolution image.
Conversely, if your image, like a single pixel, represents like 100 meters, right?
We're talking about a very low resolution image.
So you can tell that the spacing actually is inversely proportional to resolution.
In other words, the larger the spacing, the lower the resolution.
Okay?
I don't know whether this makes sense to you, right?
So similarly, this number is also the smaller the better, right?
If you have a smaller FS divided by N, that means you have a better resolution in your
DFT spectrum.
Okay?
So this basically represents the spacing.
So like I said, you know, having this number, right?
Having this resolution can represent a digital frequency by simply doing a K times FS divided
by N. In other words, K here means the K bar or the K spikes in your DFT spectrum.
Basically, if I'm talking about the fifth spikes, that means five times this spacing,
that's what the spikes represent in the frequency domain.
So if you know the spacing, if you know how many bars you can calculate, what is the frequency
range you were talking about.
So this is basically what the FS divided by N represents.
Okay?
I hope this clarifies some questions we have last time.
If you're still confused, you can ask me, right?
But this is important.
It could be some of the questions you see in the final exam.
So make sure you understand what this resolution represents.
And if not, you can ask me now.
Okay?
Yes?
So it's said again?
Somebody frequency and frequency samples.
I see.
That's okay.
So his question is that, well, it looks like this resolution depends on two things.
The N is not number of samples.
The N is how many points you have for your DFT.
So N, nothing to do with sampling.
Like I mentioned, FS is determined fully by the sampling process.
The N has nothing to do with your sampling process.
It depends on what is your size of the transform, how many points you have for your DFT.
Remember, DFT, you always have to define.
It's eight points DFT or maybe 10 points DFT.
That is the N.
All right.
So back to your question.
You're saying that there are two numbers.
They decide the resolution.
So how can I, what number should I play to increase the resolution?
That's basically your question.
So it depends on which one you can control.
Okay?
So I'll give you one example.
Right?
So right now, I give you a sum-hold signal.
I give you a disc-grade signal.
Already disc-grade.
If you want to increase the resolution, can you change the FS?
No, because FS is, like I mentioned, FS is already determined and 100% determined by
the sampling.
Okay, what is sampling?
Sampling is the process converting analog signal to disc-grade signal.
All right.
That's the sampling.
So if I already give you a disc-grade signal, that means I already sampled the resolution.
I sampled for you.
The sampling is done.
Right?
The FS is fixed.
You cannot touch it.
So if I give you a disc-grade signal, and if you want to increase the resolution, the
only thing you can do is just by increasing, sorry, increasing the N. Right?
So this is like, you cannot control the FS, so you have no choice.
You can only do the Dn.
So you can only do the N. Right?
But sometimes if I give you an analog signal, I say, hey, do something and give me a DFT
pattern.
And now you have the choice.
You can choose to, well, I want to spend more computational resource to do a more frequent
sampling.
In other words, I'm actually increasing my, oh, sorry, I want to, oh, sorry, I want to,
let me see.
Yeah, I want to decrease my FS.
Oh, yeah, I want to decrease my FS.
So now you can choose.
Right?
You want to play with N or you want to play with FS.
So you have two choices.
But what it means, you have to look at the question.
Right?
If the question gives you something already fixed FS, now you have no choice.
You have to do N. Right?
But in principle, you can play with two.
So I think this is the answer.
Right?
So by the end of another question, you know, if I were you, I would ask, it's like, say,
how can I play with N?
Right?
So if I give you a discrete signal, how can I actually increase the N?
Exactly zero padding.
Right?
We learned this last time, zero padding.
So you still use that discrete signal.
Right?
So what you can do is you can actually make the signal like literally longer by adding
zero.
All right?
If I add zero, I didn't change the nature of the signal.
But I can increase my number of points of my DFT.
Right?
That's where the zero padding comes from.
Yes?
So your question is like, if I give you a discrete signal, right?
So I do zero padding.
Let's say I double the number of N. Right?
So I do DFT.
Then I do IDFT.
I get it back.
Right?
So what will I get?
It's going to give you a zero padding version of the signal.
So we don't get any information loss?
No, no, no.
But if I decrease the points of the DFT, so...
Oh, okay.
Yes?
Exactly.
Okay.
So that's a very good point.
So you are saying that, okay, she's saying that, okay, you talk about increasing N. Right?
But why if I decrease N?
Okay.
Now the question is like, how exactly do you want to decrease the N?
Right?
You have several choices.
One choice is that I can do sub-sumpointing.
Right?
I can...
Let's say I pick one point from every two points.
So now you are doing another sumpointing.
Right?
Later on, we're going to learn, maybe not this week.
Maybe next week, we're going to learn multirate processing.
So this is exactly what we mean by multirate processing.
You further sample the signal such that I'm going to decrease the rate.
So this process is going to lose information, right?
Because you only keep half of the signal.
So yes, you cannot get it back.
But what I want to say is that DFT itself, it's a lossless process.
But sub-sumpointing, yes, it's a lossy process.
I hope you can differentiate the two.
Right?
So if I give you a signal, you don't touch the signal.
You just do DFT.
You won't lose anything.
The DFT is just changing the domain.
You won't get anything lost.
And you can always get it back.
Because any DFT followed by the IDFT, you always can get back to original signal.
Right?
No loss.
But if you do any kind of truncation, sub-sumpointing, which you are going to destroy the signal
itself, that process introduce distortion.
OK?
That will give you some lossy.
But the lossy part doesn't come from the DFT.
All right?
So I hope this explains.
OK, good point.
But one thing I can ensure you is zero padding is always safe.
You do zero padding, you got nothing to lose.
You only increase the resolution.
And you can always get it back.
OK?
All right.
Good question.
Any other question you want to ask?
So my advice is that when you look, I mean, for example, if you go to exam, or maybe even
homework, I have given you some question about the resolution.
Right?
First, understand how do you compute the resolution?
What determines the resolution?
The other thing is if you want to change the resolution, what can you do?
Right?
It's not always totally free.
There's always some restriction.
But make sure you know what can be changed and what cannot.
Right?
This is very important.
And I already show you one example.
Right?
So discrete signal, pretty much nothing you can do on the sampling process is already
sampled.
Right?
OK?
Any other questions before I move on?
OK, good.
So this is the resolution.
So basically the conclusion is that the smaller the better.
Right?
So if I increase this number to get a better resolution, then of course the wider the spacing,
the poorer the resolution.
In other words, when I say wider the spacing means I'm increasing this one.
Right?
I mean, increasing this quantity, I will get a better, poorer resolution.
Just like when you do discrete images.
It's the same thing.
Right?
So, OK.
I also get another question that says, well, you see that you can increase the resolution.
But what is the sufficient resolution I should expect?
Right?
In other words, I can keep increasing this n.
I can keep zero padding.
I can make it better and better, more, higher resolution.
But how can I know this resolution is good enough?
Right?
Is there a number that, something like a NICRIS rate?
Is there a number I have to ensure to have sufficient resolution?
All right.
I mean, the simple answer to that is I don't have a clear answer.
There's nothing like, say, sufficient resolution.
Right?
So, let me show you one example.
Kind of talk about how the resolution makes a difference in the image, sorry, in the
signal representation.
Right?
So, you can consider this example.
Originally, right, if this is your, OK, we started from analog signal.
Right?
Analog signal means it's before sampling.
So, before sampling, we're talking about a bi-level signal.
In other words, the signal will be kind of oscillating between 1 and minus 1.
Right?
In the period of two seconds.
So, in other words, the frequency itself is actually 0.5.
Right?
I mean, this is actually the maximum frequency of the signal.
So, the spectrum, if you do a, let me see.
So this is your original signal.
Right?
So, the spectrum should clearly define the spectrum of spikes.
So, basically, what I wish to get is the, in the spectrum that can clearly show the
spikes.
Right?
So, I can, now I can choose to represent this using a DFT.
So, but I can do the DFT in the low-resolutional way, or I can do the DFT in the high-resolutional
way.
Right?
Depends on how many, you know, ends you are going to use.
So, now, this is actually so called high-resolutional DFT.
And normally we wish to see this pattern because the spectrum like this can actually
show, wait, wait, sorry, I think this is wrong.
Okay.
Wait, wait, wait, DFT is, oh, I think what they're talking about is that they want to
have sufficient DFT such that when they get it back, right, they show clearly the spikes.
So, basically, they want to see the spikes such that the frequency is very clear that
one of the so-called harmonics of the signal.
Right?
Because this is a square wave.
So, some of you may know that for a square wave, you won't have like something like a
signal, so it's only like two spikes.
You have multiple spikes.
And some of the spikes are just multiple of the base harmonics.
Right?
But this is something like we wish to see because every spikes at the frequency actually clearly
indicates the frequency.
But if you have like a low resolution and then you want to get it back from the DFT to DFT,
you will have something like a not very sharp spikes, right, like this.
So, this is a case that you cannot resolve what exactly is the frequency of those spikes
due to the fact that when you do DFT, you don't have sufficient spacing, right?
I mean, you don't have like a sufficient small spacing to describe what exactly is the spikes.
So, it's always about when you store that and later when you restore that from the digital
domain back to the analog domain, can you still resolve those specific spikes?
If yes, that means your DFT has sufficient, you know, resolution.
If you get something like this, it means that you probably need to increase your resolution
such that those spikes can be further resolved, right?
But what exactly is the frequency, right?
It's a really hard, the resolution is really hard to tell.
Depends on the signals.
It also depends on your, I mean, the waveform of the signal, right?
But I can, I mean, here's one example to see that if you don't have sufficient resolution
and when you get it back to the analog domain, what could be wrong, right?
You will have something like this, like, you know, not very sharp spikes, but something
smooth which you cannot tell exactly where the harmonics are.
So, this is just one example to visualize, right?
The consequence of having low resolution, right?
Okay.
Okay, so actually what we haven't talked about last time, if you remember, towards the end
of the lecture, I say, well, there's something important called the fast Fourier transform,
right?
One of the most important, one of the most important invention in the signal processing
community last century is because, well, DFT is, you know, theoretically simple, right?
Remember, we have just this one line equation to describe the DFT, right?
But it's not really efficient enough for computation, right?
Because if, I hope you still remember, like, when you do DFT, you are doing a matrix multiplied
by a vector, right?
So for those of you who know a linear algebra, you know that if you have an n by n matrix
multiplied by an n less vector, you have to do n square, number of multiplications.
You have to do a row multiplier column, another row multiplier column, so in total you have
to do n square, right?
So n square is not really a very good complexity, right?
So what FFT is trying to do is that they give you the same result as DFT, okay?
No approximation, it's the same result, but it's going to save you some computation from
n square to n log n, right?
So this is why FFT is amazing because you got nothing to lose.
You don't lose anything, but you gain the computational advantage, right?
That's why for most of the device you can think about, which have to do DFT, they are
always doing FFT because it's a free lunch.
You save the computation, and there's no compromise.
It's the same result.
Okay, then of course there are many people proposing algorithm to speed up the frequency,
a Fourier transform, right?
So there are many.
We're going to learn one of them.
We don't have to learn all, but one of them, which is, I would say relatively easier to
understand, and also I will try to explain where the advantage come from, right?
Why we can save this computational resource.
So it's actually called RADX2 decimation method, okay?
So later on you can tell why there's a two, right?
Why is it actually RADX2 decimation?
Because it's always divide into two and solve everyone separately and merge, but they keep
dividing, right?
So basically all of these methods follow the divide and conquer principle.
So you have a complicated problem.
You cannot solve that directly.
You divide it into multiple simpler problems, and you solve each of them, right?
This is basically what divide and conquer means.
Okay, so the fundamental, right, I can mention, is to divide the, let's say endpoints, where
you have a signal of endpoints.
I can directly do endpoint DFT, but I don't want to do it.
That's too expensive.
So the idea here is to divide the endpoint into two and keep dividing that, okay?
Until you have a single point.
Okay, why?
Single point, I don't know how many of you realize that, but a single point signal, if
you do DFT, it's going to be itself.
I'm talking about a single point signal.
If you do DFT, it's going to be itself, no change.
All right, so basically the principle is to keep dividing the signal into two, such that
we're going to end up with a single point.
So to do so, we have to assume that the signal will have the length equal to two to power
of something, because only then you can keep dividing by two, right, to reach the single
point.
Some of you may ask me, hey, what happens if it's not equal to the power of something?
You do zero padding.
You do zero padding to make it to the power of something, right?
So this is actually the assumption.
We assume that we are dealing with a signal, ways the length equal to two to power of something,
like two, four, eight, 16, 32, 64, 128, right, these numbers.
And then we want to keep dividing that from n to n divided by two to n divided by four
and divided by eight, right?
So imagine this is the original signal.
You want to divide that into two, and then for every signal, every section you also divided
by two and then divide it, right?
So kind of dividing into every single piece, okay?
So why we're going to do this is because we believe that by doing so, the processing time
for every small piece of the signal will be very cheap, okay?
So this is actually the fundamental principle.
So let me show you how, right?
So consider you have a signal xn, okay?
And this, of course, this xn is in the time domain, right?
Every time I use the lower case, I'm always use the lower case to represent time domain
just for convention, right?
So here all the lower case x and y, these are talking about the time domain.
All right.
Upper case, I normally refer to frequency domain, all right?
Because right now both of them are discrete, but we have to somehow differentiate that.
So I use lower case for time, upper case for frequency, all right?
So I started ways endpoint time domain, discrete time signal, okay?
So what I'm doing now is I'm going to divide it into the even index and all the index,
okay?
I'm not doing, I could say, first half, second half.
I'm doing that say, number zero, number two, number four, number six goes to the even index
sample, all right?
And all the index sample, number one, number three, number five, number seven goes to the
z, okay?
So now I'm going to divide x, which is n length into y and z.
So each of the y and z will have n divided by two length, n divided by two points, okay?
Is it clear for everyone?
Like, you know how to divide a sequence into odd number, odd sequence, even, sorry, odd
index, even index, all right?
So if I do this, right, I'm going to end up with two sub-sequences, y and n.
So y equal to x2n, okay?
Zn equal to x2n plus one, all right?
And the correspondingly, the DFT of the x, by definition will be this, right?
I'm just using the definition of DFS, okay?
But here I can divide this guy, xn, into the two sub-sequences, right?
Here this is your y, this is your z.
So I'm going to separate the two, right?
So separate this guy into here and here.
Okay, how can I separate that?
Well, because this summation covers all the n, all the choice of n.
So summation is nothing but summing n terms together, right?
I just separate the summation into two summation.
So all the, all term summation goes to the second term, all of the even term summation
go to the first term.
So I'm going to have two, like, how should I say, a varied version of DFT, okay?
And in fact, these two will be the correspondingly, the DFT of y and DFT of z multiplied by a
phase shift, right?
A factor here, but this factor is nothing but just a phase shift.
You just multiply by e to the power of something, it doesn't change the magnitude, only change
the phase, all right?
So by doing so, originally I have to do a DFT for my n point signal.
Now I can only, I can just need to do an n divided by two point DFT for y and n divided
by t point of z.
And just sum them together, right?
And if you realize that if the DFT complex is n square, okay, I make it divided by two,
so every side I will save one over four.
So I will get only one over four ratio of complex, right?
I got one over four, one over four, sum them together, I got one over two.
So I already saved half of the commutation.
If the DFT is actually n square.
Okay, I hope this makes sense.
So think about the DFT, right?
The DFT as we explained last week is nothing but a matrix multiplier vector, right?
If you do a matrix multiplier vector, the number of multiplication you need to do is n square,
right?
Suppose we have four points, right?
If it's four points, I have to do four square number of multiplication, which is 16.
If I do directly the DFT, now I divided the four point into two point and two point, okay?
A two point DFT only need four operations.
So I got four plus four is eight.
So I'm reducing 16 to eight.
This is how I can save commutation.
Make sense?
Okay, so I'm not finished.
I'm just saying that where the saving come from.
Where the saving come from here, right?
As you can see, just by one stage of division, I already saved something.
I saved half.
Okay?
But let's complete, right?
So right now I can divide the original DFT into two parts, right?
So this is my first part in terms of x, right?
So my x can, I can look at my first n divided by two number of spectrum in my DFT and then
the second n divided by two spectrum.
So the first n divided by two spectrum can be written as this, which is the form I just
explained, right?
In principle, I can also represent the second half with the same number, same form.
But remember, y and z only have n divided by two points, right?
So basically I can only assign value of k all the way until n divided by two minus one.
So how can I represent the second half of my DFT spectrum?
I can use the periodic property, right?
I can do k plus n divided by two.
It's going to be periodic, right?
So by adding this, I can make the y and z into the second period.
So this is how I can represent the second half of my original spectrum, DFT spectrum.
So once I have the y and z, I have no problem representing my original xk.
And this is how you can do it, all right?
OK, think about it, right?
So this equation explained to you how or why I can represent x in terms of mathematics
using not directly using the xk, but indirectly using the DFT of the y and z.
OK, this is how I derive it.
OK, what I'm doing is just follow the definition, separate the summation into two terms and
just naturally end it up here, right?
But the issue here is that y and z are both n divided by two points.
All right, so my job is to represent the entire n point x, right, xk.
So I will use the y and z original period to represent the xk for up to n divided by
two minus one, the first half of the spectrum, right?
The second half of the spectrum I can do periodic extension of y and z to cover that, right?
Mathematically, it's the same, but I just use the second period to do it, all right?
And for simplicity, I can even represent this phase shift as the, you know, as the Wn,
which is equal to e to the power of minus j two pi divided by n, just for simplicity,
right?
I just use a dummy variable to replace that.
Such that I can re-represent this guy in a cleaner way, right, in this way.
So you realize that when I represent xk, I just need to have yk and zk plus or minus
some phase shift, right?
Of course, this term, the k will change, right?
The k depends on which index you are talking about, right?
But once I have the y and z and some kind of multiplier, I have no problem representing
the original x, OK?
So does it make sense for everyone?
Yes?
The two equations are clear.
Which one?
Top one or bottom one?
So both of them.
Both of them, OK.
Are they including all the information when you do for the signal?
Because yk and zk, they actually just separate differently, but they still include all the information.
Yes, it's all information.
You're right.
So you can't do anything else, right?
Like you mentioned, right?
Y and z, originally the time domain are nothing but sub-sub-sumpling of the time of x, right?
So the only thing I do is kind of I extract a sub-sequence from x to be y.
But when you talk about the matrix, right?
Matrix stuff.
Sounds like 18 to 8.
16 to 8 is something like some information between the enemies.
Oh, you mean matrix?
Oh, yeah.
Oh, the matrix itself.
Okay, faster for your transfer is faster than described for your transfer.
Yes.
But it sounds like when you explain it, it sounds like there was an information missing.
Okay.
It's missing to 8.
Okay, let me clarify.
When you say information, if I talk about the signal, no information missing.
Okay?
We have the difference sheet.
Are you talking about the transform or the signal?
Right.
If it's a signal, nothing missed.
Because what I'm doing here is I'm separating the old sequence out there as the y.
Sorry, even as the y, all as the z.
Right.
So all the original signals will be covered by either y or z.
So nothing lose.
Okay?
If your question is asking, okay, I'm reducing a 16 by 16 matrix to 8 by 8 matrix.
Am I losing something?
Yes, because you're making a smaller matrix.
But remember, DFT contains no information on the signal.
Right.
The transform itself is a transform.
It's a rule.
Right?
You specify, hey, this guy called DFT.
The DFT itself has nothing to do with the signal.
The result of DFT depends on the signal.
Yes?
WNK does not include the signal.
With signal?
Yes.
WNK only to do with N and K.
Okay.
So very good question.
So there's a misunderstanding when I say DFT.
Right.
DFT itself just referred to the matrix.
So DFT is fully determined by the N.
Okay?
We're talking about the matrix.
If I'm talking about 8-point DFT, that matrix is fixed.
Nothing to do with the signal.
But if we're talking about the DFT over signal, we are multiplying the matrix.
Multiplying the matrix with the vector, that results depends on the signal.
So they may be, it's a different, like a matrix, different size of matrix.
But after they complete the function, it should be the same function as the signal.
Complete the function should be the...
So when you write down the matrix with all the signal you need, and you just like simplify
the matrix or something, and you write the same function as the matrix.
Yes.
But I think you made a very good point.
I want to maybe...
I don't know how many of you have the same question.
When I learned this, I have this question, to be honest.
I didn't really differentiate very clearly.
But I think it's better to mention this.
Let's go back to the slides I talked about last week, since you have this question.
What I'm talking about is the matrix...
The matrix I'm talking about is this guy.
I hope you still remember.
Right.
This guy.
So we started by this equation.
Okay.
We started by this equation.
So this is the definition.
Right.
This is called the forward Fourier transform, how you can convert a time domain to frequent
domain.
Right.
But we say that because both of x and n are n points.
So instead, you can either choose to write, let's say, n equations.
I mean, you can write n equations because k has to be equal to zero, one, two, all the
way to m minus one.
We're saying that if you want to represent all the xk in one shot, you can use this matrix
vector form.
All right.
Why this is true?
Because by definition, if I multiply a matrix with a vector, I'm doing nothing but multiplying
the first row with this vector and get the first coefficient.
Right.
So this is exactly the x0, xk equal to zero case.
Equal to all the Fourier DFT.
Right.
And this is k equal to one, x1 equal to the DFT.
So when I'm saying that 16 point DFT, I'm only talking about this matrix.
Okay.
This matrix is literally called DFT.
Discrete Fourier transform.
In mathematics, when we say a transform, it always a matrix.
You can always represent a transform, linear transform.
Let's make it straight.
Okay.
Linear transform as a matrix.
All right.
Laplace transform.
Right.
Cosine transform.
They're always a matrix.
So the transform itself, if it's linear, should have nothing to do with the signal.
It's a fix.
It's a fixed one.
If you look at this form, right, there are coefficients in this w.
Do you see anything to do with the signal?
No.
Because wn, right, this guy is fully determined by the n and the coefficient.
Nothing, anything to do with my x?
No.
Nothing to do with my x.
So you can construct any size of the transform, whatever you want.
Let's say 16 point, 8 point.
The 16 or 8 just change the n.
Right.
So what I'm saying is that instead of doing a 16 by 16 DFT directly, what I just talk
about is by reducing the transforming to 8 by 8 transform.
Does it make sense?
I changed the factor, yes, but I didn't change the signal.
Right.
The signal is, you still preserve the signal.
I don't touch the signal.
Do you change the signal?
No.
I change the points.
I change the n point.
Remember, n is the denominator, the n.
It's not fs.
Right.
fs is the sampling frequency.
Sampling frequency only determining the conversion between analog to discrete.
Now here, what I, what, what do you think I talk about?
Nothing to do with the sampling.
Just the points, number of points I have for my DFT.
Right.
Is it clear?
I mean, I just want to make it clear.
When I say transform, I'm talking about this guy.
All right.
You can apply a transform to a signal, time domain signal.
To get, it's spectrum.
Right.
This is called spectrum.
This is called the time domain signal.
This is called DFT.
Right.
Yes.
You are using the symmetric property to do the computational, to gain advantage.
Exactly.
So her question is that, okay, what are we doing?
So basically, maybe I translated it in another way.
Right.
So why we can gain this?
The result, the gain cannot come from nowhere.
Right.
So why exactly we can gain the computational advantage?
Indeed, the reason is that why I do this computation.
Remember, if I'm doing this exactly, I need to compute, let's say the first row, multiplied
by the column.
Right.
Second row, multiplied by the column.
So I have to do exactly n squared number of multiplication.
But why, because I don't do anything, I don't lose anything.
Why exactly by doing this massage of the equation, I can save something suddenly?
You're right.
Exactly.
There's some symmetric property.
I don't know if you can tell.
Right.
These matrix is actually symmetric.
Why is it symmetric?
I mean, along this diagonal elements, all of these numbers are same.
Right.
Here's W n squared.
This is also W n squared.
So when I apply this row, and later when I apply this row, I'm doing some redundant
computation.
I'm doing sometimes the same multiplication multiple times.
Right.
And basically, why FFT works is giving you a smarter way to avoid the repeating computation.
So this is exactly where the saving comes from.
Right.
It's due to the fact that this matrix is not a random matrix.
If I give you a random matrix, there's no hope you can save it.
You have to do exactly all the things.
But this matrix is highly structured.
And this structure tells you something to save the computation smartly.
Right.
All right.
But I want to make it clear.
Right.
So when I say changing from n point to n divided by two points, DFT, I'm talking about shrinking
the size of the matrix.
Right.
It doesn't mean I lose anything because I'm going to still, let's say, separate the input
elements.
Right.
Into like these two guys goes to Y. Here, here goes to Z. Right.
I'm still processing every single number in my input signal.
I didn't lose anything.
Right.
Okay.
Make sense?
All right.
If you have any question, I can answer because, you know, I know some of you are very familiar
with this.
If I say too much, you probably think I'm just wasting time.
But if you find something you feel uncomfortable, you want me to repeat, I'm perfectly fine
to explain.
Right.
Actually, I would rather you ask me than we settle this before moving on.
Okay.
Everybody's clear?
Like, is it better?
Good.
Okay.
So let's go back to our business.
Right.
So we end up here.
So we're saying that by using this divide and conquer strategy, we can, let's say, dividing
the original endpoint DFT.
Okay.
Let me use the pointer.
Original endpoint DFT, if you want to directly use that big matrix, you have to endpoint.
Right.
Into a smarter way to compute Y and Z separately.
So Y and Z themselves, the length or number points are only half.
Okay.
Because of that, doing them is much easier than doing X directly.
So you can do this, but you may not stop there because you can do the exact same thing to
Y and Z.
Right.
If I can save for X, now why should I do DFT for Y and Z?
I can still do it dividing for them as well.
Right.
Exactly the same thing.
So from N divided by 2 to N divided by 4.
Then keep dividing until you reach a single point.
So this equation only show you the step from N to N divided by 2.
But I can keep doing this.
Okay.
So what you will have is, okay, this is actually the, okay, let's forget about keep doing,
right.
Just look at this step.
So I can show you the mathematical equation of this step.
Okay.
So mathematically, this is what happened.
I can also use a diagram to show you the exact same procedure.
So this diagram is exactly the same as this equation.
Okay.
The only difference is that I'm representing Y and Z as the input signal here.
So imagine this is my Y0, my Y1, blah, blah, blah, all the way to Y and divided by, sorry,
divided by 2 minus 1.
Right.
So I'm input them into the system.
Okay.
So let's say if I want to get X0, right.
If I want to get X0, I should get X0 equal to Y0 plus W to the power of 0 times Z0.
Right.
So in the graph, you can find that this guy equal to Y0, right.
The direct to go here, sum up with the Z0 multiplied by WN to the power of 0, sum together.
So this branch is corresponding to the equation, the first equation, which is K equal to 0.
All right.
And then exactly the X1 here and here were corresponding to the first equation, which
K equal to 1.
Right.
I'm just representing the mathematical equation using this so-called diagram.
Okay.
So later you will learn that this diagram is called block diagram.
Why we love it is because this is very good for design.
Right.
Because eventually, mathematical form is for us to understand.
But later you want to understand something for manufacture.
Right.
You cannot show them the equation.
You have to show them, okay, how exactly the signal is passed into from stage to stage.
Right.
So this diagram shows you the signal going from stage 1 to stage 2.
This is called block diagram.
And normally the block diagram will have some fundamental components like summation,
you know, multiplications.
And these are very easy to implement, right, in the circuit design.
Right.
Circuit, you know, design, you know, how should I say, future design or circuit design.
But this diagram is the same representation, sorry, equivalent to representation as the
mathematical form.
Okay.
All right.
So why we want to do this?
I mean, why we want to use the diagram to represent this stage?
Because I want to keep doing that.
Right.
So I want to take the diagram from the stage into the other stage.
For example, I already decompose my x into your y and the z.
Right.
I can do the same thing for y by further dividing the y into, let's say, y2 and z2.
Same for z, right.
But basically you have to do them in the corresponding way.
And then, you know, I can further divide my y2 into, you know, original signal.
Right.
So you keep dividing the end point to m divided by 2 and divided by 4 until you have a single
length signal.
Okay.
Then you cannot divide anymore, right.
It's only one point.
Nothing to divide.
But the good thing is, if you have a one point signal, the DFT of that is equal to itself.
So you can do nothing.
You just leave it.
That signal originally is the spectrum of itself.
Right.
So this is how you can, all the way starting from time domain, but you have to reshuffle
that.
Remember, the order is not 0, 1, 2, 3.
It's actually 0, 4, 2, 6.
Okay.
So this is something people normally make mistakes.
All right.
This is not in the original order.
But you can keep doing this 2 point FFT three times to reach your 8 point output because
2 to power 3 equal to 8.
Right.
If you want to reach 16 point, you have to do four stages.
All right.
But the principle is that you do not do the transform directly, but you divide and conquer
until you cannot divide anymore.
Right.
So when you design this, you have to go from the output all the way to input.
But when you apply that, of course, you go from input to output.
Right.
This is how the so-called butterfly form come from.
This is called butterfly form, by the way.
So you can do this in the two point division.
Sometimes people also do three point division.
But for this class, let's stick to two point.
I don't want to complicate the story.
Right.
But basically, this is how you can save computation and you can somehow, later I will show you.
So you can actually go from n squared to n log n.
Okay.
So, okay.
So if you do DFT directly, you got n squared.
Right.
And then every stage, you should have n number of operation.
All right.
Why?
Because every stage, you have to do one multiplication.
Right.
This is minus one.
This is multiplied by one.
This is multiplied by w to power of zero.
Right.
So for every stage, you have to do exactly n number of multiplication.
Okay.
How many stage?
Actually, it's log n stage.
All right.
So suppose n is eight.
Log n equal to three.
So this is where the n log n come from.
Right.
Every stage, you need n number of operation.
You have log n number of stages.
Right.
This is where they come from.
But we'll get there.
Right.
But I use this slide to show you the example of eight point.
So you can read this, but they show you the step by step division from eight point all
the way to the two point FFT.
Okay.
But I won't repeat this, but you can use this example as a practice.
Right.
To see whether you do truly understand the divide and the conquer strategy of this two
point.
Okay.
Right.
So it's a two point FFT process.
All right.
But it's the same principle.
Right.
This is, I really showed you the eight point, but you can go through this mathematics process
to understand how exactly you can go from eight point FFT to four point FFT to gradually
reduce it.
Okay.
Yes.
Sorry.
Tell me about what you're doing.
Tell me about what?
Symmetric.
Okay.
So are we totally ignoring all the negative frequency?
We are totally ignoring the, what, negative frequency or negative frequency.
For DFT, it doesn't really matter.
For DFT, it's always fixed length.
Right.
And also, even if you are careful of negative frequency, it's symmetric.
It's periodic.
You can just do another period to cover the negative frequency if you want.
Right.
So it really doesn't matter.
We only care about that end points.
Right.
This is the principle of DFT.
You have end point input.
You only care about end point output.
You can cover any frequency by simply repeating the same pattern.
Yes.
Okay.
Good.
Any other questions?
Okay.
Good.
So this is the derivation of FFT.
Right.
And also, this is one example to show you numerically.
If I give you a time domain signal as 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, right, 8 point, how I can
use my, you know, butterfly diagram to generate the output.
Okay.
I mean, again, I won't go through this because you have to try this number by number, but
I will leave this as an exercise for you.
But it's a practice for you to experience, right, how the numbers can gradually go from
the input by doing every stage to reach the output.
Okay.
I probably want to test you on those kind of tricky numbers in the exam, but you need
to know the principle.
Okay.
Even if I give you a question, the number will be relatively simple, trust me.
Right.
But you need to know the principle, right, how this division is actually works.
All right.
So, yeah, so you can complete this example by yourself by gradually going from, you know,
original stage, stage 1, stage 2, and continuously with stage 4 to reach the final number.
So number will be very ugly, but, you know, that's how the DFT actually give you, right,
the same result as the actual DFT numbers.
Okay.
And also, right, I also want to show you that if you look at the spectrum of this guy, right,
in other words, the plot of this guy, remember, these are not real numbers.
All right.
If you, even if you have a real input after DFT, very likely you will get a complex number.
The reason is this DFT measure itself is complex.
Okay.
Every time you see e2 part of something, it's very likely it's a complex number.
Right.
So the result will also be a complex number.
And normally if you want to show the spectrum of a complex signal, complex spectrum, you
have to show that in terms of magnitude and phase.
Okay.
There are only two ways to represent complex numbers, real plus imaginary or magnitude
versus phase.
Right.
For signal processing, more likely we're doing magnitude and phase plot.
The reason is magnitude is more important than phase.
Right.
So we want to know the magnitude and the phase separately.
So if you recall last time we said that if I give you a real signal input, right, I
cannot guarantee the output is very likely unreal, complex, but one thing I can guarantee
you is that the magnitude will be symmetric.
Remember that real signal, you get a DFT, you get a symmetric spectrum.
Right.
So here's one example.
You will get a symmetric spectrum like this for magnitude.
Right.
But for phase, it will be very tricky.
So for example, this one, right, in fact, this is a linear phase, but you will see that,
well, the line goes up, but suddenly comes down here.
The reason is that I already reach so-called some boundary, I have to do a truncation,
sorry, a flip sign to the negative one.
Right.
But in fact, this is actually a linear phase.
So later we're going to talk about linear phase, but I just want to show that linear
phase may have this sudden jump due to the range stuff.
Right.
Later we're going to see this.
So, okay, most important thing I want you to, let's even memorize this.
It's the actual advantage we have in terms of computation.
All right.
But first of all, how can we, okay, what can we use to describe a computational complex
of an algorithm?
Okay.
How many of you have learned this?
I just wondering.
You know, how many of you can recognize what I'm writing here?
Okay.
You know that, right?
How many others, guys?
Have you learned this big O analysis in your undergraduate study?
Okay.
You have learned it.
I see some people raising their hand.
Okay.
Let me just explain, since most of us do not know this.
Right.
So, when we talk about like one algorithm, it's cheaper than the other, or one algorithm
is more expensive than the other.
Right.
We have to quantify the complexity.
Okay.
So there are many ways to quantify a complexity of an algorithm.
The most commonly used one is called big O analysis.
All right.
Let me define what is big O analysis.
So let's first start by defining the G function as the actual number of operation that I have
to do for this algorithm.
Right.
So GN give you the exact number.
For example, 10 times, 11 times, that's the GN.
Right.
But sometimes we don't care about the actual numbers.
We care about is this function upper bounded by something?
Or in other words, what's the worst case?
What's the worst case this function can be?
Right.
Because the actual number of operation depends on the length of the signals.
Depends on your, maybe even the quantity of the signals.
Right.
But we care about is that we want the algorithm don't be too bad, even if I have a worst case.
Okay.
So this is where the big O come from.
The big O analysis provides you an upper bound saying that the actual number of operations
of my algorithm cannot be larger than another function multiplied by a given constant.
Okay.
If you can find another function fm multiplied by some constant, the constant can up to you.
Right.
Just give a constant.
Which can always surpass the worst case of my actual number of operations.
These f is called the big O fn.
In other words, if I give you say, hey, I have an algorithm that runs as the big O of
fn, that means no matter how bad my algorithm runs, the number of operation cannot exceed
a fixed constant times fn function.
So I use this fn function to upper bound the worst case of my algorithm.
Okay.
So is it clear for everyone?
Every time you see big O, you're thinking about the worst case.
Worst case of my algorithm.
It cannot be worse than that.
So of course, if my worst case is susceptible, that means my algorithm is susceptible.
I want to make sure my worst case upper bound is something reasonable or something controllable.
That's why we always use this to describe an algorithm.
So let's analyze, for example, DFT.
So I remember I say that if I directly do DFT, so you have these slides here, I directly
do DFT.
This is what I'm going to do.
I'm going to multiply this matrix with my vector.
So I have to do a certain number of multiplication and a certain number of addition.
These are something I have to do.
For example, I have to multiply the first row with the first column.
So I have to do n number of multiplications and maybe n minus 1 number of addition.
So you can count exactly how many addition you have and how many multiplication you have.
In fact, this is the total amount of operation you need for directly doing DFT.
So it's n up ways 2n square minus n.
So this is actually my actual amount of operations.
But I probably only care about the worst case.
Remember, only the worst case actually matters.
So in fact, there are two terms, second order term, first order term.
The first order term will not affect my worst case.
The worst case will be dominated by the highest order in the GN.
In other words, this kind of quality can be upper bounded by some constants times n square
because second order term grows much faster than the first order term.
So because of that, I can say that my DFT will have a big n square complexity.
So these terms matter.
You want to have this function to be as slow as possible, grows as slow as possible.
So n square, that's upper bound for directly applying DFT.
It's actually dominated by these two multiplied together.
Then let's look at FFT.
If I don't do the DFT directly, I do an indirect way to divide and conquer.
So what I was doing just now, let's look at here.
What I'm doing just now, like this, is that I have to do certain amount of stages, let's say k stages.
But every stage, what I need to do, I need to do 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, exactly n number of addition.
I have to do exactly n number of multiplication.
So that means every stage, I need to have roughly 2n number of operations.
Then multiplied by number of stages.
This will be the total number of operation I need to do for FFT.
It makes sense?
So for n point FFT, how many stages I have?
So imagine, let's say you have 8.
I do one stage, I can break 8 into 4.
I do another stage, I can break 4 into 2.
I do another stage, I can break 2 into 1.
So what I'm doing here is I'm doing log n.
So if say I have, let's say, n point, 8 points, I need 2 to power of 3 to get 8.
So number of stages exactly talking about how many division I have.
I go from 8 to 4, that's one stage.
4 to 2, that's second stage, 2 to 1 is the third stage.
So I need 3 stages.
So that number is equal to log n.
Make sense?
It's division.
Every time you just cut it by half, right?
Half, half, half, reach 1, you got log n.
So the number of stages will be log n.
So this is where this term come from.
So you need log n, of course, we're talking about the base 2, right?
So log 2 n, this will be the number of stages.
But every stage I have n number of operations.
So sum together, I will get n times log n number of operations.
So this will be my upper bound.
My big O analysis will be n times log n.
So tell me n squared and log n, which is more expensive?
First one, do you know what is the log function?
How does the log function look like?
OK, so let me just, my drawing is terrible, but I have to show you this.
Forgive me my terrible drawing, but basically, no, no, no, what is this?
OK, so suppose this is my axis, right?
So x and y.
OK, what is linear function?
What is n?
OK, n will be a straight line, right, like this.
So this will be my n.
OK, what is log function?
Log function will be something like this, right?
But the key here is that log function will grow slower and slower.
You cannot surpass the linear function.
Makes sense?
Everybody agree?
Basic math, right?
So if I ask you, right, n versus log n, which one grows faster?
n, right, n is more expensive than log n.
OK, now how about n squared versus n, sorry, n times log n?
n squared, right, because I just make it fear I just multiply by n both sides, right?
But because n grows faster than log n.
So log n squared will be faster than n log n.
Makes sense?
Because of that, right, now what the FFT shows is that it's successfully reducing the n squared
operation to n times log n operation.
So it makes it grow slower.
In other words, the worst case becomes better, right, if you do FFT.
Makes sense?
Because the function upper bound that number becomes growing slower.
So you are making the worst case better.
You save commutation even if it's a worst case, all right?
Because of that, right, this is where the advantages come from, right?
So this is kind of better than n squared.
So if you visualize the computational complex as the function of n, you will see that n squared,
eventually, initially doesn't make a difference.
But when n is large, right, the gain is huge.
You save a huge amount of commutation, right, comparing DFT with FFT.
That's why everybody uses FFT, right?
Because we're not talking about like only a five point signal.
We're talking about hundreds of points of signal, right?
Maybe a million points of signal.
Then doing FFT is terrible, right?
Nobody doing that.
So this is why in practice, everybody will do FFT.
But when we analyze the process, we do FFT because DFT is easy to analyze, right?
But anyway, they both of them give you the same result.
It doesn't make a difference, okay?
All right, it's better because last week I just mentioned the advantage, but I didn't
explain where the advantages come from, right?
So I hope this one gives you a better idea, right?
Why we have this advantage by doing the smarter way of dividing and concur.
Okay?
Any questions before I move on?
Yes, yes?
How these numbers are arranged?
Okay, so her question is this.
I guess you are saying that do we have to memorize how this function are?
So the lady was asking like, okay, do we have to memorize how these numbers are arranged?
Right.
In principle, you can derive it.
If you know how this one is derived, in principle, you can derive it, right?
But memorizing that is not a very difficult job, I would say.
Okay, why?
I can tell you how I memorize it.
I actually memorize it, to be honest.
But it's very easy, right?
For example, this is an eight point, eight point DFT, right?
So FFT.
So if it's eight point, I have to do, you know, let's look at the first half and the
second half, right?
So the first half will be always even number, even index, remember?
Why?
Because here is already divided into even and odd, right?
So all the even goes here, all the odd goes here, right?
So all of these numbers in the top half, upper half will be even.
If you see any odd number here, that means you are wrong, okay?
And all the bottom half here will be odd number.
You cannot have any even there.
So you consider every stage is like a reshuffle of the numbers, right?
So the first stage shuffled them into even and odd, all right?
Okay, so then what they're doing is keep shuffling, okay?
So here you are talking about zero, one, two, three, sorry, you know, zero, two, four,
six, right?
But if you go one step back, you are picking the even number of the even number, right?
In other words, you are picking not zero, how to say, not zero, two, four, six, but you
are picking zero and four, because zero and four are the even subsequence of the even
sequence.
I don't know whether it makes sense, right?
So you are picking, you are keep picking the even index from the original sequence, right?
So here it gives you all the even numbers.
So here they will say, well, these two have to be step of four instead of step of two,
right?
So it should be zero and four, and then you have four and six.
So four and six are the odd subsequence of the even sequence.
This is how I remember that, right?
It's not very hard, but if you want, that's how I memorize it.
Otherwise, you can always stick to the formula, right?
If you have no choice, you can think about it, right?
But if you want to memorize how these are shuffled, they are keep picking the even and
odd subsequence from the previous stage, right?
This is how I memorize it, okay?
Okay, good.
Any other questions before we move on?
Okay, so I guess, so where are we?
Okay, so we are going to take a break.
Maybe it's come back around eight, right?
Shorter so we can finish earlier, right?
So come back at eight, all right?
Okay, thank you.
Okay.
We can start.
So as a promise, I probably won't finish all the slides today.
Some of them I probably will move to next week and I will try to remove some of the components
because I think it's too much.
All right.
I will promise we will try to finish by let's say 9.10 or something so that you can catch
the bus.
So give me a signal if I run out of time.
If I run out of time, give me a signal.
But anyway, we talked about FFT.
That was something pretty much I didn't mention very clearly last time but it's important
so that's why I was going to spend time there.
But all of this we talked about.
FFT, DFT, DTFT, these are something to do with signal.
We're trying to represent the signal in the way that they give you some features, useful
information.
But another important aspect is the system.
So signal is pretty much the data you have.
You want to process the data such that you want to represent the signal such that they
can be better analyzed.
But we haven't talked about the system yet.
So the system is actually how you want to process the signal, how you want to let's
say manipulate the signal, process the signal such that they somehow satisfy your need.
So now from now on, the focus will be the system.
So now we're going from signal to system.
So how the system look like for this subject.
We mentioned a little bit last week saying that we have to say something constrained
on the system.
For example, we want to talk about LTI system, if you still remember what this means.
It means the system must be linear and the system must be time-invaryed.
This is always the assumption we make for this class, the LTI system.
And also we will have multiple ways to represent the system, just like we have multiple ways
to represent the signal.
We say the signal can be representing time, in frequency, they can be discreet, they can
be analog.
So for system, we are also going to learn a few ways to represent a system.
So which is a better way to represent depends on your task.
So one way we can represent a system is called a transfer function.
So transfer function is something to do with the frequency representation, so later we'll
get there.
But transfer function, you can consider this as a spectrum of the system, like a filter.
We talk about, for some of you have learned filter, we call the filter like low pass,
high pass.
This is talking about the spectrum of the filter.
So the transfer function is always the same like similarly describing the system from
the frequency perspective.
But based on the type of transfer function, the transfer function may have different types.
But based on the types of the transfer function, we can categorize the system in the following
two ways.
The first one is to look at what is the impulse response of a system.
So what is the impulse response?
I hope all of you should know.
So impulse function means I give you a system, I inject an input signal, which is an impulse
signal.
What is the output I have?
So this will be the impulse response of a system.
So if the impulse response have finite number of impulse in the response.
So this is called FIR, which literally means finite impulse response transfer function.
So what counting the number of impulse I have in my impulse response.
If it's a finite number of impulse, that means it's FIR.
So you keep hearing the term FIR many times because I'm going to focus on FIR for my part,
the filter design later.
But there's another type, we call it the opposite type.
So if you have an impulse response, but unfortunately you have infinitely many impulse in your impulse
response, it means this is an IR filter, IR transfer function.
So later we're going to learn that why sometimes we also call FIR as a non-recursive function.
IR is a recursive function.
It's because later when we talk about the difference equation, you will see that IR,
normally the right hand side will also involve Y. Y means the output.
So you have to represent the current time output using the past time output.
This is what we call the recursive.
You have to recursively fill it back into your system to implement an IR.
But FIR, you don't have to.
So FIR, you can just write the output as a function of X.
So it's also called non-recursive.
This is by counting, by looking at how many terms you have in the impulse response.
This is one way to categorize the system into FIR and IR.
But that's not the only way.
It's not the only way to categorize.
You can also look at how the transfer function selects the frequency.
So I assume that some of you may already know this.
For example, you can actually look at the magnitude function of the transfer function.
And for example, you may encounter some kind of transfer function in the way that they
only maybe allow certain frequency band to survive.
In other words, if you look at the transfer function, there will be one within, let's
say here, low frequency range.
So this type will be called the low pass filter.
In other words, that kind of system will only let the low frequency component survive in
the processing period.
High frequency components will be killed in the system.
You can have the opposite, which will be called the high pass filter, means that they kill
the low frequency and they survive the high frequency.
So it's exactly the opposite.
So it depends on which frequency will be passing through the system.
You can actually categorize them in the way by looking at the transfer function.
And normally we call the frequency that can survive as the pass band.
In other words, if this is my transfer function, the pass band will be here.
Can you see that?
Okay, here.
This will be my pass band.
For this transfer function, the pass band will be the opposite.
It will be the high frequency components.
And of course, there will also be the stop band.
Stop band means all of these response will be zero.
So the stop band for low pass will be the high pass components.
So all of these are looking at how the transfer function selects the frequency components
when it's processing the signal.
So it depends on the frequency.
There's also others, for example, they may not only look at the low frequency, they may
look at a specific range of the frequency.
So you can specify as a say omega C2 and omega C1.
This is the range.
If they're only selecting a certain range, not too low, not too high, this is called
band pass filter.
You can also make a band stop filter, means that only the selected range will be killed.
But very likely these four will be the general cases you will be encounter.
If you want to view the system from the frequency selection perspective.
I believe most of you should learn this, even if you do the analog signal processing.
But the frequency response can be a criteria to categorize the digital filters.
And all of these are talking about the magnitude, not the phase.
So just not mentioned that you can actually look at the magnitude, you can have the phase,
but what I'm talking about is only look at the magnitude.
So the DTFT, when we say a system, normally we use a function for example H to represent
a system.
The transfer function is normally used uppercase H to represent a transfer function, in other
words the spectrum of the impulse response.
But you can also do a DTFT to get it back to the impulse response.
In other words the impulse response can be obtained by an inverse DTFT of the transfer
function.
That's how you can convert between the two.
But basically impulse response representing in the lower case is actually a time domain
function.
Transfer function representing the uppercase, that's a frequency domain function.
This is something you must be very clear.
And just now we are saying that for specifying the frequency, remember here we need to specify
the frequency.
For example here we have to specify omega c indicating what is the low pass we are talking
about, what is the frequency range we are talking about.
Sometimes we need two numbers, omega c1, omega c2 to represent a specific range of the frequency.
So all of these numbers, omega c, omega c1, omega c2, we call that cutoff frequency.
Means the frequency that I go from surviving to killing, or in other words from passing
to stop.
That kind of threshold we call the cutoff frequency.
So these are some terms we usually use to describe the frequency behavior.
So just now I think one of you asked me, I think that gentleman asked me say hey, all
of you talk about before, like anti-aliasing filters, reconstruction filters, you are assuming
a very ideal case.
In other words, all of these transitions are very sharp.
Suddenly it goes from passband to stopband.
So yes, all of the so-called low pass filter, high pass filter showing up here, we call
it ideal filter.
Once the ideal, I mean I don't assume any transition.
They can do a sudden transition from stopband to passband.
So this ideal case will have the magnitude of response equal to one, exact one in the
passband and exactly zero to the stopband.
That's what we want, but unfortunately not always can be implementable.
That's something we're going to talk about later, filter design.
But ideal case, we always assume that they have zero phase everywhere.
Means the phase response is always zero.
I'm talking about ideal case.
But this is useful in theory because they make things simple.
But bear in mind that if you see such kind of filters, like sharp transition, exactly
zero, exactly one, zero phase, it's not something practical.
It's only called ideal.
So like I said, ideal filter just like a brick wall.
The frequency is actually very sharp.
And very likely they are not causal.
We talked about the causality last time, if you remember.
Current signal cannot depend on future input.
This is the causality we're talking about.
Unfortunately those ideal filters, they are not causal.
There's another reason like they will be never realizable in the finite length LTI system
because causality, this is something we must have.
You cannot see the future value.
That's a fundamental rule.
This is just to explain that all of these are ideal filters.
But of course, they will have some ideal characteristics.
For example, you can always do DTFT, IDTFT to convert between transfer function and
the impulse response.
All of this we have learned, DTFT things.
The ideal filter can be represented in this way.
The magnitude can be one or zero depends on they are within the color frequency or outside
the color frequency.
I won't really repeat, but basically these are some mathematical theory for ideal filters
and assuming the phase to be zero.
Mathematical way, this is what just now the previous slide means mathematically.
Likewise, this is actually low pass filter.
All of this is low pass filter.
You can also do the same thing for high pass filter if you want.
I won't really repeat, but you can explain or describe the magnitude of the high pass,
sorry, band stop filter.
This is band stop filter in this way.
And correspondingly, you can also compute the impulse response by simply your inverse
DTFT to get it back to the impulse response.
But here's a summary of all of this ideal filter.
Let's make it specific.
Ideal filter, they can be represented in the following way.
Low pass, high pass, I won't repeat, but you can use this table as a summary of all of
the four popular ideal filters we have, band pass and band stop.
But bear in mind that all of them are not practical.
You cannot have them in practice.
But they are mathematically simple and beautiful.
This is something we like it.
So now talking about practical implementation.
We always start from the ideal filters.
Ideal filter is something we can design.
We can start in ways.
But then when you want to eventually develop something realizable or practical, how can
we do this?
Or what compromise we have to make?
So basically, we can never have this very sharp transition.
Once you move to the practical filters, you have to do some so-called relaxation to include
a transition band between the pass band and stop band.
So the big difference is that in practice, you will never see a sharp transition from
zero to one.
What you will see in practice is that when I move from pass band to stop band, or maybe
the other way around, you have to have a certain range of the frequency to accommodate the
transition from one to zero.
And the range here is called transition band.
When the transition band is zero, that means it's ideal.
But in practice, transition band will never be zero.
It will be something.
We want to minimize it, but you cannot get zero.
So this approximation, well, permits the magnitude response to decay slowly.
Here it's decay slowly from the maximum to the minimum to zero.
In other words, from the pass band to the stop band.
And also, this is one compromise we have to make.
Another compromise we have to make is that even within the pass band and the stop band,
you will not have exactly one and zero.
Remember, if you look at all of the functions, very, very ideal, all of these are one.
All of the stop band are zero.
In practice, this never happens.
What you will have is some small deviation, fluctuations around the one, but they will
never be one.
They will be like up and down, up and down.
So this is something we normally call it a ripple or smaller fluctuations.
And also, we want to design the filter such that this deviation is minimized, but never
be zero.
So these are the two major phenomena you will observe.
If you go from ideal filter to the practical filter, transition band and the ripples.
So bear in mind that when we talk about filter design, these are the two factors you have
to bear in mind that you want to use the limited resource to minimize the transition band and
also minimize the ripple.
So these are the two major phenomena.
And again, this is actually magnitude, not phase.
Remember we have two things, magnitude and phase.
Here, we are talking about the magnitude.
We will also talk about the phase separately.
So now phase.
So ideally we say that ideal kind of filters, you are going to zero phase anywhere.
No phase change if you just apply that.
They only preserve the signal phase, no change.
But in practice, again, this is not kind of practical.
So what will actually happen is that there will be a frequency shift property of the
DTFT to impulse response of an ideal zero phase low pass filter.
So what you will arrive at is the following.
So this will be the actual impulse response.
If you directly do the inverse DTFT of this low pass filter, you will get some kind of
zinc function.
If you don't do anything, remember last week we also showed this zinc function, remember?
Like a kind of spread out from zero to infinity.
But if you don't do anything, this zinc function will give you a non-causal behavior.
In other words, you will get an impulse response from both pass and the filters.
And also they give you infinitely long kind of impulse response.
So both of them will be making the design to be unrealizable.
So what you have to do is two things.
You have the first truncating impulse response from infinitely long to finite number of terms.
And also you have to deal with the non-causality here by doing some shift.
So the truncated approximate may or may not exhibit the linear phase.
Depends on the value n we choose.
So in practice, even though we cannot make the phase to be zero, we wish the phase to
be linear.
So later we'll see that there is some trick or some rule to select the n such that even
if we make the compromise, we can still land it at the linear phase filters.
So this is something we wish to achieve.
But here I just give you some kind of preview.
We will have another lecture, I think maybe next week, to talk about design, the actual
design of the filters.
But here I just give you some idea of what exactly we need to do, going from ideal filter
to practical filters.
So the principle is that if you want to pass the impulse signal to a certain frequency
range, for example, here is the low frequency range, you do not want to have a lot of distortion.
Basically you want the signal to be undistorted, both in magnitude and phase, such that your
transfer function should exhibit a unit magnitude response within the passband and also a linear
phase response in the band of interest.
So this is something we wish to have, like no distortion in the magnitude and only a
linear phase in the band of interest.
So to do so, what we actually need to do is that we need to make sure the zinc function
is going to be like this.
So basically you kind of shift the major component to the past, this kind of will solve the non-causality
problem and also you want to do the truncation, which make the impulse response finite only
within the window.
So these are two practical things we normally need to do to make an ideal low pass filter
to a practical low pass filter.
So but actually these two major steps also need to determine how much you have to shift
and what is the windowing function you are going to use.
So this is actually something to do with the filter design.
But basically if you have a windowing function to truncate the approximation and also doing
a proper shift to make the filter causal, you will have something like this.
So for example this is a n to equal to 13 point low pass zinc function, this is n equal
to 14 zinc function.
So both of them because of this time shift and also truncation, they will become a linear
phase FIR filter.
Remember what is FIR?
FIR is counting the number of response in the time domain.
If I have finite number of response in the time domain, that's FIR.
So once I do truncation, I can convert an IRR into an FIR filter because within the window,
the number of impulse or number of spikes are finite.
So 13 or 14, this is FIR.
And also because all of these spikes are moved to the past, this filter becomes causal.
So by doing the shifting and truncation, I can make originally a non-causal, infinitely
many kind of response into a causal and FIR filter.
So this is what we need for the actual implementation.
But this is one example to show you that the following doing this way will give you approximate
transfer function which is not the same as the ideal but good enough as the approximate.
So we'll get to the actual design later, maybe not today, maybe next week, but I just want
to show you what's the gap between all of the things we covered before like ideal filters
to the actual things can be designed.
But basically you have to get very mind, you know, a time shift and the truncation.
These are two things you have to do to overcome the non-causality and also the IR nature of
the filters.
So I'll also show some simple filter examples.
I mean not too much.
So here's one example.
I don't know if I want to skip this because...
Okay, let me see.
Maybe I will skip this to the next time because next time I'm going to talk about design.
So I will skip that but I will get back to this when I talk about the filter design because
I think these are two details.
We don't have time here.
So I will skip here but I will get back to this next week on the actual design.
But I want to directly go to the implementation part.
So we talk about that, you know, we want to implement the filters that can be realized
in practice.
What will be the actual structure of the digital filters?
So we have to...
Normally with the way we represent feasible filters, we can use something we call it difference
function, like this.
So what is a difference function?
So the difference function will be represented in terms of the output, the Y, as a function
of both current time input or past time input plus possibly some past time output.
Okay, let me explain why do we need my past time.
So first of all, Y always used to denote the output for this course, I mean for filter
design.
So assume that Y always talking about the output of the system.
X refer to the input of the system.
I use lowercase because both of them are in time domain.
So the index of the signal represent time step.
So this N can be something in the past or something in the future.
So for example, if I'm care about the output of time N, all the index with M, I can use
N minus some positive number.
These should be the past time.
Make sense?
So I want to represent the output at the time step N.
Suppose N goes to equal to zero.
So all the time step that is kind of smaller than this time step will be the past time.
For example, if I'm care about my current time zero, my time minus one, minus two, minus
three will be the past time signal.
Because of that, I'm saying that here, even though this term involves some Y, but all
of this Y are only the past time output.
Why?
Because if you look at index, it always equal to M minus K, and all the K here are positive
number.
So we are taking only the past value of the output.
This is where the first term represent.
They represent some past time output.
We can use them to represent the current time output.
The first term, the second term X, X means the input.
But input can also involve current time input or past time input.
So how should I know?
I should look at the index.
So the index here also equal to M minus K. But remember, be careful.
Here the K can be zero.
If my K could be zero, it means I'm using exactly the current time input.
So here the second term involves both the current time input and the past time input.
In other words, a general representation of a futures, in terms of the difference equation,
will be representing the current time output using the past time output together with current
and the past time input.
This is a general expression for any kind of filters.
Now what makes a difference for IR and FIR?
Remember there are two kind of filters.
If you view the filter in terms of how many spikes you have in the impulse response, IR
and FIR, these are two categories we're just saying.
So if you are talking about an IR, it means this term, this term can be non-zero.
Let me repeat.
If you have a difference equation that do involve some contribution from the past time
output, it means this is an IR.
If you don't see this term, for example here, if you see a difference function only representing
the output using the past time input or current time input, this is an FIR.
This is how you can tell whether it's FIR or IR from the difference equation.
This is one thing you can use to tell.
And also you can view the FIR as a special case of the IR.
Why?
Because for IR, if you let the decay, which is the coefficients, to be all zero, you can
reduce the IR representation into FIR.
So in this perspective, you can actually view the FIR as a special case of the IR.
Make sense?
So this is how you can view it.
So the actual implementation, there will be correspondingly the design principle for
FIR and the design principle for IR.
And actually the implementation depends on either in software or hardware form.
Depends on the applications.
So now we have to talk about the structure.
How can we design this digital filter structure using, for example, a certain principle to
design FIR?
So let's see what this slide is talking about.
It's a practical interest to do.
Using interconnecting the basic buildings of the FIR.
Okay I don't even know what this is talking about actually.
But anyway, so what I want to say is that, okay, like I mentioned just now I explained
FFT.
I'm saying that you can represent some filters in the mathematical form.
If you remember, I showed you the mathematical form of FFT in the first place.
Later I'll show you another block diagram, the butterfly diagram if you remember, to
show equivalently what I explained the mathematical form.
So why people are interested in that diagram?
I mean, of course, sometimes it's simpler.
For example, the FFT case, they keep showing how you can divide the eight points all the
way to one point.
But also people like it is because showing this diagram can also give you a straight
forward way for filter design.
Because when you design the filter, you are doing nothing but assembly of those components
together.
So by showing the block diagram, it's also the way to show how the filter is designed.
So here's why we need to learn equivalently how can we use this block diagram to represent,
let's say, any filters in general.
We have already learned that you can represent a filter using a transfer function, using
an impulse response.
But these are mathematical forms.
They are good, but even if you know that, it's not straightforward to design the filter.
So here we have to learn that you can actually use a diagram, we call it a block diagram,
to represent the actual digital system that you want to design.
I think FFT is one example.
That's one example you can use the diagram to represent it.
But here I wish to share with you the general way to represent the filter using the block
diagram.
So to do so, normally we need to use some building blocks of the diagram.
Some of them you have already seen in FFT.
For example, this symbol means addition.
You have two inputs, you want to sum them together.
You will use this kind of addition, kind of a block, to indicate you are doing adding
two numbers.
So normally the way is that if you write it like this, it means the output equal to x
plus w.
The addition is one of the commonly used building blocks.
Another one is a multiplication.
You want to multiply an input with some number.
You will just write a triangle to say that y equals to a times x.
Remember, this triangle, the direction matters.
The input always goes from the h and output goes from the corner.
This is how it means.
The orientation matters for the multiplications.
The last one may be a little bit new to you.
You see this kind of block with z to the power of minus one.
So this is actually called a delay, time delay operator.
How many of you have learned the z-transform?
I want to show you how.
Some of you have learned z-transform.
For those who do not know z-transform, so z is nothing but e to the power of minus j
omega.
Sorry, j omega.
Basically, it's a simpler way to represent a Fourier transform, basically.
But because of that, we learned that if you have a phase shift in the frequency
domain, it will be corresponding to a time delay in the time domain.
Remember, we learned that.
So when you want to implement a time delay in the time domain, it will be
equivalent to impose a phase shift in the frequency domain.
So that's why they will use a z to the power of minus one to indicate that I'm
multiplying a e to the power of minus j omega in the frequency domain, which will
be equivalently doing a delay of time by one in the time domain.
This is where the z minus one comes from.
But basically, if you see a block with z to the power of minus one, it means all
the signal will be delayed by one.
It's very simple.
So using these building blocks, you can use them to represent, I would say, the
commonly seen filters for this subject.
And it's already good enough.
Like I mentioned, the advantage of using that is it's easy to write down a
computational algorithm by just looking at the diagram.
And also, you can use this diagram to determine explicitly the relationship
between the output and input, which is easy for design.
So let me show you some.
And let me show you the principle of constructing a diagram.
Normally, when you want to construct a diagram, you have to first write down the
expression for the output signal of each other as the sum of the input signal.
So basically, you have to develop a set of equations that relate the input and
output signal in terms of all internal signals.
And then eventually, you want to eliminate the unwanted internal variable and
obtain the expression.
So these are basic steps.
So you start from the mathematical relationship of the original signal, and
you break them down into multiple steps that can be represented using these
modules.
And eventually, that's how you can write on a diagram.
This is how you can design it.
But another way you can get for the question is that they can give you a
diagram first.
And they want to analyze the diagram and write down what is the relationship
between the x and y.
Okay, I would say this is the most common question you are seeing in the exam or
in the homework or quiz.
So I mean, and this is actually very important.
We have to learn how to do this.
So let's look at this example.
So as you can see, this is a block diagram where you can tell that there's
input x and there's output y.
So the entire process here represents the system.
Basically, the system processes the input and generate the output.
But of course, it's not very easy to tell, for example, the transfer function
directly from this block diagram.
Because the block diagram only uses the fundamental building blocks, like addition,
multiplications, or maybe delay.
So our job is to derive, let's say, the transfer function,
mathematically represent the filters from diagram here.
Okay, how to do it?
So just now I'm saying that we're saying that if you want to write the block
diagram from the equation, you have to divide the equation into multiple steps.
And make sure every step or every sub equation are
representable using the building blocks.
Now we're doing the opposite, right?
So we do have the block diagram.
How can we get the equation?
We have to first write down the simple relationship at certain
portion of the diagram.
So for example, I can start from this part, right?
I can tell that, well, this w1, even though this w1 is not the final input or
final output, but that's the signal I get here, right?
I can tell that this w1 will be obtained by adding, let's say,
x plus this branch, all right?
Remember, this is definition for summation, right?
The addition operator says the output equal to the first branch plus the second
branch.
The first branch will be x, so I write x here, all right?
The second branch, you can tell that it's equal to here,
let's say this is s2, right?
You give a name, right?
This is anywhere intermediate kind of a signal.
Say if this is my s2, this branch equal to s2 multiplied by minus alpha, right?
So the final w1 will be x minus alpha times s2, right?
So I complete the simple equation only considering this junction, all right?
So the step one is always write down the simple equation considering only,
let's say, one junction using those intermediate signal or variables, okay?
You can do the same thing for w2, right?
W2, for example, here equals to, so what is this?
This is actually w1, right?
W1 comes here, become the first branch.
Now, second branch equal to s1 multiplied by minus, you know, sigma, right?
So you can do them sum together, give you w2.
All right, you do the same thing for this junction and
for this junction, you got w3 and you got w1, right?
W, sorry, y, you got y, y is here, this is coming from this junction,
w3 coming from this junction.
So you can use those key junctions to write multiple but simple equations by
considering the fundamental building blocks.
But make sure you cover all the building blocks, all right?
If you don't cover all the building blocks, you may miss some information.
Okay, now what's next?
Now you have four equations, but of course,
none of this equation will tell you directly what is y over x, the transfer function, right?
So the second thing you do is to simplify that.
Okay, let's see how many variables we have.
We actually have w1, w2, w3, s1 and s2, right?
So these are the so-called intermediate variables.
So our job is to cancel all of them and
to only leave x and y in one equations because that's how you can get the transfer function.
So you can do some kind of simple trick.
For example, here, we can easily tell that s1 here, right?
How can I get s1?
s1 will be getting from the w2 multiplied by phase delay, right?
So you can use the s1 equal to w2 phase delay and also s2 here is equal to w3 by phase delay.
So these two will help you to kill two intermediate variables, right?
So eventually, you are saved two and you will have w1, w2, w3,
three intermediate variables plus two input output variables.
So now you can perfectly solve, let's say, how should I say?
Three unknowns with four equations, which is definitely solvable.
So you can do all of this kind of cancellation.
For example, you can start from the second equation to get rid of one of the, let's say, w3, right?
Also, you can use the third equation to get rid of some of them.
So to combine them, I won't go into detail, but I believe all of you can know how to cancel variables
using multiple linear equations.
But all of them, by doing all of them, your job is to cancel or to kill w1, w2, w3 because
all of them are intermediate.
You invented them, but you have to get rid of them, right?
And only ways are there constant in your final expression, OK?
So your final expression will still keep the y and x because they are the actual input and output.
You can keep all of these constant, which are introduced by the multiplication, right?
And divide x, sorry, divide y with x.
So these will be your final transfer function, right?
Transfer function is defined as the final output spectrum divided by the final input spectrum
using the z-transform, right?
So these are, this is actually the overall transfer function.
Then you can derive from the equivalent block diagram, all right?
So let me just repeat, right?
Or let me just summarize what we have done.
So the question, what the question gave you is just a block diagram, right?
The block diagram uniquely determines what is the system, what is the filter, all right?
So your job is to derive the transfer function of the filter.
So where do you start with?
You start with the key conjunction within the plug diagram.
So very likely you can use the addition sign as the key junction, right?
So here we've got four addition signs.
You can use them to formulate four simple equations describing the relationship in that junction.
Plus there are also some kind of relationship between W2 and S1, W3 and S2, right?
But here you actually have six equations with how many unknown, right?
W1, W2, W3, S1 and S2.
So you have five intermediate variables you want to get rid of.
You have six equations.
You should be able to kill all of them.
Only leave Y and X survive, right?
So your job is to use all of these equations, get rid of the intermediate variable, even though you can start with them,
but you have to somehow remove them by cancellation, right?
You can do all sorts of cancellation you like, all the way until you only have the constant or phase delay
introduced by the block diagram to form your final transfer function.
So your job is to find a single line equation representing Y divided by X, right?
So this will be the final destination.
So if you reach here, you actually get the answer, right?
This is actually the transfer function.
So this is one example.
I hope you give you how you can actually translate a block diagram to a mathematical expression of a transfer function.
But both of them are representing the same system, just two different ways.
But you have to know how you can go from one to the other, right?
OK.
So any question for this?
I mean, it's important, and I wish you can know at least know the principle, step one, step two, step three, right?
So any question about this example?
We're better clear now, right?
So, OK, one common question is that you somehow get a fewer equation than you need, right?
For example, I only get the four, right?
I find out, oh, I have six, maybe five variables, intermediate variable, but only have four.
Then you must meet something, OK?
You will always have, let's say you have n intermediate variable.
You should always have n plus 1 equations, OK?
If you somehow find you got fewer, you keep finding.
You must be able to find some more, all right?
So the principle is this, except for X and Y, OK?
All of those intermediate variables, let's say n.
You have to get n plus 1 equation.
That's how you can solve it, all right?
So check until you have n plus 1 equation.
Then you can start to do this kind of elimination, cancellation of intermediate variables, right?
Otherwise, you cannot get rid of all of them, OK?
Good.
OK, great.
So, I mean, this is one of the important things I want to emphasize.
Of course, right?
This is a general way, right?
A general way we show that how you can go from a block diagram to get the actual transfer function.
Well, there are some special type of block diagrams.
So first of all, if I give you a transfer function, there are actually many, many ways to design the block diagram.
So it's not unique.
Block diagram is not unique.
You can have multiple ways to design the block diagram to represent the same transfer function, all right?
And because of that, sometimes we don't want the structure of the block diagram to be arbitrary, to be random.
We want the structure of the diagram to be something compact, right?
We want to minimize the design.
So this is why we need to ensure that the structure or the diagram is called, you know, canonical kind of structure.
OK, so what does that mean?
Well, if you say a structure is canonical,
it means the number of delays in the block diagram will be exactly equal to the order of the transfer function.
OK, so first of all, what is the order of the transfer function, right?
Here's one example.
Suppose this is my so-called difference equation.
Difference equation can be easily transferred to a transfer function, right?
By the way.
But you can analyze the order also from the difference equation.
So this difference equation, remember, difference equation, right hand side got two parts, right?
One coming from past time output, one coming from the input, right?
You look at what's the highest order of each of the polynomial.
OK, so this polynomial, what is the highest order?
One, right?
So and this polynomial is also one.
So in other words, the order of this transfer function should be one.
It's a first order transfer function.
So the canonical structure should also have only one delay function,
or delay block, module in the diagram.
If you have a block diagram representing this transfer function with only one delay module,
that means that structure is canonical.
OK, apparently this one is not because this one you can find two delay module, right?
That means this block diagram must be redundant.
So there will be some redundant structure in this block diagram.
It can be further simplified, right?
So which means this structure is, we call it the non-canonic, not kind of minimized or not compact,
because it used two delay to realize a first order difference equation, right?
So the reason we love canonical structures is because it gives you the minimum cost
when you actually pass this block diagram for implementation, right?
You definitely want to minimize the structure such that the implementation can lower the cost, right?
This is the principle.
So I mean, this is just some example for you to check.
So you can't get something like this.
I mean, suppose this is your exam question, right?
So say, hey, I kind of give you this block diagram, right?
So they want you to first determine the transfer function,
and they want you to answer or to check, is this kind of block diagram canonical or not, all right?
So you can have something like this in the exam.
So how should you do this?
Well, you have to think about yourself, right?
How can I determine whether a block diagram is canonical or not, right?
The principle is to check or count how many delay I have
and compare to the order of my transfer function, all right?
Is it hard to count to the number of delays?
It's not hard, right?
You can just say, well, I have how many?
One, two, three, four.
I have four delays, right, in the blocks.
The thing you do not know for sure is what's the order of the transfer function.
So the key here is you should always first compute the transfer function,
and that's how you can compare, right?
So how can we compute the transfer function?
We just learned this.
You start from some key conjunction, junction in the block diagram.
For example, here and here, you can form the three junctions, maybe here as well.
You can form a list of equations using these junctions, right?
And somehow cancel all of these intermediate variables to learn it at a transfer function, okay?
You have to get this first.
And this is how you can tell the order, right?
How to tell the order?
Well, you look at the numerator and the denominator.
So apparently this, for the both numerator and the denominator, these are second order,
right, because the delay got two, right?
You got second order, polynomial.
That means this is a second order kind of transfer function.
That means if this block got only two delays, that's going to be a canonical, right?
Apparently these doubles.
So this is not a canonical function, a canonical structure,
because it got more than needed in terms of number of delay blocks, okay?
So always, if you want to do something, you think about do I have all the condition I need
to make a decision, right?
To decide whether structure is canonical, I need to know two things.
First one is how many delays I have in the block.
The second thing is what's the order of my transfer function, okay?
The first thing is easy to count.
The second thing is you have to compute, right?
So always compute the transfer function.
Count your number of delay compared to two.
If they're equal, that means it's canonical.
If not equal, very likely you got more than needed in the block diagram.
That means it's actually non-cononical, right?
So this is a common pipeline when you do the question like this, okay?
But of course you have to know how to compute the transfer function, right?
If you do not know how to do this, I cannot help you, all right?
So you have to go back to the process, right?
Example here.
This example shows you how you can exactly compute the transfer function
from a given block diagram, right?
And then this example tells you how you can link the transfer function
to the actual, you know, the property whether the block diagram is canonical or not, right?
Okay?
Clear everybody?
Does it make sense for everyone?
All right, so make sure you can do this.
Okay, I say this twice means it's important and it could be somewhere in the exam or homework or quiz, right?
I hope you know what I mean, right?
But you make sure you can do this and, you know, make sure you know all of these definitions, right?
Okay, so one last thing I want to cover.
I finish this.
I can end the lecture today.
So just now I say that, you know, if I give you a transfer function, let's say to represent a system, right?
You can get more than one block diagram.
In fact, you can get many, infinitely many block diagrams if you want, right?
But if I give you a block diagram, there should be a unique transfer function.
So it's one too many, right?
The relationship is one too many.
Okay, because of that, if I give you a block diagram, right, it's possible for you to find another block diagram,
which represents the same transfer function.
Make sense?
Right, because it's one too many, right?
So these two block diagrams, if they are representing the same transfer function,
we call the two as the equivalent structure of the equivalent block diagram.
So the equivalent means, even though they look very different,
but they are representing the same system or same filter, right?
So that's why we say that we define two digital filter structures to be the equivalent
if they have the same transfer function, right?
So now the question is like, can I have a way to find an equivalent diagram if I have one?
Okay, why I want to do this?
Because sometimes one version is hard to implement.
I want to go for another version, right?
Maybe another version may become easier, right?
So there are many ways to generate the equivalent structure by giving a block diagram.
But we're going to learn one, okay?
Not every method, but one method because it's simple, all right?
So this method is called a transpose operation.
Okay, so what does the transpose means?
Because if I give you a structure like this, and I want to find, let's say,
one specific equivalent structure, I can actually do the following step
to find the transpose of this block diagram.
So here's what I mean by transpose, right?
So you have to first reverse all of the pass direction.
Okay, so what is pass direction?
If you see a line here, right, every kind of a signal have a path,
and there's a direction indicating by this arrow, right?
So this arrow means the signal goes down through the multiplication, right?
So the step one you have to do is make the direction reversed for every path.
Okay, so if the original is like this, I have to go the other way around, all right?
So step one, reverse all the pass direction.
Step two, replace the pick off nodes.
So this is actually a pick off node.
It means the signal will be branched into two from one, all right?
So replace all of the pick off nodes with an adder.
So if here this is a pick off node, make it an addition operator, and vice versa.
So if originally this is my addition, I make it a pick off, okay?
So just swap the pick off nodes with the addition.
This is step two, right?
Step three, interchange the input and output.
So in other words, this is going to be my y, this is going to be my x.
All right, makes sense?
Very simple, right?
Change the order, change the direction of the path, replace pick off with addition,
replace addition with pick off, swap the input and output, right?
So you can easily find something called the transpose diagram, right?
So why we call the transpose?
So I guess all of you know what is the transpose of a matrix, right?
You can flip the matrix and make it a transpose.
This is like when you flip the diagram, make the other diagram.
And by doing so, these two diagrams, even though they are different,
they will be equivalent.
So they will give you exactly the same transfer function, okay?
But we have to do this in the correct way, right?
So you have to exactly follow the three steps.
If you miss anyone, you will be wrong.
So the answer will be wrong.
But if you follow exactly all the steps, you will get at least one equivalent
representation.
And because of this is easy, so we just learned this, but it's very useful, right?
Because it's very easy to get some alternative version.
Hopefully it's going to be, how should I say, simpler, right, in implementation.
But I hope everybody knows, right, how I can get from here to here.
Any question?
Ask now, right?
So it makes sense for everyone, like how I can go from the top.
This is my original diagram.
I want to find the equivalent.
This is how I end up with.
So how can I go from here to the bottom one?
I'm doing the three steps.
All right, so make sure you see the change, right?
And make sure the change makes sense for you, okay?
But it's a very simple change.
I mean, it shouldn't be very hard to understand.
But if you do this, you will guarantee to have an equivalent, I mean,
block diagram for any given one, all right?
So by doing so, right, I mean, there are other methods for equivalent, but
they are either very complicated or they may be based on some specific
algorithm for structures, so we won't learn it, right?
And in fact, if I give you a diagram, there should be, by theory,
infinitely many number of equivalent structures, realizing the same kind
of transfer function.
And you cannot, it's impossible to develop all the equivalent realization, so
we will just focus on the common use structure for this course.
So for any given kind of structure, you should be able to apply that method to
get the equivalent one.
So you don't need to worry about other methods, right?
But there will be some special case, which will be beyond the scope of this course.
All right?
Okay, so I will just leave this for next time, maybe,
because it's already not as a promise, I'm gonna end now.
So there will be, you will see that there will be some slides removed from these
lectures, I will move them to the next lecture, right?
So there will be update of the slides, so don't be surprised if you see that.
And I could have some updates for the next week, so
do check updated version once I make a change.
And if you see some slides, I remove them, means you don't need to worry about them.
They won't be examined, they won't be taught.
You only focus on the content I cover in the lecture, it should be enough.
Okay?
Okay, great, thank you.
Let's end today, I hope you can catch the bus, right?
Thank you, I'll see you next week.