All right. First of all, sorry, I went to the wrong room. Sorry, I didn't know that
this course is actually not fine. I believe all of you are here for 6401, right? Advanced
digital signal processing. Okay? At least I'm in the right room now. So hopefully,
we should have already given you an introduction last week. All right? So how many of you were
here last week? Okay, great. All of you are here. So you probably know basically what
you're expecting for this course, right? And I wish to emphasize this again later in the
slides, because you are still in the end-and-job period. In other words, if you don't find this
course suitable for you, you can still drop it, right? But we do need some, you know,
basics. I mean, we do need you to have some background on signal processing to take this
course. The reason is that if you look at the title of the course, it says advanced digital
signal processing. In other words, you should have some background on signal processing
in principle, right? So, I mean, so think about it, because we do have some students before
reflected that everything is so hard. And so if you think this course is too advanced,
you can also consider dropping that, right? So I mean, the reason I'm mentioning this
is, you know, it's now still time for you to think about it, all right, before it's too
late. But anyway, let me start this lecture first. Oops.
Don't sign. Skip it.
Got it.
Of course, advanced signal processing.
Lecture one. All right, great.
Oops. All right, so let's start. Sorry that I'm late for five minutes, because I thought
it's in the soft spot again. You know, I will note that, you know, this year actually we
got more master students. So I think that's the reason we have to schedule here. So basically,
this is your second week, right? Propheting was covering the first week. So I will be
covering all the remaining lectures before recess week. So basically, I'm going to talk
about the main contents for, you know, signal processing, filtering, filter design, and
also multirate processing. So my name is Bi Han. You can call me Bi Han, or Wen, I mean,
either way. So I'm the system professor at the School of Triple E. And you can find my
information, my email, my homepage here. So, you know, this is a course maybe quite classic,
right? So it's mainly for signal processing. And we're going to focus on digital signal
processing. So I believe some of you may also take an analog signal processing for your
during undergraduate. All right, so kind of show of hands how many of you are like EE
background, like electrical engineering background, or maybe like control or, you know, at least
not computer science, all right? Okay, how many of you are from, I don't know, computer
science, math, or other kind of discipline, which you have never done signal processing?
We have a few. Okay, so any of you like never heard of signal processing? Like you do not
know what is signal, what is system, what do you mean by processing? Okay, so the reason
I'm mentioning that is that I do know that all of you coming from quite diverse background.
Okay, so that's why, you know, you are realized that for this week and next week, what I'm
doing is basically help you to review and recap on some of the, you know, basic knowledge
about signal processing. So today I go through like the DTFT, you know, this create for your
transform, while you know, aliasing, right, you know, errors. So this may be very obvious
for some of you, especially for those who have already taken the digital signal processing
undergrads, right? So you can treat this as some review, you know, in case you, I mean
too, for you to refresh your memory, refresh your memory. But for those of you who find
the things I'm talking about today, you know, not familiar, right? You find like everything
is quite new to you. You probably need to look at, you know, learn more from, let's
say, textbook, because you probably have not taken any course in signal processing in
your undergrads. So you need to get those basic knowledge in order to learn the new things,
you know, in the future weeks. All right. So kind of do it, treat this as a checkpoint
for yourself, right? So to evaluate whether you are pretty much know a lot or you need
to catch up, right? It's okay to, you know, not knowing too much about signal processing,
but you need to spend more time to catch up, right? This is what I want to say. So we do
have a textbook. I believe you can find them in the library, but it's not something compulsory.
In other words, even if you don't read the textbook, you follow the slides I'm talking
about, maybe later, Prof Lin is going to talk about, it should be sufficient for exam for
this course. But if you wish to go beyond what we talk about, you want to learn more,
or you want to catch up to maybe kind of learn those things you haven't learned undergraduate,
you are more than welcome to check the textbook. All right. So this is what I, the reason I'm
mentioning here, so we do have one, but it's not compulsory. Okay? So, oh, by the way,
for my course, at least for my half, you can ask a question anytime. Okay? You don't have
to wait until the end. Of course, you can ask me questions during the break. So we're
going to have a break, maybe in one hour, okay? Because it's a three hour lecture, it's very
long, right? So we're going to have a break. So you can ask me, or you can ask me anytime.
So now if you have a question, don't hesitate, raise your hand. I can answer your question.
I actually prefer you to ask me. Anytime you have any doubt, you have questions, because
that probably means I didn't get things clear. Right? So ask me, don't wait, don't wait until
too late. All right? So ask me anytime. You can interrupt me if you have a question. Okay?
So this is our textbook. So this is like our plans for my part. I cannot speak for profanity,
but for my part. So basically the first two lectures, right, this week, next week, you
can consider as some review or kind of an introduction to the fundamental of digital signal processing.
So today I'm going to talk about what is the sampling process. In other words, how can
we convert analog signal? Or in other words, continuous time signal to discrete time signal,
right? Sampling process. Mathematically, what does the sampling mean? Right? And also,
how can we represent signal, especially discrete signal, in frequency domain? The reason is
that everybody loves frequency domain because frequency domain tells you more about the signal.
It's a better representation for you to understand, for example, where it is income from, how can
you design your filters, right? So you need to get yourself familiar with frequency representation
because you're going to use that for the whole subject, all right? And also that's why we
use all of these kind of transforms, right? Later you will have continuous time for your
transform, discrete time for your transform. All of these transforms you heard is to convert
time domain signal to frequency domain, right? That's all the purpose. The reason is that
we believe frequency representation means can represent more information. They are better
for us to analyze, okay? So we'll talk about how we can represent them in frequency domain.
And the next week we're going to move on to this processing, right? Today we'll be focusing
on signal, you know, how can we sample signal, how can we represent signal? Next week, it's
going to review the processing. In other words, the system, right? How can we design the system
to process the signal, like low pass, high pass, band pass, and all of these kind of
filtering, right? And something new is that, okay, we know how to, we know how we want
to process the signal, but how can we exactly design the filters to do things as we need,
right? So we'll talk about filter design. How can we design the filter that exists in
practice, not just theoretically, but existing in practice, okay? So we'll talk about filters
in lecture three. Lecture four and five, right? Last but not least, one of the very important
things for, at least my part, is still going to teach you the multi-rate signal processing.
How many of you heard of multi-rate processing? I mean, there's a mono-rate, there's a multi-rate
signal processing. How many of you heard of multi-rate processing? Okay, not too many.
How many of you heard of wavelets? Okay, you heard of wavelets, okay, very good. So wavelets
is very popular, and wavelets is actually a multi-rate signal processing tool, right?
If you look at how you design this low, low pass, low high pass, it's actually keep dividing
the signal into half and half, right? The thing we're doing this division is nothing
but introducing multi-rate processing, okay? So later, you know, the last part of actually
my half, we'll be focusing on multi-rate processing, we're going to deal with, you know, increase
the sampling rate, decrease the sampling rate to process the signal in different rates,
basically, and we're going to teach you what is the reason of doing that, right? There's
a reason we're going to do it, okay? But these will be mainly the components for my part,
okay, like how many, five lectures in total, right? And you're going to have a homework,
okay, by the end of the week five, okay, which is the second last week before recess. The
homework will be just a bunch of questions. You can do it at home, but we have a deadline,
so I'm going to give you like a week, or maybe I don't know, a week and a half for you to
do it, and you're going to submit them through NTU Learn, and I'm going to grade it. So it's
going to be 20 percent, all right? So it's a reasonable portion of the marks, all right?
So, and also, I mean, this one, maybe we don't have it, but we're trying, I will try to,
I mean, maybe I don't have an extra saving, but I will set up some time for you to ask
me questions, especially, you won't see me again in the second half, right? So maybe
in the last week, if you have any questions, I will leave some time for you to ask me before
maybe towards the end of the exam, right, final exam, okay? And then, you know, after
recess, we're going to have profiling back, right? He's going to teach you something else,
like IRR, you know, this kind of field design, which, you know, wait for his part. So in
total, right, you know, marks, you know, this is also important for you because this is
going to affect your GPA. So 100 percent, that's the total marks we have. We do have a final
exam, right? Final exam is the most important thing, 60 percent, okay? So it's very standard,
but I don't know, how many of you are first year here? Or maybe, let me ask you the other way,
how many of you are not first year? I mean, how many of you have been here already, like,
semesters? Okay, but you have done some exam, right? So you know how the exam works. So basically,
if I know exam is maybe similar as you did, maybe in your home country, like, you just sit
there, we have a time for you, you come and see it, we give you three hours to do, like,
six questions, all right? Very formal, very standard, but, and then of course, that's 60 percent,
okay, final exam. But before that, we have two continuous assessments, right? Basically, before
exam, we have two assignments, like homework. So I will give you one, profiting will give one,
so each of them works 20 percent. So that's how you can get your final score, right? 40 percent
coming from, coming from two assignments, 60 percent coming from exam. So exam is important,
you have to prepare for exam, but also CA is also important, okay? So this is all you need to do,
to get the marks, okay? Any question? Yes? Exam, you mean? Yes, close book, close book. So final
exam will be close book, homework you can check, I cannot control, I mean, you can read your book
if you want, but most likely homework will be more difficult, okay, as expected, because you can,
check your textbook, right? So homework, you can read whatever you like, use a computer, use a
textbook, whatever you like, but final exam will be close book, okay? Good question, yes?
Oh, okay, good question, good question, table formula. We haven't decided yet, but if we need you to
use some formula, those will be provided, okay? So if, let's say, there's a question,
for example, I need you to do a Fourier transform for, let's say, Zinc function, right, Zinc function,
nobody knows what's the transform, but we're provided, right? The purpose of having the exam is not to
ask you to memorize it, it's ask you to apply there. So we do not know yet, we're going to set the
question very soon, but not yet, if there's an in use formula, we're going to provide it. So don't
worry, don't need to memorize those very weird functions, how you do transform. So they will
provide it if they are needed, okay? Good points, any other question?
Sorry?
What are you going to publish this time? The first one?
Oh, the first one, okay, good question, I just mentioned, right? The first assignment will be
announced in week five. So this is week two, week five will be, how many? Three, four, five, so three
weeks from now. It's not due time, due time will be before recess, okay? So the reason I announced
later is because you need to have the knowledge until week five to do it, so I didn't announce now,
it doesn't make sense to announce now, but it's going to be announced in week five, provided that
all of the knowledge you need will be already covered, okay? Good, any other questions? Yes?
So it's not a quiz, you mean who said that?
Oh, Professor Lin said it's quiz, oh no, it's homework actually, it's homework,
maybe he got it wrong, so it's not a quiz, it's homework, but again, you know, 20%, right? You
have to be serious about it, so it's homework means you can bring home, you can do it at home,
but you have to submit before deadline, so I'll give you a deadline, maybe give you a week to do it,
maybe a couple days more, so you don't have to come here to do it, but you have to do it at home
and give me the reasonable answers, okay? Good, any other questions?
No more? Okay, great, so I can move on. So, okay, some useful information before I move on, right?
So as I mentioned in the very beginning, these course do need some math, okay? Unfortunately,
unfortunately, they do need some math, so, you know, we are trying our best to minimize the
requirement of the math, in other words, we don't really dump you with all of the formulas,
but still, you need to have basic mathematics, I believe maybe all of you should have that,
but you know, you do some evaluation, right, whether you are comfortable with the level of
math, but we do need to have some math to teach the course, so if you feel like very uncomfortable
with the math, you may think about it because that's something you need for the entire subject,
all right? So, we will provide the, you know, notes every week and every week, I'm going to
quickly review what we talked about previous week for you to do a recap, meanwhile, if you have
questions you can ask, right, I will provide the chance to ask questions, and for some of you,
maybe a good option for you to form groups among students to learn, you know, study together,
right, that's a common strategy people use, so this is just a suggestion for you, and like I said,
if you have a question, I strongly encourage you to ask immediately, just now I think some of you
did a quite good job, right, so don't wait because if you wait, you may forgot your question, so it
doesn't make sense to wait, right, so if you have any question, or maybe you spoke about the type
of what I have in the slides, right, feel free to let me know, you know, I'm happy, you know,
if you ask me, rather now, rather than later, okay, so yeah, so some of you, like, and then some of
you may be very strong, you know, I don't know, because I also participate in the, you know,
application review, right, so some of you are graduated from very good universities, you have
really good GPA, oh sorry, GPA, so you may have already know this, right, sorry, I'm using GPA
every day, so anyway, some of you have really good GPA, so you probably find these are something
pretty old for you, so well consider this as a review, right, but you will find new things
starting from the week after next week, I promise that, we do have recording, so you see there's a,
is there recording, I think there's a recording, right, so the recording will be posted online,
right, have you found the recording for week one, okay, so means it's going to record,
means that you can replay, in case you are absent for some of the weeks, it's fine, you can still
watch the recording, right, this is the, it's good for you to do a recap later, and it's going to be,
it's going to be made available after the lecture, okay, so these are some of the information,
all right, so now let's move on to the actual content this week,
oops, okay, so like I mentioned, right, we, for this course at least, we are going to focus on,
you know, this quick signal, in other words, digital signal, right, because all of the signals
stored in the computer, your phones, they are not analog, but of course our real signal in
nature, they are analog, for example, when I talk, my acoustic signal is analog signal,
my view of this kind of environment is going to be analog signal, goes to my mind, right,
but how can we actually convert analog signal to digital signal that can be stored or can be
transmitted in the digital system, right, so we need to have a pipeline to process or to convert
continuous time signal to digital signal, so this is actually a very typical pipeline,
where you can see that the signal comes in not directly to the processor, right, so consider
this process as, you know, maybe your computers, your phone, which are actually processing the
system, so before passing the signal to the processor, you have to have this two stage,
right, the first stage would normally refer as A2D, right, analog to digital conversion,
the second stage is actually D2A, convert digital back to analog signal, you have to have these two
stages, but you may also realize that there are actually two modules, right, beyond just AD or DA,
okay, the first module, which is the very first module, we call it anti-adiasing
filter, how many of you heard of the term anti-adiasing filters? Anyone heard of the term?
Oh, I'm surprised, okay, we have some, you never heard of AD-Azing, okay, that's why I think you
have to pay attention for today's review, okay, because AD-Azing is a big problem for many many
application like communications, you know, image processing, nobody wants AD-Azing, okay, the whole
idea of designing a system to be good is to prevent AD-Azing, right, so later I'm going to teach you
what exactly, what I mean by AD-Azing, but because of that, we have to have this something called
anti-adiasing filter to avoid AD-Azing, so AD-Azing is kind of distortion, kind of error that we do
not want, so we want to get rid of it, right, so, but basically later I'm going to teach you that
anti-adiasing filter is nothing but a low-pass filter, okay, but you have to design the low-pass
filter to the way that it's going to kill the AD-Azing, all right, so, but this is something
we have to have, it's before the A2D converter, right, before analog to digital conversion,
there must be anti-adiasing filter, okay, it's before, then, you know, we can do this A2D converter
to convert a, you know, like a conscious time signal to a finite amount of discrete signal,
and this A2D process is actually referred as sampling, okay, so you keep here the name sampling
like many, many times for this subject, but sampling is nothing but conversion from analog
to digital signal, right, so we are going to use sampling to represent this process for the entire
subject, right, so once you do sampling, we are getting the digital signal, and we can apply
the DSP system, right, digital signal processing system to process the discrete time signal,
and this will be the main focus for this course, not today, right, but maybe starting from tomorrow,
we're going to learn how we can design this DSP process, right, in the way we want,
and in the way that's going to be practical, all right, so it's going to be going to be the main
focus, but of course after you process the digital signal, we have to convert it back to the real
life, so that's why we also have to have this inverse process, right, like digital back to
analog converter, which is nothing but reconstruction of the analog signal from the digital measurement,
so it's the reverse process of the A2D, right, now we have to do D2A, and when we do this reconstruction
process, we also have to have this extra filter, we call it reconstruction filter, the reason is to
make sure in the output, all of these so-called other components beyond the bandwidth can be
somehow eliminated, so we only evaluate the baseband signal, later on we're going to see what do we
mean by baseband signal, but to do it, only D2A is not important, not enough, you have to have the
last one called reconstruction filter to get rid of the replicates, right, only keep the baseband
signal, so also the last filter is also low pass filter, but it has to be there, right, so now you
can see that in the beginning we need a low pass filter, it's called anti-aliasing, okay, in the
end we also need another low pass filter, it's called a reconstruction filter, okay, so these two
are also something like a mast in the pipeline, on top of the A2D and D2A, right, so the four things,
together with the DSP system, form the classic pipeline of signal processing, all right, so this
is something like an overview of what we're talking about, when we say advanced signal processing,
right, and these fundamental blocks are actually common, right, no matter we are talking about
audio signal processing, image signal processing, even NLP, right, text processing, these pipelines
are common pipelines, so you have to have them, but of course the actual digital signal processing
will be different, but the way we convert analog to digital anti-aliasing reconstruction, these are
common, right, so what we are learning today will be applicable to all sorts of applications,
right, this is a common pipeline, all right, so you know just now we say that you know that's
the common pipeline, and the reason we want to do this DSP is to basically, you know, once you
have a signal, right, the reason we spend a lot of time designing this DSP, the objective is to
extract information from the signal, all right, so there's a difference between information and the
data or signal, right, so we're dealing with a lot of signal nowadays, right, you have, you know,
every time you use your phone, you are receiving many many kind of signals, right, but information
may be still limited, right, what you want is not the signal themselves, what you want is the
information, so this is the whole idea why we need to process them, right, the idea is to process the
big amount of signals and only extract information you need, right, this is the whole reason we want
to process it, and that's why we need a DSP algorithm, which is going to depend on the type of
signals we're talking about, and also the characteristics of the information that is
carried by the signal, for example, if you want to, for example, you want to focus on certain bandwidth,
maybe that bandwidth is the only meaningful part, the other bandwidths are noise, right, how can we
denoise, how can we extract those bandwidths, you need to know where the signal is, what kind of
frequency this signal has, right, so if you know the characteristics, you can design the corresponding
bandpass filter to select the useful bands, right, so this is actually one of the principles
of designing the algorithm, and also we need to have multiple ways of representing the signal,
so later we're going to look at all sorts of transforms, and the tool of them is to represent
a signal in the right domain, right, right frequency, right spectrum, right, so that's why we need to maybe
be familiar with both the time representation, like you represent a signal as a function of time,
as well as representing the signal as a function of frequency, right, different kind of frequencies,
because maybe one of them is good for you to extract information, some of them may not be so
obvious, right, this is the reason we need so many transforms, okay, and also, you know, one of the
common methods we use to design a processing system is by filtering, okay, I believe all of you
should know filtering, right, if you're taking a basic signal processing, you may have heard of
filtering, right, it's a kind of the basic components of a system, right, filtering, and the
filtering could play different roles, right, for example, some of the filters may choose to pass
certain frequency components, right, you may have heard of high pass filter, right, low pass filter,
it means only these frequency range will be survived in the processing, will either be killed, okay,
also there could be some filter they try to block certain frequency, right, maybe like a band stop
filters, they only survive the rest of the band, those band signal will be killed, right, so this
is actually where the name come from, so it depends on the function, the filters may preserve some
components, they may also kill some of the components of the signal, right, and for this course, we're
going to focus on digital filters not only for moderate, so most of the filter you learned before
may be moderate, right, but we also focus on multirate filters, right, in other words, the
filter can deal with the signal maybe in a faster sample version or maybe in a slower sample version,
right, for some reasons, maybe for efficiency, maybe for effectiveness, right, so this is also part
of things we're going to learn, okay, and like I said, right, the basics of DSP is important,
which you learn in the first three weeks, so the first three weeks will be quite fundamental,
but they are very important, if you do not know like the basic formulations, basic terminologies,
you will have some difficulties when you learn the more advanced topics, right, in the future,
I mean, in a week four or five, six, okay, so don't kind of feel like a very, very relaxed,
even though you know them, I strongly encourage you to still pay attention, all right, because
fundamental is always important, okay, so starting from sampling, right, just now I'm saying that
sampling is nothing but converting analog signal to digital signal, right, in practice, you can
imagine a sampling process as a sampler, right, like this, maybe I use a pointer, like this,
so you can consider a D2A system like analog signal coming, okay, so how to represent analog
signal, you represent it as a function of T, right, so here the T will be a continuous number,
they can take every value, like you know, you know, doesn't really have to discretize, all right,
and after this sampler, which means only, sorry, only with certain time, maybe the multiple time of
the period, time step, the signal can pass, right, other time instances, the signal will be killed,
so this is actually a sampling process, so after the sampling process, right, your output will no
longer be a continuous time signal, so normally we will represent the so-called discrete time signal
using a variable not like T, but like N, right, so by default, T normally means is a continuous
variable, all right, and will be a discrete variable, means N will be integers, okay, so I
believe all of you know the difference, right, discrete, continuous, right, discrete means,
for example, you can only take A, A minus, B plus, there's nothing between A minus and A, right,
this is discrete, continuous means your score, right, it can be 98, it can be 98.2, right,
so you can take every value between it, discrete means there's only a certain value you can take,
all right, so after the sampling, your representation will be like XN rather than XT,
all right, so this will be something by default N will represent discrete variable,
T will represent continuous variable for this subject, okay, and if you want to visualize the
signal, right, continuous time signal will be a continuous function, right, in this, you know,
2D plane where this is your signal, this is your time axis, it's going to be continuous,
dense everywhere, right, but discrete signal will be not continuous, the only sample at say,
you know, T, 2T, sorry, 0, T, 2T, 3T, 4T, like the integer value of the period, only those
NT times, T time step will be sampled, otherwise it will be 0, right, so this will be the big
difference, so this is like illustration of the sampling process, so there are two important
two important variables you have to pay attention, one is the upper case T, all right, so upper case
T will be the sampling period, okay, sampling period means only when the time equal to integer
multiple of T, there is a value in the discrete signal, means like, you know, how separate the
two bars are, right, T actually describes the distance between two bars, two time steps,
the larger the T, the sparser the discrete signal will be, all right, so the T will describe how
you do the sampling, okay, you can represent T in the other way called sampling frequency,
FS, right, FS is nothing but 1 over T, right, it's a reciprocative of T, it's the same thing,
but you can represent either as T or FS, which is 1 over T, it's the same, but either of them
will describe the sampling process, it's important, it's going to categorize how fast you sample it,
how frequently you sample it, okay, so this is the only variable for sampling, so every time when
people say, hey, I'm doing sampling, you have to ask yourself what is the T or what is FS,
without knowing it you have no idea how the sampling is conducted, okay, so this is actually
sampling, so mathematically, right, you can define the signal, you know, continuous time
signal as xA, analog signal, A stands for analog, equal to maybe for example, let's just choose a
cosine signal as for example, right, and if you sample it, it's going to convert xT into a xN,
right, I mean the simple way to do that is just replace T with N times T, remember,
only when T equal to N times T there's a value, otherwise it's zero, so you simply just swap
the variable from T to N times uppercase T, right, that's the sampling process, as I mentioned,
uppercase T means sampling period, FS means sampling rate, so these two will be uniquely
describing the sampling process, okay, okay, so T and FT, these are actual sampling frequency and
actual period, we can also normalize them in the way we can represent them, for example,
instead of using FS, you can represent the smaller, sorry, lowercase, lowercase f as the
normalize sampling frequency, and I mean the reason we want to do that is to make sure the f is
actually within zero and one, okay, in principle you can design any uppercase f you want, you can
something very, very fast, but because the dat number can scale like from very small number to very
big number, you want to make them normalize, you can actually normalize it to make it within zero
and one, okay, it's the same but just the scale, you just scale it, so every time we use lowercase f,
it means normalize frequency, and lowercase f can be only within zero to one, right, that's the only
difference, and if you multiply by two pi, you can make it, you know, radiate, right, rather than
hertz, it's just change of units, but you have to differentiate the uppercase f with the smaller
case f, this is important, all right, any questions so far? Yes?
Why the time can be, oh, okay, good question, so you are saying that how can we understand the time
in the past? Well, in principle, you can have signal in the past, right, that's the first thing,
later we're going to get there, so there's something called causality, causal signal versus
non-causal signal, right, then there's a difference in terms of future time and the past time,
but mathematically, a function can have variable with negative number in principle, right, so we
didn't limit to the t to be positive-negative, but sometimes if we consider the signal, is it
practical or not, then the time matters, right, mathematically, you can make it general, right,
so t larger than zero is future time, t smaller than zero is actually past time, right, nothing
prevent you of doing that, okay, good, yes, uppercase f, you know, fs, right, so sampling rate,
oh, this f, okay, so this f is the, how to say, what's the frequency within the, how should I say,
what's the frequency within the sampling rate, so for example, if my sampling rate is, let's say,
1000 hertz, right, but why we present, let's say, the frequency bandwidth, frequency spectrum, right,
you can actually represent any frequency within it, so this, you know, uppercase f is the actual
frequency, but if you normalize f with the total sampling rate, it's going to be normalized frequency,
so the small f is not equal to fs, but it's going to be a frequency that is normalized within the
sampling range, okay, so later we're going to talk about why we care about the sampling rate,
because sampling rate actually limits the baseband, right, because only, you can only represent the
frequency within fs, which is the baseband, beyond that is actually the replicates, all right, but
the value of f, the small f, can be only taken within one, so it cannot go beyond one, okay, great,
any other questions? Am I running too fast? It's okay, right, if I'm running too fast, you
can, I mean, all you think I'm running too slow, I can also speed up, all right, okay, good, because
I need to, I need to also learn from you, right, because, you know, every batch still doesn't
are different, so I need to understand whether my pace is okay, so let me know, right, if you have
any feedback or comments, because the whole idea is to make you learn, right, if you don't really
can learn anything, it's actually my problem, so I have to, you know, adapt to it, right, okay, so
this is actually how we do A2D, right, sampling is going to do analog to these digital signals,
but the question is, can we design a sampling arbitrary way? In other words, can we sample
the signal in any way we like? In principle, you cannot, right, there's a risk, right, the risk
happens at the time if your sampling rate is too slow, right, you cannot have enough information to
like, well represent the actual signal, right, this is also reasonable, if your sample rate,
like, the signal is very slow, but the signal changed too fast, you didn't capture the change,
right, you have to make sure the sampling is sufficient, right, so what can be wrong if my
sampling rate is too slow, okay, so this is one example, say for example, if I fix my sampling
rate, the rate is on the right, but I have two different signals, right, top one and bottom one,
so even though the analog signal is very different, you can tell it's a different signal, right,
but if you don't have sufficient sampling rate, you can end up with exactly the same discrete
signal, so different analog signal, because you are sampling too slow, they can be represented
exactly the same, which means you are not representing the signal right, because they should be
different, right, so if your representation cannot capture difference, it means you have a huge
representation error, right, so this is where the problem comes from, so you have to have a sampling
rate that is reasonable such that two different signals in the analog domain can be different
you know, differentiated in the frequency, sorry, in the discrete domain, right, so this is where
the idea comes from, if you have this kind of scenario, that means something is wrong, you lose
information in the sampling process, all right, so because in the end, right, remember after your
process, you still have to reconstruct the analog signal from the digital domain, right, so you
have to make sure when you represent a continuous time signal, they can be recovered later, uniquely
and well recovered, right, this is where, I mean, the objective we have to design the system, right,
so in this case, you can treat the digital form, the thing on the right, xn, as an approximation
of the xt on the left, okay, of course it's always an approximation because you lose something, right,
but you want to make sure the approximation gives you an acceptable accuracy or acceptable error
such that you can well represent it, okay, but of course you can always have a super high sampling
rate to make it very good, but there you have to pay the price for the computational cost, right,
the faster your sample, the more computation you need, so basically we're talking about the tradeoff,
you know, between the accuracy, how well you will represent the signal and how much you pay for the
computation, right, this is a tradeoff, you pay more, you get better representation, but then you
have to pay the price, you pay less, you may lose the signal in the beginning, right, so this is the
tradeoff, the thing we're learning here is what is the right, how should I say, what is the minimum
requirement of the cost such that we can still recover the signal in a reasonable way, so this
is what we're going to learn, you know, next, all right, but you understand where the problem
comes from, it's a tradeoff, you want to make sure the sampling rate is not too low such that
signal can be still recovered, but how to determine this requirement, what is the, what the way we
say not too low, what do we mean, right, what is the minimally required sampling rate, right,
this is actually something we wish to know, right, and this one linked to, oh sorry, before that,
right, so okay, like I said, there are two components which are important, frequency,
sampling frequency, right, we need to make sure it's not too low, actually before that, there's
another thing also need to be considered is the number of bits you use to store the value, right,
something like a quantization, you have to, you cannot store the value in the infinite
precision, right, also the bits also matters, but like I mentioned, because of this tradeoff,
you have to make sure that this FS number of bits cannot be too low, neither too high, right,
too low or too high will give you some kind of a cost, right, you have to bear, so the idea of this
design is to make sure the original signal can be recovered from its digital version with acceptable
distortion, error, in other words, so this distortion is actually dominated by aliasing,
okay, this is where the aliasing comes from, aliasing is the distortion caused by, you know,
not sufficient sampling, insufficient sampling, all right, so just now, in the beginning I asked
you how many even knows aliasing, most of you didn't know, so this is a definition,
aliasing is nothing but the error, the distortion caused by insufficient sampling,
okay, so here I show you the exact formula, right, but that's the concept, right, so here's
actually the exact derivation, okay, so mathematically, just now we say that you can convert a discrete
time, sorry, continuous time signal to discrete time signal by simply, you know, changing the T
with N times uppercase T, right, so this will be the digital signal, and of course you have this
parameter T and FS, which are basically the same equivalent to represent a sampling, right,
and we know that sampling frequency is 1 over T hertz, right, and also you can do the radius,
radian sampling if you want, times 2 pi, right, so the frequency domain representation,
we know, I mean all of you know this, right, how many of you never heard of even like a
continuous time for your frequency, sorry, continuous time for your transform, how many of you have
never heard of even CTFT, all of you know that, right, so I don't have to repeat, okay, so there's
something called a CTFT, which can convert a CT analog signal to frequency representation,
it's called Fourier transform, but it's going to deal with CT, all right, and this is the formula,
okay, so I sure, do I need to explain this, or all of you know,
okay, I saw all of you know it, if you don't know it, come to me, I can explain for you,
all right, after the break, but what we care about is actually the DT version, all right,
so CTFT deal with continuous time signal, so basically the function here on the right hand side
is GA, is analog signal, you can do a Fourier representation of this guy, get the corresponding
frequency spectrum GA, all right, but that's for CT, now we have to deal with DT, because for
this subject, BT will be the focus, there is a corresponding version of CTFT called DTFT,
so the only difference is that on the right hand side, you realize the time domain signal is actually
not a GT, but the GN, all right, and because the A is not continuous, you cannot do integration
anymore, right, how can you do integration over a discrete signal, you have to replace
integration with summation, right, summation is the counterpart of integration when you have
discrete signal, so you will see that the change is from the integration to summation,
the range is still like from minus infinity to infinity, the base will be changed, right,
here is actually omega t, but here is small omega, small omega means the frequency in the DTFT domain,
okay, so then correspondingly you will get another spectrum, but this spectrum will be a
discrete signal spectrum, right, so going to be a DTFT result, so this is the tool we use to
represent either CT or DT in the frequency domain, all right, okay, so, okay, I have these slides to
okay, just in case, okay, because I don't know how many of you actually learned DTFT, if you already
know DTFT, forget about this slide, right, there's this recap, but if you have it, you've never
learned DTFT, so this is basically the pairs you need, all right, you need a forward transform
on the top, which is going to convert the time domain to frequency domain, right, and some,
we also refer this as an analysis process, you analyze the signal in the frequency domain,
all right, and there are a few things you have to be careful, right, first one is this guy,
the GP, the left-hand side, it's going to be a periodic function, so in other words,
it's going to repeat itself in the period of 2 pi, you can try this, but mathematically you can
tell that this is actually a periodic function, always, no matter what signals you are talking about,
it's always a periodic function, and I believe all of you know what is this e to the power of minus j omega,
if you use the Euler formula, you can represent it as a real power, which is a cosine, imaginary
power, which is the sine, minus sine, okay, but it's actually the base function, it's a unit circle
in the complex domain, right, and then you can also get it back by applying inverse DTFT to
convert the spectrum back to the time domain, so it's going to give you back, give you recover
signal from the frequency domain, one thing you have to be careful is that there's a 1 over 2 pi
in front, okay, so some of you may ask me why there's 1 over 2 pi, right, it's only a scaling factor,
you want to scale back to the original scale, so you have to compensate this 1 over 2 pi,
right, because we are doing this summation, okay, especially this this integration, you have to
normalize it over the range, right, but it doesn't really change the form, it only changed the scale,
so you will get back to the GN, and the GN will be completely determined by only one period of the
spectrum, you only need one period, because this guy is going to be periodically repeating, right,
but only one period can completely determine GN, because the integration is only over one period,
right, so later you will see that why we only care about the base band, because that's enough,
you don't have to go beyond, right, it's the same, okay, this is just a recap if you do not know what
is, you know, DTFD, okay, but you can actually imagine the difference between DTFT and CTFD
in the following way, right, so consider this 2D plane where you have to care about analog side,
which is on the left, you have to talk about the digital domain on the right, okay, there's always
these two domains, so you can convert the signal in the two domain, that's the DA and AD converter,
we talk about how you can convert the two, correspondingly there will be a tool to convert
signal from top to the bottom, which is actually time domain to friction domain, right, so for the
CT there's something called a CTFD, for discrete signal there's a DTFD, DTFD, right, so both of
them will be the tool you need to get the frequency spectrum, but depends on what signal you're talking
about the tool is different, and you can get back by running the inverse transform, all right, so this
is how you can memorize it, and now what we could really care about is this guy, aliasing, okay,
the whole reason we're talking so many these kind of things like transform, you know, DTFDs to
finally reach the topic we need, the aliasing, right, so this is actually for you to understand
the relationship between the functions, between the signals, how can you do inverse transform,
forward transform, this always appears, right, but how this one end up with the aliasing formula,
okay, so we have to look at the frequency, okay, so sorry, this is not the illustration for you to
understand, right, so basically, right, DTFD is actually a shifted version of CTFT, right, so
just what I'm saying that when you go from digital signal, sorry, analog signal to digital signal
is nothing but the sampling, right, just sample at a certain time, right, so when we say sampling
mathematically what are we talking about, we're talking about, okay maybe I used the mouse,
we're talking about an analog signal multiplied by an impulse train, right, what does impulse
train mean, so you have a lot of impulse at the period of T, right, so if you multiply together,
only the time T or NT will be sampled, right, so sampling process can be viewed as an analog signal
multiply where is the impulse train, right, the impulse train is actually having a period of T,
right, this is a mathematical way of describing sampling, okay, now you can do CTFT for the analog,
you can do DTFD for the discrete signal, right, and you end up with the same thing in the end,
right, if you do CTFT of the CT you will have the spectrum, right, this will be your continuous
time for your transfer result, you can also do the DTFD to get your, you know, DTFD spectrum,
but how are these guys related, right, CTFT result, how is it related to DTFD, well some of you may
learn that the multiplication in time domain is equivalent to a convolution in frequency domain,
right, okay, anyone doesn't know this, anyone doesn't know, but it's very important, right, so
whenever we talk about frequency domain one of the important thing is you can always convert a
multiplication into a convolution, or the other way around, if you have a convolution in time
domain you can do a multiplication in the frequency domain, okay, you can prove this, but it's always
true, so in time domain we're talking about signal multiplied by an impulse train, right,
correspondingly in the frequency domain it's actually a CTFT spectrum convolved with the impulse train,
all right, so this is how these two CTFT and DTFD related, so if I have a signal
I'm convolving the signal with an impulse train, what am I doing here, what do I have in the end,
so I have a signal, right, this for example if this is my signal, right, so I'm convolving the
signal with a bunch of impulse function, so what will I get, what actually happens in this convolution,
exactly repeat, right, because if you have one impulse function it's going to be the self, right,
if you have a signal impulse function it's going to be a shifted version of the function,
if you have impulse train what actually have is a repeated version and a shifted version,
so you are creating duplicates, so this is my original function, I create duplicates with the
shift of t and now the duplicates with shift of 2t, right, sorry, f, sorry, the noise is already f,
right, fs and 2fs, so what happens is that the DTFD results of the CTFT will be nothing but the
duplicate and shifted version, okay, so this is how you can relate CTFT to DTFD, right,
mathematically if this is my CTFT, all right, what I have of the corresponding DTFD will be the
shifted version, of course the shift can be multiple of k, right, k negative means shift to the left,
k positive shifts to the right, but you will create infinitely many replicates of the base signal
by shifting them in the integer of you know omega t here, so that's how you can get to the DTFD
result, yes, yes sampling frequency, yeah, but it's actually, let me see, the small one, yes,
but it's normalized, normalized sampling frequency, yes, so this one depends on sampling frequency,
the higher the sampling frequency, the more shift you have, so the sampling frequency will
determine how much you shift, so we'll get there very soon, right, but you're right, fs is sampling
frequency, yes, okay, but I want you to understand you know because next slide is going to be the
result, but I want you to understand where these replicas come from, it comes from the fact that
all the DTFD will be the shifted version, and repeated version of the CTFT, right, it's coming
from the fact that we're doing multiplication in the time domain, so we're going to be equivalent of
doing convolution in the frequency domain, right, and the convolution with impulse train is nothing
but repeat and shift, okay, I mean if you don't get it just just memorize it, okay, I wish you'd
appreciate that, but you know the important thing is in the end, right, our DTFD result on the left
side will be the shifted version and duplicates of the baseband, Gn, GA, right, GP will be the
you know duplicates of the GA, okay, all right, so now this equation two is important because this
equation is where the AD is in come from, we call it AD is in formula, okay, because something
sometimes is going to be wrong when we create the duplicates, all right, so let's understand why
way it goes wrong, but before that let's define some, okay, not really, okay, fine, so this formula
will be the fundamental or essential to understand what is Nyquist-Umpolian theory, which is basically
maybe the most important theory in signal processing, right, Nyquist-Umpolian theory,
it basically the foundation for all the modern communication signal processing system, but
in the end it's going to be determined by this AD is in formula, okay, and the AD is in well because,
like I mentioned earlier, it's going to be caused by insufficient sampling, in other words, this one
omega t is too small, omega t is large, you are safe, but omega t is smaller, based on the equation
two, you get a problem, okay, so where does this problem come from, let's look at this example,
right, so if this is our CTFT result, spectrum of the continuous time signal, right,
when I'm doing the sampling, I mentioned, what I will have will be the repeated version of my GA,
okay, so this is my GA, I'm going to have my GP like this, okay, so GP is nothing but scaled
and repeat version of my GA, all right, so this is what I mean, just not the formula,
I'm visualized the formula in one example, using this example, right, this is the upper case is
before sampling, this is after sampling, all right, so after sampling you will get this kind of
replicates, right, integer multiple, in the space of integer multiple of omega t, right, one time,
two time, or minus one time, minus two time, okay, so looks okay, right, you just create duplicates,
right, but it may not always be okay, okay, let's define this, okay, so the one in the middle,
we mean in other words, the baseband signal without any shift, we call it baseband,
because this frequency range will be exactly between minus omega t divided by two to positive
omega t divided by two, right, so this is something called the baseband portion,
most likely this will be enough to describe the signal, because otherwise it will be just
repeating, right, this periodic function, so we call this frequency range as the baseband,
or we call it the nyquist band, it contains the entire information of the signal, all right,
and this is one example where you call this baseband and you call the rest of like replicates,
so it is actually clear that you, you know, when your omega t is larger than two times omega m,
okay, so here omega m is defined as the maximum frequency in the signal, okay, what is maximum
frequency in the signal, so consider this is your signal, right, your signal, well, if the signal
has limited band, the maximum band, it means the maximum number of frequency that give you non-zero
response, right, so if your signal is band limited, it's going to, there's going to have a omega m
which is described the maximum bandwidth, okay, so if our sampling rate is large enough, in other
words, if the sampling frequency is larger than two times maximum frequency band, we are safe,
well okay, because our space, the spacing is actually enough, your next duplicates will be
far enough to deviate from your first baseband, okay, there's no overlap, okay, the problem
happens at the time there is overlap, in other words, if my sampling rate somehow is very small,
especially smaller than two times omega m, what you will have is not something like this,
right, this is okay, you have enough spacing, but you may have the case that the first replica's
overlap with your baseband signal, okay, I hope this one is on, everyone understand this, right, so
omega m, remember omega m is the maximum bandwidth, nothing to do with sampling, just the signal,
how wide the signal is, right, that's omega m, the omega t is the how far you shift the signal
to create the first replica, so error happens when the shift is not enough, you don't shift enough
such that your baseband signal somehow overlap with your first replica, and the overlap will create
some kind of a superposition of the overlap part, you will have the smooth part, okay, so this is
actually the error because this part may not be recovered anymore, you cannot recover back the
original signal, sometimes, all right, so this is something we call the aliasing artifacts,
aliasing effects or artifacts depends on whether you think it's good or bad, this one will be
happened if you have your omega t smaller than two times omega m, it's going to give you this
kind of distortion, okay, the distortion happens when the two bands overlap to each other, okay,
oops, so these will create the shift, overlap of the shifted replicates, and there's a chance that
GA can never be recovered by the later, the D2A, right, now it's actually the digital domain,
but it may not be recovered and that caused the problem, so this is because the distortion from
the part of the replicas immediately outside of the baseband folded back or aliased, right,
into the baseband, so you have some interference between the replicas and the baseband, right,
this is where the error comes from, okay, so this is what we call aliasing, so this portion,
right, the portion within the low pass bandwidth of the filter, so I mean, like I mentioned, right,
well every time we do what is A2D, before that, you remember there's actually something called
anti-aliasing filter, right, so what does the anti-aliasing filter do is to control the bandwidth,
you think about like a low pass filter, right, you can specify, say hey, even though my signal
spread out very, very wide, but I know that my sampling rate is only in such kind of a frequency,
right, I want to do some kind of cut before creating the replicas, and the cut here is to make sure
that, you know, the bandwidth is actually within the recover range, right, so this is actually where
the anti-aliasing filter comes from, so if you don't do that, right, when aliasing occurs,
the original signal cannot be perfectly recovered because they mix up together, right, you want to
make sure this mix up doesn't happen, so this is actually where the low pass filter come in,
right, and of course later when you do recovery, you also need another low pass filter
to cut the baseband, so if you don't have anti-aliasing, you will have this aliasing here,
and this part, even though we know that, is actually a, you know, triangle, right, but actually
going to be a rectangle in this case, right, this is where the error comes from, so this amount of
distortion is due to the aliasing and due to the insufficient sampling frequency, right, so here's
one example, actually I like this example, consider this is actually a very simple function, the cosine
function, right, the reason we like cosine functions is because cosine function of spectrum is very
simple, right, all of you should know what is spectrum of cosine function, it gives you two spikes,
right, two impulse functions, right, one at the positive, one at the negative, all right, so if
this is my cosine function, which is analog, right, I'm starting from a signal like this, right,
one impulse at f0, one impulse at minus f0, right, so I'm going to show you like what happened if I
do have sufficient sampling, right, so when I do sampling, what I'm going to do is create
replicates in the frequency, I'm doing sampling in the time domain, but I'm creating the replicates
in the frequency domain, right, so what I will have is if this is my baseband signal, right,
after sampling, I'm going to introduce the first replicates, okay, and these replicates, we can
tell that the distance between the center and the baseband 0 will be the fs, right, remember the fs,
the larger the sampling frequency, the further away there will be between the replicates and the
baseband, right, so the distance between 0 to the center of the first replicates is actually fs,
all right, and you will create another replicates to the left-hand side, right, so you can keep doing
this, right, remember you can create infinitely many replicates from minus 0, minus infinity to positive
infinity, all right, but when I do this, clearly I don't have enough sampling frequency, right,
you can tell that these fs are smaller than two times of f0, right, remember the safe sampling
frequency must be larger than two times maximum frequency, right, f0, so clearly this fs is
smaller than f0, so this is what I'm going to have eventually, you can tell that the first
replicates clearly overlap with my baseband signals, right, so this is actually the portion of overlap
here, okay, let me go back, all right, so this is my this is my baseband signal, right, the baseband
signal has a range of the frequency, okay, the maximum frequency of my baseband signal is called f0,
just now I called omega m, it's the same thing, right, here I called omega m, right, here I just
called f0 is the same thing, but it's described, what's the band path, I mean what's the baseband,
right, how wide the baseband is, so this is the first parameter you need to know, right,
suppose you have a question in the exam, right, I give you a signal, the first thing you want to
know is what's the maximum frequency, all right, and now the number is the sampling frequency,
the sampling frequency, nothing to do with the signal, is how fast you sample the signal,
all right, so this frequency is called fs, all right, these fs will determine the shift, how
much you shift from the baseband to the first replicates, okay, so it's a distance between the
zero and the center of the first replica, how much they shift, right, so now you should tell
the difference, what is f0, what is fs, fs only to do with the sampling, f0 only to do with the
signal, okay, the problem happens when the fs is not enough, in other words fs is smaller than two
times f0, now you have a problem because clearly the first replicates overlap with your baseband
signal, okay, the dashed line here belongs to the replica, right, the solid line here belongs to
the baseband, right, so this is my baseband, when I create my first replica, clearly this is the
overlap, and overlap causes adhesion, causes distortion, okay, and you can keep doing this
and you'll create a lot of distortion like this, like this, you have a lot of overlap between every
two adjacent replicas, right, so now what happens if I somehow have to do a recovery,
when the recovery, remember I only care about baseband, I will do a low pass filter to kill all
the frequency range beyond baseband, in other words I only care about the information up to f0,
okay, so to the, sorry, not f0, actually half of the, let me see, what is,
f0, okay, f0 basically, so you only care about the things within, right, so when you do the
filtering, right, you will only keep the things within the baseband, right, but clearly when
you keep the baseband, these two guys, like this dashed line, this solid line, they are not part
of the baseband, they are coming from the replicas, so this is the adhesion, right, these cause the
error because that's not true, that's not the original signal, so all of these unwanted components
are adhesion, okay, you can try, you try by yourself, if you, for example, if you shift your signal
far away, you won't have this overlap, so having sufficient large FS is the solver,
to overcome adhesion, right, so this is where, I mean, where the problem comes from and how
you can solve the problem, so I hope this example tells you, like, you know, where the spectrum
happens, like how you can actually have this adhesion when you have your FS that's not enough,
right, smaller than 2f0, and the reconstruction is always based on fundamental frequency range,
which is a certain range, out of the frequency, oh, okay, so this is going to tell you that you
can't get rid of it by having a shorter range, right, but it's going to still give you some
adhesions, even if you apply the shorter range within the low pass filter, right, but basically
the adhesion coming from the overlap, so these actually lay the foundation of the sampling
theory because sampling theory tells you that when you sample the signal in order to prevent
adhesion, your sampling frequency must have some minimum value, right, and this minimum value will
be, we call it Nyquist condition, okay, if you want to get rid of adhesion at all, you have to
satisfy the Nyquist condition, in other words, you have to make sure your sampling frequency is
larger than 2 times the bandwidth, right, 2 times omega m, if you satisfy the condition, you are
safe, you don't get this adhesion, right, okay, so this is actually where the Nyquist condition
comes from, right, we explain this and this is going to prevent adhesion, all right, and now,
of course, if this is my sampling rate, right, I can divide it by two to kind of tell you that,
okay, this is actually the folding frequency, so within folding frequency, every information is
safe, but beyond folding frequency, you will have a risk of getting the adhesion, right, so
the first Nyquist condition tells you how to design a sampling, how to set the sampling rate
sufficiently large, right, a folding frequency tells you from the signal perspective, why pass a
signal to a sampler, what is the safe range, right, the safe range will be half of the
Nyquist, half of the sampling rate, which is called a folding frequency, beyond that you will have
overlap, you will have adhesion, right, so this kind of highest frequency of the signal
contained in the baseband is usually called Nyquist frequency, right, and this one determining
what's the minimum required sampling frequency, you could do two times it, and this must be used
to fully recover, if you want to fully recover the signal, you must satisfy the Nyquist frequency,
two times it, right, this is the minimum required, okay, so basically this is, you know,
the most important things in the sampling theory, right, but we went through all of this for you
to understand where this comes from, it comes from the fact that we do not want overlap, we do not
want adhesion, all right, any question, is it still okay, okay, good, yeah, so then you know,
two times O M, right, this is called Nyquist rate, so Nyquist rate is going to define the
Nyquist condition, right, every time we say Nyquist rate, you have to remind yourself,
Nyquist is equal to two times the maximum bandwidth, right, omega M, so here's one example, right,
after example we can take a break, okay, here's one example, right, consider you have analog
signal, which is like cosine signal, the reason why like cosine is simple, right, cosine only
gives you two spikes, so it's very simple, but every time, right, if I give you a signal,
for example, if this is my signal, what information you need to read from the signal,
okay, suppose this is exam, right, I give you say, hey, my signal is equal to five times cosine
two pi times one thousand T, right, what is the information come to mind if you see this signal,
or what you need to get, extract from the signal, sorry, frequency, yeah, what frequency?
Yeah, exactly, right, so we actually went through this, so you're right,
basically what we care about is this omega M, okay, because all of these things, you can tell
that how to determine sampling rate, the only thing matters is the omega M, okay, in other words,
why give you a signal in exam, right, I can make it like sine, cosine, whatever I like, but the most
important thing matter is what is omega M, you have to have this information, okay, amplitude
issue doesn't matter, the omega M matters, this is a starting point, right, so in this example,
right, if I give you the signal like this, can you tell me what is the omega M,
or how can I know the omega M in this case,
so does the five matters, no, because five is scales, right, you know, if it doesn't have five
amplitudes, one, five is amplitude, the number in front of cosine doesn't change the frequency,
right, so this number doesn't matter, okay, what matter is this guy, all right, what matter is
this guy, so you should look at what is the coefficient before t, okay, so this one thousand
actually is the f, is the frequency, all right, remember, oh, the standard definition of cosine
is cosine 2 pi f times t, right, you can represent omega, you can represent f, but if it's f,
the fs equal, sorry, f0 equal to 1000, or omega M, right, depends on how you name it, so these
matters, you have to tell yourself like, okay, this is a band and limited function,
where is omega M equal to 1000, okay, that's it, another thing you do, you don't need,
forget about five, it doesn't matter, only 1000 important, okay, extract that immediately if I
give you a signal, all right, okay, now the second thing you need to know is the sampling rate,
right, all of these micro things is about omega M, omega t, right, now we have omega M, now omega
t, what is omega t, 8000, that's it, you just need these two numbers, add other things, forget
about it, right, doesn't matter, five, cosine, sine, doesn't matter, you have these two, you can play
all the trick of your Nyquist, right, okay, so now the question says first, sketch my spectrum,
all right, sketch spectrum, it's very simple, right, cosine is just two spikes, but where the
spike matters, right, the spike will be located exactly at 1000, right, remember the maximum
frequency is actually omega M, and this omega M equal to 1000, so the two spikes will be exactly
located at 1000 hertz and minus 1000 hertz, of course the height will be determined by the
coefficient, right, so if it's five, it's going to be half of five, right, so this will be the,
I mean you can also do the Euler formula to decompose cosine into a, you know,
what is that, the real plus imaginary part here, okay, but important thing is the second question,
right, so they want you to sketch the spectrum of the sample signal, so this is unsampled signal,
right, I haven't considered a thousand at all, right, it's just original signal,
once I sampled it, right, when you heard the term samples, the thing come to mind is two things,
what happened in the time domain, what happened in the frequency domain, okay, for this subject you
have to think about two, right, time domain, frequency domain, time domain is nothing but
just discretize it, right, they only sample at time of t, 2t, 3t, most important thing is frequency
domain, we just learned that sampling time domain is equal to, you know, shift and repeat in the
frequency domain, right, in other words, I'm going to start with my original baseband signal,
I have to create multiple replica of this guy, if I sample it, right, if I start to sample it,
I'm going to equivalently modify my frequency spectrum by repeat the same signal with certain
shift and this shift will be determined by the sampling rate, right, and as the shift is exactly
equal to a thousand, right, so you can actually refer back to this example, right, this is where
the shift come from, this shift is exactly equal to FS, all right, so here this shift is equal
to a thousand because a thousand is my sampling rate, all right, and you can do many, right,
but the signal, but the question says only, okay, I only care about the spectrum from 0 to 20k,
okay, so I only care about 0 to 20k, so I don't have to create infinity many, I just create,
you know, baseband first replica, I already reached 17, so that's all, right, but you have to make
sure you know the shift, the shift equal to the sampling rate, right, okay, and of course,
another thing don't forget is actually the scale, right, when you create the shift, you have to
also scale the signal by divided by t, okay, so t is actually your sampling period, which is one
over sampling frequency, okay, so two things, repeat and scale, right, the scale is just divided by t,
okay, I mean this is also easy to understand, right, so if you want to, if you like to shift this
to the very sparse way, like you shift a lot, means the f is very large, your t will be very
small, right, so entire energy will be the same, you create a sparser, I mean fewer spikes, every
spike will have more energy, right, so it makes sense, right, I mean if you create a very dense shift,
in other words your f is very small, your t will be very large, so mpt will be smaller,
correspondingly, right, so basically the sampling doesn't, you know, violate the conservation of
the energy, right, okay, but you do two things, scale and shift, right, both of them depends on the
fs, right, okay, so another example as well, I can also change the baseband, right, into this form,
but same thing, right, even if I change my signal, you have to extract information from it, right,
like I mentioned, the important thing is what's omega m, right, but clearly these have two terms,
the first term omega m is 2,000, the second term is 5,000, so you will have signal with
summation of the two, right, but the omega m will be determined by the larger one, right, because the
larger one will dominate my spectrum, right, so there will be one signal, one cosine within
2,000, there will be another cosine within 5,000, right, but the 5,000 defined the entire omega m,
and you can also do the, I mean, the replicates, right, for example, this is my baseband, right,
this is my 2,000 version, and this is my 5,000 version, so I create the first shift to here,
remember this is my 8,000, I will have my first replicates of the, this 2,000 version and the
5,000 version, okay, so you can try this yourself, but you will have aliasing because this 8,000,
some point in rate, is smaller than 2 times 5,000, right, because remember this entire
big omega m is dominated by 5,000, so the Nyquist rate will be 2 times 5,000, which is 10,000,
right, clearly 8,000 is not enough, so you will have replicates, you will have aliasing due to the
violation of the Nyquist sampling rate, all right, but you can actually figure out where this aliasing
come from, all right, so I encourage you to try this yourself, okay, just try it, and if you
figure out anything weird, you can come to me, I can explain for you, but always it's good to learn
by doing things, right, not just listening to me, right, listening is not effective, trying
yourself is actually more effective, all right, the second question is very, it's the same, right,
I want to recover the analog signal, right, how can I do it, well you can apply a low pass filter,
so they want you to apply a low pass filter with color frequency 4k hertz, right, in other words,
even though I have this GP, but I don't care about all of them, I only care about the frequency
within 4k hertz, so I will remove all of the frequency components beyond 4k, right, this is
actually the result after low pass filtering, so I will have this guy survive, but clearly all of
these are aliasing, right, all of these are not the fundamental signal, these are aliasing, so this
is what I have, so if I recover my original signal, I cannot basically, right, I will get something
wrong, okay, so you can tell this is different from the original, right, so this is how the aliasing
can give you the wrong recovery, wrong reconstruction, okay, all right, so you know, a quick summary,
okay maybe one more slide, right, so it depends on what your sampling frequency is, we're talking
about three kind of sampling, either you over sample it, in other words, your sampling frequency is
very large, more than needed, right, more than Nyquist rate, or you can be under sample, in other
words, your sampling frequency is like 2 small, right, aliasing, over sample too large, under
sample too small, critical sample is that your sampling frequency is exactly equal to Nyquist rate,
okay, so this is critical, over sample, under sample, but in practice, normally people do
over sample, right, no, very few people will do exactly critical sample, this is due to the fact
of noise, right, normally the signal is not ideal, you may have noise, or your future may not be
ideal, they may have some kind of a transition band, right, to prevent those things, people leave
some space, people do over sampling, for example, if you are talking about telephone, right, telephone
system, even though my acoustic signal is actually within 3.4 kilohertz, in other words, this is my
omega n, the sampling rate is actually 8, right, you can tell this is more than double, right, so
they leave some space, so they can actually go over sampling, same for your CD, right, maybe nowadays
you don't really play CD, I'm the old guy, so we play CD when I was a child, so CD actually also,
right, you can tell like 44 kilohertz is more than double of the 20k, right,
yeah, so basically the sampling frequency is also sometimes affected, the system design, so
just give you some example, but take away, right, until now you should be able to understand where
the ad is in come from, right, you should understand what does ad as in mean, and also without
understanding ad as in, right, if you have still have some doubts, you better ask me because
without knowing this, you will have some difficulty understanding the following content,
so ad is important, some point is important, okay, and also you can read the textbook at the
section 6.1, where they have more comprehensive explanation if you want, but the main points
for up to now is that we have to appreciate the ad is in formula, where the replica is generated,
right, and what's the condition for perfect recovery, right, over sampling, critical
sampling, and what is the condition for the sampling rate, and what are the ad is in formula,
for phenomenon, for you know, radio images, these are something practical, right, but these are
something for now, until now, okay, any question, will I take a break, let's say maybe 15 minutes,
all right, you can ask me a question in between if you want, all right, but let's take a break,
we come back at 8.15, all right, okay, great, so let's take a break,
yes, oh, okay, so I have a question, yes,
Is this multiracial sampling ratio, like, is it changing?
Yes, yes, so, you know, right now we have this FS, right, and normally we have one FS for the
system, so if you only have one FS in the system, it means monorail, but in some system you may
have multiple sampling in different branch, and they are going to learn that there's a reason
of doing that, it may change, it also may change in the single branch, right, so like I mentioned,
one of the examples is the wavelets, right, when the wavelet transform, you sometimes look at the
low-low pass, but you realize that low-low pass actually is actually down-sampled, right, the
reason of doing that is you want to make sure there's a perfect reconstruction by merging
the low-low and the low-high, high-low and high-high, right.
So is it only happening in the AG conversion, or it can also happen at the digital side?
It can happen at the digital side, so for example, if I give you a fast sample digital signal,
I can further down-sample it, right, this is also like a rate change.
So it's a little bit like when we processed the image.
Yes, yes, yes, you have a image, say 500 by 500, you can make it 250 by 250, right,
this is like a lower the rate.
Digital, yeah, two-dimensional, one-dimensional also, but basically rate change means you do
down sampling, you do up sampling.
All kinds of, yeah, all of these are fundamental, yeah, all kind of signals, yeah, okay, good,
but we'll get there, don't worry.
Can I see the first page of the exercise?
This one?
Yeah, I don't understand why the employee two days, 2.5.
Oh, because it's half, it's half, you are formula.
So you have this cosine, right, you can decompose cosine into two, how should I say,
spike function.
So the question, don't want me to draw the picture of five cosine two by 10-smash-
Oh, what do you mean, draw the picture?
Draw the picture?
Draw the picture, why the amplitude is not five because-
Oh, this is time domain, we're talking about frequency domain, so you cannot draw the cosine,
but this is the frequency spectrum of the cosine function.
Oh, okay, I know.
Right, the reason, how to get it, you have to do your formula to decompose the cosine into two,
you know, complex number, because each of the complex number will be just a spike in the spectrum.
Right, okay, good.
Yeah, sure, sure, sure.
Oh, you said this is finite, right?
Yes, this is finite number.
So it's just that it's a finite number.
Oh, right.
Ok, you are in question.
Depends.
So nivel it can generate a linear layer.
But in practice, it is vilified.
The result of the fact is...
Yeah.
You said it's in the math.
Yes.
How to make a linear series of equations?
You just need to make a Zinc function.
You want to limit the left.
Left is just a rectangular function.
You just need to make a rectangular function
and you need to come up with a sinc.
The frequency of the function is sinc.
It's the same.
I didn't hear your question.
If I have a particular place,
it's called the finite number of signals.
It's called the number of signals.
If I have a particular place,
it's called the number of signals.
By English.
The first step is to find the eigen-linear.
It should be the linear series of signals.
If you do this, it should be the finite number of signals.
I'm telling you.
In the math, it's the infinite number of signals.
The point of this is that
in practice, the number of signals
is just the finite number of signals.
So, in practice, it's just the number of signals
that we've actually agreed to.
Yes.
I want to ask you about this.
If we have a given value,
the number of signals is just the finite number of signals.
No.
Your point is in the current.
But why do we have to put this in the current
because we want to get the value of the current
and we don't want to get the value of this current?
Yes.
So, it's actually in the system,
you have to consider the weight,
and the storage.
Because it's discretized.
So, this is also just a practical question.
Yes.
So, the next step is to consider the weight.
I'm not going to talk about the quantization.
What else?
I have a question.
Now, grab a little bit of the answer.
Okay, go ahead.
My question is, how does this DGA come about?
Oh, interpolation.
So, later, we're going to learn that later.
Not this class, but later.
You can interpolate to come back
from the discrete signal to an analog signal.
After the process.
So, basically, there's a way to convert
a discrete signal to an analog signal
by so-called interpolation.
It's a...
It's a difference.
A difference?
Yes, interplay.
Yes.
No, it's not a signal.
It's a signal that's after the third layer.
The first layer is not analog.
The second layer is not analog.
So, when we convert these two signals,
we only need to convert it to an analog signal.
Why not?
So, you can see here,
this is the first signal,
the second signal, this is the harmonization.
But, this time, it seems to be not
the analog signal.
We have to convert it to an analog signal.
This is...
You just converted it.
You mean two signals,
and this is not...
So, you can see here,
this is the first part of the three-core.
And these two are the two-core.
Yes, this is the second layer.
The second layer.
This is 5,000 and 2,000.
You have to count it.
5,000 and 2,000 are basically.
You said that the third layer is an alias.
Yes, the third layer.
Yes, you have to...
You have to read it.
I just said, where the spikes are
depends on the frequency.
The frequency is 2,000 and 1,000.
The spikes are only 2,000 and 2,000.
The spikes are basically.
The three-core is 5,000 and 2,000.
That's...
OK.
No, no, no, no.
8,000 and 5,000.
This is not our signal.
The other side is not the bandage.
The replica.
I don't know.
The bandage is the signal.
Is this because
I want to see the difference between the two?
Don't be afraid.
I think we still have to go back to...
Because I can't answer.
I can answer, you can choose the bandage.
I don't know what you're going to say.
I think I still have to...
You can ask me.
I don't have any.
But if you ask me, I'll ask the bandage.
Sorry.
Is it because of the production?
Oh, yes.
You can think of the sample as
a multiplication of the signal.
Yes, so we...
So we are...
So your sample is going to be a multiplication of the signal?
So your sample is...
I think...
I think you should first think about
your own problem.
You have to be clear.
First, I just said
the sample process can be expressed
in mathematics.
But the continuous signal
and an impulse train
are not an impulse,
it's a state impulse.
It's a method.
Yes, but I want to ask you
why it's a multiplication.
Because the sample,
the sample is not just a sample.
It's a state impulse.
You have to figure out the difference
between the two.
So your...
The signal of your process
is a state impulse train
called an impulse train.
Yes.
So it's not an impulse,
it's a non-er
It's a non-erkte.
And every step is a state impulse.
No steps.
You just said an impulse function.
Well, if...
Because...
Because if you step on a function,
if you make a mistake,
it means...
Because of this,
so it will be a lot more...
I just said
the method of the actual response
if you do a Fourier transform,
you will get a frequency
of a combination.
Yes, yes, yes.
So the Fourier transform of the impulse train
is also an impulse.
The impulse function of the Fourier transform
will not change the wave shape.
It's still an impulse.
So you say
the method of the actual impulse train
is equal to the function
of an impulse train in the frequency of a frequency.
Yes.
So the impulse train of a signal
is equal to
a shift of a state-of-the-art.
Yes, yes.
So you have the shift.
Oh, that's good.
You just said that the method of the actual response
is equal to the...
The new shifting.
You said
even using how we conform with impulse function
with time, with shift,
for example,
my impulse function is like a delta
at the heat of f minus fs.
What I'm doing is
I'm shifting my frequency
minus spectrum to fs.
Then you have a series of impulse.
So you are
you're saying fs, 2fs, 3fs,
the shifting of the transmission,
a series of replicants.
The actual operation
and the frequency of the operation
are the same.
Which two are the same?
The actual response.
The actual response
of the frequency of the operation
is equal to the function of the frequency.
The function of the frequency
is the shift of the signal.
Yes.
Oh, impulse train.
Impulse train.
Yes, impulse train.
Yes, yes.
Thank you.
Okay.
So you have the shift.
What?
No, I don't have shift.
Oh, no.
No, you can't.
You can't.
I think you can't.
You can't record.
I have to.
But you have to be in the test.
Of course, you have to.
No, you can't.
Okay.
I'm sorry.
This is...
This is a...
Wait, wait, wait.
Before...
I say no,
this is a...
You should be here.
You should come.
One of the things that you do absolutely well, that's fine.
But you have to make sure you keep the problem.
Keep up the problem.
OK?
E, T, M, G, F, N, J, H.
I'm not going to go.
I'm going to go.
I'm going to get my!!!!!!!!!!!!!
Oh, good, good!
Literally scan?
Good good.
We can have a look.
What?
Look.
Oh, south of you?
Going to think about Mongolia?
Oh, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes
yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes
alright okay I think we can resume okay just now I got some questions in the in the
break I think some of them I wish to share with you because you may have the
the same questions, or even though you didn't ask.
So there are, I think, two students ask me
about this exercise, right?
I realize there's maybe a misunderstanding, all right?
So all of you know that, you know,
we just now show two examples, right?
The first example, this is a safe case
because we do have enough sampling rate,
and this case, there's no adiasing, right?
All of you know this.
The second example is the case where we do have adiasing,
and I will really explain to you that the reason is,
if you look at this signal, right,
the omega m should be determined by the 5,000.
All right, so we have two components.
This is 2,000, this is 5,000.
So the whole, the overall signals, right,
the omega m, the maximum frequency will be determined
by whichever is larger, right?
So the 5,000 will be the omega m for the entire signal, right?
And based on Nyquist condition,
you need to have a sampling rate
that is at least two times 5,000 to be safe, right?
Clearly this 8,000 is not enough, right?
Okay, I hope all of you know this,
but I think there was some misunderstanding
about the plots because there's some students ask me,
hey, I cannot see any adiasing here.
So it seems like you still have the signal, right?
The two components survive.
Even if you say that there's adiasing, right?
But you have to be very careful
about the spikes, okay?
So which is the baseband spikes?
I mean, this is actually the spectrum after sampling.
It's a mixture of the baseband and also the replicants.
But can you tell me which of the spikes
are coming from the baseband?
Exactly, 2,000 and 5,000, right?
Because you have to check what is the frequency components
of the two cosine.
So with so many spikes,
the baseband components will be only this one,
right, this one clearly is at 2,000, right?
And these spikes coming from the first cosine.
All right, this guy, the small one here,
this is not baseband.
You don't have a cosine with 3,000 components, right?
So clearly the second cosine should contribute to
the spikes at 5,000.
So the baseband signals are actually the spike at 2,000
and the spike at 5,000, all right?
So 2,000 and 5,000, these two are the baseband signals.
The little guy here, the 3,000,
this one is actually the adiasing, it's not the baseband.
And this is what I exactly mean, the adiasing,
because these three is coming from the first replica,
all right, because I have my eight minus 5,000,
give me 3,000.
So this is actually adiasing.
That's why if you do a reconstruction,
you will keep the adiasing without keeping
the original baseband signal 5,000.
And this is exactly where the error are.
So this one do have error due to the fact
that it violated the Nyquist condition.
So don't misunderstand, I mean,
even though you still have two spikes,
but these two spikes are not the original spikes.
You can easily tell from the location of the spikes, right?
So this is actually where the,
I don't know, I mean, there are some students ask me,
so I think there could be a common misunderstanding here.
And another question is, I realize some of you
may not even know Euler formula, right?
So Euler formula is the one you can use
to decompose a synosoids, right?
So a cosine function can be represented
as two complex number.
Why? Because every complex number, for example,
E2 part of J theta equal to, you know,
cosine theta real and then sine theta,
which is imaginary, right?
And because there's a minus sign,
the two imaginary cancel, I will end up with 2.5
of the spikes at the minus one,
sorry, minus 1,000 and the 2.5,
the spike at the positive 1,000.
So you can always use the Euler identity
to decompose a cosine and a sine, right?
So I will prepare something for you next week
because I realize maybe not everybody know it.
So next week, before starting,
I will give you some recap on this, all right?
But just bear in mind that if you have a cosine function,
you will have two spikes, okay?
Both of them are positive.
If you have a sine function,
one of them is an active, right?
This is the only difference, okay?
All right.
So this is where we end it just now.
Oh, sorry, this is where we end it just now, right?
So summary of what we talk about.
So mainly in the ADSY, right?
And sampling theory, that's what we cover
for the first half.
So now, right, we talk about sampling
and now we can formally move to the representation
of the signal, transforms.
We already talk a little bit on the CTFT and DTFT.
So let's learn that more systematically, right?
So it's all coming from this guy, right?
Fluorier, so you know, fluoride transform, right?
Fluoride transform is coming from a name after this guy.
And because he's the first one,
discover that basically you can represent any signal
using a bunch of basic components, right?
So in other words, even though the signal
can be quite different, you know,
acoustic signal, image signals,
but we can use the most basic elements
to represent each individual signals.
And this is where all of these fluid transform come from,
right?
They concluded that all signal can be generated
by combining nothing but the single source wave
with different frequency and amplitudes, right?
So the single source is actually referred to,
just now we talk about, you know, this one, right?
This is actually the so-called the single source.
You can always decompose a very complicated signal
into a combination, not only, not one signal,
but many, many signal so is together, right?
This is where the fluid transform come from.
And of course, there are many versions
of fluid transform, we already talk about two,
CTFT and DTFT.
So DTFT will be something you need to know, okay?
So just now one still asked me like
whether the formula will be provided,
except for this one, I mean,
this one you're supposed to memorize it, okay?
DTFT, inverse DTFT, DFT,
which we're gonna see, discrete fluid transform,
sorry, inverse DFT.
So these are not formula, these are two, right?
You have to know it, okay?
So I may not give you this,
but it's very easy to remember, all right?
So how to remember it?
DTFT, clearly the starting point is DT, right?
So the right hand side of your transform
will be a discrete signal, right?
So there's a major difference between CTFT and DTFT.
And because your starting point is discrete signal,
you should do summation rather than integration.
You cannot do integration over the discrete signal.
So the right hand side will be a summation
of your discrete signal multiplied by a sinusoid, right?
So this is what we call a signal can be represented
by combining multiple sinusoids.
So this is the sinusoids, right?
So you're saying that no matter how complex
your frequency spectrum is,
they can be represented as a summation
of multiple sinusoids.
And the weights are determined by the XN.
So you can just sum them together.
You can form the corresponding frequency, right?
So that's how you can generate the left hand side,
which is the frequency spectrum of the discrete signal.
And you can do inverse, right?
You can always get it back.
You can recover the signal from the spectrum.
So remember, the spectrum is continuous.
Later, we're going to learn DTFT, which is discrete,
but DTFT, even though the signal originally
is discreet in the time domain,
the frequency is continuous.
That's why you have omega, not K, right?
Omega here is actually a continuous frequency, right?
You can get it back from the continuous frequency spectrum
to the signal by doing integration, okay?
So when you do integration,
you only need to do minus pi to pi.
Why?
Just don't we know that?
The DTFT spectrum is always two pi periodic.
Remember, we just say that?
Because it's periodic,
even if you integrate over entire range,
it doesn't give you anything new, right?
We only care about one period.
So that's why you only need to do integration
within the two pi period, okay?
So this is how you can memorize it.
And also you have to multiply by the sinusoid, right?
Which is e to the power of j omega n
because the n is the discrete variable.
So n must be there.
Okay, but don't forget the scale, right?
Why you need to scale by two pi?
It depends on how large,
how wide your integration range is.
If the range is two pi period,
you have normalized by two pi, right?
If it's four pi period, you have normalized by four pi.
So it's going to normalize such that
you don't really have this scale ambiguity, right?
It's gonna make sure you go back to the right scale, okay?
So this is how you can memorize it.
But just say that forward is summation,
minus infinity to plus infinity.
Universe integration, but only within two pi range.
And don't forget the normalization.
That's how you can memorize it, all right?
So this is basically the DTFT.
And we always say that DTFT have this periodic property.
In other words, no matter what kind of signals,
you will always have a spectrum that is two pi period, right?
So this is actually also a result of
AD is in formula, just now we just say it, right?
And this is your time domain, right?
You are discreet and you end up with the frequency like this.
And one period is actually between the base band,
the first replica, right?
So this is the visualization.
And this is actually the inverse,
sorry, forward and inverse transform of DTFT, okay?
All right.
So DTFT, also a few things to be noted.
First one is this symmetric property, all right?
So as you can see, right?
Most of the frequency you will realize is actually symmetric.
Means that the positive and negative are equal.
But there's a very, very important condition.
That is your signal, time domain signal must be real, okay?
If I ask you, say, hey, is it true to say that
the spectra of any signal is always symmetric,
is wrong, okay?
Not true.
Symmetric property is only true
if your original signal is real, okay?
Most likely you have real signal, like when I talk,
when I have an image, it's real.
But there are some signal in practice are complex.
Surprisingly, it's complex.
For example, radar signal, right?
If any of you know, like when you talk about EM, right?
It's actually complex.
MI, right?
Magnetic resonance imaging is also complex.
So there are some signals which are complex.
And if you look at their spectrum, it's not symmetric, okay?
So it's a symmetric for most of the case,
but you have to make sure the signal is real, all right?
So this is a common mistake people make, all right?
But if you have a real signal,
you have this symmetric property.
In other words, if you look at amplitude,
it's always symmetric, right?
So the positive side equal to the negative side,
but this is actually the magnitude.
Not exactly the same because you have to consider phase, right?
Even if you have a real signal, if you do DTFT,
you are going to end up with complex number,
not real number.
So any complex number will have two parts,
either real plus imaginary or magnitude plus phase, right?
So when we say symmetric, it's just the magnitude,
it's equal, right?
Phase will be the complex conjugate,
means it's going to be the opposite.
So you can consider this as magnitude,
even symmetric, phase or symmetric.
So phase is the opposite, magnitude is the same, right?
This is how you can remember this.
But of course, if we're talking about real signal, right?
Due to this symmetry property,
most likely, right, we can only just use half of the spectrum
because the other half, you can perfectly derive it, right?
So it doesn't give you anything new.
This is true for real signal,
so most likely we just need to analyze or store
only half of the spectrum, right?
This is also very fair.
For example, if you have real signal,
in principle, you actually assume the imaginary to be zero,
right?
You already lose half of the information.
So corresponding the spectrum, you only need half.
If you have complex signal, you have this imaginary part,
you also have to pay the price to store the spectrum, right?
So you cannot only save the half, okay?
This is fair.
But for this subject, most likely we're talking about
real signal, so you can assume that only half of the spectrum
will be enough, okay?
Because the other way you can directly derive it, okay?
And you can consider that the next half will be just a mirror,
right?
You can just mirror it from the middle point,
half of the FT, right?
And this spectrum is often given in terms of only the frequency
range from zero to FT, right?
And in the radius will be just zero to omega t, right?
So other parts can be just by repeating this period, right?
So actually periodic function.
If you normalize that is a corresponding way,
you can normalize the frequency, you can normalize the radius,
right?
Okay, so, yeah, just now it's about the DTFT, right?
So you can also do this practice, right?
You can try to calculate the impulse response of an ideal
low-pass filter, right?
So suppose this is my low-pass filter.
Low-pass filter is nothing but equal to one within that
frequency range, zero outside the frequency range.
And mathematically, low-pass filter is a rectangular function,
right?
So if you want to do a so-called impulse response of this
filter, what does that mean?
I give you a filter, right?
I know this filter is low-pass filter.
I want you to give me impulse response of this filter.
So mathematically, what does that mean?
So first thing about that, like when I say low-pass filter,
am I describing the frequency domain property or time domain
property of the filter?
Frequency, because low-pass means low-frequency pass, right?
When I say impulse response, am I talking about the time domain
signal or the frequency domain signal?
Think about an impulse response.
Do you know what is impulse response?
Impulse response means I have a signal.
I have a system, right?
I give the system an impulse signal.
I want to see what's the output.
So the output of the system, when I inject an impulse signal
as an input, the output is called impulse response, OK?
So I didn't know.
OK, so this is the definition, all right?
So if I ask you, what is the impulse response of a signal,
am I asking a time domain signal or frequency domain signal?
Time domain, because impulse, think about injecting the signal
to the system, right?
These impulse will be only have impulse at a certain time.
So it's actually time domain signal, right?
And the expected outcome is also time domain, right?
Time domain signal.
So how can I know the time domain signal of my impulse?
It's actually the inverse DTFT of the frequency spectrum
of the low-pass filter.
So imagine you have a frequency response.
You have a frequency spectrum of the filter, right?
This is the frequency representation of the filter,
right?
But when I'm talking about impulse response of the system,
right, I'm asking you the time domain representation
of the filter, right?
So what I need, actually, is the inverse DTFT
of my low-pass filter spectrum.
OK, how many of you never heard of impulse response?
I thought this should be taught in your analog signal course.
Have you learned this in the analog signal?
Impulse response, right?
So how can I tell what is the impulse response of a system?
I need to figure out what is the time domain representation
of the filter, right?
So how can I get the time domain representation of the filter
given a frequency spectrum?
I need to do inverse DTFT, right?
In this time, it's inverse DTFT.
But here, we have to do inverse DTFT, right?
So in this case, you can tell from the low-pass filter
what the frequency spectrum is for this filter, right?
It is a spectacular function, right?
I need to know the impulse response.
What I need to do is to do inverse DTFT of this guy
to convert it back from the frequency spectrum
to the discrete time signal, right?
So how can I do it?
I can apply my inverse DTFT we just learned, right?
By doing integration over the, you know, I mean,
ideally it should be 2 pi, but because here,
you know that this bandwidth is limited by minus omega c
and c, right?
You can directly do integration over these two.
I mean, if you do minus pi to pi, it's all going to be zero,
right, in this high-pass range.
So you can't get limited to only minus omega to omega, OK?
And you know that within the range is equal to 1, right?
Because this is actually an amplitude of 1.
You can just substitute 1.
You do a simplification.
You will have a sync function, right?
So a low-pass filter, if you look at the time domain response,
it's always a sync function, right?
Because that's how you can do IDTFT to get back
to the time domain, right?
So this is actually a very simple.
You just apply IDTFT to the spectrum,
but you have to understand what does the impulse response mean,
right?
OK, you can check, but I already explained to you.
Impulse function is the output if you inject the impulse
function as input to the system, right?
The corresponding output is the impulse response
of that filter, right?
So if you observe the waveform of this impulse response,
you can tell that this signal will
appear at both future time and past time, right?
Just now one of you asked me a question,
say, how can I have a time which is negative, right?
In fact, this is a problem, but mathematically,
this is what you got, OK?
But this function, or this filter,
may not be realizable because there
are some value in the future, right?
How can you design an impulse response which
is happening at the future?
So normally, if you observe an impulse response which
are spread out in the time domain, which is normally,
we call it the not causal or not realizable, right?
So this is a problem not for math,
but for practical implementation, all right?
So let's define what does the causal mean here, right?
So we say a system is causal, right?
You may have heard of the term causal, right?
Causality, like LTI system.
OK, so C stands for causal, right?
So we say a system is causal if you
can represent the output only using past or present
value of the input.
So if I have an output y, which is only
a function of the current time x or past time x, this is fine.
So this is called causal, right?
Because you do not need the future value of the input
to generate the output.
So this is causal, right?
So for example, there are two options, right?
If my output is equal to yn, current time n,
is equal to the current time x plus the past time x,
this is fine, because I already see my past time values.
I can generate my output.
But if I have an output that depends on the future value
of x, you cannot do it, because you never
know the future value at the current time step, right?
So this is called non-causal, because there's
a dependency to the future.
So this is normally not realizable in practice, all right?
So now the question is, now we can
design some good filter, just like the filter here, right?
This is the perfect low-pass filter.
We want to use it.
We like it mathematically.
But we just cannot have a filter like this,
because output depends on future of input, right?
So how can I first, how can I make sure the system is
causal system, right?
You have to measure that.
How to do that?
You have to work out this relationship between output
and input.
If you find there's a dependency on future,
means this system is non-causal, right?
So you know that this system, even though it's good,
but not realizable in practice, OK?
So the signal is that if you see any x depends on future time,
it means it's non-causal, all right?
So you have to somehow get rid of it.
You have to modify your filter to make it causal,
because only so you can make it, right?
You can generate it.
OK, how can you do it?
Well, a common way people do it is by add a face, add a face term.
All right, just now this response has nothing
to do with face, right?
It's just an amplitude only, zero face, all right?
I didn't consider any face here.
So it's actually one, right?
It's a real number, only magnitude, face zero.
But I will end up with some non-causal filter.
One thing we can do is by shift all the signal to the past,
right?
So you can actually make the future value like past.
So a shift in the time domain will
be a face change in the frequency domain.
This is another trick people normally play, right?
You want to generate a shift, let's say, in the time domain.
You do face change in the frequency.
The other way, also the same.
You want to do, how should I say, face change in time,
you will do a shift of frequency, right?
So this is like a correspond, just like multiplication
in time, just equal to convolution in frequency, right?
This is another commonly used pairs when we do manipulation,
right?
So here, if I want to have a shift of the entire impulse
response, what I can do is add a face term.
I'm saying that, well, within my low pass range,
still the magnitude is equal to 1.
But I will have a face, which is also
a function of omega here.
In other words, the face is not equal to 0.
It's going to be a linear function.
OK, so adding this face, in other words, the linear face
here, if you again do the inverse DTFT, you will find that.
I will have a zinc function, which is still a zinc.
But the entire zinc is shifted to the past, right?
So you have a corresponding time shift
when you have a face change in the frequency domain, right?
And by doing so, you are going to delay the impulse function,
impulse response, by a certain range, all right?
So you can tell that the face here is actually
minus n divided by 2.
The time shift will also be equal to n divided by 2, right?
So there's a correspondence between the two.
OK, if you do so, well, you still
have something left in the future, right?
But I can do a truncation, right?
I just forget about those smaller future values.
I just forget it.
I only keep the past value, right?
This is one way to design the filter in practice.
You won't have exactly the ideal low pass,
but you have a good enough low pass.
Where is the face shift?
Right, so this is one way you can somehow
make a non-causal system to be causal,
to make your impulse response to be
within a finite duration and shifted by a certain range,
right?
This is one way you can do it, all right?
But two things.
First, you need to know how to identify a signal, whether it's
causal or non-causal.
That's step one.
How to identify?
You have to look at this function, right?
To see whether there's any dependency on future.
Yes, it means non-causal.
Nothing means causal, all right?
Second thing is how to solve it,
how to change the non-causal system to causal.
It's by introducing a face shift here, right?
The face shift will be some linear function
of my face change as a function of frequency.
And by doing so, you will have a face not equal to zero,
but as a linear function.
So the face shift in frequency will
be corresponding to a time delay in the impulse response.
So this is how you can convert the non-causal system
to causal system.
So you have to know two things, all right?
Yes?
Which side of the face is the non-causal?
So normally the signal will come in from, let's say,
from here, arriving from left to right.
So whatever after the zero will be the future,
oh sorry, will be in the past, whatever
have arrived will be the future.
Yeah, yes?
I always know if the signal is called
causal from the spectrum.
It's causal from the spectrum, right?
Not very, sorry?
Do I have to transfer it from the spectrum to the function?
It's better to transfer, because it's not very obvious.
If you're good, you can tell, but not very obvious.
Every time it's obvious.
So it's better to, OK.
So this is a very good question.
So I would really recommend to Anna with here,
only when you have this equation to make a decision.
Otherwise, it may be risky, right?
But I'm not saying you cannot do it.
Some can still do it, right?
But it's not very reliable.
Sometimes you may make a mistake.
So I would strongly encourage you
to have this input-output relationship
to tell the difference, to tell whether it's causal or not.
This is the one way.
The other way is to figure out the time impulse response.
The impulse response can also tell you
whether it's causal or non-causal, right?
OK.
But in the exam, it should give you something simpler, right?
They won't give you a super complicated function
to do ID, TFT, right?
But you should know the principle, right?
How can you tell, and how can you make a change, right?
OK, great.
Any other question?
OK, good.
So this is something to do with the causality, right?
And also, just now I'm saying that even if I do a time delay,
I still end up with infinitely long impulse response, right?
The z-function can actually go to infinity.
So another way people normally do is by a truncation.
They will drop the signals, maybe beyond a certain range.
So you are going to convert an infinitely long signal
to a finite length signal.
OK, even though if you do this, even though, for example,
the signal Iq is very small, it still gives you some artifacts.
In other words, if you do so by truncating the impulse
response to a finite length, you will not end up
with a perfect low pass filter.
Normally, if you have this kind of very sharp transition,
it means your impulse response will be infinitely long, right?
But this is not practical.
You have to do some kind of truncation.
But if you do truncation, make it finite length.
You have to introduce something called the repose.
So later, week five or four, I'm going to talk about filter design.
You will see the actual artifacts.
But you will have some artifacts.
On one side, you make it real.
You make it practical.
But also, you end up with non-ideal low pass filter.
And non-ideal is coming from the truncation.
You truncate the infinite long signal
to a finite length signal.
This is where it comes from.
So you will see some repose in the pass band and the stop band.
And there will be a transition band
between the stop and pass.
So this will be practical filter,
how the practical filter look like.
We'll get there.
So just some preview.
We'll go to the details in week five, I think.
Another thing is, just now we talk about causality.
So we say that a practical system must be causal,
because nobody can predict the future.
So it must be causal.
And for this subject, we give two other conditions
to make it simple.
Causal is one.
The other two is linear and timing variant.
So what do we mean by linear?
Linear means the system will be, if you look at the,
how should I say, the impulse response.
You can always represent output as a convolution of input
signal and impulse response.
If so, this is a linear system.
So it's a linear.
In variant means this impulse function will not change
from time to time.
The opposite is time varying.
Time varying means maybe at time one,
the impulse function look like this.
But afterwards, it's going to change.
So this is time varying.
But time varying system will make the whole thing very
complicated.
So for this subject, you can always
assume that the system is always linear and timing variant.
No change, always linear, or always can write as a convolution.
So in this case, under the LTI assumption,
we call it LTI system, linear timing variant causal system,
you can always write the output as the convolution in time
domain, the convolution of the input and the impulse response
of the system.
I believe all of you should learn this.
An analog signal is the same.
The only difference in analog signal,
you have to do integration.
In digital signal, you just do summation
when you do convolution.
But basically, you can represent output either in terms
of time domain convolution or frequency domain multiplication.
Either way, you can generate the output.
So basically, this is actually how you do it.
But this is called convolution.
So multiply, shifted, and summation
is actually same as convolution.
But convolution is actually permutable.
You can actually do x come up with h, or h come up with x.
It's the same thing.
Now, we're going to use the convolution notation as a star
for the entire subject.
Every time you see the star, it means convolution.
Dot means multiplication.
Star means convolution.
So also, just now, some of you asked me
about the impulse thing.
If you remember, I show you just now.
I hope you still remember.
There was a, where is it?
Sorry, much earlier.
Where is it?
OK, here.
Just now, I show you a figure that's saying, well,
sampling is actually multiplication in time domain
between the time signal with impulse train.
I say that, well, this is equal to, in the frequency domain,
I'm convolved the frequency spectrum of the input signal.
Where is the impulse train?
So just now, somebody asked me.
So this is true because if you do a DTFT of the impulse train
in time domain, you will get a scaled version of the impulse
train in the frequency domain.
So impulse function, no matter you do inverse DTFT or DTFT,
the waveform will not change.
It's still impulse function.
So this is also important.
That's why here it says, whoops.
So here it says that you have to be familiar with yourself
that impulse train, the time domain, if you do DTFT,
you will get another impulse train.
But there's a scaling factor of the omega 0.
But the waveform doesn't change.
And this is actually how you can get to the alias
informator to generate this replicas of your baseband
frequency, sorry, baseband spectrum.
But you can derive this by yourself using the DTFT
and the inverse DTFT without a problem.
You can try it.
But the conclusion is that impulse function will not
change the waveform if you do DTFT.
So last topic, I know it's very late, but let's talk about
last topic.
So we talk about DTFT.
We talk about CTTFT, then DTFT.
The difference between CTTFT and DTFT is whether your
input signal is continuous or discrete.
The continuous signal, you want to find a spectrum, you do
CTTFT.
Discrete signal, you want to find a spectrum, you do DTFT.
But both spectrum from CTTFT and DTFT, both of them are
continuous.
I'm talking about spectrum.
Spectrum for both CTTFT and DTFT are continuous.
But we know that continuous states cannot be
stored in computer.
Computer cannot store continuous.
You have to somehow discretize it.
This is the reason we need another, maybe the one last
we call it DFT, discrete Fourier transform.
The name is very confusing.
If you see a T there, it means you get a continuous
spectrum.
Without a T, instead of DTFT, I say DFT, you end up with a
discrete spectrum.
You get a discrete signal, you end up with a discrete
spectrum.
This is what the DFT is doing.
So even though there's only one word different, it means
different things.
So now we're talking about a discrete Fourier transform,
no time.
Just discrete Fourier transform.
So discrete Fourier transform, first, is going to deal
with finite length discrete signal.
So just now here we have to talk about how many points
we have.
So if it's n points, we're going to say this is n
point DFT.
So DFT, just like DTFT, you have forward transform, you
have inverse transform.
Both ways, we obtain the spectrum and get back to the
signal.
But both the left-hand side and right-hand side are
discrete.
You start with discrete n point signal, you end up with
n point discrete spectrum.
So this is the property for DFT.
The dimension doesn't change.
The format doesn't change.
OK, let me repeat.
DTFT, you start with a discrete signal, you end up with
continuous spectrum.
That's DTFT.
DFT, you start from n point discrete signal.
You end up with exactly same length n point discrete
spectrum.
So you don't change the dimension.
The dimension is the same, with or without this DFT.
So this is the most important part.
So that's why I'm having the right-hand side, xn, to be
within 0 to n minus 1.
When I do this, I will end up with another spectrum, xk,
which k also range from 0 to n minus 1.
So length is the same.
In other words, later we're going to see that this
transform is a square transform.
You are multiplying the square transform to a vector.
You get the same dimension of the vector as the output.
So that's why people love it, because you can represent a
DFT perfectly using a square transform, a matrix.
And also another thing is the base.
Remember, DTFT, the base is equal e to the power of minus
j omega n.
Remember, that's the DTFT.
Now, DFT, there's no omega, because it's discrete.
You won't have omega.
What you have are two integers, small n and a small k.
Small n is the index for discrete time domain.
k is the index for discrete frequency domain.
You need to have both.
The other thing is the same, j 2 pi, but divided by n.
So this n is the n point you have, the larger the n,
the larger the denominator.
So four-way transform have a minus.
Inverse transform doesn't have a minus.
That's the difference.
But basically, both of them will be doing summation,
rather than integration.
Here is another normalization term.
But it only normalizes at one side.
It depends.
You will see some other version of the DFT that says, here,
I have a 1 over square root of n.
Here, another square root of n.
It's just a scaling factor.
It doesn't matter.
But together, you have to divide it by n to get it back.
So for this subject, let's just think about that the
inverse transform have this scaling.
Forward doesn't have a scaling, just for simplicity.
So this is DFT.
DFT can be considered as a sample version of DTFT.
Remember, DTFT, you have a continuous spectrum, omega.
Now, if you want to relate DFT to DTFT, you can consider
DFT as a sample version of DTFT.
I'm going to show you in a minute how exactly.
Maybe now, I'm going to show you this first.
So just now, I showed you that how you can go from CTFT to
DTFT.
Remember?
I'm saying that the difference happens at the
sampling stage.
I'm sampling the time domain signal as an impulse train.
I end up with a convolution.
So this is how you can go from CTFT to DTFT.
Now, I go one step further.
I want to go from DTFT to DFT.
So what I'm doing now is a sampling of the frequency
spectrum.
Remember, DTFT gives you a continuous spectrum in the
frequency omega.
Now, I want to have a discrete spectrum.
So you can consider this as equivalent sampling in the
frequency domain.
How to do sampling in the frequency domain?
You can just do a multiplication of the impulse
train.
Same trick.
So that's why you can end up with something like this.
So it's like a sample version of my DTFT spectrum.
And this is what you get for DFT.
So here from here is go from CTFT to DTFT.
You can also do one step further to reach the DFT.
If you do inverse DFT, you end up with the original signal
but with the sample version.
So I hope this figure somehow unifies all of the three
transforms we learned.
But it's just an illustration.
I'm not deriving this mathematical.
I have promised.
I try to minimize the mathematics.
And I won't really test you on that.
But I hope you have a feeling.
These three are not something separate.
These three are related.
Just like how you want to sample time domain, you want to
sample frequency domain, you end up with a different
transform.
But it's the same kind of principle.
So this is how you can relate.
But for DFT, there's one concept.
Very important.
I wish you to understand this.
For every DFT, there is something called resolution.
How precise your DFT spectrum is.
We use the term resolution to quantify it.
What is exactly the resolution of DFT?
So the resolution of DFT depends on this guy.
It's actually the Ft divided by m.
So two things.
First one is how many points?
This one, how many points?
So the more points you have, the
poorer resolution you have.
What does this resolution describe?
It describes one sample in the DFT spectrum.
How much information it contains, basically.
I'm putting the layman term.
So let's say I have eight points as my spectrum.
What does one of the points represent?
Or how much information does this one point convey?
It's actually the minimal resolution.
The more information it conveys, the
higher resolution it has.
So if you think about a spectrum, if I sample using a
thousand points, every point only captures 1 over 1,000
portions of my information.
So the larger the n, the fewer information I have.
So that means the larger the n, the poorer resolution I will
have per measure, per point.
Makes sense?
So this is one more factor.
So n will determine partially the resolution.
This is the first thing.
The other thing is the Ft.
Ft is the sampling frequency of the signal.
So Ft has nothing to do with your DFT.
Ft only determined by the original discrete signal.
Remember, the input of DFT is already sampled.
I give you a signal that already determined the Ft.
So you can see that there are two things you can manipulate
the resolution.
One is that how did you get this discrete signal, which is
before applying DFT.
But they're likely you cannot change it.
But the only thing you can change is the n.
You can change the n to manipulate the resolution.
But resolution depends on these two numbers.
How fast do you sample the signal in the time domain?
How many points you use for DFT?
These two numbers determine the resolution of your
discrete DFT spectrum.
So visually, we all see that you can actually design the
DFT to change the resolution.
Zero padding.
Later, we're going to see there.
But this is a very important definition.
I may ask you in the homework in the exam.
So make sure you understand what they are.
It's a ratio, Ft divided by n.
And how can you compute it?
Well, for example, if I have a signal, which is sampled at
8 kilohertz, what does this 8 mean?
So 8,000 means Ft.
Remember, Ft is how fast you sample the signal.
So when you read this phrase, you should tell that this 8,000
is actually the Ft.
Sampling rate.
Now I say that I apply a 1,024 point of DFT to
represent this signal.
What does this number mean?
What does 1,024 mean here?
Is the n.
So now I can use this number to derive the resolution.
It's nothing but 8,000 divided by 1,000 over 24.
By definition.
So to compute the resolution, you need two numbers.
First one is how fast or what's the sampling rate.
The other one is how many points your DFT is.
You get this two number, you just divide it, you get the
resolution.
But you have to identify what are these two numbers.
You read it from the question.
You get those two numbers, you can compute the resolution.
So this is one practice.
But you can easily get it if you read the question
carefully.
Sampling rate, number of points for the DFT.
So DFT is actually very commonly used because for most
of the digital world, you have to do DFT.
And also there's a faster version of DFT.
It's called FFT, fast Fourier transform.
So I'm going to keep this for next week because I feel like
the slides for this week is very brief.
So I doubt you can get it, but I will prepare some more for
next week.
But FFT is most likely how we use to implement DFT.
Two reasons.
First one is faster.
By name, you can tell it's faster.
The other one is FFT is exactly equivalent to DFT.
Not even approximation.
It's exactly the same.
Which is amazing.
So somebody even think this is one of the most important
invention for signal processing.
But anyway, DFT is the equivalent to FFT.
That's something you want to memorize.
And FFT is faster.
I think that's all you need.
But theoretical repetition will always use DFT because
DFT is more straightforward.
In practice, people do FFT.
But these two are the same.
In terms of outcome, it's the same.
So this one, I already went through this one.
Basically, it's an illustration.
So I want you to give you a way to represent the DFT
using matrix.
So I just want to show you how many of you know when you
represent a discrete transform, you can actually use a
vector matrix form.
Like for example, some of you told me that you have learned
wavelets.
So wavelets, you can actually use a matrix to represent
the wavelets.
Same for DFT.
You can actually use a matrix to represent a DFT.
Why?
Because if you look at this form, my outcome, my output is
actually an n-dimensional signal, n-point signal.
My input is also n-point signal.
So if I want to relate n-point signal to the other n-point
signal, I can use a square matrix to do it by simply
multiply the square matrix with my input signal.
It's a matrix vector multiplication.
But the question is, how can I figure out this square matrix?
So this is what I'm going to do.
You have to start with the fundamental equation here.
This is actually the definition of forward DFT.
But this DFT, the basis is very special.
Why?
Because the basis, the e to the power of minus j 2 pi k
divided by n times n, is special because 2 pi divided by n,
these are constant.
The only two variables are k and n.
So if I rewrite the e to the power of minus j 2 pi divided
by n, big n, we as w subscript n, I can represent this by
this guy to the power of k n.
Expansion, you're just writing special to a fixed base.
This w n is a fixed base, which equal to e to the power of
j minus j 2 pi divided by n.
I just power it with k n.
I give back to my original base.
Just for simplicity, I use a notation to represent a very
long exponential.
But this w n is a constant.
Only depends on n.
I can write it as constant.
So why this is interesting?
Because the change of the k n, the k of n will be changed
because it depends on which input and which output we are
talking about.
They will be changed.
But they are basically finding the sample point in this
unit circle.
Why?
Because this guy is actually a unit circle.
What does that mean?
It's a circle in the complex plane where the length is
always equal to 1.
The magnitude is always equal to 1.
The only thing change is the phase.
So basically, the change of the phase will be a sample point
on this unit circle uniformly.
In other words, if my w part of 1 will be here, 2 will be here,
3 will be here.
So it's going to be sampled around the unit circle.
And how many shares it has, it's going to depend on the
subscript.
If a is equal to 8, I have n points.
So I have a point in this unit circle.
So the reason I'm doing this is I want to represent the
DFT as a least of equations.
So why do I need a least of equation?
Because the k and n must be changed from 0, 1, 2, 3, all
the way to n minus 1.
So by changing the value, I can write actually n number of
equations.
So the first equation is when k equals to 0, how can I
derive the xk, x0 from the DFT?
So the first line is the DFT for k equal to 0.
I'm just applying the formula.
This is my formula.
I want to get my x0.
I just expand the right-hand side.
This is what I get here.
And now this is k equal to 1 case, k equal to 2.
So I'm going to end up with a linear system of n equations.
And it depends how many points you have on DFT.
So this is actually the n equation I need to come up
with my discrete spectrum.
But why do I want to write in this way?
Because if I can write in this way, I do not have to write
any equation every time.
I can just write a single equation with a so-called
DFT transformation as a matrix.
So how many of you have learned how do you do matrix
vector multiplication?
Or how many of you do not know how to do matrix
As a matrix, I multiply a vector.
How to do the computation of this?
How many of you do not know this?
I just want to know, does this make sense for everyone?
I do a matrix multiplied by a vector.
I hope you know it right.
So if you do a matrix multiplied by a vector, what
actually happens is that the first row of the matrix
will multiply by the column and up with the first value.
So this x0 is here.
When I multiply the first row and this column,
it will be 1 times x0, 1 times x1, 1 times x2.
So that's exactly the first equation.
Now the second element, x1, will be the second row
multiplied by the same vector.
I'm going to have x0 plus x1 times wn plus x2 times wn
to power 2.
So that's exactly the second equation.
So I'm just rewrite my DFT with an equation,
and it was one equation, but involve a matrix vector
multiplication.
I didn't do anything.
It's the same.
It's the same, just equivalent representation.
The reason we want to do this is because this guy, this wn,
this is actually literally the DFT.
A DFT can be represented nothing but the matrix.
Next time you have another input signal,
you just multiply it.
You will get another output.
So basically what actually happened for transformation
is a predefined matrix multiplied by a given signal
to generate the output.
So this is why we call the linear system,
because it's linear.
Just multiply a row or a column.
That's why we call it linear system.
Make sure you, OK.
I strongly encourage you to try this,
because it comes from the formula here.
The reason how I can go from here to this row
is by substitute k equal to 0, 1, 2, 3, all the way to n,
n minus 1.
And also using n equal to 0, 1, 2, all the way to n minus 1.
So I didn't do anything change.
I just keep using this with different n and different k.
And now I just rewrite n equation using the matrix vector
form.
So nothing changed.
I just make it a different form.
You can give a try, but I wish you
to be familiar with the matrix vector form,
because what can you use that for many of the cases?
Because it's actually cleaner.
You just need one equation rather than n equations.
But the size of the matrix will be n by n.
If you have 8 points, the matrix will be 8 by 8.
So it's always a square matrix for DFT.
So now we can see that all DFT can be represented as a matrix.
And this matrix is actually symmetric.
If you observe it, it's actually symmetric.
Why?
Well, this row equal to this column, apparently,
is always 1.
This row equal to this column.
You can tell this is symmetric, because n and the k
are symmetric.
If you look at the formula, n and the k are actually
symmetric.
If you swap them, it's the same.
It doesn't make a change.
Because n and k are symmetric, this matrix
must be symmetric.
So it's always a symmetric matrix and always square.
And the base is always written like this.
Only depends on how many points you have.
N points, the only difference is the denominator.
It becomes n.
So if you can do that, you can actually
use this to compute any DFT.
I give you an input signal.
I just write the signal as a vector.
I multiply the matrix to the vector.
I get my output.
So it's just a one line equation.
And how to do inverse DFT?
It's a matrix inverse.
You just invert this matrix.
You will get your inverse DFT.
So now you can see where the inverse transfer comes from.
It's by directly inverting the matrix.
So now w is the forward transform.
W inverse is the inverse transform.
So you can actually do it.
And technically, it should be Hermitian transpose.
Because this is a symmetric transform,
the inverse will be the Hermitian.
Hermitian means flip them and take the complex conjugate.
But if it's a real number, then it doesn't matter.
I mean, it's not a real number.
You have to take complex conjugate of it.
So for some simple value of the DFT,
you can actually compute it yourself.
For example, if I'm talking about a 2 by 2 DFT,
this is my 2 by 2 DFT.
So if it's 2 by 2 DFT, I can simply compute the inverse,
which is actually the complex conjugate, which is itself.
If it's a 4 by 4 matrix, you can also
compute the complex conjugate.
You just need to make it symmetric and take whatever
j becomes minus j.
So this is how you can do a complex conjugate.
And you can compute, for example, what
is the DFT of this signal?
You just multiply my 4 by 4 DFT with the signal.
This is with the output.
So this x will be the corresponding 4 point DFT
spectrum of the 4 point signal in the beginning.
So like I mentioned, it's equivalent.
But having this matrix vector form
will make the entire representation cleaner.
When you write it, it's just one line instead of n lines.
But in practical, it's equivalent.
So I will skip the FFT to next week.
But one last topic, I probably won't give you an exam,
but just for your knowledge.
So in many applications, especially involving
this time series, like acoustic signal, LLP,
you will not have finite length signal.
Remember, DFT can only deal with finite length signal.
But if your signal is keep coming,
how can you figure out the spectrum, especially your signal
is actually time varying?
A common thing people do is so-called short time
Fourier transform.
So what the short time Fourier transform means
is nothing but just truncate the signal, divide them
into n point segments, and doing a segment-wise DFT.
It's very simple.
But your n is a multi-segment spectrum.
But this multi-segment spectrum will
be a function of time.
And it can keep change.
This is actually how you visualize music,
visualize your acoustic signal as the waveform.
This is that they're doing nothing but a short time
discrete Fourier transform.
But I won't test it on this, but I just
want to make sure that how can you
apply a limited length transform to deal with time
varying sequential signals in practice.
You can do a short time DFT.
So fast Fourier transform, I will leave this for next week.
I don't have time, but I will give you some details.
But just one takeaway.
I will get back to this next week.
One takeaway is the efficiency.
Why people like to do this fast Fourier transform
is because it's fast.
By name, you can tell it's fast.
And it actually happens.
It's actually fast, especially when the number of signal
becomes high-dimensional.
So this is the plot.
When the n increase, you can tell that the runtime,
or the complexity of DFT increase as a part of 2.
But FFT will give you n times log n.
So FFT will be much more scalable than DFT,
especially when you deal with large-scale signal.
Small-scale signal doesn't be too different,
but large-scale is a big difference.
And that's why in practice, always people do FFT, not DFT.
But analyzing you always do DFT is simpler.
So this is the only fair issue to know.
Other derivation, I won't test you,
but I will tell you more next week.
So yeah, so FFT, basically, you just
need to know this, the operation.
DFT, n squared, FFT, n times log n.
OK, I believe all of you know how to analyze.
n squared will be more expensive than n log n,
because n linear function increase much faster
than log function.
All of you in log function will be slower than linear function.
So this is the common sense.
So basically, that's the only thing you need to know.
OK, one last slide.
Zero padding.
Zero padding is a common trick people
use to increase resolution.
Remember just now I say, for DFT,
there's a concept called resolution.
Two things, sampling frequency divided by the n.
When I give you a signal, you have
no way to change the sampling rate,
because it's already sampled.
The only thing you can change to increase the resolution
is by changing the n.
How many points you do DFT?
Suppose I give you a point signal.
How can you make the n larger to apply DFT?
The only way you do is adding zero.
You can add zero to the signal to make it more.
For example, if this is my original signal,
let's say 16 points.
If I don't add zero, I have no choice.
I have to do 16 point DFT.
So I'm going to end up with a spectrum like this.
So of course, the spectrum will be still 16 point.
So my resolution will be FS divided by 16.
But if I want to have a higher resolution signal,
so what I can do is I still keep the waveform,
but I add zero to it.
You can see all of these zero are added.
While at zero, I didn't give any new information.
It's the same information.
But I changed my resolution.
So when I change my resolution, you end up
with a spectrum that's still the same waveform,
but the samples are more dense.
You are making the sample dense.
So this is the only way you can change the resolution
if I already give the sample signal to you.
You have previous to n.
But FS, you cannot change it.
So this is basically a common trick in the exam
if I tell you, say, what can you do to change the resolution?
Answer is always zero padding.
And this is how you can do it.
So you can go through it.
But I think zero padding is nothing but just
increase the change the resolution.
Nothing's too important.
OK, so that's all I want to cover for today.
I think I'm just on time.
And basically, for today, two things.
Adasing.
You must know how to get adasing, where it come from,
and how to avoid it.
Micro-sumpling condition.
And then we learn the three things.
CTFT, DTFT, and DFT.
Know the difference.
Know how they are related.
And know how to apply DFT to arbitrary signals.
These are something you need to know.
OK, so that's all for today.
If you have questions, I can take questions.
Otherwise, feel free to go.
So I see you next week.
Same time and same place.
Thank you.