All right.
Let's start.
So this is our lecture three.
I hope you have all reviewed the things we talked about before, right?
Because this will be probably the last lecture we're going to review or recap some of the fundamental things for signal processing.
So from this week, maybe the later part of this week, we're going to see new things, right?
So pretty much what we're reviewing right now, as you can see, the first lecture, second lecture of my part,
is like talking about different representation of the signals.
And we talk about the repetition of the system, right? The few years last time.
So today we're going to finish the, you know, future representation.
So I'm going to do a quick recap of what we talked about last week.
And also we're going to learn something new, right?
And after that, we're going to move on to the future design part, which is, you know, maybe may not be the new thing for everyone,
but definitely new to some of you, right?
So this will be something we're going to wrap up today.
And starting from next week, we're going to see multirate processing, which is one of the main focus for my part.
All right. So this is roughly the plan we have.
But first of all, let me just do a quick recap of what we covered last week.
I hope you still remember, right? We spent some time talking about how to pretty much come up with this fast Fourier transform idea,
which can exactly reproduce DFT, discrete Fourier transform.
So they will give you the same results.
But, you know, normally when we talk about theoretical analysis, we do DFT because it's more standard, easier.
But in the actual implementation, fast Fourier transform is always the thing we're using.
So you need to understand first, what are they?
What is DFT? What is FFT?
And more importantly, you need to know why there's a speedup.
If you remember, we talked about how we can do this complexity analysis.
I hope you still remember. Big O, right?
And we say that, well, the reason people love FFT is because the complexity can go down from n squared to n log n.
And we say that, well, people love n log n because log n grows much slower than linear function.
So I showed you the plot. I hope you still remember that.
And you need to know why there's a speedup.
And after that, we say, well, all of these DFT, FFT are acting on the signals.
You can represent the signal using the spectrum.
And similarly, we can also do different kind of representation of the filter.
All right, so signal is the data you're processing, right?
The input you're processing. Consider this as your image, your acoustic signal, your text.
All of these can be treated as signals.
So pretty much the first part of the review we were doing are on signals.
And later we say, well, for the other part of the system, right, the filter,
they can also be represented in different forms.
That's why we say, well, we can either represent it using impulse response,
which is the time domain representation, right?
And also we can also do, represent the same thing in the frequency domain, right?
Which in other words, you can do transfer function or frequency response.
The reason we want to do two is because sometimes frequency domain representation
give you some better idea to understand the characteristics of filter,
but sometimes impulse response do, right?
So you need to know both. So later I'm going to talk more about it.
And, but basically, we say that by looking at the transform,
sorry, transfer function, which is nothing but a Z-transform of the impulse response,
you need to be able to categorize type of filters, right?
If you still remember, there are, I mean, in terms of the amount of impulse,
we have FIR, we have IR, in terms of which range of frequency we're representing,
we have low pass filter, band pass filter, and high pass filter,
or maybe band pass filter, right?
So these are different ways to categorize the kind of filters, right?
So you need to be able to categorize them, and also you need to be able to derive
the transfer function from the given signal flow chart, the block diagram, right?
I hope you still remember. We're going to revisit that today as well.
But block diagram is different from the mathematics expression, right?
Which we normally write as, you know, HA or maybe uppercase HZ.
Block diagram is more about a visual way or graphical way to represent the filtering.
The reason we want to do it is because eventually, if you want somebody to implement the filter for you,
you have to show them the block diagram, because that's exactly how you assemble
the multiplier, the adders, the time delay together to really implement the filter, right?
So theoretical analysis, we use mathematics form for real implementations, real design.
People normally do block diagram, right? So that is what I mean by flow diagram.
So you need to be able to derive, let's say I give you a block diagram.
You need to derive the corresponding transfer function, or maybe the difference equation, right?
And we also say that how to do it, right, if you still remember.
And also, another thing, actually the last thing we talked about last week is about
equivalent structure of a given filter structure, right?
So we say that if I give you a filter structure, you can always do this transpose operation.
I hope you still remember what is transpose operation. You just flip the sign,
you change the addition to the point where you speed out the signals, right?
And you change the input to output, output to input, so you can easily end up with the equivalent.
I mean, one of the equivalent block diagram of any given one.
Alright, so this is called equivalent, sorry, this is called a transpose operation.
It's not the only one. There are many methods we can do it, but this is the easy one.
I hope everybody can do it, and that's part of the scope.
Alright, so this is what we covered last week. But after that, I received some emails
and asking many of the basic things. I didn't know that you probably, not everyone knows,
for example, what is Z-transform. And it turns out that some of you have some questions about
how one can relate a difference equation, transfer function, frequency response together.
So I wish to spend some time to give you a recap on how are these things related from the mathematics perspective.
So everything starts from this difference equation. I hope you still remember.
Difference equation first, every time you see the word difference equation, it's always in time.
Difference equation is one of the time domain representation of the filter.
Because if you look at the equation here, how to tell whether a representation is time or frequency.
The easy way to do it is look at, are we using uppercase or lowercase?
By convention, we normally use lowercase to represent time domain.
Uppercase represents frequency domain. So if you are given an equation which has all the lowercase,
and the index is like n, it indicates this is a time domain representation.
So difference equation is one of the time domain representation.
We also learn impulse response, that's another one.
But difference equation is the starting point.
Everybody knows how to interpret a difference equation.
So first, difference equation. The most important thing you want to identify from that is the order.
So last time we keep saying that there's an order of a given difference equation.
So how to identify the order? You look at this polynomial, and you look at what is the maximum, let's say time delay here.
In z domain, it's going to be z to the power of minus something.
In time domain, you look at the time delay.
So the largest time delay you have will be the n, which is the order of this difference equation.
Later we're going to see the same kind of filter in the transfer function.
But in time domain, this is called difference equation, and you need to be able to tell the order of a difference equation,
which is the maximum amount of time delay, either in the input or output.
So last time we said that this is the general expression for difference equation.
But if you look at the right hand side of the equation, there are two parts.
This part is something to do with the input signal, which is x.
And it could be something to do with the past time output.
Remember, this term, the delay starts from 1.
There's no current time input, sorry, current time output, because current time output is on the left hand side of the equation.
So it could be, depends on both the current time, past time input, or the past time output.
So it depends on whether the first term is 0.
If the first term is all 0, this filter is called FIR filter.
Remember, we say that FIR filter, one of the characteristics is that all of the AM will be 0.
But in general, you have both.
Because if it's IR, you have both.
But the same always look for the largest amount of time delay.
Look for this big N.
This big N will be the order of the difference equation, no matter if it's RF, IR, IR, IR, it's the same.
So this N, capital letter N, is the order of the filter.
That's the first thing. I feel like many people are confused about it.
Let's just get it straight forward. This N is the order of the filter.
All of these parameters, like AM, BM, are called the filter parameters.
The key thing is that if you tell me all the AM and BM, I'm going to uniquely determine this filter.
So no ambiguity.
You tell me the AM, BM, I can uniquely determine the filter.
No ambiguity. That's unique.
There's a one-to-one mapping.
The other filter will have a unique set of parameters, and one set of parameters will uniquely determine the filter.
So basically, these are the only parameters you need to define a filter.
And then, as I just mentioned, if you see that all of AM equal to 0, this will be an FIR.
In other words, an FIR, in terms of difference equation, current time output will only be depending on the input.
What I'm going to do is the past time output. No feedback.
So this will be an FIR.
Now, this is all about difference equation.
Like I mentioned, difference equation is in time domain.
Nothing to do with the frequency.
But how can I convert this time domain difference equation to the transfer function or to the frequency domain representation?
Same filter, but I want to represent it not in time, but in frequency.
So how can I do it?
You can actually do the so-called Z-transform.
If you do Z-transform, you will get the transfer function.
If you do, let's say, DTFT, you will get the frequency response.
So either way, you will convert time domain to frequency domain.
So that's what we talked about last time about the transfer function, if you recall.
There's something with Z.
But how do we do this?
I didn't realize, not everybody knows Z-transform.
So let's recap about this Z-transform.
So Z-transform, it has a very similar form as DTFT, if you realize.
So I hope you still remember what is DTFT.
DTFT still take the discrete signal on the right-hand side.
You do a summation from minus infinity to infinity.
The only difference is the base.
I hope you still remember what is the base for DTFT.
E to the power of minus j omega n.
So here, if it's a Z-transform, you don't see the E to the power of something.
You have this Z to the power of minus n.
So the only difference is that it's going to simplify the DTFT.
We replace E to the power of minus j omega,
sorry, E to the power of minus j omega, not minus, minus sign is still here.
So Z-transform is nothing but replacing the E to the power of j omega in the DTFT with simply a Z.
It's just as that simple.
It's the same thing, but I just changed the notation.
Why we want to do this is because doing that will make the whole thing simpler.
You won't see these E to the power of things time to time.
You only see Z. So make things simpler.
By doing so, it still gives you a kind of frequency representation,
but it's the different kind of frequency.
They're defining the frequency using Z rather than omega.
That's the only difference.
But if you do so, you will end up with a Z-transform of the difference equation.
And that's going to be your transfer function.
This is how you can get a transfer function.
You simply do Z-transform over the difference equation.
The Z-transform, in fact, is nothing but representing a time delay.
Why?
Because talking about this definition of Z, if you have Z to the power of minus m,
these terms denote an n-time-stab delay.
Remember we say that in DTFT, the time delay will end up with the phase shift,
but the phase term is represented as the Z.
So you can easily denote any number of time delay in terms of Z to the power of minus m in the transfer function.
This is why last time we were seeing the block diagram, you keep seeing this Z to the power of minus 1.
So that's the reason that one time delay can be represented as Z to the power of minus 1.
It's because of that definition.
So if you have a time delay of m-time-stab, you can see equivalently right as the original transfer function,
multiplied by Z to the power of minus m.
So this is the reason.
It's due to the definition of Z-transform.
I hope this is clear now.
Last time I just run this too quick, I think.
But I wish you understand why we keep writing this E to the power of minus 1 minus 2
is because it's equivalent to a time-domain delay.
Okay, make sense?
So by doing so, originally we have this time-domain difference equation.
But if you do the Z-transform on both sides, left-hand side, right-hand side, you do Z-transform on both sides,
you are going to end up with this transfer function.
Also it's easy to understand.
So you just need to denote the Z-transform yn as the yz.
And every time you see a time delay, just write it as a Z to the power of minus m.
And the other term you can just keep it, am, bm, because these are constant scaling.
Constant term doesn't really change the scale. It's the same scale.
So if you extract the common factor, yz and xz, you are going to end up with something like this.
It's nothing but a Z-transform on both sides.
After this term, you can now come up with the so-called transfer function.
Because transfer function is defined as the ratio of the Z-transform of output versus the input.
So this is the formal definition of transfer function, it's the ratio of yz versus xz.
And how do you get this? You just simply do a Z-transform of the time-domain.
Oops, okay, let me use the pointer. You just simply do a Z-transform of the time-domain difference equation.
Both right-hand side and left-hand side, you're going to end up with the equation here.
And you just need to move the x to the left-hand side, to the denominator.
You move this term to the right-hand side to become the denominator.
So this is how you can get the transfer function.
So you will always have something at the numerator and something at the denominator.
So this is how you can derive or compute it the transfer function, given a time-domain representation.
So is it clear now? How are these two related?
We haven't talked about frequency response yet, but everybody knows how you can...
Let's say I give you a difference equation. How can you derive or corresponding transfer function?
I hope this is clear for everyone.
Or any question you can ask me before I move on.
Okay? Clear?
All right, so why are we interested in this transfer function?
So you will see this transfer function many, many times.
It's one of the most commonly used representation.
It's because if you give me this transfer function, I'm able to analyze the properties of this transform easily.
So what property I want to know?
Well, I'm first interested of the denominator here.
Because, first of all, everybody knows this denominator is actually a polynomial.
Because you see different terms and every term will have different order.
This is a very standard polynomial.
So we are interested of the roots of this polynomial.
In other words, what are the values that can make this term to be zero?
The denominator to be zero.
Okay? Because the roots of that, of course, is going to drive the transfer function to be infinitely large.
But this value of the roots...
Sorry, the roots of the denominator is called the poles of the transfer function.
We'll give a name to that.
It may be one, maybe two, maybe multiple, so we put an S here.
So it could be multiple poles.
Or maybe no poles, right?
Either way, it depends on the actual denominator.
And why we're interested of the poles is because if we find that all the poles, all the pKs, which make the denominator be zero,
if all of these values are somehow located inside a unit circle,
in other words, you look at the magnitude of these pKs.
If everyone are within the magnitude of one, you say that this filter is a stable filter.
In other words, you won't have any input going to drive the response to be infinitely large, right? Exploding.
So we love this filter because everything is bonded, it's finite, so it's going to be a useful filter, right?
Consider it as a system.
How to determine... So if a question asks you, hey, is this filter stable or not?
You should know that. Okay, what I need to know...
First, you need to obtain this transfer function, right?
Second one is looking at the denominator of this transfer function.
The last step is to figure out, okay, how can I find the roots of it?
You can do some factorizations, you factor it into multiple terms.
If you see adding term is making that to be zero, you know that that's a root, right?
So we can... All the roots, if all of them are within one, you can conclude this is a stable filter, right?
So this is why we need to use the transfer function.
Okay, well, another thing people are interested in is the zeros, right?
Zeros is correspondingly the roots of the numerator, okay?
Numerator, if you find a root, you will drive the whole transfer function to be zero.
And also, you know, a filter can have multiple zeros, and those zeros are normally called the z-case.
So normally, we are interested in all the poles and all of the zeros of a given transfer function, right?
Okay, so this is actually why we need... I mean, why we like to analyze the transfer function, right?
And you know how to get there, right? Doing the z-transform.
Okay, so transfer function, we know that it's by doing the z-transform of the difference equation.
But like I mentioned, you can also do a DTFT over, you know, let's say, difference equation, right?
So how are these two related? So both of them are in the frequency domain, right?
So both of them are considered as the frequency representation of the filter.
In fact, transfer function and frequency response are nothing but a different way to express it, right?
They are basically the same thing.
And how to relate the two? Well, it's very easy because it's just by swapping the parameters.
So if you give me a z-transform, which is the hz, I simply just let all of the z equal to e to the power of j omega.
I can end up with my frequency response.
So it's only a swap of the variables, right? But the form is the same, actually.
But by swapping the variables, you are going from the z-frequency to the omega frequency.
So it's a two kind of frequency, but both of them are equivalently represented, right?
So now you see how they are related, right?
So you're starting points to the difference equation.
If you do z-transform, you end up with the transfer function.
If you do DTFT, you end up with the frequency response.
And these two are nothing but a swap of the variables, right?
So this is basically how you can organize all of the possible ways to represent a filter, right?
Okay, is it clear enough?
All right, so the next time if there's a question, give you any form, right?
Let's say one form of the representation.
You need to be able to convert it to any other form, right?
Because they are equivalent.
So you need to know what tool you're going to use, right?
So let me give you a quick test, right?
So if I give you the frequency response, I ask for the difference equation.
What are you going to do?
What should you do wrong to get the difference equation?
Okay, let me repeat.
If a question says, hey, here's a filter, and here's the frequency response of the filter,
how can I get my difference equation of the same filter?
What should I do?
Sorry?
Any guess?
Difference equation?
Yes, that's correct.
So you are suggesting let's first get to the transfer function, right?
How to go from frequency response to transfer function?
Well, you do the variable swapping, right?
You just swap the variable.
Let's say you swap it back.
We have to somehow figure out a way to swap it back.
And then you do a so-called inverse Z-transform.
Yes, that's possible.
But maybe a more straightforward way is just simply do an inverse DTFT, right?
Because like I mentioned, both of these two terms, like frequency response and also Z-transform are,
one way to represent them in frequency, but depends on what frequency you are talking about.
You just need to find the corresponding so-called transform, right?
If it's a transfer function, it's in the Z-transform.
If it's a frequency response, it's actually in the omega domain, right?
You have a question?
Okay, so you are saying, okay.
Your question is like, if we already have this frequency response, right,
which is done by DTFT, why we need a Z-transform anyway?
Anyway, they are the same, right?
You're right.
All of these forms we have, we're talking about here are equivalent.
The same thing, right?
But why we need specifically a Z-transform is because it's simpler in terms of the form, right?
You don't have all of these, you know, the whole idea is to get rid of this repeating Z to the power of something.
It's not easy to write and also not easy to rate.
People want to get rid of it.
And for the sake of simplicity, they replace it with Z.
That's it.
No other reason.
And because people realize that time domain is actually equivalent to just simply a Z to the power of minus one.
And due to that reason, they purposely invent this Z-transform.
Because what we're going to do is time delay very frequently.
Later you will see, right?
Multi-prosessing.
Next week we're also going to talk about this time delay very, very frequently.
So instead of writing this e to the power of minus j omega every time, they just simply write a Z to the power of minus one.
For simplicity, no other reasons.
Yeah.
But you're right, the equivalent is the same thing.
And in fact, if you're dealing with signal processing, you will find that people invent many, many transforms.
Like wavelets, cosine transform, Fourier transform, sinusoidal transform.
And why do we want to do it?
Because they may be compact in some transform, just like here.
They may be compact in Z-transform and people like to use it.
Most likely for the sake of compact representation.
Yeah.
Okay.
Any other questions?
All right.
But just ask yourself, are you able to go from one way of representation to the other, any other way?
Because in the exam I can give you any question.
But you need to know at least one approach to convert one to the other.
And that's it.
You should be safe for the test.
And I think I already explained basically the pair-wise relationship.
Okay.
So we have two time domain representation.
Impulse response, difference equation.
We have two frequency domain representation, right?
Transfer function, frequency response.
So think about how they are related to each other.
Right?
And then you should be very clear about all of these representation.
Okay.
So that's it.
Here's a simple, here's one test.
All right.
So one example.
Suppose that I were given a filter.
And this, apparently the filter is represented using a difference equation.
Again, this is a time domain representation.
So they first want you to find out what is the zeroes and what are the zero and poles.
Okay.
So to get the zero and poles, we just say that you can read that only from the transfer function.
So the first thing to do is to ask yourself, how can I obtain a transfer function from the difference equation?
It's actually a Z-transform, right?
You need to apply Z-transform to get the transfer function.
That's step one.
So what you need to do is apply to both sides, right?
Left-hand side, right-hand side.
So you're going to enabrate this guy goes to YZ and this guy goes to 0.5 times YZ times Z2, sorry, Z2 power of minus 1.
Because this minus 1 gives you one time delay, right?
And the right-hand side is also XZ plus XZ times Z2 power of minus 1, right?
So now what you need to do is you want to figure out the transfer function, which is nothing but YZ over XZ.
So you want to move the X to the other side and you want to move the other term to the right-hand side, right?
Both of them become the denominator.
So that's how you can get this term, which is the ratio between Y and Z.
Sorry, Y and X, alright?
So now you need to ask yourself, how can I find a zero?
How can I find a pole?
Right, this is the second step.
So the first step is to get the right representation.
In this case, it's the Z-transform.
It's the transfer function.
Alright, the second step is to figure out the answer to the question by using that function.
So here, zero will be the value to make the numerator to be zero.
So what is the zero here?
The zero will be this term becomes minus 1.
How many zeroes have... well, I can only have up to 1 because the numerator is order 1.
For, let's say, nth order, you can have at most n zeros.
That's the nature of the polynomial.
And then, correspondingly, how many poles I have?
Well, I have one pole.
If this guy is equal to 0.5, it's going to make this denominator to be zero, which drives the whole thing to be infinity.
So you have one zero, one pole.
This is how you can answer the first question.
Now they say, is this stable?
Well, we just learned how to tell if the filter is stable or not.
It's by looking at the poles, not the zero, the poles.
And we're only interested in the magnitude of the poles.
So now we see the poles is 0.5.
What's the magnitude?
0.5 because that's a real number, right?
No phase.
So 0.5 gives you a magnitude which is less than 1.
In other words, that pole is within the unit vector, unit pole.
So in this case, you will have a stable filter.
Now you see how to do it.
So always the step one, ask yourself, what is the right representation I need?
And figure out how to get there.
The second is, extract information from that expression, from that representation.
You need poles, you need zeros, you need stability.
Find out the corresponding condition, right?
And answer the question.
This is how you do it.
And now the second question says, well, let's compute the frequency response at omega equal to pi over 4.
So now the keyword is frequency response, right?
Do we have the frequency response now?
Not yet, right?
What we have is the difference equation.
We already got the transfer function.
So we need the other type of frequency representation, which is the frequency response.
So how can I get my frequency response now?
Sorry?
Please use the pole minus 12 to replace the unit pole over the j-value.
Omega, exactly.
So you're right.
So actually you have two ways.
You can simply, that's what you suggested, directly go from the transfer function to the frequency response, right?
Because most of them are in the frequency, so you don't have to do another transform.
But just simply change the variables.
How to change the variable?
You just need to replace the z-waste corresponding e to the power of j omega.
Right?
So this is the simple way.
Or if you want, you can also do a DTFT to this guy.
But I don't really recommend that.
But if you want, you can do it.
You got the same result.
The simple way is just go from the z-transform.
All right?
So if you do the change of the variables, you're going to end up with something like this.
Okay?
So now we have this variable of omega.
So now you can substitute the value of the omega equal to pi over 4.
Of course you have to do some calculation, but somehow you can get the corresponding complex number.
And of course you can use a calculator if you want.
You're allowed to bring a calculator, by the way.
So by after having this guy, you look at the question.
The question is asking for the frequency response.
So in other words, you need both the magnitude and the phase.
Right?
So the magnitude will be the 2.5078, which is the one before the e to the power of something.
And the phase is actually in the exponential term here.
So these will be the corresponding answers.
So normally when people ask you a response, you need two things.
If it's a complex number, you need a magnitude plus phase.
So that's how you can extract from the complex number.
Right?
Okay?
It makes sense.
A simple example, but give you some idea, right?
What could be the question, you know?
But I don't really give you the same question.
I can give you something similar.
Right?
But any pair of the representation, you need to know how to compute.
Okay?
Questions?
No?
Okay.
So I think that's pretty much enough recap for those of you who are not familiar with
the transform function.
Now we go back to what we left out last week.
All right?
If you remember, we talked about the so-called equivalent structure.
Right?
We say there is a transpose operation.
I give you a block diagram.
You can give me another block diagram with the same kind of a filter design.
Right?
By doing the transpose operation.
Actually, right?
That's one way to do it.
But if you're doing that, it's going to give you the exact same filter.
All right?
So it's the same kind of equivalent structure.
But in some cases, even the equivalent structure, right?
How should I say?
That kind of transpose operator will not give you something desired, right?
Because that's only one way to find the equivalent.
So we want to look at what is the basic structure that we can use to design an FIR filter.
Right?
Because FIR filter, which we talked about last week, basically you can have an older
N FIR filter, which is representing in terms of the transfer function here.
Right?
We just say that, well, how to determine the order?
You look at the highest time delay.
Right?
Here the highest time delay will be z to the power of minus upper case N.
And, well, of course, this is going to be a polynomial.
Right?
And corresponding to the time domain, we just say that this can give you a difference equation.
Also, you know, order of N.
And actually for an Nth order of a filter, right, you need exactly M plus 1 coefficients
to represent this filter.
Right?
So because just now we say that actually all of the, you actually have M plus 1 terms
of polynomial, right, including the zeroes order.
So in total, you have M plus 1 coefficients.
So to implement this in a block diagram, remember we say that these are the mathematical expression.
But we also have a corresponding block diagram.
So if I want to represent an Nth order filter in the block diagram, in general, I'm not talking
about a special case, but in general case, we need M plus 1 multiplications or multipliers
and two input adders together.
Okay?
Why this is true?
It's easy, right?
Because you will have M plus 1 coefficients.
You need to multiply them to each of the terms in the polynomial.
And each of the terms in the polynomial represents the current time and the delayed version of the signal.
So you have to multiply them together.
And these require M plus 1 multiplication.
And then you have to sum them up.
Right?
Summing up M plus 1 term need N number of adders.
So these are the necessary amount of computation you need for general case.
Okay?
So when you design, let's say a design an FIR filter, right?
Directly translate that expression into this block diagram.
So how can I interpret this?
Well, I have an X and coming in.
Right?
So this branch is actually the zero order branch.
Okay?
Why?
Because there's no time delay.
Right?
So this branch is actually the zero order.
In other words, the current time input contributed to the output.
Right?
And this branch denotes the delay by one branch, which is the first order polynomial.
I mean, first order term in the polynomial.
Right?
Corresponding this term becomes the second order polynomial.
So if I give you, let's say, a general form of the difference equation or the transfer function.
The direct form, we call direct form to design the block diagram is by doing the exact writing
them down as the, you know, M, sorry, M plus 1 number of multiplication.
So this is M plus 1 together with N number of addition.
Right?
That's how you can form the Nth order.
In this case, it's the fourth order polynomial for the Z-transform.
Right?
Okay, so I just want to repeat this.
So just now we say that you can represent a filter using either Z-transform or difference
equation.
Right?
And we say that if it's a Z-transform, we can represent it as a polynomial.
And polynomial have an order, highest order.
Let's say we have Nth order polynomial.
Right?
In other words, if it's Nth order polynomial here, you have at most M plus 1 terms if you
write them up.
Right?
Because you have to count from zero's order, first order, all the way to Nth order.
So you're going to have N number of terms here.
Make sense?
Does it make sense?
I'm saying that if you have an Nth order polynomial, you are going to have M plus 1 term.
I mean at most, right?
Some of them could be zero, but let's say in general form, you have M plus 1 terms.
Okay?
Every term will have a corresponding coefficient, this hN.
N range from zero to N, right?
Eventually have M plus 1 number of coefficients.
So you have to multiply them with the corresponding Z term.
So you need M plus 1 number of multiplier.
Right?
And that's why in the direct form, you will have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 4 plus 1 number of multiplier.
And these will be the corresponding coefficients here.
Right?
Okay.
And we say that every Z to the power of something denotes a time delay.
So if it's first order, you have one time delay.
If it's second order, you have two time delay.
So in other words, the A's order term will have N number of time delay.
Right?
So that's why you end up with the first delay, second delay, third delay, so together, you have N number of delay.
Because this is actually the highest order term.
Now the only thing to do is just sum them up.
You need N number of summation.
Right?
So this is actually the direct form of writing an Nth order polynomial in a block diagram.
And this is called direct form because we don't do any manipulation.
Right?
You are given whatever polynomial you have, just write them down, term by term.
And you're going to end up with N plus one branches here.
So these will give you one realization of the FIR, which can be ready for development.
Right?
And this is nothing but a convolution.
If you think about it in this way, right?
You have a signal, you time something, you delay, you time something, you delay.
This is actually a convolution sum description indicated for Nth order.
I mean, fourth order in this case, polynomial.
Right?
And these will be the form you need to know how to design.
If I give you a, you know, difference equation or a Z-transform, right, the transfer function,
how to write the block diagram.
So last week, if you remember, we say that if I give you a block diagram, you need to be able to write down the difference equation.
Right?
Now this time it's the opposite.
They can give you a difference equation or transfer function.
They want you to write down at least the direct form of the block diagram.
This will be the way to do it.
Okay?
Does it make sense?
I mean, this is actually the easiest way to do it.
Right?
No manipulation.
I mean, you have exactly N plus one number of multiplication plus N number of summation.
Right?
And you have N number of time delay.
That's how you can design that.
So, how wide this structure will be depends on the order.
Right?
So the number of branches is exactly equal to N plus one number.
Now, if you do this, right, you can analyze the form by just saying, well, if I'm giving this block diagram,
I can write my YN as the corresponding summation.
Right?
And this will be precisely the form of a convolution sum because you are multiplying the signal gradually with time delay
where is the filter impulse response?
Right?
So this is how you can, how you actually interpret the direct form of it.
And last time we said that actually you can easily do a so-called transpose.
Oh, no, no, sorry, no, no, no, no, no, not yet, not yet.
Okay.
This is actually called, you can easily do a transpose operation to the direct form.
So, one can easily convert it into the transpose version.
Right?
Remember, we just say that you can do the transpose operation.
And any form of the block diagram, you simply need to flip the directions, right,
change the, sort of the addition with the splitting point, you can have another equivalent form.
Right?
So this is how you can do it.
But, and if you do so, both the direct form and the transpose, the transpose version are guaranteed to be canonical with respect to the delays.
Remember, we say that we want the repetition to be compact.
Right?
So there's a rule to check whether the block diagram is actually canonical.
If you do direct form, it's going to be always canonical.
All right?
Okay.
So, so this is actually where we started with.
Right?
And, but this is not the only way you can design the block diagram.
So, just not what we're talking about is the general form.
Right?
If you have any polynomial, you can always derive the direct form in that sense.
Now, normally for a higher order FIR, let's consider FIR which is very high order.
In other words, you are going to end up with a super long structure.
Remember, the width of this structure is actually proportional or exactly equal to M plus 1.
Right?
In other words, if A increases, your structure will be very long.
Which is not always good for design.
So, to handle the higher order FIR design, one can actually choose not by simply doing a
direct form.
You can actually do something called Cascade, Cascade inversion from the directed form.
So, the way to do that is by writing this polynomial not by simply just, just N's order kind of
expression.
You can try to decompose it into a product of multiple low order polynomial.
Right?
So, just now, what we wrote is a summation of the N's order polynomial.
But if the A is too large, you probably want to factorize it and write it as a product of,
let's say, 2nd order polynomial.
Right?
And by doing so, every term here becomes lower order.
So, in this case, when you realize it, you don't have to realize that always into a direct form.
Right?
In other words, making them as a linear kind of form.
But you can decompose that into multistages, Cascading one by one.
Right?
And how to determine every stage?
Well, every stage will be determined by this, you know, one factor of the polynomial.
Right?
So, for example, if I, if I have k equal to 3, I will have three stages.
Every stage, you will have this omega, sorry, beta 1, beta 2, correspondingly as the multiplier
factor.
Right?
And the delay will always be 2 in this case.
So, it gives you some idea to avoid a super long design, especially when the order is
very, is very big.
Right?
But of course, if you can guarantee that this factorization is true, is correct, the form
will also be equivalent.
Right?
Because you're Anna Boyce's equivalent expression, so the corresponding design will also be equivalent.
And the coefficients, you know, of the function, if you look at every stage, right, they also
follow a similar way as the direct form.
But the order is actually upper bounded by the choice you have for every term.
Okay?
So, it's just one way to simplify a higher order FIR.
All right.
Make sense?
Okay?
But if you want to do it, you have to find a way to decompose your original polynomial.
But not every polynomial can be decomposed, right?
But if you find a way to decompose it into multiple factors, then you can come up with
the corresponding, so-called cascaded version of the block diagram.
Right?
So, you know, you need to see first how mathematically this term is related to this term.
So, mathematically, what you do from direct form to the cascaded form is by factorization.
Right?
Then, blockwise, you are reducing the width from m plus 1 into multiple stages.
Then every stage becomes a very small one.
Right?
But you have to have multiple stages.
Okay?
All right?
But, you know, by doing so, you probably don't even save any amount of multipliers because
you still have to do, you know, actually six.
Right?
So, the amount of multiplications and additions are the same.
It's just like you want to avoid a super long design in the implementation stage.
Right?
Okay.
So, this is basically what we end up last week because last week we only covered, like,
give a block diagram.
Right?
How can we derive the mathematic form?
But now we're doing the opposite way.
So, we're going to give you a polynomial representation of the difference equation or transfer function.
How can you design the corresponding block diagram?
So, the other way.
So, now you should know both ways.
Right?
How to give you a block diagram, write the expression, or give you an expression, write the block
diagram.
But, we haven't said anything about the actual transfer function.
Right?
So, what are the so-called desired property of the transfer function?
So, all of these transfer functions we're talking about are in general form.
Right?
So, we just write the general form of the polynomial.
We didn't say what are the polynomial that could potentially be implemented and something
we like.
Right?
So, after that we want to look at one of the pretty much all very desired property for
the FIR, which is the linear phase.
I think I briefly mentioned this last week.
Right?
So, we say that, well, if you have an ideal low pass filter, right, you won't really implement
it.
You have to do some kind of time delay to make it a causal, remember?
And we say, if you make it a causal, you have this kind of time delay, you're going to
introduce phase.
Right?
So, if you have to have phase, you better make the phase linear.
So, that's why, if you are talking about the real lasting filter, you won't have the
ideal low pass filter like that.
So, you always have phase.
We cannot make the phase zero, but the second best thing we want is we want to make the
phase to be linear to the frequency.
Okay?
So, we can tell you why this is something people always like.
That's the first one.
So, the first one is you understand why the linear phase is desired.
Or in other words, if you don't have linear phase, what could be wrong?
Okay?
That's the first thing I want you to know.
The second thing is how to make the filter linear phase.
Okay?
What are the things you have to constrain such that the filter will be linear phase?
So, these are the two things very important, right, for the folding part.
So, first, let's talk about motivation.
Right?
We say that, you know, FIFotor can be used to design digital filter.
But for many cases, you have to make some compromise, right?
Talking about the causality, talking about the finite length.
So, you won't really have zero phase, but the second ideal thing you want to have is
the linear phase response.
So, why linear phase is always needed?
Let's just use this example to showcase, right?
What could be wrong if you don't have linear phase?
So, this function is also pretty simple.
You can, as you can tell here, it's just two different kind of single solids, right,
summed together.
But the two single solids will have different frequency, right, different kind of, like,
omega, right?
This is actually pi over 7.
This is 2 pi over 5.
So, if I consider this as my input signal, okay?
I want you to pass that into a filter.
Now, this filter, let's make it general, right?
This filter, let's say, the filter itself doesn't have any magnitude amplification,
but the phase term depends, right?
I write this phase term in general as the phi omega, okay?
The phi omega is a general form for the phase, right?
It can be linear, it can be anything, but just write it as a phi omega in general.
Now I want you to pass my signal into this filter.
What will be the output?
Okay?
We say that, you know, you have an input, you have a signal, you have a filter.
To get the output, you can either do convolution in the time domain, or you can do multiplication
in the frequency domain, right?
Two ways to do it.
Because this guy is actually a very special function, right?
Synosoys.
We say that, we have just two spikes in the frequency domain.
So computing the response in the frequency domain will be very easy, because it's zero
elsewhere, only impulse function at the corresponding frequency.
So you will only have some response at the frequency of pi over seven and two pi over
five, right?
Only these two places.
So correspondingly, you can look at the response at these two frequency, but given that, your
filter is actually in the form of d omega.
At that frequency, you will have certain amplification and phase change, right?
The only thing you are going to do is the phase change and also the amplification.
Oh, sorry, time delay, sorry, time delay at the magnitude, right?
And we say that, well, let's just make the magnitude to be one, right?
No amplification.
So basically, you won't really change the amplitude.
Amplitude will also be one.
The only thing we introduce is the delay here, right?
Time delay here.
The delay will be correspondingly the phi omega applied at omega equal to the corresponding
frequency, right?
So here will be phi at the omega equal to pi over seven.
Here's the phi at the omega equal to two pi over five, all right?
So this will be the general form for a filter that without any amplification, right?
In other words, the unit amplitude response.
All right?
But we haven't said anything about the phi, right?
The phi here can be anything, okay?
Now we consider two scenarios.
The first scenario is that this phi is actually minus three omega square.
Okay, what does this mean?
This is not a linear function, right?
So what is a linear function?
A linear function cannot have a second order term.
It can be a first order term, right?
So if you have a second order term, you violate the linear phase assumption.
So the first way to design the phase response is a nonlinear way.
Agree?
I mean, second order is not linear, right?
This is a very mathematical question.
You can go for third order, fourth order, but none of that will be linear, right?
We can also design a linear phase scenario which is equal to, let's say, minus three
omega.
So this is actually a linear function, all right?
So let's consider two, right?
Either way, how will be the output look like?
Okay?
So I just plot, let's say, the first row to be the input signal, right?
So this is just some arbitrary input signal, sorry, not arbitrary, cosine, right?
So cosine sum together, this is actually the input signal, all right?
So this is the signal corresponding to the nonlinear phase case, all right?
And the last row will be the output corresponding to the linear phase case.
Okay, so one thing we can tell is that, let's say, first, let's compare the first row with
the last row, okay?
Compare these two waveforms.
So first of all, they are not the same, right?
Apparently they are not the same wave, okay?
You don't really find a match.
But the good thing is that you realize the only difference between the two, right?
The first row and the last row is the time delay, right?
For example, you can see here the minimum goes here, right?
This minimum goes here.
Here the minimum goes here.
So basically you will have a fixed amount of time delay in the last row.
But you, except for that, the waveform is not distorted.
In other words, even though I have a different kind of output,
I can simply do a reverse time shift to get back to my original input.
All right, so this is something easy to restore or easy to represent, right?
But if you are going to have a nonlinear phase kind of system, you will have distortion.
So this is actually the corresponding to a scenario
in which you have nonlinear phase response, right?
In this case, you won't have the exact match.
You won't get some distortion because this is not more than just time delay, right?
And in this case, you may not even have a chance to revert back to the original signal.
In other words, you have distortion, okay?
So this is actually one example to show that linear phase,
if you cannot get zero phase, linear phase is the second best thing you want
in designing the filter, right?
And just now, last time we already explained that if you want to stick to zero phase,
you normally are going to end up with the non-causality,
which is impossible in practice, right?
So that's the reason in practice, linear phase is always what we want
because you cannot get zero phase, so you do linear phase, right?
Well, pretty simple, if you don't have a linear phase,
the output could have distortion.
Compared to input, all right?
So this is the reason, I mean, the reason why we care about the linear phase, okay?
I'm not going to prove it.
I mean, you can try to prove it.
It's not so hard, but at least I want to have some feeling, right?
Why linear phase is important to avoid apparent distortion except for time delay, okay?
That's the first thing, why?
You know, motivation to do it, okay?
So now, the second question is always ask how to do it, right?
How to get this property of linear phase.
In fact, if we're only talking about FIR, right?
So far, we only talk about FIR.
I believe Prof. Lin is going to talk about IR in the second part,
but my part, FIR, just FIR, right?
For FIR, linear phase is actually very simple, okay?
Only two conditions, and all of the two are related to symmetry property, okay?
Make it very easy to remember.
Okay, let's look at the first condition, right?
The first condition will be exactly symmetric, okay?
So the theory says if I'm going to analyze this FIR, apparently this is the transfer function, right?
So I'm going to say if this FIR is going to satisfy the following symmetric condition.
In other words, they look at the BMs.
Okay, what are the BMs?
BM are the coefficients, right?
Of the input signals, right?
So I'm looking at all of these BM if I observe a symmetric condition of the BM.
In other words, for any M ranging from 0 all the way to M minus 1,
okay, M minus 1 is equal to N, right, in this case.
So if I have all the BM equal to BM minus 1 minus M,
in other words, the corresponding the symmetric part, right?
Like 0 versus M minus 1, sorry, 0 versus M minus 1, 1 versus M minus 2,
sorry, 2 versus M minus 3, right?
So you have this kind of symmetry.
If they are pairwise equal, I can see that this future will be linear phase, okay?
But pay attention.
It's like, okay, so it's not a sufficient necessary condition.
It's actually a sufficient condition.
In other words, if the symmetric is true, it's going to be a linear phase, okay?
But the opposite is not right, all right?
So I'm not saying the equivalent.
I'm saying if I have this symmetric property, I'm going to have a linear phase.
Okay, the reason I'm saying that is because there's another condition also give you the linear phase.
So it's either one, all right?
This is only one of them, okay?
So but this one is actually saying that pairwise, for example, B0 and B4,
B1 and B3, B2 and B2, they must be equal, okay?
The value doesn't matter, but they have the pairwise equal along the center point.
Okay, makes sense?
Okay, so let's look at some example, right?
So let's say this one, right?
This is actually a transfer function.
So if I give you this transfer function, tell me what's the order of this transfer function?
Three, right?
Because the highest z-order is three, right?
So this is a order of three transfer function.
So you're going to have four terms, all right?
So based on the definition, right?
Let's go back to the definition.
The definition says you need to make sure if you want to conclude that this guy is a linear phase,
you have to make sure B0 equals to the last term, right?
So here, sorry, the last term is actually B3, right?
So you must make sure B0, the first term, equal to the last term.
The second term equal to the second last term, okay?
That's how you can pose the pairs, all right?
So if all of them are pairwise equal, you can make the conclusion,
say, hey, this is a linear phase, all right?
So for this example, you need to make sure B0 equal to B3, apparently they are equal, right?
And B1 equal to B2, right?
Apparently they are equal.
So if all of them are equal, you can conclude this guy is a linear phase.
Simple, right?
You just need to pair them up, first term, last term, second term, second last term.
Everything is equal, then it's a linear phase, right?
Very simple, right?
But you also have to be careful, right?
Especially, let's look at this example, okay?
Hz equal to this guy, all right?
Tell me what's the order?
What's the order of this transfer function?
Ha, seven?
Okay, how to tell, okay, we just talked about this, right?
How to tell the order of a transfer function?
We just talked about this one hour ago, right?
What, okay, my question is what's the order of the transfer function?
Here, this is the transfer function, right?
What's the order of it?
Five, right?
Just look at the highest order.
Just now this is three, now this is five, right?
Okay, so now my question is, out of so many terms, right?
What should be the first term here?
First term referred to the B0, right?
What is the first term here?
Sorry?
Zero, okay, anyone else, any other suggestions?
What's the first term we're talking about here?
Okay, it should be zero, right?
The reason is every time you count, when you write the polynomial, right?
If it's a fifth-order polynomial, how many terms should I have?
Sixth term, right?
Remember, don't forget the zero-order term.
So if it's nth-order polynomial, you will have in general form n plus one number of
terms because the zero-order also counts, right?
Apparently, these expression only have one, two, three, four, five, five terms.
It means the B0 is actually zero and that's why it didn't write it down, okay?
But that doesn't mean that you only have five terms, you have six terms.
So don't forget the B0.
Here, the B0 equal to zero, all right?
So when you want to create these pairs,
the term to pair up with the number five is actually B0, right?
Not one, okay, not this term, but B0.
The first term must be starting from B0, all right?
Okay, now if I look at simply this guy, right?
I find that, well, B0 equal to zero, my B5 equal to one, so they're not equal, right?
So can I direct conclude that this is not a linear phase?
Remember, it's not necessary and sufficient, right?
It's actually only sufficient condition.
Means if you can find all the way to form the symmetric,
you can conclude it's a linear phase, right?
But not the other way around.
So if I form this as the fifth order polynomial, I cannot find the pairs, right?
It doesn't mean it's not a linear because it could be other condition, okay?
So here, the solution to that or the other way to look at it is to pose the whole
polynomial as the sixth order polynomial.
Okay, because you can actually have a sixth order polynomial, but
treating the BZ6 to be zero, right?
It's actually a sixth order polynomial, but the B6 equal to zero.
Why I wanna do this is because now I have a zero to match with my B0.
All right, just now we see that B0 is zero, that's why it didn't show up.
Now I want to pair up this zero.
I can add another term, even higher order, right?
That gives me another zero to pair them up.
So this is how you can view the polynomial, right?
We use the A equal to six case.
Makes sense?
So that's why you can see that, well, my B0 is equal to B6, right?
So this is a valid pair.
Now I look at the second term, which is the B1, and the second last term,
which is B5, they are also equal, right?
One versus one, okay?
Now B2 is also equal to B4, right?
And then, let me see.
One versus that, here, here.
Okay, now, the only term here is B3, right?
So what is the pair for B3?
B3 itself, right?
Because by definition, if you look at this definition, right?
It says BM equal to BM minus M.
So here the N, after increasing order, becomes six, right?
So in this case, I have B3 equals to B6 minus three, which is also B3, right?
So can I say B3 equal to B3?
It's always equal, right?
So that pair also is valid.
And due to that, I form all the pairs to, I need all of them are equal.
So then I'm going to end up with a conclusion saying,
this is a linear phase filter, right?
So this is one example to tell you that it could be a little bit tricky, right?
So don't conclude so quickly, because, I mean, two lessons.
First one is, don't forget the B0, all right?
So my suggestion is always looking at the order.
And you need to write, let's say you have an order of N, right?
You always need N plus one term.
If you miss any term, it could be B0, or maybe there's any order missing there.
So do a careful check if there's any term missing.
That's step one, all right?
If you're somehow treating this guy as the first term of the day,
I cannot help you, right?
You'll get the wrong answer, all right?
That's the first thing.
The second thing is, if you cannot work it out for, let's say,
Nth order, try N plus one.
Because you can always put in the N plus one,
the N plus one order term to be zero, right?
That's also a valid expression, all right?
So that's actually the lesson, right?
But if you get that settled, everything should be quite simple.
You just follow the definition here, right?
That's how you can conclude, all right?
So okay, how many slides I have?
Maybe we can take a break right now.
So I will take maybe a 10-minute break.
Maybe a slide there.
Let's come back around 7.45, all right?
7.45, then we can start the second half, all right?
7.45, all right?
So like a 13-minute break, okay?
All right, thank you.
Sorry, I think I started a bit late.
Just not got a lot of questions.
All right, so let's resume what we talked about just now.
So I think through this example, sorry, actually,
yeah, so this example you can tell that
if you are given a transfer function, right?
Using a theorem one, you can at least say something
according to the symmetric property.
Even though later we're going to learn another condition,
but this is one of the condition, right?
And I hope all of you can first identify
whether or not the symmetric property is satisfied, right?
So there could be some trap, for example, here.
This is one example,
but you have to clearly form the pairs.
If you can form them, you can conclude
this is definitely going to be linear phase, right?
Okay, but just know what I'm telling you
is directly give you the theorem, right?
I didn't prove it.
I'm just saying that if you have this, right?
You will have a linear phase,
but I never say anything why, right?
In fact, you can try to prove this yourself
if you want to do a general form.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to prove it
for two special forms.
In other words, these theories should be true
for any order, right?
Order one, order two, any n,
but I'm going to show you two special case, right?
Why having this condition, the theorem one satisfied,
you will have a linear phase.
Four, m equal to three and m equal to four, okay?
m minus one is n.
So in other words, I'm proving for n equal to two
and n equal to three, all right?
So let's look at the first case.
Well, m equal to three,
you're going to have a second order polynomial, right?
Second order polynomial,
the standard form should have three terms, okay?
So under three terms,
the way you can form them is to group the zero order term
with the second order term, right?
This is actually the pair you have.
And then this first order term aside, right?
So if let's say I do have the symmetric condition, okay?
What I'm proving here is I'm saying
if the symmetry property holds,
I want to show you that the phase is linear, all right?
So I can assume that the B zero equal to B two.
I can get rid of B two and just write it as B zero.
Okay, that's why I can simplify everything into this form
and I can extract the Z minus one out
and leaving the other term left, right?
So if this is my Z transform,
again, I can easily get my frequency response, right?
We can just simply swap the Z
ways e to the power of j omega, right?
So by doing so, I will have my frequency response
which equal to this form, all right?
So why you can merge these two into a cosine?
Actually, this is actually called Euler formula, right?
Euler equation where for those of you who know it, right?
If you have e to the power of something,
you got a real and imaginary, right?
The real part is cosine, imaginary part is sine.
And if you have the two terms sum up,
the imaginary part will be canceled.
That's why you have a cosine term
doubled by the magnitude, right?
Okay, so now if this is my frequency response, right?
I want to analyze, if I want to analyze the frequency,
sorry, the phase response,
I need to separate the magnitude and the phase.
In other words, I need to write this term
in the polar form, right, in other words.
So in the form like this.
So you have to rewrite this form
into the magnitude times e to the power of J phase, right?
And this kind of a theta R becomes our phase term.
Okay, so how to do it?
Well, so you can tell that HR is actually equal to,
okay, now I'm just separating the two terms, right?
So these terms have nothing contributing to the magnitude.
Only the second term has magnitudes.
But this term I know is a real number, right?
So I can actually form the polar form,
but only for the second form, second term,
not the first term.
And this term I can tell that my theta R is equal to,
because it's a real number, remember?
If it is a real number,
I will get either zero or pi, right?
Because I cannot get other value.
If I get other value,
I'm going to end up with a complex number, right?
Not the real number.
So this is actually the phase response
for only the second term, all right?
So it's going to be, if my real part,
sorry, my magnitude goes up, positive, I have no phase, zero.
If my magnitude is actually negative,
I have to absolve the minus sign, right?
So I will have a pi,
but either way, they will not have other possible phase
because this part is actually real number.
Okay, real number means basically zero phase, right?
But positive real number means zero phase.
Negative number means minus pi phase, or pi phase, right?
Okay, so, but this is only the second part.
Now I have to consider the first part,
which is this guy, right?
Sorry, this guy, e to the power of minus j omega.
So what I need to do is I have to kind of multiply
the minus pi into my phase response.
Just now I'm talking about the theta R,
which is either zero or pi, right?
But now I have to take into account of this minus omega.
So my overall phase response will be minus omega
plus theta R omega.
Okay, so this will become my overall phase response.
So can we see something about this function?
Right, so this function apparently have two terms.
The first term, I think everybody agree,
this is a linear term, right?
Minus omega, it's a first order, it's a linear term.
The second term, well, it's not a constant, okay?
Sorry, it's not always constant,
it's actually a piecewise constant.
Means sometimes zero, sometimes pi, but this is for range.
All right, so by having this kind of function,
we can say that the overall phase response
is actually a so-called piecewise linear.
In other words, if they have some sudden change
from the, let's say pi, three by zero, right?
But in the entire range, except for that sudden change,
everything is linear, right?
So this is also something we desired.
In the relaxed kind of a concept,
this is also considered as a linear, right?
So by doing so, we can show that the theorem one
will be always true, at least for m equal to three.
All right?
Makes sense?
I'm just showing a very simple example, right?
And the key to do that is by first grouping the term,
applying the symmetric property, group them together,
and form something you can easily represent
and using the polar form, right?
And that's why you can deal with the magnitude
and the phase separately, right?
Now, if you look at the phase response,
which is piecewise linear, right?
Okay, this is the m equal to three case.
Now, m equal to four.
So m equal to four, you will have third order,
order equal to three.
You will have four terms in total.
So the right way to group them together is by
zero order versus third order, right?
So these two terms together,
let b three equal to b zero, right?
So now you can extract the b zero out.
And then the middle pair, right?
Middle pair is here, you extract the b one out.
You do some kind of a common factor extraction,
which is z to power minus three over two.
Now, these are the pairs.
You can actually cancel the imaginary part.
So you can tell that the way I'm doing here
is just to form this so-called compressed conjugate, right?
Because if you extract, so if you swap the z
with e to power minus j omega,
you can tell that every pair in the bracket
are actually compressed conjugate.
Means the phase is exactly the opposite, right?
So by doing so, these two will always cancel
their imaginary part, right?
So the summation of a compressed conjugate
will always be real number, right?
So that's the only way you can form the cosine,
similar for the second term, you'll form two cosine.
Very similar to the previous question.
We can guarantee that these four,
these terms will be always real, right?
So because there's no imaginary,
cosine, cosine is always real.
So let's analyze the phase response inside the second term,
right, which is let's call it HR omega, okay?
So how to analyze HR omega?
Because it's real, so it can be either zero or pi,
depends on the term itself is positive or negative, right?
Because if it's negative, you have to absorb the minus one,
right?
So it's equal to e to the power of minus j pi, right?
So in this case, you can tell that,
well, the theta omega, sorry,
theta r omega is kind of piecewise constant.
And plus the turning front,
this guy has a linear phase, right?
Because a linear function is here.
So together, the entire phase response
will again be the piecewise linear, right?
So it's going to be linear except for the sudden change
from zero to pi, right?
Otherwise it's always a linear.
So now you can tell that at least for m equal to three,
m equal to four,
both of them will guarantee to be the linear phase filter,
right?
In fact, you can easily do five, four, six, right?
Because it's the same way.
You just need to group the similar term together,
form the complex conjugate, extract the real term,
and then tell that the real term will have the phase change,
the other term will always be linear, right?
You can do this perfectly for other kind of orders,
which I won't repeat,
but give you some idea why this is true, all right?
Okay?
Make sense, everyone?
Okay, so now after the proof, right?
Now we pretty much knows why the theorem one is true
for saying that it's linear and how to use the theorem one,
right, to tell whether the filter is linear or not,
right, linear phase.
But theorem one is not the only condition
to end up with a linear phase.
In fact, there's another condition,
which we call in the theorem two,
also can show that a filter is linear phase, okay?
So instead of showing the symmetric property,
you are talking about the opposite,
it's anti-symmetric property, right?
So the only difference is that instead of saying that
the pair of coefficient are equal,
they can be also the opposite, right?
The only difference here is previously,
it was Bm equal to Bm minus one minus M,
but right now it's actually the minus sign here, okay?
If they are the exact opposite,
we call it anti-symmetric, anti-symmetric property, okay?
But it's the same, you just form a polynomial,
you determine the order, you find the first term
and last term, you check are they opposite, right?
If they're opposite, fine, you look at the second pair, right?
If they're also opposite, every pair is opposite,
you can also conclude that this filter
is actually linear phase, all right?
So in this case, you will also end up
with the phase response in the following term,
but you will have a slightly different form
than the condition one, but both of them
are giving you the linear phase kind of a filter, right?
Now I won't prove it, but I'm giving you one example
to apply that, right?
So I'm saying that, well,
let's look at this kind of a transfer function, right?
So this transfer function, right?
What is the order of it?
It's order four, right?
So I should have five terms, right?
Fourth order polynomial got to give you five terms.
Now, how many terms are showing up here?
Four terms, right?
You got zero term, first order term,
but the second order term is somehow missing here, right?
It didn't show up, but it's there, it's zero, right?
We know B two is zero.
I got B three, I got B four, right?
So now I want to form the pairs.
I need to pair up the B zero and the B four, right?
So B zero is one, B four is minus one,
so these two are actually anti-symmetric,
okay, which sounds like the second condition, okay?
Now B one, which is minus two, and B three is actually two.
So minus two, two are exactly opposite.
So I have the second pair, right?
The last pair, okay, this is tricky.
So for this scenario, if I'm going to the condition two,
and I have a middle term, which is the B two, right?
The only number that equal to the negative sign
of the same is equal to zero, right?
You have to make sure the middle number must be zero.
Other than that, for example, if I have a,
let's say, plus z to the power of minus two there,
I'm going to violate my condition two, right?
Only the zero equal to minus zero.
So let's say if you are talking about the fear of two,
and you have a middle term like this,
you need to make sure this guy equal to zero.
Otherwise, you won't have the condition two, right?
This is the special case for fear of two.
Fear of one, you can easily form an equal pair.
Any number equal to itself,
but not every number equal to the opposite of itself.
Only zero does, okay?
So this is actually the special case for condition two,
but this one apparently satisfy the condition two.
So it's going to be a linear phase response, right?
A linear phase filter, okay?
So this shows you that there's another way
to prove or to design a linear phase filter.
So we have two conditions, right?
Symmetric condition or anti-symmetric condition.
And these are the only two condition
that will lead to a linear phase FIR.
In other words, if I say condition one or condition two
becomes a sufficient and necessary condition
for linear phase filter.
So it's like both sides, right?
If I'm telling you that there's a FIR filter
that's a linear phase,
you can always say that it's either condition one
or condition two to be true, all right?
Because that's the only two possible condition
that can give you a linear phase, okay?
So any filter, I mean, any linear phase FIR
will satisfy either condition one or condition two.
So you can treat this as the equivalent condition, right?
To tell the linear phase, all right?
Okay, so I mean, this is actually a general form,
but I really won't go through it
because it's, I think it's a little bit hard,
but you can remember that normally we're talking about
there are four types of linear phase, right?
Depends on whether they are, okay,
k equal to zero means it's symmetric.
k equal to one means it's actually anti-symmetric.
So the general form of the symmetric condition is this,
right?
You can easily find, you write down the symmetric
as minus one to the power of k, right?
k equal to zero is actually equal,
k equal to minus one is the,
sorry, k equal to one equal to negative sign.
But it depends on whether they are symmetric
or anti-symmetric, whether the M is ordered,
even or odd, you have four type of filter,
which are all linear phase, right?
So next time if you heard of like type one,
type two, type three, this is what they mean, right?
It depends on different type of symmetry
and different number of, different order of your polynomial,
right?
So, and okay, so, but basically, I mean,
it's also easy to remember, right?
Type one and type two are both symmetric,
corresponding to the theorem one, right?
Three and four corresponding to a theorem two.
Now, one just says M is even, in other words, N is odd, right?
It means that even number of terms,
odd number of order, right?
Type two is actually the odd number of terms
and even number of order, right?
But basically, I mean, if you want, you can memorize that,
but it's also not hard to memorize, right?
But what I mean is, if you see a question tell you,
it is type one, you must know what they mean, right?
Type one means it's going to be a symmetric property
and also we're talking about the number of terms to be odd,
right?
So M is odd, in other words, N is actually even, right?
So you may have a question like this saying that,
okay, I give you a type one,
if I transfer function and if they say type one,
you have to make sure it's actually theorem one
not theorem two.
If they didn't say anything,
they say it's in your face, that is either one, right?
But they explicitly say type one,
it means you cannot have anti-symmetric property,
it must be symmetric property, right?
So, okay, if they explicitly say M equal to six,
type one, you have to make sure the coefficient
satisfy the type one, sorry, symmetric property.
So in other words, you can group the first term
and the last term together and make them equal, right?
H zero to be equal to H six, all right?
So this is how you can write it.
And if you have this linear face,
kind of property for your future, right?
Due to this symmetric property,
your broad diagram can be simplified, right?
Why?
Because it's simple, you kind of reduce the degree of freedom,
right?
Your choice of the coefficients are not completely free.
So by doing so, you can save half of the multiplier, right?
Because here the H zero can be used for both,
the zero order term, which is going to this branch,
and also the delayed version, right?
The delayed version of the six will be here.
So both of them will be multiplied by H zero.
So H zero are applied twice, right?
For the original signal and the delayed six version.
Similarly, your H one will be used for the delayed one version
and also the delayed five time version, right?
So basically having the linear phase property
on one side you avoid distortion of your signal,
just now we show in the beginning, right?
Nonlinear response has a risk of distortion.
That's the first thing.
The other thing is that in designing the filter,
you also save some of the commutation
because this symmetric property
will save you half of the multiplier, right?
So this is another kind of a benefit
to ensure your filter is linear phase, all right?
Make sense?
So the previous kind of direct form is a general form, right?
No property, they have anything,
but this is the form with the type one symmetry property.
All right, but not every polynomial can be written like this.
Only with your type one symmetric property, all right?
But this is just one way to show it
and here's another possibility like type two, right?
So if it's a type two,
the only difference is length become a eighth length, right?
In other words, you still have the symmetric property
but you will have another length.
In other words, you are going to end up with this term here,
right?
And similarly, you save half of the multiplier.
Instead of eight, you have four multiplier in this case.
All right?
This is the same thing, but just give you some idea, right?
Why the linear phase is like everybody loves the linear phase,
right?
Okay, so just to summarize,
I think normally this is a good table
to remember the four type of a symmetric property, sorry,
four type of a linear phase filter, right?
So type one, symmetric, left is odd,
but basically you can use this to memorize, right?
And I mean, the only way,
the only thing I want you to remember is
you need to know correspondingly, right?
Type one, two, three, four, what do they mean?
In terms of length, in terms of the symmetric property, right?
But it shouldn't be there, they're hard to analyze.
But basically I show you the, you know,
some of the example and why this is true, right?
The only thing you remember is how to apply that, right?
So this is actually the table you probably want to memorize.
I don't know whether they will be provided in the exam,
but it's not very hard to memorize.
So you can actually easily memorize it, right?
Okay, and also here's another table.
I don't think this is actually needed,
but this one shows not only the symmetric,
but also what is the corresponding phase response, right?
But you know, I won't test on this, but it's for information.
You have the corresponding form of the phase response
and also the coefficients, right?
If they are belonging to each of the type
of the linear phase filter, right?
Okay, so I think that's pretty much all I want to cover
for this part, so let's look at this one last example, right?
So basically, okay, this is slightly more challenging,
but you know, it's still relevant to what we learned.
So they're saying that I have a linear phase FIR,
but this FIR can be written as a product
of two kind of filters, right?
You can consider one filter after the other,
and I'm giving you the F1, which is one of the filter, okay?
I give you one of the filter,
exactly as the order two polynomial.
I want you to determine the other filter, F2,
in order to make the overall response to be linear phase.
Okay, so this is like slightly more challenging question
than the one I showed you just now, right?
Which one?
The previous one were like pretty straightforward.
This one is slightly, you need to think about it,
but basically you have to understand, right?
Every time when they say linear phase,
you need to ask yourself, what does the linear phase mean?
Right?
So in this case, what they mean is that the overall product
must have something like a symmetric property, right?
So this is actually the product we were talking about.
To match with this guy, how can I form a product
which are going to be symmetric?
If one of them is given, right?
How can I form another one?
Multiply it together can give you
some kind of symmetric kind of structure.
I mean, there are many ways to form it,
but one way to do it is by using the symmetric of this term.
Right?
So right now I have a number,
I can extract the 2.1 out.
I'm going to have the second order polynomial like this.
I can easily construct a corresponding term,
which is the same term, multiply by e to power of minus two.
So, but these terms, I have to make sure
every term is the complex conjugate.
Remember?
So here's z to power of minus two,
here I have z to power of two.
So it's a complex conjugate of the first second order term.
Now I have a positive second order term, right?
Similarly, here I got z to power of minus one.
I can construct a z, right?
Which is also the complex conjugate
of my original first order term.
So why do I need to construct a complex conjugate?
The reason is to cancel each other, right?
Remember, complex conjugate,
if you multiply the two together,
is going to give you the constant, right?
Because the order cancel each other.
So the only thing left out is the cross term, right?
And the cross term will have the symmetric property,
which are because by having the same coefficient,
I'm going to have the symmetric property.
So all the cross term will be canceled,
and the other term will be the symmetric property.
So I can form some kind of a symmetric property like this,
where this term will be equal to the first term
because of my symmetric property here.
So this one times this one, this one times this one,
both of you give you the two, right?
And similarly, five is like here and here,
this one and this one, which will give you both five
in this term.
So all of the cross term,
or sorry, all of the, how should I say,
corresponding multiply will be canceled.
All of the cross term will survive.
But the cross term, you can always form the symmetric part
because the first term in the first factor multiplied
by the second term will always have a counterpart,
which equal to the second term in the first factor
multiplied by the first term in the second factor.
So that's the only way you can create the symmetric term
that end up with a condition one kind of polynomial here.
So the small trick to play with the complex conjugate.
But the important thing is that you have to understand
what is the objective I'm trying to do here, right?
The objective is to form the final polynomial
to be linear phase.
And that means your polynomial for the final kind of filter
must have the symmetric property, right?
So I know it's a little bit challenging,
but I'm just saying that in the exam,
I may not give you something like very straightforward.
I mean, very straightforward, I already go through them,
but I can be a little bit tricky,
but the key here is to understand what is the objective
when you want to derive something, all right?
So, but think about it,
that won't give you some kind of idea, right?
So what can be the varied version of the basic question
I already covered, all right?
Okay, but I'm with that, I'm actually end with all of this,
how do I say?
Linear phase, block diagram,
and also equivalent expression of the block diagram, right?
Okay, now I want to, okay, how much time I have?
Okay, maybe slightly more than 30 minutes,
I think I can finish this part.
So the other thing I want to,
I mean, actually starting from this week
and continue next week,
I'm going to move on to the so-called filter design, right?
I mean, this is also very straightforward.
We talk about ideal filters,
we talk about what is that ideal frequency response,
but we also mentioned that not all of this ideal filter
can be realizable.
In other words, we also want to care about
how can I really implement some filters?
If not the same as my design,
how can I make the actual implementation
to be as close as possible to my design, right?
So this is normally referred as digital filter design.
In other words, I need to design a realizable filter,
in other words, realizable transfer function
for a given kind of specification.
So the idea is that my theory give me my specification.
I want to have a low pass filter, maybe,
but I want to find the corresponding
realizable transfer function
to be enough approximating my specification.
All right, so this is actually what we want to do.
And apparently we have two kind of filters.
There's FIR, this is IR.
So, you know, our focus will be mainly on FIR, to be honest.
And we're going to look at how the design process will be,
right, so for example, we need to derive the transfer function
to be approximating enough of the intended specification.
And what is objective, right?
So when we say approximate,
we need to talk about minimizing some errors.
So what exactly is the quantity we want to minimize
when we do design?
So these will be some problems we're going to study,
not complete by this week, but continue next week, all right?
But this week, we're going to, let's say,
focus about the magnitude approximation
of an FIR filter first.
Okay, so first, forget about IR.
So IR, I'm not going to talk about for my part, all right?
So FIR only.
The second thing is forget about the phase first.
Let's look at the magnitude first, all right?
So how can I approximate the specified magnitude response
with a feasible filter design, right?
This will be the problem we're going to talk about first.
So let's look at this low pass filter as example, right?
We see that there are many, many kind of filters,
there's low pass, high pass, band pass,
but let's look at the low pass filter as example, right?
So we say that for ideal low pass filter,
normally you will have the form like this red line here,
right?
Very sharp transition, ideally no transition period,
suddenly going from the pass band to the stop band, right?
This will be your ideal low pass filter.
So you can consider this ideal low pass filter
as the specification, means that this is the objective
you're trying to achieve, right?
The ideal design.
And also this is your so-called target magnitude response, right?
So this is actually what indicated as the design objective,
but in practice, you won't get this,
you won't get the red line here.
You will have the practical response,
kind of frequency response,
indicated as the black line like this, all right?
So the entire objective of design
is to make this black line to be approximately enough
the red lines, right?
In other words, you want to make the error
between the black line and the red line
as small as possible, right?
But of course, you have to give all of this constraint
you have in a practical design.
So this is actually the objective.
So, but just now we said that you won't really
have the perfect red line,
so you are going to fight against all of this
non-ideal kind of phenomenon.
So what are the non-ideal for phenomenon
we are talking about, right?
Mainly there are two, sorry,
there are actually three to be specific.
The first one is the so-called repose in the pass band, right?
So what is the repose in the pass band?
You will have some fluctuations here,
not always centered at one,
but a value is kind of alternating
between one plus sigma p and one minus sigma p.
So you are going to minimize the variance in the pass band,
right?
This is actually one of the first the term you want to minimize.
The second term is actually the transition band here.
So ideally the transition band will be zero
because you suddenly transit from the pass band
to the stop band.
But in practice, the transition band will be not zero
and normally it's actually specified by the range
between the omega p and omega s.
So omega p is the end of the pass band.
The omega s is the start of the stop band, right?
The distance between them is actually the transition band.
All right?
So last but not least,
we also have some repose in the stop band, right?
We also want to minimize the repose here.
So all of these quantities that we want to minimize
are something as the objective of our,
of our design kind of a procedure, right?
So let's look at them one by one, right?
The first one is the pass band.
So the pass band is defined between zero and omega t, right?
So this is actually the pass band range.
All right?
Remember, this is the low pass filter.
So the low pass filter will always be pass band
centered as zero, all right?
So this omega p will define how large is the pass band.
So basically within the range,
it's going to be the pass band.
And the magnitude of the response will be not exactly one,
but approximately equal to one.
Raise the arrow plus or minus this small sigma p, right?
And basically your pass band magnitude response
will be bounded by this range.
So we want to make sure this bound
is actually as small as possible, right?
So this is actually the first kind of non-idealness
we're talking about.
The second one is so-called the pass band,
sorry, the stop band.
The stop band is defined between the omega s and the pi.
Remember, we normally only look at the zero to pi
because first, right, this is actually digital filter.
So the period is always two pi, right?
And we're talking about the symmetric kind of response.
So the negative half will be the same as the positive half.
So we only look at zero to pi, right?
So the stop band will be completely determined
by this range.
And again, there will be some repo
and the stop band will not exactly equal to zero,
but approximately zero.
And everywhere will also be bounded
by the so-called the peak repo in the stop band.
So basically for any practical design,
you will need these four parameters
to specify how ideal or how practical
your design filter is.
So you will keep seeing these four parameters
in the filter design kind of questions.
But you need to know what are the four parameters here, right?
So omega p specify the end of the pass band.
Omega s is the start of the stop band.
All of these are H frequency called, all right?
Repo are two, p is for the peak repo,
s is for the stop band repo.
Sorry, it's a piece for the pass band repo, right?
So all of these two are the quantity of the variance
in the stop band and the pass band correspondingly.
All right?
And of course, the transition band
will be the difference between the two H frequency, right?
That will also be something you want to minimize.
All right?
So this is the filter specification, okay?
So, you know, in practice,
where we're going to have, like I just explained, right?
In practice, your so-called DTFT response
will always be a periodic function.
And ideally, right,
we're talking about a real coefficient filter.
So in other words, we're talking about the filter
are originally real.
So after DTFT, you're going to have an even function
of the omega.
Remember, you do a DTFT of the real function.
You're going to have the even symmetric kind of functions,
right?
In other words, you know, every point here
will be the same as two pi minus the magnitude, right?
Okay?
In this case, that's why normally,
even though we know that function is actually
two pi periodic, we only look at the range of zero to two pi
because pi to two pi will be exactly the reflect
of the first kind of a first half, right?
So no point to analyze that, right?
So that's why every time when you look at the frequency
response of a real coefficient filter,
they only show you zero to pi
because all the information is contained there, all right?
So that's why you see that all of the specifications
are within the zero to pi range.
But let's be clear.
This only applied to real coefficient filter.
And for this course, it will only be real coefficient.
But for a complex coefficient filter,
which may happen sometime, you do need a zero to two pi range
because it's not even symmetric, all right?
Okay?
All right, so the specification,
just now we're talking about,
it's usually given in the term of the loss function.
In other words, when you design that,
you need to make sure this loss function
is somehow minimized, right?
And usually the loss function is represented
in the dB term, right?
The decibel term.
What is decibel?
You take the log function of it
and then you do minus two, 20, right?
That one will give you the dB scale
rather than the linear scale.
It just changes of scale, right?
But that's the usual way people quantify, for example,
the amount of repose, amount of energy loss, right?
So in this case, usually, for example,
the peak passband repo will be represented
in the form of dB, right?
And also the minimum stop attenuation
will also be represented in terms of dB, right?
So next time if you see the dB as the unit,
you should know what it really means.
It kind of converts the linear scale
into minus 20 times log scale, all right?
So the magnitude to specification
may be alternatively, sometimes giving you
a normalized form or if it's normalized, right?
The passband will always be one in this case, right?
But if it's not normalized, the passband may not be one.
It can be something larger, right?
But very likely, if they give you a normalized form,
you can always assume that the passband is centered at one,
all right?
So this is normalized kind of a magnitude response, OK?
Some of the other things you need to be careful are,
for example, the magnitude, the maximum value of the magnitude
in the passband is assigned to be unity, right?
In other words, if this is one, if you take the log of one,
you always get a zero, right?
So in other words, kind of a passband is actually
starting from zero dB.
That's actually where you only have one response, right?
This is actually why people use dB,
because dB will always put one into zero,
means no game and no loss, right?
This is really the case.
And also, one over square root of one plus epsilon square
is actually the maximum passband deviation given
by the minimum value of the magnitude in the passband, right?
So I won't repeat this, but basically these
are some of the specifications that say that sometimes they
will represent, for example, a tenuation gain in terms of dB.
So you need to be able to tell the difference between two,
right?
How to convert from linear square, linear scale to the dB scale.
It's just like a conversion.
It shouldn't be too kind of specific, right?
What else are we talking about here?
So normalized band age frequency are needed to compute it.
OK, same thing.
The frequency also need to compute it
from a specification in the hertz, right?
So we talk about that when you represent the frequency,
you can represent it in terms of radians, or maybe the hertz.
How to convert the two, you should do 2 pi f, right?
That's how you can convert the two.
But if they are talking about the frequency in terms of hertz,
and you must do 2 pi f to convert between hertz
and also the radians, right?
That's how you can unify the, how should I say, the units,
right?
So this is one example.
If you are given, for example, the stopband color frequency
at 7 kHz, passband at 3.
So you can convert into the radius kind of units
by simply times 2 pi with it, and divided
by the kind of a sampling frequency, which is actually
25 Hz, right?
So this is something we presented using the omega
rather than the hertz, right?
So there's some kind of a unit conversion.
You must be careful about it, right?
So what else do I have?
Sorry, I just want to see how many slides I have.
I'm reaching, OK, almost here, almost here.
This is the last slide I have, OK.
Because I still have some slides about the frequency, sorry,
about the windowing method.
All right, I think I can finish overnight.
That's great.
OK, so like I mentioned, we're talking about FIR in this course.
So very likely the starting point of the design
will be the transfer function, which we just talked about.
And the transfer function can be represented
as a polynomial in the Z-transform domain.
And usually, we have to make sure that this n is as small
as possible, right?
So in other words, we will not handle a very high order
polynomial in most of the cases.
Another thing I really explained is that the linear phase
is always desired.
So in other words, most likely when
we talk about the field design, we
will use linear phase filter.
So very likely you will apply the symmetry property
or anti-symmetric property to really reduce
the coefficients by almost half, right?
This is some of the common scenarios
you can foresee in the field design.
So like I mentioned, we are focused on FIR,
but you need to know the advantages
and these advantages of FIR, right?
Apparently, the advantages that FIR
will give you simpler kind of design.
And you can easily design for linear phase, which we just
talked about, right?
Two properties, symmetric, anti-symmetric.
And always, because FIR, you will always
get a constant denominator.
So FIR will always be stable.
Makes sense?
Because just how we say that the way you determine
is stable or not is by looking at the poles, right?
The poles are the roots for the denominator.
FIR will have denominator always equal to 1.
So in other ways, you got no poles.
So in other words, you will not have any pole
outside the unit circle.
So FIR is always a stable filter, right?
So this is another properties that you don't have to check.
It's always stable.
But of course, FIR will also have something not perfect.
Otherwise, nobody care about IR, right?
So the first thing is that if you
want to design some specific kind of filter,
comparing to IR, if you stick to FIR,
usually the cause is that you have to go for higher order,
right?
So you have, equivalently, comparing
FIR and IR to achieve something similar.
FIR normally force you to go to higher order,
whereas IR can sometimes afford a smaller order, right?
So that is actually the reason that FIR is usually,
to do the similar performance.
And as IR, it's going to give you a higher
computational complexity.
Why?
Because higher order means more number of multiplier,
more number of addition, and more number of time delay.
So that's something you have to pay for the ease of the design.
This is actually the trade-off between the two.
OK.
So I think here I lay some kind of foundation
for filter design.
We talk about the specification.
We talk about how to interpret the design from the FIR
perspective.
So today we're going to look at the one specific method
for designing a kind of a practical filter, right?
Which is pretty much the easiest possible method I can think
about.
It's the windowing method.
I'm not going to complete today, but next week we're
going to continue, right?
But first, what is this kind of design
for kind of FIR, right?
So FIR, usually we need to develop a direct approximation
of the specific magnitude of response.
In other words, if I give you a, let's say, ideal low-pass
filter, I want to use my FIR to approximate that.
And also I wish to have this additional linear phase property.
But FIR will only have up to n order of the polynomial, right?
So in other words, I will have a limited amount of response
functions in the entire kind of domain, right?
But the ideal filter will not be that, right?
We talk about this.
If you have ideal low-pass filter,
you're going to end up with a zinc function.
And the zinc function will have infinitely many impulse
response.
So in this case, you will not have the exact ideal kind of
a low-pass filter by using FIR.
So that's actually why we have to do something
onto the original low-pass filter to enable
an FIR to approximate that, right?
So the commonly used approach are many.
I mean, there are many ways you can do it.
There's a windowing method.
There's frequency sampling approach.
There's also like your computer-aided or computer-based
optimization method.
So we're going to look at the windowing method only
for this course, all right?
But you should be aware that there are other methods, which
I'm going to give you some slides, but I'm not going to
test on the other method.
Windowing method is the only method.
I may ask you in the exam, but you must be aware that this
is not the only method to design a FIR filter.
So now, OK, so I will provide some detail for the other,
but they will be put separately as the slides.
Won't be tested.
So only here will be tested.
So OK, what is windowing approach?
It's actually very simple.
We say that last time, we say that let's take this ideal
low-pass filter as an example.
Ideal filter means you have a very sharp transition from
the stopband to the passband.
And if you look at the corresponding time domain
response, impulse response, you're going to have a zinc
function.
You can easily do an inverse.
What is that?
Inverse, maybe DTFT to get my time domain response.
And this kind of function can tell that it's actually
infinitely long.
You have to have infinitely many response to
approximate that.
Apparently, this contradicts the FIR assumption.
FIR means finite length, finite length kind of a
response function.
So in this case, you have to do something.
And plus, this function is apparently non-causal.
Because you have some value in the future.
You cannot have that because you cannot relate your output to
a future input.
So this is another issue making them non-realistic.
So our objective becomes to find a finite duration kind of
an impulse response.
Let's say we have nth order.
In other words, your impulse response can have at most
n plus 1 kind of length.
Whereas these guys, DTFT or these guys, Spectrum, must be
good enough to approximate the ideal case.
OK, let me just repeat.
So we started by having this ideal filter.
This is the ideal filter.
Maybe I used the pointer.
This is my ideal filter, my ideal low pass filter.
I want to approximate that as much as possible.
But unfortunately, I can only use an FIR to do it.
So now I want to find the best FIR such that the spectrum of
my FIR become as close as possible to my objective.
So this is the objective of the design.
Let's think about what we're trying to achieve first.
This is what we're trying to achieve.
OK, now this is just some rough description.
But how can I quantify it?
When I say I make them approximate the same, I
have to quantify the difference.
In other words, I want to minimize the error.
So how to quantify the error?
In fact, you can easily quantify the error in the
frequency or time domain.
You only need to do a difference.
You do subtraction between the ideal version and your
design version.
You do the subtraction.
You look at energy.
That's going to give you the error.
You just need to minimize the energy of the difference.
This is actually the objective we're trying to do.
So it's going to be very simple.
Let's say that the HD is the design spectrum.
HT stands for, let's say, the ideal spectrum.
Oh, sorry.
HT is the design.
Let's call this HT is the practical FIR.
Spectrum of the FIR.
HT is the objective spectrum.
In other words, HT is this guy.
HT is this guy.
And HT is the DTFT of our FIR.
So the error we're trying to minimize is nothing but the
difference of the two integrated over the entire
2 pi range.
Because if they are the same, you've got zero.
If they are not the same, the smaller the better.
The larger the worse.
This is how you can quantify the difference.
And we see that, well, our design FIR will have finite
term.
In other words, I only consider the term, let's say, up to
n, m equal to n divided by 2.
So I can use my Possible theory.
I don't know how many of you know the Possible theory.
It means the energy difference in the time domain can be
related to the energy difference in the frequency domain.
So what I want to minimize, which is the integral square
error, can be represented as the difference in the time
domain.
So I really want to approximate that in the frequency
But Possible theory give me the equivalent expression that
the difference of the two, same pair, in the time domain is
also equal to the error, mean square error.
So I can actually look at the impulse response of my
objective ideal filter and my FIR, take the difference and
sum them up in the square way.
And this is something I want to minimize.
Make sense?
OK, so first of all, anyone doesn't know what is
Possible theory?
Have you learned this?
I mean, it's just something covering your basic signal
processing.
So the Possible theory says that, let's say two filters,
or maybe two signal even, you take the difference and
consider energy in the spectrum.
It's going to be equal as you take the difference and the
energy in the time domain.
Because these two are related by some orthogonal transform,
like DTFT, or maybe like a CTFT.
So the transform preserves the norm such that the energy
difference in the spectrum will be the same as the energy
difference in the time domain.
So why I'm doing this?
Because if I'm relating the difference in the time domain,
I can separate the error here.
Because in front, there's a summation, all the way from
minus infinity to infinity.
I can separate the summation into the difference within
what I have.
Because my FIR will be resized in this n range.
I can say, well, I consider the difference within the minus
m to m range.
And those outside the range, I separate the error into two
parts.
Why?
Because what I have in FIR, the only thing I can
manipulate is the one within the range.
Because FIR will have finite number of response only
within the range.
Within the range, I can design whatever I like.
I can adjust my impulse response, whatever I like.
But only within the finite amount of the response.
Beyond that, nothing I can do.
I have to leave them zero.
So this part of error is something I cannot avoid.
They are always there.
It depends on the original signal, the target signal.
But what I can try to do here is to make this one minimized.
Ideally, zero.
But if not zero, minimize.
So if I follow this kind of principle, the best way I can
do is say, hey, within this range, I make my design to be
exactly same as the objective.
Make sense?
So I have a target.
I have a target.
For example, if this is my target function, original is a
zinc function.
It's finite infinity long.
But I only have a finite length response function, impulse
response.
But the order of non-zeros is within the minus m to m.
So what I can try to do is make sure those within this
range are exactly the same as my objective.
By doing so, the red term here will be killed.
It's going to be zero.
All right.
But outside the range, those beyond minus m and plus m, I
have nothing I can do.
Just leave that.
And those are the errors coming from the original desired
objective.
If they are large, I'm going to have a large error.
If they are small, I'm going to have a small error.
But whatever I do for my FIR, I cannot help for those
outside the range.
OK?
Make sense?
So by doing so, these indicate that the best approximation
to the ideal response is to make sure that within here is
exact match.
In other words, how can I come up with FIR is nothing but
taking the original waveform, the black line here.
I think a truncation.
I just truncated.
Beyond m, I just make them zero.
Within the m, I'm just keeping them the same.
Right?
So this is literally a truncation function I'm applying.
So I'm doing a truncation function over the original, what
is that, HD.
Right?
And after truncation, that's going to be my HT.
OK?
So this is why windowing method makes sense, because windowing
method is nothing but truncation.
Right?
Windowing literally means truncation.
You have a window.
You keep whatever within the window.
Outside the window, you don't care.
Right?
So this is what the windowing method means.
So then mathematically, I'm just trying to give you some
intuition why the windowing method makes sense.
So you want to make sure all the coefficients within the
window are the same.
Outside the window, I have nothing to do.
I just don't care.
Right?
So then exactly what the windowing method means is this.
I will start with the ideal HD.
So HD is the ideal filter.
I take that into the time domain.
I do the IDTFT into the time domain.
Then starting from there, I'm imposing a windowing function.
So this windowing function will be finite length, just like
FIR.
It's going to be finite length.
Let's say this guy has m minus 1 length.
So I'm going to have this function only non-zero within
n equal to 0, all the way to n equal to m minus 1.
It's called a windowing function.
Right?
Window function means non-zero within the window and 0
elsewhere.
So after having this windowing function, I'm going to
multiply my original time domain response point by point
with my windowing function.
It's like you have two functions.
Originally, for example, you have a zinc function like
this.
I multiply by a window.
Within the window, I'm going to multiply the non-zero
response.
Outside the window, I'm just zero out the rest.
So after that, this becomes my design, FIR.
It's a windowed version of the original infinite long time
domain response.
And that's going to be the FIR using the
windowing method.
Or if not, let me know which part doesn't make sense.
I can try to explain.
All right, so if you don't ask, I assume you'll know it.
But here's something I want to mention is this.
This window function, WN, they have many choices.
It's not the only choice.
So basically, this window function can have different
window function.
But all of them will have this property that only non-zero
within this range and 0 elsewhere.
But whether the non-zero part are they constant, are they
certain shape, it depends.
They have many choices.
So next week, we're going to look at what is the
phenomenon by choosing different windowing functions.
But it's all windowing functions, a different kind of
windowing function.
And also, window method can be used to design basically any
type of digital filter, as long as this guy is given.
So you have to be given a very specific objective.
In other words, if you don't tell me the ideal filter, I
cannot do windowing function.
If you give me this, I can use the window function to deal
with any given kind of ideal digital filter.
So this is a must condition.
So like I said, there are many choices of window functions.
So today, let's just look at one.
So next week, we're going to look at all the possible
choices.
But today, the simple window function can be, let's look
at this example.
So suppose I give you a target, let's say, ideal low
pass filter.
So ideal pass filter will be 0 if it's beyond the pass band.
Within the pass band, I'm giving you some kind of a
complex number.
But this number will have some phase term.
You can tell this is a linear phase.
This phase term, even though there's a phase, it's a
linear.
And the magnitude is 1.
So this is my target.
This is my ideal low pass filter.
Apparently, if you do an inverse DTFT, you have a Zinc
function.
So for example, if you directly do a DTFT of this guy, you
can get the ideal time domain response, which is
something like this.
And if you plot it, you're going to have a Zinc function,
but discretized version.
Depends on your M. Your M is 12.
This is your time domain response.
If it's 13, this is your time domain response.
So you cannot use that as direct as FIR, because it's
infinitely long.
Now, how to do windowing function?
We have to first use a window function.
The simplest possible windowing function is a
rectangular window, which is 1 within the range of 0 to M
minus 1 and 0 elsewhere.
So it's like exactly a rectangular function.
So this is actually how you plot it.
This is the plot of the window function.
So when you determine the objective ideal filter and
then your windowing function, the only thing you do is
multiply the two together in the time domain.
In other words, multiply this guy with this guy in the time
domain point by point.
So by doing so, all of the coefficient within this range
will survive.
All of the response outside the range will be killed.
But it's 0 out.
So by doing so, if I'm going to, for example, multiply, let's
see, where's the multiplication?
Oh, here.
So the unit impulse response of the FIR designed with such a
window will be your original HTN, which is this guy.
Multiply by your window function.
So it's going to be point by point multiplication.
That's how you get your FIR.
So after that, you can tell that now your HTN, which is
after windowing method, will also have the symmetric
property.
Sorry.
No, no, no, not yet.
So you're going to make sure that your BM equal to the
corresponding ideal coefficient only within the
range, 0 to m minus 1.
Such that you can now form the FIR with only the first
m terms.
So this one will give you a m minus 1 order
polynomial like this.
So this is going to be FIR, but not ideally as the original
low pass filter.
But that's a good enough one, where is the
windowing method.
And note that this guy, HTN, originally is a symmetric.
Remember, we say the linear phase.
So it's going to be symmetric.
The FIR filter after a windowing method is still a
linear phase.
But with a slope slightly changed, there's a minus sign
front, which is exactly one of the characteristics you
desire by that.
So in other words, windowing method, if you design a
window in the center way, you can preserve the linear phase
property.
Going from originally the target that you are trying to
approximate, you can preserve that property by using the
windowing method, which is something we like.
But the magnitude response, however, will be different,
of course, because we truncate all of the zeros
outside the bound.
So you won't get the same response, which is something
you have to pay.
But at least you kind of maintain the linear phase
property, which is something we like.
So after windowing, this will be something you actually got.
So it's not ideal low pass filter, everyone can tell,
because first you have this kind of a very slow transition.
And then we have this kind of repo.
Remember, this is actually the repo in the stop band.
You have some repo in the pass band.
So basically, you won't get the same kind of low pass
filter, but it's still a low pass filter, with this
approximation.
And this one shows you two versions.
One is the 61 as the M. The other one is 101.
So you can see that with the amount of M increases,
actually you can suppress the repo.
So this repo becomes smaller than the first version.
So basically, there's a trade-off between the
approximation quality and the computational complexity.
You pay the price for having more higher order.
You can make the approximation better.
So this is actually one of the trade-off you can tell.
And also, you can also tell that what is the first
side loop.
So the first side loop here, by increasing the M, you are
also decreasing the quantity here.
So you are making them more like the stop band, rather
than the first one.
So this is something kind of practically happened as the
phenomenon after applying the windowing method.
But just one example.
I mean, give you some idea of how the windowing method can
work on that.
But like I mentioned, windowing method depends on the
window you choose.
The phenomenon and also the trade-off will be different.
So today, we only look at one of the function, rectangular
window.
Next week, we're going to introduce two more windows.
So we're going to compare what's the pro and cons for
every window.
So no window is perfect, but you need to know what is the
advantage of certain window.
Depends on your specification.
You need to make the right choice.
This is what we want to cover.
But I will end here, and it's nice, so you can go for bus.
But before that, a quick summary.
So what we are talking about today, we started by talking
about what left out last week.
We go through the z-transform.
We know that frequency response and difference equation,
these are the representation you need to know for filter.
And we talk about how we can do the direct form of the block
diagram.
We understand what is the filter specification.
We say that there's two h-frequency, omega s, omega p,
two repose, stop band, pass band.
These are something we have to keep in mind when you do
filter design.
So we also understand the effect of this one will be
covered next week.
But the effect of windows and also how to estimate the
complexity, how to trade off between complexity and the
quality of approximation.
So this course will cover, this might probably cover FIR
only.
So you can assume that all of this filter design will be
just FIR for my part.
But profiting will go to IRR in the second part.
All right, so that's all for today.
And I hope I end in time.
So next week, I'll come back to look at more for the filter
design and multirate.
And also next week, there's a big homework.
So homework will be announced by next week.
And you can start to do something, but you will see
some questions which need future knowledge, like the week
after next week.
So don't be worried if you see something not very
familiar ways.
You can start doing those you already learned.
But the due date for homework will be the end of the
recess.
So you have four weeks to do it.
So don't worry about it.
All right?
Thank you.
That's all for today.
So any questions before I leave?
All right?
No questions asked?
OK.
So now I'm going to close the slides.
All right?
Thank you.