chapter, so the quiz will be only on the first two chapters, and for the part two, not the
Pro Woon Byung's part, which you already finished the assignment. Okay, so I hope this is clear
to you. I will also make an announcement later, maybe next week or so, to remind you, or maybe
tomorrow after the class. Any questions so far? I think we start this part two from last week,
although I did a little bit background on Dealing Week 1, and then continue from last week. So yeah,
so this part is quite different from the part one, where you already finished. It required,
of course, some knowledge from the part one, and some others, related ones, such as probability,
random process, and some matrix, algebraic matrix theory, which we will introduce for the mainly
for chapter three. The second chapter, there are also some, but maybe not very heavy, and also some
complex numbers. So maybe, okay, so come back to this later. So last week, before I left, I asked you
to try to figure out how to do these exercises, which is quite useful, because it links power,
density, spectrum, and the AR, which is a weekly stationary AR process, and also filters, and
different equations, and so on. So any of you finish, and you would like to, perhaps, you want
to give your solution here. Sometimes I encourage students, you know, come up to the stage to do it.
Also, now the bigger class size is not so easy. We do that for tutorial or small class size. But
anyway, it will be good to try. Any volunteer, any student, going through these several steps,
as you can see here. No? Okay, so maybe, let me try to explain it here. So this may also serve as
review or summary of what you should learn, and also important to take notes. So let's start with
reviewing, say, jet planes. I think you, you see here? You already learned, you know, like,
transfer functions, jet transforms. So in the jet plane, which is complex, you will have a lower part,
okay? Of course, usually you need to write zero, and imaginary part, all right? So this is very
important to link jet transform, you know, transfer functions and the Fourier transform,
which we also need here for the power density spectrum, like you can see here. So you see here,
if you draw so-called unit circles, you know, in the jet plane, of course, this is minus one,
this is one, and this is j, also 90 degrees. So this will be minus j. So this is more like the
year two signaling systems, you know, like contents. So I always emphasize you should
have a good understanding of this. And then, what happens if j is the whole complex plane?
If I let z equal to e to the power j omega, of course, this j is what you know, the
minus one, take the square root, and that's here. So this is complex.
So these are very basic maps here. Sometimes we also do it by 2 pi f. This is the angular
frequency, this is the frequency in hertz, and it will be continuous because in the complex plane
you go by one circle, it's 2 pi, 360 degrees. So we call this unit circle.
So the unit circle is here, also here. If you draw, it will be here. Then you use this.
So you all know in the transport function and so on, we have edge to the edge of jet.
And in, normally we represent it by rational functions, which is, say,
it's b of j plus a of j. And I think this is very well known, like IR filters, which
I think part one is focused more on FIR filters, but you should already learn that maybe in DSP
or in some other courses. I need to emphasize both IR filter and FIR filters are quite important in
in this part two. Also, probably in part one, he may spend more time on
FIR filter, which is somewhat easier. But in this part two, I think you need to get used to
rational functions, which is like corresponding to IR filter. So if you all have the transport
functions, then you want to link to Fourier transform, or we call that frequency response,
depending on you're talking about a signal. You know, signals, we normally say you take the
Fourier transform, but if you are referring to the linear time invariant system, you see,
such as you have the input-output relationship, so you can have edge of jet, or you may also call
that as H e to the power j omega, you see. So that's the input, can be time domain, can be
in frequency domain, or can be in the jet domain. So these are all very important
relationships, and you should have a good understanding of that. Typically,
although we also need to pay attention, although we call that edge of jet, but if you write down,
we are talking about causal filters, then we will write it as jet to the power of negative power,
you see. So don't get confused, jet corresponding, if you write it as a rational function,
it will be a function of jet to the negative power. So say if you have higher order, you will
be a to jet to the power of two, and so on, and then for b, normally this is normalized,
but for b, we may just starting from the zero constant b one j minus one, and so on.
Okay, so these are the notations, because for,
when you talk about, you know, real world signals, normally we will be talking about
filters, causal filter is your base on past sample to filter the current value or predict
future value, and that will be the main topic which we are going to talk about,
linear prediction filter. Okay, so get it clear here, and then what's next? So
try to provide some important background before we tackle that question. Okay, so
let's see, after that we will have, now if you remember earlier, we have h of j equal to
b, b is for the numerator, so we have this, and then if you substitute
z into the unit circle, you will get the frequency response, which is like
like that. So that means in this case, we are not looking at the whole complex variable of z,
so this is more like if you are talking about the input is sideways, and then, you know,
you use Fourier analysis, and then the output also sideways, goes through a linear system,
you go through this frequency response, so you have this, okay, and this is what you get here.
Now, since you put this complex, you know, j is, as I already say, is a complex,
in general, complex j number here, so then you may talk about if you are going back to the DSP,
not the advanced DSP here, you may talk about, you know, amplitude and phase response, so I think
phase for now, you don't really care too much either way, talk about amplitude, because that's
very important, you will see which component you have the more dominant, higher value, you see,
then this is any complex number, you see, polar form, you take the magnitude, okay, then you'll be
taking the absolute value, and then taking absolute value, sometimes the operation is not
very easy to manipulate, so you can also take the amplitude and then raise the power of two,
so this is, in this case, is very interesting, you can write just as product of, say, I have,
of course, here I have to make the assumption, the filter coefficient a lower coefficient,
okay, so that's always being
assumed here, because when you build a circuit or algorithm, normally we will use a lower
coefficient, but sometimes you may consider complex coefficient, which is probably only
mathematically interesting. Assume you have lower coefficient, then what you can have the
relationship is, instead of take absolute value raise power two, you can just simply
multiply, you see, I have an edge to the power e j omega, if you put that in, and multiply by
e to the power minus j
j omega, so this is, you see, the same filter coefficient are the same except the variable,
you have one is e to the power j omega, while the other is a complex conjugate, you see,
because this is a pure complex number, then you can also write this way, you can write like
e to the power j omega, multiply by this same function, you see, so you be careful,
one is you have the negative part, now I write the same one, but if I take the complex conjugate
operation, it will be the same, so these are very basic from, you know, like complex number
and so on, and as I emphasize, you will be assuming lower coefficient, okay, so what's the
implication of here, you need to just give a quick summarize, if I start from say h of j,
then if you take the, evaluate along the unit circle, you will get
frequency response, so that's
an easy one, and then now if I give you this,
you see, if you write as the frequency response, but you have expression of power of two,
so how are we going to get back the original function of the linear time invariant system,
so what you do here is you can first of course you write this as a function of e to the power
j omega, and then so what you get is you can get as a product of this, so from this absolute value
and raise the power of two, you can get that, so the way to do is like the reverse is I let
you identify the e to the power j omega, and then after that I just make a variable change,
you see, from e to the power j omega go to j, and if you have the power of minus j omega,
then you will just do it to the power minus one, because the corresponding is in,
because in j is a complex variable, you can invert the j, but you're not taking the conjugate,
conjugate is you will be referring to the e to the power j omega, okay, so therefore with all this
you know background, what can we do for this XIG, so you see here this one is given,
giving this form, so you see here we give the power density spectrum, when we talk about power
density spectrum, we will be right in the frequency domain, say this is
omega, this is a function, so we simply
like simplify this, it will be the same here, because like you can see here in the
expression, so we see it as a function of this e to the power j omega, sometimes we also call
if you replay this into j, you see, like what we already done early, you see, by
writing this way, sometimes we also call this product in the j domain also a power density
spectrum, also it's not a regular power density spectrum, it's only referred to frequency,
so sometimes we may say this is the power density spectrum in j domain, because from one you can get
to the other, like what we see in these XIGs, okay, so therefore with all this
preparation for these XIGs, you can see here from the given one
omega here, you can rewrite it into this, you see, so remember we are given the absolute value
raised power of two, so what you can write here, instead of absolute value raised power of two,
you can write it as one minus e to the power minus j omega,
and you'll be the same, you can, so you can verify by yourself by expanding it, you see, here
to the power minus two omega, so this is the one, you see, the given one, instead of taking absolute
value with power two, you just simply write without absolute value, but then you have to multiply by
the other factor in the denominator also, so maybe I explain using this page, so it will be
continuing this way, it will be just one minus e to the power j omega, okay, and then plus, you see
all the other coefficients are the same, except only the whatever power you see, one factor is all the
minus j omega, the other will be j positive, okay, j to the power two omega, so here you don't need
you don't need to take the absolute value, because you take absolute value raised power
two is the same as you explained that, and then as a product, so therefore based on what we
analysis here, you can from here to get the corresponding
so-called power spectrum density in the Z domain, in this way by just simply
now you get the product of H of Z and H of Z to the power minus one, so this is what you can
you see you can do, and then where is this H of Z, you see H of Z is the one corresponding to
corresponding to the e to the power minus j omega, so therefore our H of Z in this case it will be
one over one minus z to the power minus one, and then plus 0.5 z to the power minus two, okay,
and then if you want to verify the filter is a stable one, you have to get the poles, you see,
this is second order, so I'm sure you know how to get the rules of second order
equation polynomial, okay, so this is how your gate, so this is our LTI is linear and also
stable, you can you can verify, so this is a function, you see, if you look at that,
and then from here, you know, here we are trying to get the different equation because this
filter is an opposed filter, so I assume you also know how to get from this
input-output relationship, because this, you see, as I already said, this is the ratio of the
output that comes from first input, so therefore our corresponding difference equation in the time
domain, it will be give you like yn, if you use yn or perhaps I think we use w here, so maybe
I can write, is it not to confuse, it will be x of z versus w of z, because w normally
is like white noise because we use omega w, okay, so therefore the in this case input is w,
like the wn, where output is xn, so with the input-output, you have to write it
clearly, okay, so in that case, how from this, it should be very easy, you can write the
corresponding difference equation, since xn here is the output, so our xn is,
this is a causal filter, it only depends on the pass value, and then minus 0.5, so
n minus 2, because you see here, z to the power minus 2, I mean your delay, delay two sample,
and then finally in the numerator here, corresponding to the input, so in this case,
the filter doesn't have any zero, so the numerator is one, so corresponding to
wn, okay, so this is what our sub-question A, determining the difference equation for
generating this AR process when the excitation is white noise, okay, so you can see here,
because lastly we also talked about the innovation and representation, so innovation,
so you see here, this is the random process related to filter, related to white noise, and
the description, you can also use the proper difference equation, which you learned before,
except in the past, you always assume, you see when I talk about filter, you assume the input is
a proper unit state function or impulse function, you go through a system, you generate another
deterministic function, or sometimes even input is a side way, you go through a system, generate
another side way, but here we are trying to lean into the random signal, so random signal,
the input will be like white noise, you go through a system, you will generate this AR process, okay,
so it's quite, quite related to what you learned before, except the nature of the input signal
and the output change, but the system in the middle, except it will not change, you see here,
so this is still the same as what you learned before, so finally the second sub-question is
determine the system function for the white turning filter, so white turning filter is the
reverse, so now we have the output which is x of n, now if we want to generate
generally white noise, how are we going to build another filter to go back,
actually it's very easy in this case, once you get this H of z, what you do is just take one
over H of z right here, it's an inverse filter, always the other round, and then from the input
output relationship you can also see here, I guess, yeah, if this is the ratio, you want the
reverse, you see, the input become output, output become input, of course the filter you just take
the, you know, take the inverse, so in that case very easy our inverse filter, one over H of z
it will be just equal to, you know, this is all poles, then you will become a IR filter,
okay, then simply you just write it down as one minus plus 0.5 z to the power minus two,
okay, so this is also an IR filter because you have all poles IR filter, your inverse will be
the numerator here is one, so you become the denominator, the denominator one is the same as
you're not dividing anything, okay, so this xij is at the end of the chapter one, somewhat
link what you learned so far, although not all, but at least several concepts, and in particular I
hope it helps you to get a better understanding about the filters and complex numbers and
frequency response, transfer functions, and all these, okay, any question before we
start the new chapter two?
Because the review here is also important because subsequently we talk about still linear
prediction filter which is very much related to the discussion here, okay, if no question let's
continue here, we will,
we have two just two main chapters, chapter one is the more like it's quite long you
introduce some concepts, some maps, backgrounds, and so on, and that's why in the past I also do
the same for this quiz, it will be, there could be one question from more like
probability related, and then it could be two questions for the chapter two which is,
which we are going to discuss for the quiz. It's not a very difficult question, just like
small question similar to exam question, a little bit simple, maybe half of one question equivalent
to half of the final exam papers and paper question, and then in the final exam paper
usually I will not exam on the mass background again, but it could be incorporated into part of
the part of the question related to chapter two and chapter three, so usually one chapter will
have one proper question, have some sub-question, so that's what you can take note in
preparing for the upcoming quiz in grade 12 and the final exam. Okay, so what do we
have here? We will first go through introduction and then after that we talk about forward and
backward linear prediction, so this is very relative to filter but not exactly the same,
you have new concepts here also, and then one of the important ones is to solve
normal equation arising from this linear prediction, and then after that we will talk
about one another important filter, Wiener filters, which can be used for filtering and
prediction, so that's the outline of this chapter, and like in part one and also in your
previous study, such as DSP and so on, you already learned how to design filters,
FIR, IR filter, or even filter paint, you have several filters putting together, and then you can
have very wide applications in communication, control, geophysics, or even some biomedical
things. But here we also talk about filter, as you're just seeing, we are also mainly dealing
with linear filters, but then we will be looking from the statistical viewpoints, a little bit
similar to the statistical signal processing, the 7402, some of you also taking that one.
And then here, it's no longer in frequency domain, sorry, in the early part one, the
conventional filter design, we normally call that frequency selective filters, that means you have
low pass, high pass, bank pass, you're based on the frequency bank to design, your specification
is based on frequency, so we call that like frequency selective filters. Here, because our
signal and noise, it could be mixed together in the same frequency bank, you can't separate the
low or high frequency. So what you do is you're based on some statistical property, say like
Gaussian signal, or AR processing, and so on. And then we get the best by minimizing
in terms of the mean square errors in the statistical viewpoints. And then
we will use mainly second order statistics, of course in that case also include the first order,
first order is the starting point, like mean values, and so you need that to build up the
second order statistics, which is autocorrelation and cross-correlation. And this is the same
approach we will be also studying in chapter three, the power spectrum estimation, which are
also based on the autocorrelation and cross-correlation. So this two chapters are very much
related, it's just the emphasis are a little bit different. One is more in the time domain
analysis in the linear prediction, where the power spectrum density is more like in the
frequency domain. Okay, so that's the background, seems not working here.
Yeah, so what's mean by forward linear prediction? I think this is,
again here you can, nowadays it's very common you try to link into machine learning and so on,
and this cause it does have some connection, and actually you can see this is more the traditional
machine learning approach rather than using neural network. So this, for example linear
prediction is very popular and very important in the speech signal processing, and even nowadays
you still have some, you know, if you are processing or analyzing speech signal, you can
still use linear prediction. So nowadays, very often you use deep learning models to do
like the learning from the last data, data size, and so on. So the meaning of linear prediction is
you're given some pass value, then based on the pass value you try to, if you are using linear,
you just do the linear combination to predict the current value. But you don't know the current
signal value yet based on, say, pass p if you are using order p. Okay, so this is,
you see, like what we call forward linear prediction is you use pass value then
predict the next value in terms of the time sequence, say one, two, three, then you predict
three. So you can mathematically, you can see, we try to predict the current value,
which is x of n. n is the, you can take n equal to three or four and so on, you just give this.
And then in that case was a pass value. If it's one step, meaning you see you go back by one
sample, and one sample at a time, and then we're dealing with discrete time signal, then of course
it will be n minus one, n minus two, and so on. Until when? Then depending on how many
samples you're predicting, say if order p, then you will be using p values, one, two, three,
up to p. So mathematically you can define, this is the value. We don't know x of n, we use hat.
So this symbol is estimation, like what I did in the statistical signal processing. The estimate
value we use hat. And then here we purposely use the coefficient of minus sign. Of course, whether
you take a minus sign or plus, depending on your writing. The way we
put minor, because later you want to combine this coefficient to make it positive. But the
value, the coefficient value exactly could be negative. So whether it's minus sign or not,
doesn't matter. It's just a way of convenient. Okay, so this is what we'll be doing here.
So remember, you take know the summation is k is from one to p, not from zero here, because
n minus one is the first pass value, and so on. Okay, so this is the way to write.
And then you can take an example like p equal to three. So that means you use three pass values.
And then I'll end here to be zero, at that zero moment. So the pass value, of course,
you will go back to before zero. And how many values? Okay, p over three, you have three values.
Minus one, minus two, minus three. Okay, so you write in this way. So this is a forward linear
predictor of the x zero value. So I need to take note here is a way to not involve the x of the
true x zero of value here, and pass value. They're all from the same random process. And then the
value here, you can see that as a realization. A random process, you can take one realization,
you will get extra signal value, like speed signals. Once you measure one speed signal,
it's a proper realization. Okay, so from here, you can see a forward prediction filter. It will be a
causal filter, because your color value based on pass value. And then from here, we want to see
how good we do the prediction. So that's what they call forward prediction, prediction errors.
So assume now we know the true value of x of n, like in machine learning, you had
the ground truth. You want to compare how good you are doing. Then, of course, you take the
difference and see, ideally, we're hoping this becomes zero. But in fact, usually, it may be
small value. So I call there four prediction errors here by take the difference. Okay,
so remember here the notation f of p. Take the difference, and then now you'll see why we put the
negative coefficient here. If you minor this, then previously our coefficient is minor. So
minor is minor, become plus. So you can now conveniently combine these together.
You see this also looks like a filter, you see, based on the x of n minus k. But the
summation now is k from zero up to the same p. And why? Because you're adding one more here. And
when k go to zero, n minus zero will be just equal to x of n. And then the coefficient here is,
of course, equal to one. So you need to take note of the relationship and
the difference between the two. Okay, so it's very important to take note. This
filter, you see, there will be two relative filters. One is what we call forward linear
predictors. This is the filter. You are only based on pass value, you see. You're based on the
p pass value to predict the current value. So this is the one we call linear prediction filter.
In this case, forward is in the middle. But then if you want to represent this, this is
forward prediction error filter. It's also a filter because the representation here,
they are very similar. All these are filter representation. And this is also a filter.
Except this one yields the xn value. You see, you now know up to the xn value.
So we want to see how much is this forward prediction error after you do the prediction.
So you see here, this is the block diagram for this filter representation. The input is xn.
So you go through one delay and then go through this filter, estimate that. Then the output here
is fp of n. The output is not the xn of n. So we're talking about only the forward linear
predictor filter. It will be this part only. So don't get confused. This is what I call
error prediction error filter. And similarly here, you can write in another way by
expressing the coefficient clearly here, including this coefficient of one. This is
directly from xn. So again, the filter output here is the fp of n, not the xn of n. If you
want to get the prediction of this xn, you will need to exclude this branch. So you only
predict based on this. And also the filter coefficient based on our equation, it will be
minus. But whether you put minus or not is less important because filter coefficient can be
possibly negative anyway. It doesn't really matter. What's important here is you need to
differentiate the two filters. One is a prediction error filter, while the other is a linear
forward prediction filter. So I don't show the other filter product, but it's very clear if you
if you remove this branch, they will become the prediction filters block diagram.
And then we'll call it Z-Sung form. That's why before starting this, I gave you the background.
That's precisely what we already I just revealed. Can have Z-Sung form of this fp of n. Then
of course in that case, you can write into is equal to ap of z and multiply that. Or
from here, you can also get the ap of z or equal to the ratios and so on.
And then here, the ap of z is in this case will be the f by r filter because it's all
coefficient and then z to the power minus k is in the so-called denominator,
the numerator. The denominator again seeing this is equal to divided by one. So that's easy.
And then now, remember we tried to get the mean square of the forward linear
prediction error of that because in general because we're dealing with random signals. So
we will need to look into the mean square errors. So what you'll do is you'll
take the power of two, the absolute value of power of two. But this is in the time domain,
different from our earlier discussion in the frequency domain. And then you'll take the
expectation in the mean square value. And then you can, if you'll explain this, because
fp of n is the first order. You'll take the power of two and then assuming here will allow
the coefficient to be complex in general. But if it's all real, then taking the conjugate is just
equal to except. So in this expression, assuming we allow it here, then when you explain this,
you can write this is like the second order, like the quadratic equation depending on the
coefficient. And for this first order part, we need to take the real part. Otherwise,
you will be complex because when you're dealing with mean square row, we're trying to
since we take absolute value raised to power two, it should be a
positive and lower value, no longer complex. So this is the quadratic function of the
predictor coefficient ap of k here. And then you all know for quadratic, if you want to minimize,
you take the first order derivative, set it equal to zero. And then I won't show the detail here.
To minimize that, then you end up with a set of linear equation because in total, we have
p coefficient. So you see here the relationship is you have the autocorrelation here.
Remember last week, we talked about you can link this with the autocorrelation fact. When you take
expectation, you end up with the second order correlation, you will give you the
autocorrelation coefficient. And then in total, if you have p unknown, then you will have p
equation. And it turns out to be in this case, assuming you know the autocorrelation,
you can solve this because they will all be linear in terms of the coefficient.
Okay, so that's why I call that as a normal equation for the coefficient of the linear
predictors here. Remember our definition. And then once you get the, you solve, you get the
optimal value coefficient here, you substitute back, then you can get the minimum mean square
prediction error in this case. So you see the difference. This is the mean square error in
general, okay, for all the different combinations. And then you'll choose a set of the coefficients
such that it becomes the minimum one. Then we use the smaller, this is a capital Ipsilon,
this is a small one. Then the error, except now reduced to the linear equation of that, rather
than the quadratic one. Quadratic one is not, in general, it works for all the different
coefficients. Once you get the optimal coefficient set, you substitute inside, you will get linear
forms in terms of the autocorrelation and the filter coefficient here. Okay, so this is the one
here. One very important, another filter structure, because so far, normally when you discuss a filter,
the easiest way to represent is a direct form, where you're, so you can see here the input,
you go through the filter coefficient, and then just sum that together. Mathematically, direct
form via filter is the same as this so-called P state lattice filter, because it represent the
input and go through the coefficient, you go through the output. But in practice, I don't know,
most of you are only studying for MSc students, you're now semester one, but for some of the
students who came last year or came one semester early, you may have already taken the other
related course, 6402, which is a lawyer time DSP and application, where emphasize a lot about
practical, like finite wall length and those quantization effect and so on, which, for example,
you're building up, building an Arduino controller or signal DSP processor, which is a very finite
number of bits. So you will see here, there will be different, mathematically, if you allow
infinity precision, then they are the same, these two filter structure. But in terms of
practical application, the lattice filter is much more robust, in a sense, if you make
the filter coefficient change a little bit, the direct form via filter, the result will be quite
different back here. So you can see here, we can use another equivalent, an all-GILO lattice
filter, which if the, our FIR filter is a P-state, you will get also the P-state lattice. So this,
for those who are already learning FFT, you will see it's very similar to FFT, you have
the, every state looks more like a butterfly, you know, kind of structure. So you have input
signal at the beginning, you're branching to F0n, 0n, and then go through first state, you
produce two output from two branches, and then go to the second one, and so on. So
mathematically, it's the same, but this one is more robust in terms of application. So this is,
so this lattice filter, you can describe it as, remember here, it's all the recursive equation,
you see our normal recursive filter is in terms of the time sample, you see, say n depending on
the path value is n minus one, so. So you, if you look closely, the, all the, all the values
subscript, the FGLO is the first one, then you go to the F1, and similarly G of one, and so on.
So you can see here, both at the time also recursive, so in terms of filter structure,
it looks a little bit more complicated, you start with the initial value, and after you recursively
build to get the next output value, both based not just on the past value,
it's one sample early, and also the early filter, filter order, so you start from
order zero to go to order one, order two, and so on. Eventually you go to order P, okay.
And then here, you can see instead of, you know, early on we have A0, A1, and so on, those filter
coefficients. Here, we have a different set of coefficients, so each, each state will have this
KM coefficient, they're just one coefficient, but of course, again, totally a P, so you have K1,
K2, up to KP, so this coefficient we call reflection or partial coefficient, okay, for this, and
and then it's quite interesting to know there is a relationship, and the relationship is one-to-one
mapping. If you're starting from a fire filter in terms of the A1, A2, up to AP, the one we just,
you know, stay early at the beginning, then you can get the corresponding
K1 all the way up to KP. In total, there are P coefficient of A, and the same as the K1, so
from one way, you can go to the other end, vice versa, so yeah, that's, so we can, we can
briefly discuss the relationship. So if you know KM, how to get AL, and then remember you, you will
do it by similar to the order recursive in, so, so in the end, eventually you want to get this
AJ up to the order P, but we start from the A0J, A0J is the zero order, then it will be just a
constant equal to one, and the other day you use this recursive equation to calculate things.
We already know A0, which is one, then you can get the next AJ, A1 object by, so see the
the relationship is, it depends on the previous A0J, for example, A1, then you need to have this
K1, and then, because K1 from here, you already know, and then also, so here is a very important,
you see here, once you know the AM minus one, the previous order of J, then you reverse the J,
change whatever you see J here into J to the power minus one, so okay, they'll create another
create only one, and then you must multiply this J to the power minus M, then the M is
depending on this M, okay, and then finally you do it one by one, depending on those up to P,
then once you get P, you'll get this, you see in total P coefficient, AP1 and so on, so every time
this small p is not up to the final, we call that the capital P, then you haven't done yet,
you have to continue doing that, so we can later give some example and finish this part,
and on the other hand, you can also do it the other way around, once you know this set of L,
you can get the K of A, so how to do that, so this is the reverse spec, you see, so you need to be
careful, here is a way, since we know the A1, A2 up to AP, we already know the AP object, so we
we fix this, we start from the P, the last one, AP object, I already know, and out of that,
so we get among this filter, we only take the first one, KP go to AP, and out of that, again,
you recursively build down, you see, from AP, you go to the next value P minus one, and so on,
so you see here, you get the order, this subscript corresponding to the order,
early, the lower order, and then here, we denote again here, A minus Z is equal to that,
once you get this, you can see this is the, it will work out into the, something like that,
FIR, FIR filter, the numerators only, then we get the next K minus one,
the value is getting from the highest coefficient, you see, so first one you get one,
then you get the second one, and so on, so you keep going down, so let's go through the two
examples, one to the other, and then you can see how you do, for example, P goes to three,
and now we know the coefficient set, K1, K2, K3, so you see here, all these, the absolute value of K
is all smaller than one, so the filter will be stable, you can ensure that, and then we start
from A0 of J equal to one, and from here, you're using the formula, you get A1 of J here, then we
know these are value given, okay, and now that, because it's not done yet, in total, it's three,
so once you get A1J, you get A2 of J, so remember here, you need to take note, as I emphasize,
when we talk about A1 of J here, the J doesn't have a negative power, but the filter coefficient,
filter is all in terms of J to the negative power, see, so J to the minus one, then what
happens if you want to get A1J to the, change J to the power minus one, so whatever you see
J to the power minus one, you'll reverse back to be positive power, it will be, because J to the
negative power minus one, and then you'll raise another power minus one, then become J to the
powers one, so it becomes positive power of J, and then, but how are we going back to,
because eventually we want to, still want to get the FYI filter in terms of negative J, so what
you'll do is multiply by this, this is the highest, because J to the, whatever you see here, they're
all lower than two, so once you multiply that, they become, you'll reduce to the negative power,
so that's why when you combine, you'll get this, and similarly you'll go to the next one, A3 of J,
and now you'll get a proper third order of this, okay, so this is the one when T equal to three,
you'll get A3 of J, and you already get the A1, A2, A3 coefficient, so this is done,
and then, because we all involve this, you see, so it may be easier we define this,
BM of J is equal to that, then the equation looks a little bit, a little bit simpler, you don't,
so you replace this with that, and similarly with this notation, you can also get this
relationship, and this is what you will be, you will calculate the other round from KM back to,
yeah, back to A1, A2, yeah, so that's,
so now let's see
how we can get the KM coefficient if you are given this by a transform function, F by R here,
because this is F by R, so what you do here is, remember, as I say, this is the highest order,
we start from A2J, and then your K2 is, you will be this one, okay, so once you get K2 and A2J,
you can get B2 of J, if you check that here, so you see here, yeah, so what you define is
here, so, and then after that, you get the next, you see, from AM of J, you can get AM minus 1,
seeing this one, you can already get, and this is known, and you already know the KM coefficient,
so you keep going down, A2J, then B2J, then get, from here, our first, this is highest coefficient,
we will get this, and then you can move down to A1 using this, since all these are known,
and then you can see, you always end up with J to the power, negative power, and furthermore,
you can see the highest coefficient always cancel out, so you will go one, one of the lower, okay,
so the one of the lower, the highest coefficient, you will be, you'll be K1, and then we are done,
because here is a second order, K1, K2, okay, then you can, you can apply this to other
example recursively, and the important one, as I mentioned here, these are very important properties,
is the zero of AJ all inside, you see, yeah, we want to ensure this AJ to be like the,
remember it's the minimum, minimum phase, that mean if AJ or the, the zero are all within, within
the unit circle, your inverse this filter, you will get stable and causal, causal linear, linear
filter here, and then that's very easy, you can, necessary and sufficient condition is all these
must be absolute value is smaller than one, so it's quite easy to test, rather than if you know
those A1, A2, you need to solve the Young's order polynomial, sometimes it's not easy and particularly
when you have high order, so that's, yeah, so I think it's a good time to take a break here before
we move on to the backwalk linear prediction, you know, based on the clock, we come back at
7.55, now it's 7.41, usually we take a break about 15 minutes,
okay, any questions you can raise here or you can ask me during the break or after the,
after the lectures also. I am now, I'll see you later, 7.55.
So
so
yeah so just now we talk about forward linear prediction and now we want to reverse back to
backwalks so let me do some proper drawings first
so if we have the say we have x n here
okay then the previous value will be n minus one and that one going back n minus two and so on
so the time is in terms of time will be yeah in in this this direction so this are for example
current value you based on the based on the past
several value to to predict so for example the one we talk about the p p order then there will be
n minus p okay so yeah that's how we will be uh previous previously doing here it's from past
value up to the kind of one and this is what we also uh learned from before like the causal
causal filter the filter is called your base on pass value now we want the reverse back which is
anti-causal is now still given in total say you have x p minus n minus p all the way up to x n
now what we're doing is you see this is the x n minus p is the is a value we want to predict
assume we do not know maybe they were too noisy and so on so we already
get whatever up to x of n so our backflow backflow is the one is we base on
the x n minus p the next value will be n minus p and then p minus one so it's it's one
one value after this n minus p n minus p is the earliest one so your next
at least one is so so what we are doing is assuming is there p order you know we use p
order mean we use in total of like p value so so so the way we do is now we want to predict this
last value here from the observation of the those past value of the process but this past value is
for example we are talking about the current value is up to x of n but now assume we already
measure all the way up to x of n so so so we want to do this backward and
again here we are using one step backward linear predictors of order p then so the
value we are predicting it is x n minus p which is the earliest one actually give the
prediction of this value by the weight linear combination of all those past value
but all these very well after this x n minus p okay then once we are clear about this relationship
then the expression is very similar to what we you know already wrote early but you need to pay
attention to the to the summation index here okay we also we call this as b or p instead of a
we call it b or p and then we also use a minus sign here a but the summation is from k from 0
up to p minus 1 because you see here we still refer the reference for is there this x of n
okay then now we use x of n so that mean k equal to 0 mean we are talking about x of
x of n here okay and then after that x n minus 1 so k equal to 1 and then we'll
previously we're up to p but now we only sum up to p minus 1 because our starting point is k from 0
okay and all these a coefficient this minus b p k because there is also prediction coefficient of the
one step but here is a backward linear predictor of order p okay so so you can just imagine this
is a totally a reverse process of what we discussed earlier linear the forward linear
prediction but it's other around and then one thing important to point out where the forward
linear prediction is a causal filter this is not causal because you are using future value to
predict the early value okay sometimes we call there is a anti-causal because it's a totally
reverse the process but by any case this is not a causal filter and then you can also look at
an example here if p equal to 3 then we are using this x minus 2 minus 1 x 0
assume 0 is our current value then we'll try to predict using this 3 value back to an even earlier
sample x of minus 3 so here you may say why do we the pass value we already know what
do we need to predict because sometimes what you measure the here those major
signal may be noisy because remember we are dealing with random signal and also signaling
noise so it could be the noisy movement so even when you have those value the value may not be the
true value so since you're you know some property of this random process and then you'll get some
future value you may still use it to try to improve the pass value in the same but collectively
we also call that as a linear prediction except is predict the early value okay
so i hope this is clear to you and then once you know that and also know this relationship then
you can you can work out the backward prediction errors and so on so so assume this is the true
value and that estimate value then you can you can define the backward prediction error by taking the
difference and substitute back and then again this coefficient is equal to one so you can
combine together so now this looks nice almost the same as our previous one summation is from
k from zero up to p but you need to take note the the in the the forward
prediction error filter the coefficient is the first one is one but here is the last one is
vp up to the p this because this corresponding to the to the
index of p okay so don't get confused here similarly in the z domain you can you can
substitute and then get the relationship and it's quite interesting to know the if you are dealing
with in general like complex coefficients then the two these two coefficients are
related by conjugate conjugate but but the order also reverse so so that mean if you are listing
say a1 up to ap again then the other one is it will be from from b0 and then up to b p minus 1
so the relationship is not say i i get the b1 to a1 is it will be reversed by you know p minus k
if say for example if k equal to zero our bp zero you get from the from the last one p minus
zero it will be corresponding to the p so from one end to the other and yeah and that's that's a
similar concept if you are if you are taking the 7402 we call that as a max filter is also doing
the same you get the filter but you reverse the reverse the order here okay so therefore
this relationship help us to to link this to bp object if you're you know is initially expressed
in terms of this bp now using this relationship your substitute inside then if you're
oh the highest order is p then you can pull out this z to the power minus p if you pull this out
and make the change of of of available so you will see it turn out to be this part is almost the same
as the ap object except this is a positive power z to the power positive k and of course the
coefficient is conjugate so so you can see here so so uh writing it as ap to the power conjugate
here the conjugate only mean the coefficient you are taking the conjugate because we do not take
conjugate of this j as i say j is complex better but normally we we don't take a conjugate directly
we take j the corresponding one is j to the power minus one and so on okay so this is the very
useful relationship here yeah and then the very important implication here is if you are trying
to get the zero because both of them are fir filter it's all numerator then yeah using this
system function this is bp of j then they are just conjugate reciprocal of the g law of ap object
so both are related say if you have zero say minus j then the other one will be j and in the case of
the coefficient are rare if you have lower coefficient then that means the g laws if complex
they always conjugate so you get the same cell of of zero if the coefficient they are always rare
so therefore this bp of j here we call there is reciprocal or reverse polynomial of this ap object
so they are relating in this way okay any questions you do have here to ask or
if not then we can carry on with this so very similarly we can define the
mean square value of this backward linear prediction error so basically is similar to the
forward linear prediction things involving random signal you take the expectation
and raise the power of two and yeah and then take now the this
backward linear prediction error is defined in this way is a reverse order and now we
we already used the ap of k the forward linear prediction filter coefficient here
and it turned out to be the the the same here since if you
square it and then you will see this is also a quadratic function of this prediction coefficient
error and then you'll minimize it you end up with the same cell linear equation which is given
previously so therefore in this case you'll minimize you'll get also get the same minimum
mean square backward linear prediction prediction error the same as the forward one so
so we don't need to go into the detail discussion here
okay any question before we move on to another relative topic which is we try to link now to the
our auto correlation coefficient so far we only talk about
prediction filter either forward linear prediction or backward
but remember we are dealing with like the stationary random process so
eventually we still need to find out the auto correlation or cross correlation
to get a better understanding of this random process and the relationship with the linear
filter involved so how do you feel the cause so far after this point is it easy to follow or
difficult or average say compared to part one for example you already finished part one by
phone like the i mean the multi-ray one because the early part dsp probably some of you already
learned so normally i'll assume multi-ray field bank the one new to you so do you
so now we also start to learn something which is not from dsp here it's some new
contents so so do okay you you find with the current progress the not say
too difficult or too too easy or everyone fear is easy to it's all linear equation
like that okay so so no no much problem and we can carry on yeah so so now
as i say we are dealing with random process and random process there are three types
ar which is like the opal's ar and p's order process or ma moving average or the combined
of the two ama ar plus ma so it's ah in short so ar is we'll say in between is not not too
difficult compared to the ama ma is more like the fir filter ai is you're saying it
looks like the opal's ir filters later you will see this so now remember here even if we are
dealing with a linear prediction because we are involving the the random process so we need to
to find out the relationship of this coefficient and the autocorrelation
sequence you see you because from a random process we are assuming those
are weakly stationary so it must exist those autocorrelation by definition so from the
from the chapter one we already know they are related the coefficient the
autocorrelation coefficient related to this the linear prediction coefficient in in this way so
and that depending on you see you see the autocorrelation you can
starting from and we don't need to look at the negative one because autocorrelation
i think this is important properties always symmetry is even even function assuming of
course we are dealing with coefficient are all rare okay so so therefore we look at the case of
m equal to equal to zero when m equal to zero because ar process is you know starting from
is driven by white noise something like you always remember ai is like white noise white noise goes
through opposed opposed filter ir filter which is only the post one of the that one over this so
so therefore m equal to zero our white noise you will come in into the picture so you have this
you see sigma w raised power 2 that's is the is a white noise
barrier and then the other part there will be auto correlated like the you see the m depends on the
the pass value so in this thing is a is similar to the filter relationship
you know m equal to zero then what adding one more tell me this is noise so you need to differentiate
m equal to zero or m greater than zero then the noise will not will not come into the into the
picture because white noise is only involving at the at the starting point after that equal
the other correlation it will be just depending on the the pass value okay yeah okay then depending
on what's the order of p is up to this p here so recursive you see once you know the first one
then the past p value you can get the you can get the next one and then keep keep going and what
what about the m negative one as i say once you get this other side you you'll get the symmetry
symmetry value and this relationship is very important and what we call there is a
euler walker's equation or if you're writing metric form you see so i hope you get
you try to get familiar with how you're expressing metric form here say so you see here the the first
one the first line here is corresponding to m equal to equal to zero here you see so this this
term is at the coefficient equal to one so you multiply by one look at this and then remember
all this term you can move to the left hand side you see they will become become the positive
coefficient and since our k index is from one up to p so you will have because there are m here is
a you see i evaluate this m equal to zero so zero minus one it will be the will be minus one and
then next value minus two and so on all the way up to minus p and that corresponding this a1 ap
coefficient so that gives you the first you see when you multiply this matrix your the first row
multiply this column is common so you're doing doing one row by one row so this one you get this
and you have remember you have this term equal to this so now the next value is if m equal to
one you see so you see here so this value is corresponding to here you see you are starting
from m equal to zero then you go to one and so on okay so now if you look at m equal to one
so you have to use this equation you see this one is no longer this one only for m equal to zero so
therefore you see our summation is always k from one to p and then one minus one to the next value
it will be zero yeah so it's very easy you can you fix the first uh first intake here zero one
and so on so subsequently you just each of the next value you will just minus one one then zero
and then zero minus one become minus one and so on okay so it's very easy and this one of course
is always there all these ak coefficient they are all there and yeah then the one is always
corresponding with this one okay and then now for other than this m equal to g load or the rest
you don't get distance so n w is equal to zero yeah all right okay so in the same way you can
move down and then you easily get those and and also in views of the symmetry you see here
uh you can replace things what we normally interest is the positive
autocorrelation function value to from zero up to the positive one divided by symmetry
so you can replay this with one two and so on okay so therefore you can see here
uh this is a topology matrix mean all the diagonal elements
here then the next one also called diagonal so this is a principal diagram and the other is
just diagonal diagonal lines you see you can keep moving up and down here okay
so they are all the same value and also symmetry one and one and two and two and this is p and p
okay so how
uh yeah you can also see here if you very carefully if i
delete the first row and and this one so what do i get if i start from this one here okay then
we will get we'll get this so instead of starting from zero starting from one so this is the
part of the you can see the equation that you you'll take part of it you'll get this
right okay so why do we do we get this because sometimes we do not know the noise variance or we
do not need to import that one we want to uh we want to find out the
linear prediction filter coefficient and the autocorrelation here okay and uh so
how do we move from here to here any any idea why suddenly become become here
so this is a little bit of simple submatrix manipulation so i hope you can
uh get a good understanding of that if you look at the upper part of that i if i
consider that as a submatrix you see if i i call this a and then this bigger one
speed and then miss you know the one or the a1 so on i also call that as i break down into into
into two
two vector okay okay so this is uh no problem as long as the dimension is compatible you see here
so this is a very useful technique like sub sub matrix operation then
remember the running size is still equal to zero so we get the zero zero is a vector
okay so therefore in this case you can see it will end up with just just imagine these are the
are the two numbers is a sub-matrix so this is equivalent to say of course you make sure the
matrix are compatible it's ac a multiple ac plus b d will be equal to zero just just imagine you
will be dealing with say a row vector multiplied by another column vector okay so you all know
if you multiply this of course it will be equal to one mile divided by two plus two
miles divided by three you know like so yeah okay so in the same way in some matrix operation you
can you can break down into block block matrix then as long as the matrix i make sure a can
multiply by c and b can multiply by d yeah you have to make sure the dimension met okay and
that's that's how we we we we do it for for this if we partition this first column with i call this
a then this is the big one is b and similarly this one is corresponding to c and this is d
yeah so what happened if in using this uh we'll end up with let me write down this x x
uh one okay this is just a column vector x x is auto correlation okay so this is our a
and then this is just a column vector then of course it can c is just equal to one it can it
can multiply by one all right because when you multiply you make sure the the first metric the
column the same as the second metric the number of rows so it is one this is also one okay and then
weapon this b b is the big one the one uh very big one uh it will be x x g low and so on so
so i don't write down here and then you multiply by that vector uh removing one so what the d is
starting from a1 okay after ap okay all right so let me see you can yeah you can see so therefore
n w is equal to equal to zero okay so uh
so therefore uh you see using this operation you will see this is our p there okay multiplied by
this is this is a b and then uh so by right the a multiplied by c equal p you see you have this
one multiplied by this little thing it will be just equal to this vector plus the whole thing
equal to zero but of course this vector we can move it to the right right hand side then you
will become minus so that's how we get the uh still another cell equation but this is one number
less and also this matrix now is square matrix it's p by p where this one is not a square one
the one early this is a p plus one because you can total p plus one this is square matrix
when we move that one you make the matrix not a square one but after this operation we recover
this one okay so that's that's how this equation gives you the relationship between the auto
correlation function and the linear prediction filter coefficient okay yeah so from assuming
you know this autocorrelation you can solve this using this relationship you do not need to involve
with the noise noise value the white noise in in this case okay so i hope yeah yeah this is clear
so now when we are solving that we use the p p order we we do not know the underlying process
of this x of n is the x of n is the ar process coming out coming out from from uh
you know in involving the underlying ar process but our our order of the
linear prediction filter we are using key just we just try to guess based on the
past p value assume it's a forward linear prediction predicting that value so the the
the number of parameter i mean the order of the our linear prediction filter it may or may not be
the same as the underlying process the process may even not as ar processor it can be other so
if it's ama or ma you use this to predict you will get a much bigger error but even if this
is ar process but if the order are not the same say the underlying ar process is order of 10
then you use the order of five to predict then you'll get some some kind of some kind of
of errors the coefficient may not be the same but in the case of your you're doing the right thing
you know the underlying ar process is 10 for example in speed signal prediction typically
each of the one the order is roughly about 10 so you can use all the 10 filter to estimate then in
in that case your prediction will be very good and actually in this case the optimal ones here
at least theoretically it will give you the exactly the same coefficient so you you minimize
then you you happen to get the true coefficient corresponding to the ar piece order if you are
using in this case you're using piece order so that's so that's how this is matched perfectly
you see so uh so this so by right usually the ak and this apk they are not necessarily the same
one is inherently is defined by your given ar process you see remember ar process is
corresponding to to some ar coefficient by how they get that is you assume you
you're generally white noise then you go through that you know each of the ar process defined by
uh like the oppose irr filter you get from there generally you may create a ar process so they want
that that's determined by the ar process except and then now what we are doing here is a big
because we may not know you know so we only have the major the major the random process
you measure like for example you take a speed signal so you take the path p value then i use the
estimate we try to build up this prediction filter and i i based on the major data we create
the coefficient then if the p happened to be the to be the same then you're lucky you'll just
heat that that coefficient set but usually not not the case you may get something
closer to it okay so try to understand the relationship in this case and then in in that
case are your the minimum mean square mean square errors in the piece of the predictor it will be
equal to the value of the white noise process and that's the best you can get because because
white noise the if you have the white noise value you go to that that's the that's the minimum
minimum error because you cannot reduce this you know this this one your mean mean square
error may be bigger than that but will never be smaller uh smaller than that and most equal is
the best you can get you know to those taking the statistical signal for saying this something
similar the criminal law power is here yo yo yo the lower power is the best you can achieve that
one so that's it lucky otherwise you have some bigger bigger errors or bigger
barriers okay so yeah so therefore if we our prediction error filter we have this system
function or ap object yeah it will be a noise whitening filter so you'll see here that's the
reverse whitening filter is the one we we start with ar process then we go through the
whitening filter then we produce the innovation innovations process i mean the white noise
why not process it will be the reverse so the forward one is you i repeat again you
try you use this white noise input goes through this ar
ir filter then you produce this uh
the random process which is xn now assume you already know the
chunks of function the filter you'll make the inverse and you can make this as an input then
the output will be a new white noise so it's a reverse process of course assuming you can get
this whitening filter properly if this is a stable one okay any questions at this point before we move
on it's getting a little bit more involved any any question anything you'd like to
ask or like to clarify before we move on move on
okay so you'll see here we need to solve this set of the normal
equations say for example we are not dealing the the the equation involving the involving the noise
value we're just trying to find out those linear prediction field the coefficient and the
autocorrelation so this is what we call the normal equation in yeah in total we have p
and then the coefficient uh the the term is p plus one because you start from k from 0 to p
uh but then our first coefficient is equal to one so we only have p coefficients here okay
yeah so therefore this is the normal equation in total a system of equation
p equation at p unknown to solve and then the resulting minimum mean square
error is given by the previous equation equation 88 and then uh if you uh we can
again add in the one here this is the one related to the to the noise the minimum mean square one
so okay so so that's the one uh you see this l equal to one two up to p and that give you all
this equation but if l equal to 0 then we we get then addition you know minimum mean square
mean square error which is also recursive except at the end equal to this
minimum mean square mean square error which in the case of if your order happened to be the same
you will get the value of the white noise
so therefore uh yeah you minimize that and then we will need to solve this
equation so let's look at any one example to see how we can actually solve particularly if the
order is very high yeah so let's consider the case p equal to three then you can lease out the term
here so as i say in total it will be p plus one term because our summation start from from zero
which is l minus zero so this is the one but the coefficient here equal to one so you have a
three one two three so you'll be careful here we have two index here one is the
subscript here is you see a three mean though the order p equal to three but among this
uh other three linear prediction filter you have three coefficient so that's why a three
of a one is the first one and the second one two and that's the one okay so that's uh is
the coefficient of this uh other correlation with the shift okay l this is minus zero that's minus
one minus two and so on okay so depending on uh yeah l yeah equal to here l if l equal to zero
you put l equal to zero in you will have to equal to this term but if l equal to one two three then
it will be equal to zero so this is very similar to what we state early the Euler-Walker
equation okay so that give you the more concrete expression here because we know that p
equal to three so you have this and also make good use of this symmetry relationship
and uh here is easier to see the the matrix here it's uh properties that's uh I think maybe one
scientist name here that discover this property so this metric here is uh you see all uh three
so we say the all the diagonal they are the same values yeah equal to the same value here so this
is the principal diagonal then this is one offset from this one you can move up upper right yeah
and then one move up one position you get this then the another position further up and right
and you get the other one of course finally you only have one element so if you have more than one
you can see these are the same value and this is same then this is same similarly you move down
left and down you get the others from four reduce three and then two and finally one okay so these
are very useful property of this symmetry property of the auto correlation matrix
it's not just symmetry but also satisfy is a symmetry of course because this so this is a
very important property because later on in chapter three when we started
the
the power spectrum estimation we're also involving matrix similar to that so that's
yeah please take note of that yeah any questions at this point
yeah okay so we can move on yeah so how to solve that of course nowadays uh
you you have a computer's algorithm very powerful so you may may not worry worry too much even if
you have a big matrix equation you can always solve it but in the early day you see here
1947 or 1959 which is very many same uh yeah quite
yeah many years back so yeah so so at that time you have involving a big matrix is
no easy no easy to solve inverse a big magic and therefore you can develop computationally efficient
and iterative methods to solve that and these are the two of them we're not going to
too much detail because this is a little bit more involved and they're they're also recursively
algorithm to really solve and i think if you use mallet you should have already some
building functions to solve it so but they just we just go through one of them as a simple
example to illustrate but don't worry about this very complicated and involved just use that as an
example and here the the algorithm the idea is also similar to what we discussed early is more
like all the recursive so so what i do is because low order is easier to solve so you can start with
a predictor of order p equal to one then in this case you're only solving because p equal to one
you only have one coefficient which is a one you see so remember i say p referring to this order
and of course p equal to one is you only have one coefficient and then you're putting into the
normal equation where p equal to one we have two equation one is equal to that the other equal to
zero then it's very easy to solve these things you have only one coefficient you have two equations
you are assuming this one you do not know you may want to solve so so anyway we are more interested
in solving that then you can easily get a one of one equal to this okay so that's done and then
once you as i say here your two equation two unknown then once you solve one you need to
solve the other so so in this case assuming we know the autocorrelation and we substitute
you can get into the second equation they'll cause your base on a one of one and so on so you
can see this is a relationship because of that it'll make good use of the symmetry so this is
done if the order p equal to one then what next is going to using what we solve for p equal to one so
the recursive is you solve from lowest order then your other one you get coefficient and then your
next go to order two and after that you'll solve order two you go to order three and so on so
here is we are illustrating using this equation but as i say you can drawing algorithm to
uh automatically solve it rather than writing down so let's just illustrate uh what we can do
once we already solved for the one then we go to p equal to two then in that case p equal to two
we have two coefficient plus this term here so you have three equation three three unknowns and
assuming these are solved okay then you'll see here what we solve is a one of one
so these two coefficients since the order changes you you cannot assume our a two of one is
equal to a one of one there will be there will be different once you change order you have to
solve the two coefficient different but you in a way you can find out they are
somewhat related to the early one okay so let's see what we can do here this is look complicated
but then using some simple trick usually you try to solve with the equation without involving
that one okay so if you look at the the last two equation and then using what i described early
you can simplify into this matrix uh equation two equation with two unknown and then after that you
can you can you can solve using the previous one our a two of two which somehow you make good use of
the you see relationship here our a one of one is a ratio of these two then the the idea here is
you make make use of the lower the solution already rather than going back you may directly
solve using those uh you know autocorrelation function but the idea here is recursive so we
make good use of that you can you can see i won't go into detail but you will see here this part is
actually turned out to be the same as the ratios a one of one so you substitute then this is all
you already solved you can substitute and then uh yeah and then yeah you you also make good use of
this one this one is also solved so early so it turned out to be simplified if you already know
a one of this one and this so it's quite easy right here similarly a two of one you also need
to solve assume this one so so a one of one also solved turned out to be to be easy here and once
you know this then now you you want to get this you put back here and of course the autocorrelation
function you know so you can solve that so you see here there is a recursive in the
sense of all the recursive you solve for lower order first and then you build up to the higher
one and so on okay rather than always solving these big matrix equations okay but i will say
this part is not not our main discussion okay any any questions you like to raise
we still have some time you can talk a little bit on wiener filter
so so far so good is it okay
no no issue need some discussion
so
okay yeah as i say this more or less we finish the discussion of like the linear prediction
filter and uh so before uh ending this lecture i will just
probably introduce this concept of wiener filters because these are in the same you can
think about this is a generalization of what our linear prediction filter we
discuss you know up to now so this is a little bit like moving one step forward to consider one
more important and related wiener filters this it can be used for filtering and prediction so
somewhat we also try to understand the relationship what's meant by filtering
and then what's meant by prediction so and you can very conveniently using wiener filter to
uh to link these two actually the same wiener filter depending on how you define you can
you can serve for these two purpose okay so uh remember so far when you talk about linear
prediction we are always assuming we are dealing with one ar processes so we have the x of x of n
which is the well actually not necessarily ar it could be it could be another other type of
weakly stationary random process but it must be weakly stationary so that we we can you know
remember we create stationary random process we can use the autocorrelation to describe it
and autocorrelation is the second order statistic so here the main difference is
now we try to directly building our white noise into this signal model you see
uh previously we are only considering the the ringdom process is driven by
by by white noise you see white noise goes through some kind of filter then what do we get is this
ringdom process the output x of a so we do not know the the the noise directly what we can measure
is only like x of n so we use past value to predict the future value or vice versa you get
all the value then predict back to the backward prediction so the difference here is we are
thinking about our input signal here xn is somewhat is a sum of the signal the signal
itself it could be also a ringdom process but it's a clear summation here we we have this
design signals this is what we want but then it mix with noise so what we can measure is
again is a similar we only have the xn here the input signal to the to the wiener filter and
what we're going to do now is we try to build another optimal linear filter such that
the filter output we call it yn and then we try to design the filter in such a way where this yn is
uh try to able to approximate our another
specify or we reference design signal we call it dn you see the dn may be because we we this is
a signal but this one we cannot we do not have assessed this one what we can measure is only xn
so in the same you can think about we try to recover this xn or some
desirable signal related to xn so later we will explain what's this da mean so so again here
a yn here is what we call our design signal da plus some noise because we may not be able to get
this d of n exactly so so that's that's the idea here so you see here our filter here is
the input is xn so so that's why i say this is a bit similar to our linear forward linear
prediction filter in the same but more general yeah because we are building a little bit of the
of the more specific model here previously we only always assume we only have x of n now okay
so that's the main difference yeah so now what's this dn if we are doing filtering so our dn we
just let dn equal to equal to sn so therefore we design this filter our field here is very
similar before we call h object to suppress our noise yn so we try to get our yn is approximately
equal to the sn so this is the filtering one and then we can also do a signal prediction so you
see here the relationship filtering is the you just get the column value out of the column input
input value the n you see the yn that you you assume you have xn available so it's not like
what we before so far with this prediction is you're based on past value so it's a causal
causal filter here and now but this one so that's why you're saying we say wiener filter is more
general compared to linearity because you can also do signal prediction why in what way we use
our referencing the dn which is xn plus d that mean if d greater than 0 so what we want here is
not just xn it will be some future value say n plus 1 if n plus 1 it will be one step
forward prediction n plus 2 is the two step as you're predicting two sample ahead and so on so
deep but d must be greater than 0 and then since we are talking about discrete time signal d should
be integer also because we only define signal at one two three four five so okay so therefore
uh is in this thing is a relative but more general than the linear prediction you see here so you
should try to know the relationship here uh yeah because before you see our early on our linear
prediction you can assume our dn is always only because x of n plus d you see we even do not know
the s of n so here is uh is more general you allow us to define what our dn yeah and then
they could even be doing the signal smoothing if the reference signal is as n minus d so this is
a little bit like the back walk uh back walk linear prediction so your smoothing is already
the past value you try to do but not exactly the same because the coefficient the the the
design is somewhat different okay so therefore uh i think we i just give the introduction so we
can finish the class here i don't want to delay you since we come down the the break time so let's
assume we have xn wn and dn and then they are all random process and zero mean and y same
stationary so what uh so you see here the in this things are the output filter the
optimal linear filter we also call it hn so yeah you see is so what we do is a similar
we try to do a mini minimization to get the minimum mean mean square mean square arrow
because you see so we now we can define the arrow which is desirable signal subtract to the output
of the of the filter and then you'll take absolute value raise power to take the expectation so in
a sense are quite similar and our winner filter can be designed if ir or ir if you're dealing with
ir then the input data must be available over the over the infinity path because ir is recursive
so you need all the past value so yeah so i yeah so just a very quick one to introduce to get
because these are very similar to what we we define uh we discussed early assume where
if i feel there is a much easier that that's a finite value and then the output you are depending
on the past finite data set of that so this is a very easy way you should all know this if ir
filter you know this and then what we do we minimize by taking developing the subject to
this is a mean square uh you know minimize take the expectation so and then from here
you see your n double is expanding that then you'll get a very similar
you see you're expanding your quadratic function to feel the coefficient you'll
minimize then you'll get a very similar linear system of equation except here
since we have the desirable input so instead of you know previously the normal equation
equals zero but we have the auto correlation this is the input sequence and there is a
cross correlation because we have a design signal dn and also the input sequence so you
now introduce this cross correlation and then this equation we call it winner hope equation
probably is uh in bank by both winner and this hope so so uh then the how to solve is a
very similar to what we discovered early and then you can also convert into this
matrix the equation because if i filter you only have to find a number of coefficients and so so
uh and yeah so
yeah so i think probably yeah we will we will we will stop here because the other part is very
much involved and the example are quite it's quite important to discuss in some
uh some detail later i also want to give you some time to probably some student will stay back to
ask a question to clarify yeah so yeah i think we are in good timing so
uh yeah so uh surely we will finish this uh chapter uh by next week or probably just
yeah so we may have some time to next week to introduce the power spectrum estimation also
yeah so any questions you have after this point i think the linear predictions and forward
backwards and so those solving the equations and there are quite a lot material and quite a some
equation to learn also matrix equation and so on
the questions oh you're you're okay so far you don't have much difficulty or anything you like to
clarify at this point
no if not then i think we will finish at this point so next week we will continue to yeah and
yeah and then you may also begin to digest what we we learned
uh so far yeah before we take the quiz week 12 i already maybe i highlight again in case
some student come a little bit late and also for the benefit of those student to not coming but
watching the video recording so i explain give a more
elaboration on what the quiz will test so yeah so we finish day one so today we finish
probably more than half of this chapter so by next week so this is week nine
we we tend surely we finish this then you can have a good preparation i will
maybe next week after finish this chapter i will metal down a little bit on the on on the scope
because these two chapters there are still a lot material some are not really that directly
uh you're useful to or relevant not the focus of this course so we may exclude at least for the
quiz yeah so we'll discard that next week yeah okay so if no question i will
uh stop here see you next week yeah thank you
you