And now, after the recess week, I'm back here again.
Yeah, so I hope so far you have done well for part one, which
actually is very good news.
Also, the assignment will be marked by pro-woon,
because that was his part.
And I have a very quick check.
At least this time, all the students
have submitted the assignment one, because I was
the coordinator for the past five years or so.
And this is probably the first time,
I mean, all the students in the class.
I don't know, maybe some of you may submit just one page
or half page.
But that's up to him to check.
But at least everyone managed to submit, so that's good news.
And at the same time, I also hope
everyone can come for the quiz for the part two,
because each in this course, we only have two CAs,
not like some other courses that have more than two, three,
or four.
So each one has 20%.
Maybe I show this again, because for those students who
are not here, at least you watch the video recording.
This is also what I showed last time,
and in dealing with one I highlight.
And it remains the same, pro-woon has finished part one,
which is deterministic SP.
And then now I resume the statistical SP.
But it's different from the other courses, 7.402.
I'm also teaching, actually.
Some students take both courses.
May I know how many of you take the 7.402 also?
OK, good.
So at least some, probably.
Let me see.
There may be about 20 to 30 students out of.
Because now these two class size are about the same, 160.
So the overlap, probably I estimate,
because in that course I'm teaching estimation.
So I do the estimation, just based on my experience.
I don't check the actual name list,
but it could be about 20 to 30 students.
So one thing I want to highlight here
is for those students who take both courses, at least
you will find it easier in this part of things
is somewhat related.
It's true, some of the knowledge is the basics are very similar,
because in both part two of this course and the 7.402.
So they are all based on two very basic.
One is probability, and a little bit of random process,
but not very deep knowledge.
And at the same time, also need some linear algebra,
as you will see in this part two.
But in the same, I also find it easier for students
for the 7.402, because all the course is about statistical
signal processing.
So it takes some time to get the basic.
So I must say, based on past experience,
students taking this path will find it more difficult,
because your part one is, as you can see here,
deterministic signal processing.
So you don't hardly touch anything
which are random and so on.
But now, of course, those students
who have a good foundation, they already
learn probabilities and so on.
As I say, maybe among the 20 to 30 students who have already
taken my other course, you'll find it is somewhat easier.
But for other students, I really hope
you can put in more efforts, because we only
have six weeks here.
So today, I will try to finish chapter one,
because I won't go through it again,
but since there are about six weeks, seven weeks,
including the recess in between.
So some of the very important ones may be forgotten.
And also, some students say they did not take the week one,
because it's during the airdrop.
That's understandable, because we are Monday class.
Some students even did not arrive in time
during week one Monday.
So today, I will balance about not going, of course,
not going through the very basic again, but I will compromise.
So my plan is let's finish this first.
So again, coming to here, you're familiar with this setting
now, hopefully.
60% for the final exam, we have four questions.
We just finished setting the exam question by this time.
CA, as I just mentioned, we already done that,
so that's very good.
But I think it will take a few weeks for program to mark.
And then I also already put, because our class size is not
that large.
So this LTE is just good enough for the whole class.
About during quiz, we will have, you
don't seek one next to the other.
You always have one seat in between.
And this size is just good enough.
I have some student TA.
So please note out this time is week 12 is just here.
And then I also say the time is 8 to 9 PM, which is one hour.
Close book, just like exam similar to the final exam,
20%.
So you already done the assignment one,
so this is the next milestone.
So anyway, I already now, so you learn,
can do that later also.
So now coming back to this, this is my contact.
I think you can easily find from the lecture notes.
So in a sense, the content looks crazy.
We have very little to learn, because other than the 7402,
almost every week we have one chapter,
so two different topic to cover.
Program's part also have quite a few topic almost every week
as one.
So here, we only have three things.
And chapter one is introduction, which
is more in some background.
But in Excel, we already have some technical content,
as you know, dealing with one for those of you who came here.
And out of that, we have linear prediction and optimal linear
filter.
But this filter is quite different from program's part.
Also, there is some relationship,
and actually, it's quite important.
If you did well in part one, you'll
find it easier, because I won't start again
by introducing filters, the property, and so on.
And then finally, there is a power spectrum estimation,
which in a sense is more difficult,
because it requires the chapter two, the linear prediction,
and then add on some metrics, theory, and so on.
So roughly, I have six weeks, but usually the last week,
I will use maybe about half of the week to cover the content.
If I can finish all, then I will make the whole week free.
But at least half of the week.
And then half a week, you know, eight to nine,
because after nine, I mean, we will collect quiz papers.
So during week 12, yeah, there's only half, one hour plus left.
So in total, about five weeks for my part.
So my plan is based on past experience.
I will finish chapter one today, one week.
And then chapter two, it takes at most two weeks,
because it's a little bit shorter than chapter three.
And anyway, because these two chapters,
it will be the content for the quiz, because by, yeah.
So the plan by week, now is week eight, nine, 10.
So after week 10, you can do the revisions for whatever
preparing for the quiz.
So the last chapter will not be the content for the quiz,
but it could be, of course, it will be the exams, you know,
content for some of you who may already
take a look at some past year exam paper.
So it should be about half, half.
Usually it's, yeah, OK.
So that's the background and some introduction
to prepare you.
Any questions?
Yeah, I think this is kind of introduction to my part also.
Yeah, anything you want to ask, feel free.
You can raise your hands or just, yeah.
So let's go back quickly again to this.
You know, this one is show some relationship,
because at week one, I say for those student,
if you are lacking background in signaling system DSP,
you will find it difficult. But I,
and that's why some student, you know, like drop out,
because they find it difficult to self-study these two.
But now, for those staying on at least,
you should already have a good kind of standing.
Otherwise, you will have difficulty
to move on to this ADSP.
So now you're finished these two, assuming at least you
learn those requirements.
So now you are partially in this path.
So as I say, it's somewhat related to probability
of random processing, the statistical signal processing.
A little bigger, not that much a linear system.
There's more control related, but some of the metrics,
you know, they are all, yeah, related.
So any questions before we go into the main context?
And I want to test your memory for those of you
who attend the week one lecture.
I did not finish the whole chapter one,
so can you roughly tell me where did I stop?
Did you read the lecture note?
At what point?
Any memory?
Where do I stop?
Here or early?
Did I talk about power density spectrum?
No?
So OK.
Anyone want to give a guess?
Do you remember?
Zhengyi?
Not to mention the 1.4 power density spectrum.
I just want to stop at the 1.0.
OK.
OK, that's true.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's very good because I did not
go into the innovation representation.
I finished the power density spectrum.
They're probably a little bit rushing.
Just talk a little bit.
Is it right?
I did mention some power spectrum.
Is it right or not?
Not talking power spectrum density at all?
Oh, OK.
OK, good, good.
Thanks.
So I cover that part briefly.
OK.
So anyway, let's start this lecture, chapter 1, again.
Yes.
Hold this.
Let me see.
Full screen mode.
OK, so that's what we are supposed to do.
Yeah.
And then the textbook, as I say, it
has the two versions, both called fourth edition.
But this earlier one is the one we'll be using in the library
as the reserve room when you go enter.
There were several books on that, so you can take a book.
Because the reason is this newer version,
I don't know why, also called fourth edition.
Yeah, they both called fourth edition.
But this is several years later.
They removed the power spectrum estimation chapter.
But I think that part is quite important and useful.
But in case you check some past year exam paper,
you'll notice some of the early paper
we have adaptive filter.
But now we do not have that part in this course
after revision of the curriculum.
So it's focused more on linear filter and linear prediction
filter and the power density spectrum estimation.
So yeah, I think by now you already
know very well for this.
And also in terms of system, there are many.
But what we are doing is just deterministic.
System is deterministic.
Don't get confused with system and signals.
The signals are mostly the random part.
The system will be deterministic.
And then we also go mostly on the discrete time and linear.
And also, because things we don't talk adaptive filter,
it will be time invariant.
So for systems, again here, your deterministic signals,
which is your cover already learned in part one
or before that, DSP and those content, multirate,
they all belong to this.
We don't talk about chaos here.
And then now our signal are mostly dealing
with stochastic and random.
Of course, when we talk about random signals,
it could be part of the signal.
It could be also deterministic.
It can be a sum of both.
But usually, we refer to the more difficult signals,
like random signal.
As you all know, it's more difficult
comparing the deterministic.
So that will be the one we'll be going.
And then we only consider stationary process, then
the gothic process, which we do not really go through in detail.
So you can see, in terms of signal, it will be this part.
So now come to random signals.
I, so still, it's good to at least,
of course, for those who do not have much background.
So you will need to build in these random signal concepts.
So random signal, for example, if I have a coin here, I free.
So you all know a coin has two sides, face or tail.
So before it falls down, no one knows it will be face or tail.
So that's the very fundamental concept about being random.
So you'll need to keep this in mind.
Random signal is not like side way or square way where
you have the waveform.
You know exactly what the next value or even future value.
So this is something you'll need to keep this in mind.
But at the same time, it's not that we totally cannot deal
with random signal.
Then you may say, since there's random, so what can we do?
You just ignore it, just guess.
Every time is guess.
So no point to study.
Is it right?
No, not really the case.
Because among the random signal, for example, the output,
you cannot predict.
But there is this statistic behind this random signal
underneath.
So typically, we try to get some information out
of random signal.
For example, different random signal,
they behave differently.
Say, for example, if I have these ties, you see,
that's the, I don't know whether you can see, six-phase.
So if I throw these ties, so different from that one.
I mean, they are similarity and difference.
The similar one is we cannot tell which number it will turn
out because it will be 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
So in this thing, it's also random.
You cannot predict until the outcome is out.
But there's also difference because the other one,
the output value, you only have either phase or tail.
So we say it either can put it as either 0 or 1.
Well, here it's 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
So the probability, you try to describe this random process,
it will be different from each other.
And then that's why for random process,
we still try to get the most out of it.
If not like a side way, you can predict.
Because this is, as we already know,
you cannot predict until the value come up.
But we are able to study some of the statistics.
Typically, it's the average, which is very common.
That's why I have a student in the 7402.
I always highlight the two most important thing
about random signal or random variable, mean and value.
So mean is you take the first of the statistic.
Because being random, we try to average
to see whether, on average, what we can get.
And this average is very important
considering every day's life.
For example, in this class, at the end,
we will take the average amount of all the students.
And this is very important, because we
need to roughly moderate so that each
course, the average is about the same or not exact.
So that's a very important committee.
And the same as you see, every student,
you'll apply to come in.
I think I assume all of you pass this average CGPA.
CGPA is also average.
Because you may be very good in one some course,
but not so good in other.
So we need to take the average to see overall how good you are.
So this average is the most important.
And that's a first of the statistic
for random variable.
And the second one is the variant.
And also very similar, the moment,
the second of the moment, which measure the correlation.
Being random, I mean, the value of a variable
except it will be how much variation.
Because being random, it must be something keep changing.
So how much change?
Is it very near the average?
It change very little.
So that's why I say the value is very small.
So if a value is very small, then it's
very close to a deterministic signal.
So in the limited case, the value becomes zero.
It will be no longer random.
Am I right?
There will be no change.
And if the value is infinitely large,
so that's why noise, there is too much change.
You don't have much property out of that.
So that's how to study random signal, random variable.
You get this very basic idea.
And then after that, mathematically,
how are we going to describe?
As I always say, the best to describe random variable
is for continuous random variable
will be PDF for discrete random variable will be PMF.
So because that give you the best description,
it include all the order of the statistic.
But if you don't have that, it's not the end of the world.
You can still get, based on the data,
you can get first order, second order, the statistic
to describe.
So I think these are the very, very, very basic concepts.
And then how to define discrete random variable from what
I just mentioned early.
You need to have the sample space,
and then define an event, how likely it's going to happen,
and so on.
Yes.
So this is the two fair dice.
The one is another good example about this random variable,
and also the statistic.
Because if you just look at the throw one dice,
you'll have six values.
So you'll know unless you purposely
make a very special dice, but a fair one, you will.
So each outcome is one out of six.
So you'll know.
So there's no problem.
But then the event will be different.
For example, if we throw two dice at the same time,
and the number of each dice, you will have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And the other one also 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
But then now I define the event of sum
the outcome of these two number.
Then it's no longer equal probability.
Because if you look at the sums, in total,
the combination will be 36, because you have 1 to 6.
And then the other dice, it goes from 1 to 6.
So you'll know the combination.
It will be just 6 multiplied by 36.
And in this case, you can see being random variable,
how you get the events out of, say, one random variable
or two random variables, you already
see the different values for this event.
For example, in this case, all these 36 combinations
is very easy to check the sum of the two value being
in the center.
2 is only 1.
Sum these two number 1 plus 1.
There's only one probability, where 6 and plus 6 also 1.
But then there are quite a number of possibility
when you sum two number equal to 6 or equal to 7.
So that's how this probability.
Also, in saying it's random, but there are still
some statistics of probabilities and of properties behind it.
So you need to base on the given either PDF or the statistic
to describe the events out of this randomness.
So that's something you'll need to keep this in mind.
And then, as I say, PMF is the one for this great random
variable.
And continual random variable is easier to understand,
because we all know, I believe, even so,
we have a little knowledge about probability.
Everyone must have heard of Gaussian distribution.
And that's a very typical case for continued random variable.
And like bell curve and all this noise,
they all follow the Gaussian period.
That's how this is done here.
Normal or Gaussian distribution.
So I always say you may not need to memorize all the PDF.
But Gaussian PDF is like you can check with your seniors
last year or the year or the year before.
I always, for quiz, always pass Gaussian.
So you should be familiar.
And therefore, Gaussian PDF, I will not give you the formula.
Actually, some students, whether in this course,
we give some other course.
They give one page.
You can, in the exam, you can bring one A4 site page.
You write whatever small part.
But knowing this course, so everything
will require you to memorize the basic one.
Not the very complicated formula.
But Gaussian random variable and uniform distribution,
these two are the simple and the required one.
So I make good use of this opportunity to highlight here.
Because Gaussian random variable,
you only need to know two parameters,
the mean and the value.
So you go back to what I just highlighted earlier,
means and value are the most important ones.
Because for example, for Gaussian, knowing these two,
you know completely the PDF.
But of course, some other random variable,
you may not have this relationship.
And then expectation is actually this
is mean, we take the mean, expectation
is a more formal definition.
And so I always say if you look at expectation,
you can, by looking at the formula,
you can try to figure out the meaning of it
The PDF here is more like the weighting function.
Say for example, if you do not add this PDF,
you are just summed for this random variable.
You are just summing up the value
of this random variable.
So something like you are taking the average.
But if you multiply p of x, that means
if the p of x for this particular x value
give you a much bigger value, larger compared to other.
So you'll give it more weightage.
That means this x with a larger value of p of x
is more important when you're doing the sum.
And that also highlights the importance of having this,
knowing the PDF for this random variable,
we call that as a PMF.
For continue, it will be PDF.
And also the difference of these two is for this grade,
you cannot integrate.
So that's a very, very basic.
So you need to do the summation with the things
where they are described values, just like what
you learn from DSP.
And for continue time, you cannot sum because there are
not infinity of them.
They are not countable.
So you need to do integration.
But other than that, the formula looks very similar.
So that's a very, very basic definition
of expectation or mean value.
And I think you can skip this moment.
So actually, you do not need that.
And the value is what here.
And how do we link these two?
Actually, if you can, yeah.
So once you know the basic definition,
what you need to do is you need to apply
what you learn in other math, calculus, and so on.
They are relatively simple.
You just expand the quadratic functions.
And you do not actually need to do integration
because based on the definition, you will get the results here.
And this table give you the very, yeah,
those are commonly used one.
And I think there is a part where there is a, OK.
So these are also very important.
If you have start with a random variable, as I earlier say, x.
So you already know how to get the expected value
of the random variable here.
But you can, from a random variable,
if you have an analytic or real value functions,
we call g of x.
Could be a side way, could be exponential function.
These are proper, just normal functions.
Not necessarily random, except.
But a random variable, you go through this real value
analytic function, g of x.
They become a new random variable, OK.
So yeah.
So the simple example is if x, you raise a power of 2,
become x power of 2.
So x power of 2 is a new random variable related to x.
So in this case, it is very important
to know the expectation, e of this, g of x,
the new random variable.
When you work out, you still use the same PDF to do the weighting.
Also, this function value changes, OK, from x to g of x.
So yeah, this result is already well known.
You don't need to try to get the new PDF of this new,
say, the new random variable y.
If this g of x, the y, is from the initial random variable x,
and you already know the PDF of this p of x.
So what I mean is just change the x value into g of x.
But this weighting function, the PDF,
you still use the same p of x.
And making this as a function, it
covers other, for example, higher order moments.
Like the fourth order moment, x to the power of 1,
which is the mean.
And x power of 2, we call it, yeah, this is 1 here.
If x raised to the power of 2 is the second order moment,
and so on, it can be higher.
And in these things, you can also
see the very important function here.
This variant is also coming from the x.
You can see this is a new function coming from x.
It's the x removed minus the mean.
And out of that, you raise power of 2.
So it's related to the second order moment.
But the difference is, second order moment,
you do not remove the mean.
You keep that x just like x minus 0.
Of course, the two are the same if the mean expectation
of this x equal to 0.
But they will be different if, say,
if this is a value different from 0.
So yeah, that's how you have this relationship
of the value of x.
And this expectation, this is x raised power of 2.
And this is e of x, the mean raised power of 2.
So don't get confused with this tool
also, because quite often, some student
in the middle of the elevation, they compute these two.
So one is you take expectation first and raise power of 2.
The other is you raise this random variable
into power of 2 and then take the expectation.
And there are three related to this formula.
Any question so far?
Because I tried to balance between the weak one,
because some of you came here.
So if I repeat everything, it's not fair.
But for some student who did not attain weak one before,
if I assume that you already learned then,
it may not be fair.
So today, I will try to highlight the important one.
But I would like to get some feedback from you
to see whether this is the right approach or how do you feel?
Do you still remember what we want?
It's too long time ago.
OK, so let's see what we can do here.
Now, we move on to the joy distribution,
this great random variable.
So this becomes a little bit more challenging,
because now you're considering two random variables
and try to find out their relationship.
And in general, you see, if you're
similar to the single random variable,
the best is if you're able to, for this guitar,
you're able to describe the joy probability mass function,
which give you a full description
of the relationship between these two random variables.
They could be independent, or they have some relationship.
So you will be trying to see what the two events that are
going to happen.
Maybe one example is, as I say, some student
taking this course, and the same student,
they also take 7402.
So these two course, they have some co-relationship.
So you may think of how, if you are studying that or maybe
going to the final exam test, I do
find there is some co-relation.
Well, now then, you go to some courses
which are almost not related.
For example, actually, there is a side story here.
I think this course is probably not half, but at least quite
the number of students from either SP or SPML.
We currently have a course on Advanced Analog Circuit,
which is GE.
But this semester, the course was
offered in this semester.
None of the students from SP or SPML choose this course.
So based on this, you can see there
is almost not much relation with our SP or SPML program.
And that's why we are proposing to remove
this course out of the SPML.
But for the other four programs, I also
checked CCA, or there are always some students, maybe 10
or sometimes 20, taking that course, but zero students.
Very interesting.
So you see the correlation also from here.
Yeah, you can find out among the courses,
whether from the contents, and then you
can somehow figure out.
So as I said, coming back here, if you are able,
if you are given the choice probability mass function
for discrete random variables, then you
can describe the probability and the relationship
among these two random variables,
how they are distributed, and so on.
And similarly, for the continued random variable,
then you will do it by integration,
but assuming, of course, you have this joy PDF.
So later on, when we come to the random process,
we do need to apply this concept.
But going into the joy PDF will be not so easy,
because from here, you can also define the independence.
It will be based on that.
If these two random variables, they are independent,
then their joy probability will be separate.
So that means you are doing the simple multiplication.
And similarly, if you apply the PDF,
you will become just a product.
But in general, if there is some correlation,
then you will not have that property.
And very often, if you don't have the PDF or the joy PDF
to describe, so what you can do is
lower the requirement.
We are just trying to find out the correlation,
because correlation is easier to measure.
You are only based on the second statistic.
You may not even know the PDF.
And that's how you can define this correlation.
And then also, you can get the covariance.
So again, this concept is extending the one variable one.
You have one variable, you call it variant.
And here, we call it covariance, because we are dealing
with two random variables.
And the formula is somewhat similar.
It will be just here.
I don't know why it is.
Oh, sorry.
Sorry, it's not doing it.
Let's see.
Let's check.
Yeah, the same, because...
Okay, yeah, I think early on,
it should be up here.
So yeah, so that's how we have this relationship
between independent and also correlations.
So there are, yeah.
And of course, the two of them are independent.
Independent is a higher requirement.
And independent will mean the covariance,
there will be not correlated, but not vice versa,
because uncorrelated is only based
on the second-order statistic, where the two random variables
are being independent, based on the period.
Yeah, so I think this is the XIGs.
I remember I did last time, but you can try it out
as a good XIGs.
And moving on is the more difficult concept
is the stochastic or random process.
So assuming you have some knowledge now
about random variables.
So the random process is, you can
consider there is a time variant random variable.
So you introduce another index of the time.
It's not necessarily our continued time.
It can be just the, it could be a sequence,
or it could be not necessarily the continued time
or discrete time.
It's just another index.
And I always like to compare this
with what you're learning from, I think all of you
should be familiar, image and video, you see.
So you can think about a video signal, which
is a moving image, you see.
Each time, if you freeze the time,
you are taking one frame of the video signal
and which becomes one image.
And anyway, I'll go on to the next moment.
Take another image.
And similarly here is a random process
is the one the random variable keep changing over time.
And that's how you, if you look at these pictures,
you will see it will be as a function of time.
It could be continued, could be discrete,
could be other index, just days and so on.
So the idea here is if you, for example, you
fix one time, say call it T1, then the random process
becomes just a random variable.
The outcome, it all depends on something
like you flip a coin or you throw a dice and so on.
We cannot predetermine it, but we
should have some PDF or some other statistic to describe it.
On the other hand, because being random,
you see, it generates many of these realizations.
So for each of the realizations, you will be just,
it will become a function over time.
It will be no longer random.
You take one realization.
Just like, for example, again, you throw the coin, you see.
So you throw it once, you already know one outcome.
Your coin, say, fades, and then you continue throwing.
You throw it first time, second time, and so on.
So you keep writing down.
It could be tail, face, then face, face, tail, tail, again.
So that will become one realization.
It will be a function of the time.
So that's why we describe it as this.
So P here is not random, where S is a random variable.
And more importantly, if you fix T,
you will become a random variable, just one.
On the other hand, if you fix, if you take one realization out
of this random variable, and let the time keep changing,
it will be a normal function of the time,
like become probably unlikely to be a sideways, but yeah.
Sometimes it could be like a sideways.
If you have a sideways with a random face,
then it will become a sideways.
So you need to know this, extending the concept
of random variable to be a sequence.
And that's why this wide noise sequence is also very important.
You can view the wide noise as a sequence of random variable.
And each index itself is a random variable.
And this random variable, according to the index,
it also keeps changing.
And that's why we have this IID, identical and independent
distribution IID, which is very important.
So again, here, we are taking it one, say,
continuous random process.
So what we do is, as I already mentioned,
if you take one particular time sample,
it will become a random variable.
Then you can also consider the, say, for example,
the N's moment at that particular time incident.
So what you'll do is almost the same as before,
except you need to take out this.
So then you can also take the statistical or example
means and mean squared and statistical or example
barrier and so on.
So the definition will be similar.
But the difference here is at two different times,
you'll need to understand these two random variables.
So you can define, for example, correlations and so on,
based on that.
But because they are generated from the same random process,
and we call this auto correlation.
That's different from the cross correlation,
because you can get two different random process.
Then you'll do the correlation at different time.
So that's how the definitions and so on.
And all these are similar.
And cross correlation is because they
come from two different process and also
measure at different time.
So that's cross.
So it become a little bit more complicated.
If you're dealing with random process,
there will be more combinations and so on.
And the definition here are similar.
So you can, yeah.
And this stationary stochastic process
it become very difficult if you are looking at the choice
period, because there will be many combination
and usually very difficult to calculate.
So what we do, we are not really looking into that.
We are looking at those based on the second order
statistic, which is some kind of a weaker requirement, which
is just based on the auto correlation and the covariant.
You'll be just looking at, for example,
we start with auto correlation.
Then we can define the second order correlation at t1.
And now we are looking at the time sample.
So at this t1, you add some time interval called tau
to the next moment, we call it t1 plus tau.
So therefore, if it turns out to be the correlation only
depends on how much this difference of this interval,
say, for example, from 1 to 2, then the time difference
is 1.
And then if the correlation you try to measure from 2 to 3,
if the difference also 1, then it
turns out to be all this, as long as the difference
in this interval is the same, you will get the same result.
So this is a very important process
we call this stationary.
And that's the other than this second order statistical way
also require the mean of this, the white sense
or weakly stationary, which we don't need the joy PDF.
The mean value of this variable, t value,
it gives you the constant value.
That means it doesn't matter whether it's
1 second or 10 seconds or so.
It will become constant.
But you take note, this random variable
you say is not a constant.
It's the expectation of this.
So don't get confused.
And similarly, you have the variance
of this at one particular t1.
Your measure is also being constant.
And this autocorrelation, it will be what I say,
it only depends on the interval.
And you can see these three conditions
not fully independent of each other.
In fact, you get from two, you may
be able to define the third one.
So these are some of the exercises.
To get a better understanding of random process,
we have some example.
For example, you look at this random process.
So be careful.
If you look at the random process defined by a formula,
you have to be careful to look at each of the parameters
or the variable, the meaning of each of them.
Typically, t will always use that.
Or later on, for discrete time, we use n.
You refer to the time index.
But other than that, you can have some other parameter a.
a is the amplitude.
And this omega g log, which is from the cosine function
with frequency.
And phi will be the phase.
So for cosine function, you always
have these three, amplitude, frequency, and phase.
And then you need to know which one constant.
That means they are deterministic,
where which one is random.
Of course, in the normal deterministic case,
all of them, they are all constant, non-random.
So that's why we have the deterministic signal.
But assuming this example, omega 0 and this phi,
they are constant.
But a is a random variable.
Then once it's a random variable,
you try to know more.
Typically, we may be given a distribution.
So in this case, it will be a random variable uniformly
distributed, given that.
So now with this, we want to check whether this
is a weakly stationary process.
So these are the things, other than the conceptual level.
You need to build in the knowledge
and then gradually move on to see
how you can actually compute and verify mathematically.
And that's, I should say, probably part of the courses
where you'll learn and you will be
passed either in quiz or in the final exam papers.
Something similar, like given this,
and how are you going to apply the condition to check.
Then, of course, you need to be familiar with your learning
before calculus, how to do integrations,
and the very simple function, sine, cosine, and so on.
So for example, you do that by taking the mean first.
And then it turns out to be the mean is still
a function of t, then, of course, not a constant.
And this is, they don't need to check the other.
You only, if one of the conditions is not satisfied,
then you can stop here.
So again, coming to the same here,
but now if we make this phase now become random,
where the other two are constant.
In this case, it turns out to be, in this case,
it will be weakly stationary.
You can also verify.
And again, you're doing integration,
but you have to be careful to see.
You see here, the integration is with respect
to a, the amplitude.
From capital A here, once it becomes random,
you use a small letter to denote, which is available.
Then here is different, you see, is this phase is random.
So you integrate with respect to that.
And then you all know cosine signal
go over, integrate over one cycle.
It's independent of the phase.
It doesn't matter one cycle, one theory.
The mean is equal to zero, whether you
shift to pi over 4, pi over 2, and so on.
So that's how we get this.
But this is not enough, because you only verify one condition.
And then you'll need to, since the first condition is
satisfied, we continue to look at the second
to see whether, in this case, it turns out to be indeed.
You see, we're applying the t1 and t2.
And then, of course, t2 is t1 minus tau.
This is just differ by tau.
Then we want to see whether it turns out
to be a function of tau, or is there
depending on this t1, because t2 is already substitute by that.
But in this case, it's a little bit more complicated.
You need to know the trigonometric identity
to do integration.
So therefore, you can work out the equal to that.
Then, therefore, it's weakly stationary.
You can verify the other condition
is coming from these two.
So this godicity doesn't mean you
are able to take the mean, the tissue
mean using the ensemble, just using one realization.
But it's long enough.
There is another exercise, verify already provide
a solution.
So I think we can take a break here.
And then we'll continue.
And then by today, the subsequent part
become more important and more mathematical,
which will be the important part of chapter 2 and chapter 3,
power density, spectrum, and so on, and model, and so on.
So yeah, we take a break.
Maybe you can come back at 8 o'clock behind.
7.55, just 14 minutes, a little bit shorter.
Same as before, it's one break, and we can finish early.
OK, any question?
Let me know.
OK.
So let's continue here from here.
I think from this part, we will have more math to.
And also, you go a link more towards what
you learned before, like DSP.
And part one, for example, you had Fourier transforms
and the Z transform, and so on.
But at the same time, we always assume
we are dealing with a random process.
So it's not just a deterministic signal, like sideways,
and so on.
OK.
So I will slow down a little bit from here.
OK, so now what we will discuss in this part two,
we'll always assume our random process is a stationary random
process.
And it's a weekly one.
It's not.
We don't need the joint PDF to be totally independent.
So what we require will be, as we point out early,
the means of this random process will be constant.
And then the covariant will only depend
on the other covariant.
Because we are talking about one random process,
or major different time.
It only depends on the time difference between t1 and t2.
We call it tau.
That's why here.
OK.
So and therefore, you can compare
in a sense about stationary random process
is a little bit similar to sideways, where sideways
deterministic, of course.
But the signal energy is not finite energy.
For example, you learn from the very basic signal and system.
The theoretical signal is infinity energy.
So it will be power type.
So we call that as power type.
Because why infinity energy?
Each period, you'll have some, I mean, talking about sideways.
Each period, you have some finite energy.
But you'll have infinity many periods.
So you'll multiply a constant, multiply infinity large value.
It will become infinity large.
So that's why we call it that.
And stationary random process is similar.
Because the process being stationary
is more or less like keep the process,
will not go to zero.
Or it go to zero very slowly.
So therefore, it's infinity energy signal.
So therefore, we cannot directly take a formation form
of this, the whole random process,
taking that as sequence signal.
But on the other hand, it works only
for stationary random process.
For non-stationary random process,
it may not have this property.
So for stationary random process,
you already know the autocorrelation function.
It will depend only on the time difference of this time.
And actually, this autocorrelation function,
except, is no longer random.
Because it's measure the average,
try to find the average correlation between these two.
The same random process at different time.
So of course, the tau is now reduced
from the two time interval, t1, t2, into just one tau.
So you'll become like a 1D signal.
And this autocorrelation, except, is no longer random.
Even it come from random process.
So this is very important.
But as I emphasize, it only work for stationary random process
if the process is not stationary,
you will not have this property.
So once we have this autocorrelation function,
which is not random, then you can
apply what you learned before.
I assume by now, even if you did not
learn DSP or signaling system before,
after going through pro-wounds part one,
and particularly you all finished assignment one.
So you should know how to do at least this Fourier transform.
All right.
Here we are considering this tau is continue variable.
For discrete time, you will need to do summation.
So this is a very, very basic.
Continue time, you'll do integration,
Fourier transform.
And then this is the very standard one.
And that's why, because this very important,
you see our autocorrelation function here
is not just out of the proof.
It's not a new sequence.
Remember, this comes from a random process.
It comes from a given stationary random process.
So in this way, this Fourier transform,
we define that as a power density function,
power density spectrum of a random process.
It's given by that.
So that's a very important one.
So keep this in mind, because this very basic definition,
we will need that again and again
in the subsequent weeks or chapters.
And once you have this Fourier transform,
you can define the inverse Fourier transform.
That's the very standard one.
And here you can get 2 pi f.
You can also combine that as omega, 2 pi f.
So those are just the different notation.
And then furthermore, there is a very important property.
If you evaluate this tau, make tau equal to 0.
So what do I get?
You will go back.
This tau equal to 0, that means this has become 1.
e to the exponent power of 0 is equal to 1.
So it will be just integrated.
And that gives you a very useful relationship,
because if you go back to the definition here,
I mean, this one is what we evaluated
by the second moment of this random variable.
At any given time t, t can be different time.
So don't get confused.
The tau is at 0.
That means it can be any t at the same t.
So that gives you the average power of the random process.
So therefore, we can see this function.
The distribution of power is a function of frequency,
because you integrate this over all the possible different frequencies.
So that's the average power of this.
So that's how we call this density function.
And then you can also extend it to two random processes.
But again here, we assume they are jointly stationary.
So two different ones, you use the cross power density spectrum.
And again, once you get this cross correlation,
so again, the two random processes are different.
But if you take time difference with time difference of tau,
then it only depends on the time difference tau here.
So you have this.
So once this is well defined, you can again take the Fourier transform
using this formula to get this cross power density spectrum also.
And continue time, you use integration.
Discrete time, you need to use summation.
This is very basic rule.
So here, you can, if you look at the discrete random process,
not necessarily time, just discrete random variable.
Then again, we assume it's stationary.
Why saying stationary?
So therefore, you get this, which now is also a sequence of m.
Then you do the discrete Fourier transform,
because this is discrete time.
But however, in this case, this is not DFT, it's DTFT, discrete time Fourier transform.
It's infinity long.
So therefore, the frequency here still is a continued frequency variable.
If you have a finite length, you become DFT, which gives you a discrete frequency.
So that's a difficult part in signaling system.
You have so many combinations, and it's very interesting.
When I, for those students under SPML, I go through all your CVs.
Typically, I find also signaling system is usually year two.
You study signaling system first, then go to DSP.
It turned out to be for most students, you get higher grade for DSP compared to signaling system.
The main reason is maybe too many concepts, too many operations, too many properties.
And the same as NTU here, we find second year signaling system, not so easy to teach.
But then you come to DSP, it's more focused.
You are focused in filters and so on.
So coming back into that, so this is infinity sum of this sequence.
The inverse Fourier transform is an integration because the f here is a continued frequency variable.
So that's why you have this.
Similarly, if you make n equal to 0, which gives you the average power, it will be just let this term equal to 1, you'll get this.
So now you can also work on some exercises.
I think this example is what we did before.
And now the random is this one.
And then this W is defined as white noise random process.
And then you have these two uncorrelated because we are dealing with white sense stationary.
Then we have to determine the autocorrelation of the Y.
Y is the sum of these two and also the power spectral density of this.
So this is one of the very important examples.
You pay attention on how to solve it.
So we already showed this is white sense stationary.
And this Wn is also white sense stationary.
Then, following our early exercises, you can conclude this.
The sum will be simply a sum of these two because they are, let's see, it's very important, they are uncorrelated.
If they are correlated, then they will be different.
So you will have a cluster.
Correlation, remember, is a second order property.
So you need to do the power of two.
But being uncorrelated, you can simply sum the autocorrelation of each of the X and W.
So therefore, this one you know we already derived.
For cosine, the autocorrelation will be a cosine independent of the phase.
And for the white noise, it will be a delta function.
So that is very important.
Also, the white noise sequence, it keeps going on, you see, take the value, it's not zero.
But the white noise means that if only the delta function, so you know the meaning,
is when n equals zero, it will be equal to, for this greater one, it's equal to one.
And n not equal to zero is zero.
So that means you only have, you only correlated to accept.
As long as you take a different m and n value, one and two, or zero to one, so it will be zero.
That's why I call it white.
So this is the one here.
Then now you take DTFT of this, because this is being described.
This sequence is no longer random, you see.
You can also see here.
This is a proper cosine function of m, you see.
There's nothing random here.
Similarly, this delta m is just equal to one, and m equals zero, and zero elsewhere.
So then we can take DTFT of this, and in this case, we get the power spectrum density of Yn quite easily.
And I hope you remember, for cosine signal, it will give you two delta functions at that frequency.
And this delta function is different from this one.
So don't get confused.
A continuous variable delta function, this delta value means it's very infinitely large, you see.
So those, if you still remember, the signaling system for delta t, for example, is infinitely large.
But when you integrate, it becomes one.
It's one impulse, singular value.
Where this one is described time, this delta m, m equals zero is not infinity, it's one.
So therefore, if you take the DTFT, then this one will just take the constant, because this is one.
So this is what very basic we will learn in the subsequent chapter for power spectrum estimation.
It will be based on this relationship.
Any questions? Anything?
Now we move on to this more difficult concept, at least.
But this, on the other hand, is also very important if you try to get a better understanding of stationary random process.
So you see here, now we link to what you learned before, like Fiota's invertible linear system.
So this part is a good combination of random process and proper linear system.
Actually, this so-called innovation representation is, we try to model this stationary random process.
You can think about it is, the input is white noise, again, so you all know we are talking about discrete time.
The input is white noise, then goes through a linear causal filter, then, of course we assume the filter is a proper one,
it's not just a constant, then of course your output will be, if you go through a constant, then of course the white noise will produce another white noise.
But if you go through a proper filter, which is the impulse response, then you all know the output of this will be a convolution of this white noise input
and the impulse response of this linear causal filter.
So remember, I emphasized at the beginning, when we talk about system, the system or the filter is a proper one, is a deterministic one.
Just take it as what you learned from part one or from your undergraduate DSP course.
So this is very important, you can think about, in this case, you inject white noise and then go through a linear system, you will produce stationary random process.
And then, if you recall, in the deterministic case, I think this is also very important, you introduce this impulse response.
So all about that, step one is, your input is a uni-impulse function, it's not random.
Then you go through a linear causal filter, then the output is the meaning of impulse response, meaning the impulse function or signal goes through a filter,
then the output is this, h of k.
But now our input, we introduce white noise input, which is different from what you learned earlier, because this is random.
So in this case, you get the convolution, and this x of n here is precisely what we are trying to classify, because the stationary random process is still a little bit abstract, very hard to describe.
So what we are doing here is, we already know property of white noise, and we already know linear causal filter.
Then it happens to be, you're passing this as input, goes through this linear causal filter, then we precisely produce the output, which is of course not an impulse response, but it will be a stationary random process.
And that's why we are using this innovation representation concept.
And furthermore, if you assume the filter, so this is very important, it is the inverse, if the filter, you take the inverse, that means if the filter, the g-load is also stable, it's within the unit circle.
You can take the inverse, and it's also a property defined linear causal filter, then you can do the reverse.
Now you have this stationary random process, making it as input, you go through that, then you produce output, which is white noise, so it's a reverse process.
So this is, actually to be honest, it took me quite some time to digest and get a good understanding of this.
Okay, so let's see how we handle this.
So as usual, we assume we have this saying, which is a weakly stationary process, then you have the autocorrelation.
So that part is not a problem, we know that by definition.
Then we can also take the power spectral density by, yeah, so this is a very important one, I believe you're already familiar.
I need to emphasize again, the z-transform and Fourier transform, they differ by, z is a complex variable, it's a z-plane, it's a complex, a real part, imaginary part.
And then for continuity, you look at the Laplace transform and the Fourier transform.
But for discretized signal, we look at the z-transform, and you evaluate along the unit circle, so this is the unit circle.
Forget the Fourier transform, so this relationship from, again, I emphasize, from here to z, you just simply change f into this z variable by extending the one along the unit circle into a more general, complex variable.
And, of course, vice versa is easier, once you get the z-transform, you let z equal to this, then it's easier, you evaluate along this.
But sometimes you are given power spectral density, which you need to express as this, it will be always a function of this complex variable, then you identify this, replace by z, you will get this.
So this is a big similar, you learn DSP, or signaling system, you have the relationship of z-transform and the discretized Fourier transform.
Where z-transform is referred to the discrete sequence, discrete time sequence, not continuity.
So now assume this is lower and continuous for all this, here is a normalized frequency of 1 over 2.
And then we also assume, now be careful, this is a function of z.
If you take the log, assume, you take log is still analytic, and that means you have, you can take derivative of many, all the order, 0, 1, 2, and so on.
In a newer region, I mean this region is, remember z is a complex plane, so you have two rings, one is R1 and the other is R2.
And then these rings must include the unit circle in the middle, because R1 is smaller than 1, and R2 is greater than 1, so that means the R equal to 1 is inside this ring.
So therefore, once you satisfy this condition, you can take the Laurent series.
So Laurent series differs from the normal series, you expand it to the z-transform, but the power is not just 0 to say the minor infinity large.
It covers all the possible powers, m is from minor infinity to infinity, that means if this is analytic, it can expand here, because this is a function.
So just like you expand it into infinity series, and then we get this coefficient in the series expansion.
Okay, so that means, so I emphasize this, I repeat this again, this is a proper analytic function, but assume we can expand it, satisfy this series, instead of looking this as a function, we can make it just infinity sum of this, and then at the same time we get the coefficient is depending only on m in the expansion.
So therefore, in this case, you can also see this is a sequence with z-transform of this, if you compare with the formula in the z-transform.
Okay, so therefore, now going back, remember, once you have the z-available, you can evaluate along the unit circle, this is unit circle.
Then we get somehow substitute this, it will become like the frequency variable, and then from here you are getting the inverse Fourier transform, where this looks like the Fourier transform.
Therefore, this looks like b, it's the Greek letter of b, this is a Fourier coefficient, if you are expanding this, this is a theoretical signal, because you evaluate by unit circle, every one circle, one time, you repeat, keep going.
And then you can see, we assume our filter is a real coefficient, so therefore this is a real and even function of that.
Then we can see this is also real, and it's a symmetry also for all the m.
So therefore, if you look at equation 51, you see here, you can, this is very important, you see, summation, if you take the summation topic into three terms.
Then one is a Z log, you see, you have this Z log, you get the summation, m always goes through the Z log in the middle.
And then, if you look at those positive index, you see, so starting from Z log, you go to the right side, it will be m from one to infinity large, you will get it.
Similarly, on the other side, you will have minus one to minus infinity, but we change the variables, we make the minus m, we call it again also m, so don't worry about that, you see the power is now changed from minus m to m.
So that means the index, you want to get a good understanding, you first call it k first, k equal to minus m, then after that, the k is the index, m is the index, you call back m, because it's a summation anyway, the index.
So therefore, this is what we are looking for, you see, so for this one, because this is a constant, e to just one value, we call that as sigma w power two, making this as like the value of the noise.
And then, you see here, this is only, it depends only on Z to the power minus m, so we call that as H of Z, and similarly, you see, the difference between this one and this one is only Z, if you call this,
so we always define Z to the power of minus index as calling H of Z, so don't get confused, and then, if our Z now is all positive, we call it Z to the power minus one, so this is a convention for filters,
also, we always take Z to the power minus one, minus two, and so on, but we normally define H of Z, where the other one is the opposite.
So you see here, this is borrowing from the log manipulation, we managed to see this one can decompose into one positive constant, and the product of this H of Z, and H Z to the power minus one, so this is a very important concept.
So that means through this filter, you can get the output, which is expanding the power density spectrum into this, from F change to Z, you will get the relationship from here.
Okay, and our H of Z is just equal to that, and here, we assume this is causal and stable, with all the poles within this, because, remember, we required this condition in our early derivation,
and then, if we further assume this given filter, you see, also has all the zeros inside the unit circle, and by definition, this is, we call it a minimum phase.
So I think in some filter discussions, sometimes you discuss this, but not often.
Here, in our contact, it's very important, this minimum phase means all the zeros are also inside this, because, why? Because later, you will see we need to inverse the filter, so the zeros will become poles.
And if the zeros are inside that, I mean, once you inverse this filter, you also get a stable causal filter.
Okay, and then, we also assume it doesn't have zeros on this.
And finally, if we have this, you know, as a function of Z, now we change it, evaluate along this unit circle, we will get this relationship.
Well, another important result, if you are in the Z domain, so one is function of Z, and then here you change Z to the power of Z to the power of minus one.
So the coefficients are all the same, only the variable changes, but if you evaluate along the unit circle, then this Z to the power of minus one, the function, you will be just the complex conjugate of this edge of F.
So this is very important, you have this relationship only along the unit circle F, not for the general Z, so be careful.
And you all know the property, you have a product of these two, that means you are taking the absolute value of the magnitude raised to the power of two, because this is a complex number.
A complex function, you have this relationship.
So therefore, here we can conclude the weakly stationary random process, I think, can be represented as output of causal filter.
Then, which filter? It depends on either you specify a random process, you will get the corresponding filter, or vice versa, once you define a causal filter, then you inject white noise, you will produce a stationary random process.
It's not arbitrary, it's related by this, when you excite with the white noise random process.
And this one, the value of this white noise is just equal to this, so this is a very important concept.
And then, in general, if you are talking about the edge of J is not the rational function, it will be very hard to handle.
So in practical applications, typically we will restrict the power density of this weakly random process.
It's a rational function, so that will be easier, and that's how, in this case, we can get a filter linked to a via filter more closely.
And then, we also assume the rules of this, our inside unit circle.
That means, you all know how to get the rules for polynomial, the z-plane.
So therefore, the linear filter, you see, so remember, when we talk about power spectral density, they always have this pair, bj multiplied by bj to the power minus one.
But when we talk about linear filters generating this, we are only taking this bj over aj.
That means a proper rational function involving, for example, here is always delay, so it will be a causal filter.
But if you combine these two, there is no causal one.
And this concept of being causal or not is also very important.
And then, this is coming back to our normal FIR filter.
I think part one doesn't discuss much. It's mostly on FIR filter, but I assume you'll learn DSP, like this, extending FIR filter to IR filter.
It's just from polynomial to rational function, so it's a little bit more complicated.
Okay, so these are the filter coefficients, and we'll determine the location of the Z log and poles of this.
So any problems so far?
So this innovation concept is just a bridge to link wide-sang stationary random process and linear filter and, of course, the wide noise, so the three of them in one.
Okay, so coming back to some, these are more related to DSP.
Here, our hj is causal, stable, and minimum phase. Assume this is satisfied.
Minimum phase being the Z log, except also within the unit circle.
A filter can be stable, but not minimum phase.
You know filter, being stable or not, we only look at the poles of the filter.
We don't care the Z log, the location of the Z log.
But if you are inverting this filter, now it becomes very important, so we require this minimum phase.
Remember, minimum phase?
Okay, so if you satisfy this, then you'll take the inverse, this is a rational function, you take the inverse, stay a rational function.
It's also causal, stable, and minimum phase, the linear system.
So therefore, you can see the random process uniquely represents the statistical property of the innovation process, WN.
So the WN here is white noise, but because this is related to our random process by going through the stationary random process.
So that means you can think about one stationary random process, it corresponds to one special white noise.
Because white noise, you can also have different behavior.
That's why sometimes we can have two white noise which are independent, uncorrelated.
So yeah, don't get confused.
So in that case, the innovation process is specifically linked to one of the random processes.
That's why we call it uniquely, and vice versa also.
Okay, so any questions here? Anything you get confused?
If not, then we can continue here. These are somewhat easier.
So now if we look at an example, we have a causal, stable, minimum phase linear system.
So you need to learn how to identify, given the product of this, you need to figure out which part is the minimum phase and the other one is not.
So you can check both the zeros if you look at the two factors here.
So if you look at this one, the zeros of this will be equal to 1 over 3.
So therefore, it meets our requirement of being minimum phase.
Of course, the poles you also must make sure are within the unit circle.
So in this case, it will be 0, 6, because 0, 6 multiplied by 1 over 0, 6 will be equal to 1.
But this one is not, because the zeros of this one is 3, because 1 minus 3 over 3, because this is to the power of z, not to the power of z, z to the power of minus 1.
So therefore, given the product, you need to identify which one is gz, and the other part must be g to the power of z, to the power of minus 1.
And now we can extend this concept further to the case where the input is one random process, goes through a linear system, then goes through the output.
So you learn this part. Always try to learn, although it's different, because here we are dealing with random signals.
But some of the concepts are very closely related to the case where you are dealing with DSP.
For example, let me go back to DSP. You have unit impulse as a special input.
You go through a linear system, you generate the unit impulse response as output.
So this unit impulse response, in a sense, categorizes your linear system.
And once you get that, you can change the input to other types of input.
It can be a unit step function, or even a square wave, and so on.
But in that case, the output will be another output. It will no longer be the unit impulse response.
You will need to do the convolution.
And similarly, in the z domain, it's the same.
If you inject a unit impulse response, the z transform is of that one equal to 1.
So the output is just equal to h of z.
So that's why, if you look at the input, it's white noise only here.
The output is just mainly determined by the filter transform function or the frequency response.
But in the case of a random variable, we are always handling second-order statistics.
So you need to, instead of h of f, you will become absolute value, raise power to that.
So that's the difference and similarity.
So in a sense, we have a similar relationship.
If now the input is not just white noise, but proper, white things stationary, stationary process,
you get autocorrelation function and the z transform of this.
Then, you can see the output of this going through this filter will be h of z multiplied by h z to the power minus 1.
Then, you need to remember the multiplied by this.
So again, if you go back to the normal deterministic signal, you only have h of z.
That's a relationship.
But now, we're dealing with stationary process.
They always come out with this product.
And then from here, as I say, you need to know the relationship from z to this.
So you substitute this, you go back to this part, the same as what we did before.
Except this one here, you will get a proper so-called power spectrum density of this.
W here is another general white things stationary process.
Again, as an example, so this is, you see, we look at now, w of n is a stationary process.
We have this autocorrelation function, which is non-ringdom.
You see, it's an intake of n, n is absolute value of n.
So that means it's a symmetry, positive, negative, you get the same value.
And also, we assume this constant, smaller than 1.
Then, first we need to compute that.
And then, after that, we have a simple linear system, which is here.
Then we excite with this, w n.
If alpha equal to half, we determine the power density spectrum of this, autocorrelation of this, and also the value.
So let's see what we can do here.
First, we can get the z transform of this.
So this is also an example to illustrate what I derived early in the innovation representation.
In a sense, similar, you see, when you're dealing with infinity sum, the index from minus infinity to infinity, it's better to break down into either two sums or three terms.
So here, we look at the negative one first, which is n minus infinity to here.
But, so you see here, for this alpha, the n is absolute value.
So you always, for the negative one, you will get minus n, being absolute value.
And for the z to the power minus n, you keep the same index.
Now the other part, you see, n from zero to infinity.
This one, you take absolute value, you become alpha of n, because n now is a positive index, so you don't need absolute value.
But the z is, based on this formula, is always to the power minus n.
And then, you see here, I want to try to combine these two.
So how do you do that?
You look at this. This one is n from zero to infinity.
This one is starting from minus one.
So I need to add one more constant term, like m equal to zero, into this one.
So that your one term will become m.
First, you change the variable. That's a very trivial one.
You see, all these are minus n.
If you want to be sure, don't get confused.
You let minus m into k first.
Then after that, you become k, and k is from zero to here.
Then after that, you change back, because we want to combine these two.
But since you add one term, the constant term, which is equal to one, you add minus one here.
So therefore, this minus one comes from adding one more term.
And now, these two, you can use the geometric summation to sum these.
And since our alpha is absolute value smaller than one, it converts into this.
Similarly for this one, it also converts.
Then this is a simple combination.
The denominators are not the same. You have three terms here.
You make them as common denominators.
Then a very simple algebraic will leave it to you to work out.
You can see this combined into this one.
But you must have a z to the power of minus one, and the one z to the power of one.
Because in this expression, you cannot cancel out one of them.
So that's why you have this term here.
Now, this is what you can do.
I don't think you can further simplify. It's already in one rational function of z to the power, z to the power of minus one, and z to the power of one.
However, if you are trying to get the power density spectrometry, this is in the z domain.
To do that, remember always substitute z to the power of e to the power of z to pi f.
So this is evaluated along the unit circle.
And then, once you do that, then you can see, I hope you know the Euler formula.
How to convert from e to the, let me see whether, I can see whether this one still work or not.
Okay, maybe it works.
Yeah, so let's see whether, I can switch.
Okay, so we have one here.
So, see here, if you have z equal to, looks like, I don't know why, it can't rotate, okay good.
Yeah, it looks like an inverse.
I hope this is, this time is, okay, okay, correct, this I auto-focus.
Again, if z equal to e to the power of, e to the power of j two pi f.
So what happen, then of course, z to the power of minus one, you see, you change the minus j two pi f.
Because if you are along the unit circle, you see, and that's precisely this become the, remember, conjugate, you see.
So that's how the conjugate also come from here.
Now if you substitute into that, all the other are constant, so we don't care.
What we have here is alpha, then we multiply by e to the power of minus j two pi f plus e to the power of j two pi f.
So this is what we have, the very famous Euler formula.
You have this complex sideways, complex exponential signal, divided by two.
That will give you the cosine, you see, no longer j, it will be two pi f.
So that's how this come from.
Therefore, of course, we don't have divided by two, then if you multiply two to the other side, it will produce this.
So this is the term when you substitute z into this using this Euler formula.
So that will become cosine two pi f multiplied by two, because we don't divide by two, then you move the two over there.
So the rest will be the same.
So this is a very useful relationship, you should know how to derive and apply.
Okay, so let's continue.
And then, in that case, our z transform.
So see here, you go back, so here you need to be familiar with how to juggle between z and f by looking at the formula.
So therefore, you have h, z, and this part.
Now if you look at the z domain, we have the h, z, then you have this.
Now you want to go back to the power density of this, you move on to the z, change the e to this.
And then you have, again, because due to this property, you simplify, you end up with, you all become like the term here, become cosine, like cosine two pi f.
And then, you use trigonometric identity, you can make it cosine pi f power of two.
So that's another relationship.
So the denominator looks very similar, although the values are different.
So that's how you, so this part we already done, but the other one is similar, you can substitute and accept numerator difference here.
So I hope you try to digest, and this part is new in this year.
This year, previous year, I only write this in the notes, so I think it may be helpful by putting it into lecture notes.
So therefore, if you do the partial fraction of this, you can, that's again a simple mess.
I hope you know how to explain from the product into sum.
And then, once you explain the sum of two terms, you need to determine this a and b.
How to do that, you add the two again to become the same denominator, and then compare coefficient, you're able to get this a and b.
So therefore, you get this a equal to that, b equal to that, so therefore you can explain it into the sum of two terms.
And then, directly, now you try to make this into the same form as what we derived earlier.
You can check, like, consider there is a formula, the Z-transform formula, then you can get the relationship, so you end up with this.
And finally, from here, the output value, your value m equal to zero, so therefore this becomes one.
You get any node zero value raised to power zero, it will be equal to one, so you're simply adding this to become 25.
Okay, I think we still have some time. We can go through the final part of this linear system.
The several process are AR, MA, and ARMA. So this is very much related to IIR filters, so I hope you have some knowledge.
But anyway, next week, we will still go through in more detail, so this is more like an introduction.
So this is like the IIR filter, or you look at the difference equation, you have this denominator, this is a numerator.
So depending on whether you have all the coefficients, node zero, or some of them become just one, you have three processes, AR, MA, and ARMA.
So first, this is AR. AR is one, just poles only, the denominator only, so the numerator is a constant, that is easy.
And therefore, this is all poles filter, the relationship is just like that.
Then, from here, you can see the noise-whitening filter, for generating this innovation is an all-zero filter, because this is all poles.
This is all poles, and you take the inverse, it will be A of Z, then the denominator equal to one, it's all zero.
So, yeah, and then we move on to the case moving average, MA. I mean, if the denominator equal to one, a constant, our filter, you just have the numerator.
And if you have numerator, this is what you should be familiar, the FIR filter probably spent quite a few weeks talking about that, and your assignment is like that, so I'm sure you do that.
And vice versa, you want to do a noise-whitening filter, you take the inverse, it will become all poles. So this MA and AR, they are just inverse of each other.
Finally, this is more general one, MA is the, you have a proper numerator and denominator, so you explain it, you have this and this part.
And then, now, if you want to inverse, of course, your A of Z denominator become numerator, and similarly, numerator become denominator.
And that's why this is pole-zero filters, you have proper poles, proper zero.
So in order to make sure the inverse is also stable and causal, you have to satisfy the minimum phase condition.
So again here, we want to briefly introduce the relationship between filter parameter and autocorrelation sequence.
So this is the part where you need to mix up, combine different knowledge, again here, because differential equation, I think you all know, this is nothing random here.
Again, it's just a proper IR filter.
But now, we start to introduce this correlation, because remember the input sequence here, W and X, they are in the sense random.
So being random, we can, for example, we multiply by XN minus N, so you see.
So therefore, now that you apply this expectation, so this right here is expectation is like taking the mean, it's very important.
So therefore, once you take expectation, then based on the definition, this give you this, and remember our process is stationary, a wide sense stationary random process, then we can get autocorrelation.
Similarly here, and this is a cross-correlation.
And then we know the relationship XN, then we can also show how to handle this, you see here.
You have this, and then this is the, you know, the W goes through a filter, produce H of N, so we have this convolution, substitute that here.
And then, you can bring in the expectation inside the H, because this is not random, you see.
So remember, not random, you can bring it outside the E, but those part random, you cannot, so this is a very basic property.
So therefore, you're bringing in, and this is being white noise. White noise means, you see, it will produce delta functions.
So that's delta function, the value equal to that.
And so therefore, this equation, you can simplify into this, so that means from the difference equation here, we know the coefficient here, then we can work out the relationship of the autocorrelation.
And here, the cross-correlation, because of the spatial WKs, we don't have here, we only need this, so that means this gives you the similar relationship with the difference equation.
So not the same, but yeah.
And also, take note of this, we are assuming we are dealing with causal filter, causal filter means H N equal to zero for this.
So therefore, you end up with our autocorrelation of X and X, it has three forms.
If N greater than Q, you only have this part here, so that's easy. This one is zero.
But if N is between zero and Q, you will need to take this, this part is no longer zero, you have to bring this on here.
But how about N is smaller than zero? Remember, autocorrelation is always even function, so you can get from the other side, you only need to work half.
So that's the relationship.
Okay, finally, the exercises here.
We want to, it's similar to the example given early, maybe I don't have to give the solution here, maybe I give you time to do while waiting for pass.
So perhaps we dismiss a little bit early, it's very similar to the exercises early, but you want to make sure our omega here is just 2 pi F.
But now the order is a bit higher, so you need to think about how to change from the unit circle into the Z variable, so get the AR process and also that.
So you can do that then, maybe next week we can come back and check, probably some of you can show your solution.
We try to interact at least for those who come here.
Okay, so I think the time is up, so I promise you to end a little bit early than 9.20.
So any questions? Of course, there are always some students staying back, so it's not early time for me, early time for most of you.
Okay, you have questions? Stay back. If not, then you take your time to do these exercises.
So next week we come back, we move on to Chapter 2, as I said before.
Okay, I'll see you next week. Don't forget the quiz will be Week 12.
I'll see you next week, and thanks for coming.
Thank you.
.