All right, let's start. So welcome back, and this is actually my lecture five, because this
is actually lecture four, this is week five. So far, we have already finished all of the
so-called review of the fundamentals of signal processing. If you remember, from week two
to week four, we started by talking about representation of signals. DTFT, DFT, these
are basically the method you can use to represent signals, not in time domain, but in the frequency
domain. So you should be familiar with all of these transforms, inverse transforms, property
of the transform spectrums, how to interpret the spectrums, and what are the basically
problems, right? We talk about thumb-pulling theorem, aliasing properties, and that's why
we say that in the actual signal processing pipeline, there was always the anti-aliasing
filter, if you still remember, that's a low-pass filter before your sampling, right? There's
also a reconstruction filtering, which is at the end, right? And later, we talk about
the system, right? How can we represent a filter in frequency domain, in time domain?
We also mentioned that there are many ways to, and how can you convert one way to the
other, right? Difference equation, impulse response, these are in time domain, spectrum
response, and also Z-transform, right? These are in the frequency domain. We also look
at why certain representation is better, and last week, we also talked a little bit about
the filter design, right? So I actually decided to simplify that part. So windowing method
is the only method you need to know. You forget about other, you know, more complicated method
because that's not the focus, right? But starting from today, you will see completely new content,
all right? So I don't know how many of you may, some of you may learn this multi-array
processing, but it will be new to most of you, all right? So I'm going to kind of slow
down a little bit and make sure all of us understand, you know, starting from basic things to more
advanced things, right? And the same principle, if you have any question, all right, raise
your hand, I'm happy you entrust me. So I can also share the question to other students,
right? So make sure everybody understands everything, all right? So starting from today,
we're going to look at this topic of multi-array signal processing. When we talk about the
rate, right, when we talk about how fast the signal can be processed or how fast the signal
is represented, right? So we already have, you know, you should have something related to it,
if you remember, like in the sampling theorem part, we say there is a sampling rate that we
need to satisfy, right? The Nyquist rate, we still remember. And some of the sampling can be
faster, some of them can be slower, right? So this sampling rate is actually the rate we're
talking about, right? But if you remember, in the fundamental part, every time we sample the
signals, we won't change the rate anymore, right? All of this filtering, all of this, you know,
processing, they will not change the sampling rate, right? If you remember, I say once you
sample, you cannot change that F, Ft, right? The only thing you change is like, you know,
zero paddings, you can make more zeros, but you won't really change the rate in the beginning.
So, but now I'm telling you that actually sometimes it's possible and also it's necessary to change
the rate when you process the signal, right? And today we're going to learn why, I mean,
in the first place, why we need to do it. And then what is this multirate signal processing,
right? This is actually the part one today. So we all learned this, right? Fundamental
concept in DSP, you need to basically make sure your sampling rate, this is Nyquist condition,
will be, need to be larger or equal to two times your maximum frequency bandwidth of your signal,
right? This is the necessary condition to avoid distortion, right? In other words, aliasing,
right, to avoid that. So, and of course, you cannot make your sampling rate super high because you
have to pay the addition, accordingly, the computational cost, right? So basically, you need
to find a suitable rate, which is kind of a tradeoff between computational efficiency and also
avoid of the distortion. In other words, make sure there's enough accuracy of your processing
system, right? So this is actually the design or the philosophy we actually need to follow
based on the sampling theory, right? But, you know, in practice, right, this sampling rate,
well, first of all, the input rate of many different applications can be, has been already
predefined, right? For example, if you have a sensor or you have some kind of a receiver, right?
They may already predefined or predetermined the sampling rate for you for specific input.
But sometimes, right, a different sampling rate will also be needed, right? For example,
in your processor or maybe at output side, determined by those functional blocks of your system,
right? So there could be a mismatch comparing your input sampling rate, signal rate, or
comparing to your processing rate, right? So there could be a mismatch. I mean, this is one
example, like, I don't know for this generation, how many of you have listened to a CD, but for
my generation, we do play CD when we were a child. And you know that for CD, right, there's a sampling
rate, which is 44 kilohertz. But if you talk about the radio frequency for broadcasting, it's
actually lower, right? 32 kilohertz. You know, digital radio tape, it's another kind of, you know,
frequency, which is 48 kilohertz. So even though all of them are sound, are acoustic signals,
right? The actual rate are different. But in practice, for example, you want to design a
hi-fi system, you may need to unify them, right, in one system. So this is one example to show that
you may need to handle different data source or signal source with different rates, but eventually
you want to handle them in one system, right? So this is one of the scenarios that you have to
convert them into one rate rather than working in different rates, right? So this is actually one
of the scenarios that why multi-ray signal processing is needed, is based on the facts, right, in the
actual system. So, you know, yeah, this is actually another example where your bandwidth of low pass
filter, right? So imagine this is your input signal, where as you can see that the frequency, maximum
frequency is pretty high, right? It's already reached, you know, fs divided by two, but no pass
filter, right, could give you a cutoff frequency that is smaller than the W, right? The original,
you know, I mean bandwidth. So it is possible that other processing system after the filter
may use a smaller sampling frequency, right? For example, if you want to have some full-load
processing, they may give you an even lower kind of a sampling frequency. So in this case,
you are going to work on different kind of rates along the system, even for the same input signal,
right? It depends on how many kind of a model you have in the processing pipeline. So as a
designer, you need to think about how to effectively reduce the overall computational complex, right,
throughout the whole system, right, to kind of, by using a suitable sampling frequency to,
for not only the application, but also the other processing applications, right? So this is actually
another motivation that even for a single source of signal, depends on the fact that there could
be multiple processing stages in the pipeline, and then we have to unify the rate required by
different modules in the processing pipeline, right? But how to do it? This is another kind of a
question, right, to do it. And in general, right, basically this multi-read signal processing is
kind of a frequently used even in the same system, and the deal with different rates, in other words,
to minimize the overall complexity to achieve a susceptible performance, right? And this process,
I mean, the process of converting the signal, let's say from the given sampling rate to another,
right? So let's say you are started by a rate, let's say, F A, you want to convert it to F B,
right? This conversion process is referred as sampling rate conversion, okay? So this is not
like sampling, okay, let me just clarify that. This sampling we learned in the first lecture is to
convert an analog signal to a digital signal, right? Just one rate, you only get one rate
from analog to digital. That rate, sampling rate, will be the rate of your output digital signal,
right? So here, we're not talking about analog signal, it's actually from digital to digital,
all right, discrete signal to discrete signal. But the rate has been changed, all right, the
sampling rate has been changed. So the conversion here, so called sampling rate conversion, is to
take a discrete signal with a specific rate and output another discrete signal with a different
rate, right? So this is actually what we call sampling rate conversion, right? This is different
from sampling, all right? And if you have a system involving or using multiple processing or
sampling rate, you can call this system a multirate digital signal processing system, right? So basically
what we experienced so far, right, before this lecture, all of the system we talked about before
this lecture are single rate system, right? We haven't talked about multirate, but later you will
see what can be different if we move on to a multirate signal processing system, right? But
as long as you involve this multiple rates, it's qualified for a multirate system, all right?
So, yeah, so actually, right, so basically sampling, this sampling rate conversion can also be
realized by passing a digital signal, passing a signal through a DA converter, right? Because later
you will see that actually the main components are very similar, right? Even though the definition
of them is different, right? And so basically if we can do this sampling rate conversion,
which is normally required in a complex digital signal processing system, the conversion is better
performed in the digital domain, right, for better performance, and then you can lead to less cost of
computational efficiency, right, sorry, less cost of computational, right? So this is actually the
reason. So here's one single example, right, illustrates how the, you know, basically the
requirement for sampling rate conversion, right? So as we see, all of the single rate we have learned
so far, I mean, before this lecture, we always assume that the signal processing system is actually a
LTI system, right? If you remember what is LTI, we say we can assume that the system is linear,
time-invariant, right? And that was the single rate. But today you will see that after having this
rate conversion system, right? The system we have will no longer be time-invariant, okay? So later
you will see the difference, right? But in fact, when is this sampling rate conversion system in
there, you will have a time-variant system. In other words, if you're, for example, you get an input XT
and output YT, right? Now you shift your XT, let's say, to two seconds, right? You do XT,
say, plus two. You will not necessarily have YXT plus two, right? So because this kind of system
will not be the same if you have some time delay, right? I mean, this was the property before,
right, before this week, but it's no longer the property. So bear in mind that having this
conversion system will make the system still linear, but not time-invariant. It's going to be
time-variant, all right? So you can consider that you have input XN, which initially was the rate
FX, right? And then after that, you will have a YM with a different rate, which let's say FY, right?
So apparently there will be a rate change. But of course, they are actually talking about the same
actually signal in the analog domain, right? Just like different way of sampling that. So you can
imagine that a rate, which is actually FX, well, corresponding to the, let's say the XN here,
XN plus one, XN plus two. So something like the, I don't know if you can see this, but the line that
is thinner, right? So maybe I use a pointer to do this, right? So this is corresponding to your XN
and this is actually, sorry, XN plus one is here, XN plus two is actually here, right? So basically
you will have those thin line, which is actually a sampled version as the FX, right? So in other
words, your TX will be larger, right? But the same kind of envelope, you can sample that in the FY
rate, which you end up with the thicker line, right? This is actually the sampled signals
related, referred as the YM here. So basically changing the rate is nothing but changing the
sampling points, right? You can either sample the signal with like a more, like a denser point,
or you can sample the signal with a sparser point, right? This is actually the difference.
So you can consider the output YM as an estimated version from the XN, right? So of course, you
don't have this envelope, but you can estimate the YM in the best way, right? You can use that,
treat it as an estimation of the X, right? And of course, this YM and XN will use different
time indices. So the N and M will have different kind of interval in time, right? So later you
will see that this is actually very important. So later you will see no matter, it's in the
frequency domain or time domain, once you do the rate conversion, you have to be very careful about
indexing system, because the indexing system will change, right? And you must be very clear about,
we're talking about closer indexing or finer indexing, all right? So later you will, but you
know, bear this in mind, right? These are something could be changed, all right? And I think I already
mentioned something, right? So this system with the time, you know, rate conversion will be time
variant, right? In other words, the system will provide a flat response and the time delay TI for
the isompole of XN, right? So in particular, if this delay is the time variant for the same I,
right? Which means the future is actually time variant, right? So basically this is actually
the thing will happen, right? But of course, using this rate conversion, end up with a multi-rate
processing where also enjoy some merits, some advantages. For example, you can, if you design
a system in a good way, you can actually have less computational requirements, right? And also
sometimes less storage for the future coefficients and his signal histories. They can give you a
fewer, lower order of future design, right? So last time we say that we actually care about the
order of your FIR, right? So the few order means actually few computational requirements for
filtering. So it's possible to actually lower the order of the filter by carefully design this rate
conversion. So basically these are the merits of them. And so these are the advantages,
something you gain, right? These are something you enjoy, but you also have to pay the price
for this introducing this additional complexity of doing this rate conversion.
So in practice, as a designer, your job is to wait the two, right? So you look at, is this like
something I gain, right? If I enjoy more benefits of doing this by paying less price for this
additional complexity, that's actually a deal, right? You're not doing it. But if you pay a lot
of price for introducing this complicated conversion, but while not gaining too much,
then probably it's not a good way to go, right? So this is actually the logic when you trade off
the two, right? You want to gain something in the overall sense, right? So basically, I mean,
this gives you some idea like why we want to do this, right? What will happen when we have this
rate conversion. But we haven't introduced anything specific, right? What's the principle of doing
that? And what happens if you change the rate? So after that, right, this part, now we're going to
learn basically some, how should I say, building blocks of designing a rate conversion system,
all right? So we started by looking at changing the frequency by a factor of integers. So in other
words, when you change the rate, in principle, you can do, let's say, 0.3 times, right? Maybe 0.4
times. Later we're going to learn how to do it. But let's start it by thinking about integer
number of rate change. So in other words, how about up sampling by two or down sampling by three,
right? So we started by doing the up sampling, down sampling with integer number of multipliers,
all right? So let's start it by so-called interpolation. Okay, so how many of you heard of the term
interpolation? Chopin, how many of you heard of the term interpolation anywhere?
No? Okay, so I mean, for example, when you do, when you see a picture, right, in computer,
you are trying to enlarge the image, right? Basically you're showing the image with more pixels.
What actually does by computer is actually interpolation. You are basically rendering the
same image with more samples, right? But interpolation, okay, this is very important.
Interpolation is not just equivalent to up sampling, okay? Interpolation is based by up
sampling, but interpolation is not equal to up sampling, all right? So this is a common
misunderstanding. So later, here we're going to see what happens here, right? So like I mentioned,
right? Interpolation is based on the up sampling process. So up sampling is very easy to understand,
right? You first have, let's say, two samples, but you want to generate maybe four samples representing
the similar signals, right? Going from a fewer sample to more samples. Or in other words, you
want to sample the signal with more, how to say, denser steps, right? Or maybe finer scales. This
is actually up sampling process. So if you have up sampling process, the, we're normally, okay,
we normally use this symbol to denote up sampling, like an upward arrow, right? So from this course,
every time you see upward arrow, it means up sampling, okay? It's a convention we're going
to use for this course. And normally there will be a number beside it, okay? Let's say two or three,
this describes the ratio, right? How many times you want to do up sampling, all right? If it's two,
it means goes from, let's say, I don't know, like let's say one hertz to two hertz, right?
One kilohertz to two kilohertz. So this is actually the ratio. So we always use this to describe
up sampling. And when you say it's up sampling process, right, the idea is to increase the
sampling rate by this number factor, all right? So illustratively, let's consider time domain
representation of a signal, right? This is your original signal. Apparently you have how many? Like
one, two, three, four, let's say five, right? Samples within this interval, right? But this is
the original rate. Now, if I want to do up sampling, let's say here is up sampling of three times.
What I have is to increase the number of sample by three times within the same time interval,
all right? So in other words, you have to, for example, here make sure within this range,
there are two more samples here, right? Again, here, every time when you measure one sample in
the original XM, you have to measure three samples in the corresponding YM, right? So this is actually
the literate, the literate meaning of up sampling. Increase number of sample within the same time
interval by I times, right? Sample the signal in a dancer rate, okay? But this is not interpolation,
right? This is only an up sampling. Let me make it very clear, right? Okay, then we're going to see
what is missing here. But for up sampling, we need to use two numbers, two rates to describe the
input and output. So FX refers to the rate of the input, FY refers to the rate of the output,
right? And in other words, if this is an up sampling of I times, you will have the FY equal to
I times FX, which is easy to understand, right? You increase the rate by I times. But most likely
when you do interpolation, the input is already a discrete signal, right? Even if you want to
sample that more frequently, you don't have information between two numbers, right? Two
measurements. So as usual way people do is by feeding zeros between two successive values in your
input, just like the way they do it here, right? So for example, if I have two adjacent measurements
in my input, I want to get two more measurements, right? Sample by three times more. I have no choice
because there's no measurements in my input. So I have to make them zero, right? Because that was
off the grade measurements in my input. So basically, the up sampling process, if you
want to represent it mathematically, right? Your output, Vm will be equal to, if your m is equal
to the integer amount of I, right? You will equal, it will be equal to x, but index is m divided by
I, okay? So think about why? Because here the m value will be selectively as the zero minus
plus I, minus plus two I. So if these are the selected value, right? Divided by I, I'm going to get
zero, one, two, three, four, right? Those are the measured numbers in my input. If the measurement
is not equal to the integer multiple of I's, there will be zeros in the output. So this is the
mathematical description in time domain of the output after up sampling by I time, okay?
Should be easy to understand, right? Time domain. You just need to insert zeros between every two
JSON measurements in the input. How many zeros depends on up sampling rate, all right? Okay,
so bear in mind that, so today we're going to learn up sampling and down sampling, right? And
corresponding up sampling will lead to interpolation, down sampling will lead to decimation. So for
both of the four operators, right? Up sampling, down sampling, interpolation, decimation, you need to
know first time domain what happened, right? So this is what happened in time domain for up
sampling, all right? Also we need to know what happened in the frequency domain. So particularly
for this part, Z-transform, okay? So bear in mind that you need to make sure you are familiar with
what happened both in time domain and frequency domain as the Z-transform, all right? This is
very important because later we're going to play the trick, right? How these two interact with each
other. So you need to know both, all right? So this is the mathematical form for time domain
representation of an up sampling operator by i times, okay? Make sense, everyone? Does it make
sense? Okay, now, right, if we have the time domain representation, we can simply do a Z-transform to
get the frequency domain representation, right? So I mean, I believe all of you can do Z-transform,
so you just need to make sure Z-transform is applied to the left-hand side and right-hand side,
right? So, sorry, no, not exactly, but I mean, yeah, left-hand side is very easy, but right-hand
side you have to play with this ratio, right? But basically by definition Z-transform is defined
as the, well, basically it's a DTFT but with the change of variables, right? So this is the
original Z-transform, but we want to represent it as the Z-transform of X. So what you need to do is
is you have to replace the Vm here with the X, all right? So how does this relate it? Well,
this equation tells you, right? So Vm well equal to Xm divided by i only at time when m equal to
these integers, all right? So in the summation, I think they kind of jumped one step, but in,
you know, going from here, right, what you can do is you can directly substitute this guy
into in here without changing the m, all right? But you see that there are many m give you zeros
as the Vm, so you only select those which are non-zeros, okay? In this case, you can actually
change the variable from m to the i times m, right? When you do, when you change the m to the i times m,
you can get rid of this m divided by, right? As the Xm directly, correspondingly the exponential
here will no longer be minus m, but it's going to be minus m times i. So there's a single kind of
change of variables, it's a simple trick, all right? But basically, you can do that one more
step further. I mean, I don't know if they can write something, but pen, okay, good. So what I'm
talking about here is you can first stick to Xm divided by l, i, sorry, i, sorry, excuse my
handwriting, it's very ugly, but you know, it's better than nothing. So originally it's this,
okay? If you just substitute that, but what I'm doing here is I will assign the m to be
i times m. Why I'm doing this? Because only when m equal to i times m, these Vm will be nonzero,
right? Remember, this was the definition here, right? Multiple time of i, that will give you
nonzero elements. Other Vm will be zero. Because of that, you can do a swap of variables and then
once you substitute this guy in, i and i cancel. That's how you get Xm, right? And also this
i m goes to index, this one gives you the m times i, right? Make sense? Well, if not, you can just
change, let's say this is, you know, you can first do n if you want, right? If you think this is
hard to imagine, so let's do n first and then change to m, right? It's just a dummy variable,
right? It doesn't matter. But mathematically, this is the change that has been made here.
How about other terms? How about those not equal to i times m? Well, there will be zero, right?
There will be zero and they won't contribute to the summation. Okay?
Make sense? Well, if not, you can ask me right afterward. But you can try this yourself. I think
that's the best way you can learn it. But this is how you can get rid of the m divided by i.
And if you look at this form, right? Apparently, this is a standard way of z-transform.
Except that you are talking about a variable that is z to the i, right? If it's z to the i,
you will make the standard form of z-transform, right? z-transform says the base must be z to
power of minus m, all right? I just do another change of base function. Remember, we can change
the base if you want, from omega to z, right? Right now, we're from z to z to the power of i, right?
So to that end, you will have a z-transform, but the variable becomes z to the power of i, right?
In other words, you are talking about a, how should I say, a faster rate of your z-transform,
right? Because you do a power of i. Remember, z is equal to e to the power of minus j omega, right?
Also, e to the power of j omega. If you have the omega times i, you are changing the rate of your
frequency, right? Okay. Okay, so I just give you a rough derivation, but mathematically,
you can actually verify it, right? You can sit down and write it. But there are two
change of variables. If you are, if you can get it, right? So here from here, there's a change of
variables. Here from here, there's another change of variables, right? But you need to keep this
to in mind how they can end up with here, right? But remember, just now I say that this is actually
the time domain representation of the ARP sampling. Okay, not interpolation, but just ARP sampling.
All right. And this is actually the, oops, sorry, where's my mouse? This is actually the
frequency relationship of the ARP sampling, right? So if you go from x to v by ARP sampling by i times,
it is equivalent to change the rate from z to z, z to the power of i, right? You make the rate faster,
basically. Okay, so you have to know the two, okay? Because we have to go and play, play around with
the two sometimes in time domain, sometimes in frequency, right? But these are the two you need
to know. Of course, you know, you can do a simple change from z to omega. I think everybody can do
this, right? So if you do a change from z to omega, remember, what is the z, right? In the first
place, z is equal to e to the power of j omega, all right? So if you have a z to the power of i,
you are basically talking about e to the power of j omega i. So that's why they have it here, right?
All right. Okay. So, okay, I don't want to get confused. That's why I strongly suggest you to
write down this by yourself. You go through it one time, you will be more clear, basically, all
right? But after a while, you should be, you know, you have to be familiar with that, all right?
Simple math, but not very straightforward in the beginning, I would say. Okay. So I think 2.1,
2.2, 2.3, that's all you need for up-sampling, okay? You need to know them, and unless you want
to derive it, you can memorize it if you want, right? Last but not least, besides knowing the
mathematic equation from time, from frequency, one last thing I wish you to know is the visual
representation, right? What happened in the spectrum visually? Okay, just now we say that,
well, mathematically, right, just go from omega to omega i, right? But when you plot the spectrum,
what happened? If you still remember, right, we say that in the sampling, we also talk about the
spectrum, right? Visualize how the 80 is in, where the 80 is in come from. Still remember that?
So here we're going to do the same thing, right? If you do up-sampling, what happened to the spectrum?
So imagine that this is your original spectrum, x, okay? I mean, just some random drawing, right?
So this is your x, and normally, like I said, we can just do a plot within 0 to 2 pi, right?
Others will be just repeating, right? This is why you do DTFT. Now, if you do up-sampling,
in this case, by 3, the spectrum of your v will be something like this. Okay, let's pose a little
bit and look at what's the difference, all right? So from x to y, sorry, from x to v, apparently,
you can say that the shape doesn't change, right? You still have the same waveform, all right? But
the resolution of your frequency has been changed, right? So you can see that the force
replicas here is actually 6 pi. Here is actually 2 pi, right? So we're talking about the same waveform,
but we are actually shrinking, how should I say, am I shrinking it or expanding it? Like shrinking the
x-axis, the horizontal axis from originally 6 pi to 6 pi divided by 3. So basically every
frequency, right? For example, the center point here originally was 2 pi, after up-sampling will be
2 pi divided by 3, okay? So this is what actually happened. And for those who know function, right,
this can be easily interpreted from here, you are multiplying the variable with i,
correspondingly you are kind of shrinking the entire axis by i, right? So this is what happened
for up-sampling, okay? Very simple. You up-sample by i times, you shrink your axis by i times,
right? Okay? Make sense? Okay, now from here, I'm going to introduce you interpolation, okay? We
haven't done interpolation yet, but up-sampling. Now this graph explains to you why up-sampling
sometimes is not enough. We have to do something extra to make it interpolation, okay? So all the
problem coming from the middle one here, right? Here, this guy and this guy. All right? Originally,
I mentioned to you that most of the function, sorry, the discrete time signals, we just need to
represent the waveform within 0 to 2 pi, right? This is where the baseband is talking about.
Ideally, the baseband should capture just one waveform. So here, if you look at the 0 to 2 pi,
they just form one kind of entire waveform, right? But after you do up-sampling,
due to the fact that you are shrinking the axis between 0 to 2 pi, you can tell that here,
within the baseband, you actually have three waveforms, right? You got two replicates or
duplicates here. So these two duplicates are formed by shrinking the axis. You're kind of pushing
them to the baseband, okay? I mean, here it looks okay, but the problem is that
interpolation or up-sampling is not the only module in your system, right? So later, you may also do
like down-sampling or other operations. So you want to get rid of these duplicates within the
baseband and only keep just one entire waveform. To this end, you need to do something else to kill
all of these images here. We call it images. We're going to kill this guy. You want to kill this guy.
You don't want to have them because they are already represented here and here, right? Because
they are just duplicates. So can anyone tell me if I want to kill the two images in here?
What operations I need to do?
So I have this as input, right? This is my input signal. I say, well, I don't like these two guys,
right? These are just replicates. There's no information, right? I want to do something to
the signal to kill all of the components here and here, only keep the baseband signals. So what
operation I need to do here? Low pass filter, right? Low pass filter because all of the baseband are
in the low frequency components. These are something in the higher frequency. I can kill them by
simply doing a low pass filter. So exactly the interpolation we're talking about is actually
a combination of an up sampling followed by a low pass filter. Okay. The sequence actually
matter here. You have to do up sampling first, followed by a low pass filter. Together, these
two things together is called interpolation. Because if you do interpolation, you are guaranteed to
have things only relative to the baseband, right? You don't have images. They're duplicates, right?
This is what interpolation want to do. If you only do up sampling, you will have images in between.
Okay? So this is the difference. All right. And later you will see that for decimation, the order
is the opposite. For interpolation, it's always first up sampling and then low pass filter.
So basically, this is my input. The input is here. You are first up sampling to get V. So V is the
scaled version with the images in between. So after you do this low pass filter, you will get the
final output of your interpolation and the Y will have the shrink waveform without images, right?
This is how the interpolation will give you, right? What the interpolation will give you.
So of course, I mean, this filter, you have to make them somehow appropriate, right? You cannot
do arbitrary low pass filter. So the low pass filter usually will have a color frequency around
pi divided by i. Okay, this is important. So why? Because if you look at here, right, you want to
choose a proper color frequency such that you don't really distort your baseband, right? Your
baseband signal must be survived. And talking about the number of images, right, you are talking about
dividing the entire 2 pi by three divisions, right? So in this case, your color frequency is
something like pi divided by i in this case. So for an i-th time in up sampling, you must apply,
or maybe you better apply, a low pass filter that is with color frequency between zero and pi divided
by i. Right, so this i will be the up sampling factor. So together, this forms a good interpolation.
All right, of course, this is ideal low pass filter. We haven't talked about real practical low pass
filter, but ideal low pass filter, you can make it like zero elsewhere and a constant within the
passband, right? Okay, so this is interpolation. Okay, you should know the difference between
interpolation and up sampling. And now we see that for all of the three we're going to learn today,
you need to know first time domain relationship and then frequency. All right, so later on,
now we're going to see how they look like. So we start by frequency, right, because frequency is
actually easier. Right, so we see that well, we, you know, if it's actually a up sampling, right,
we learn that this is the up sampling version, but the low pass version of up sample version will
be just a constraint on the frequency, right, nothing else. So without this constraint, it's going
to be a up sample version, right? Where is the constraint is going to give you interpolated
version? The only difference between interpolation and up sampling is just the low pass filter,
right? You add another low pass filter, give you the frequency constraint, that's going to be
interpolation, right? So this is easy to remember, right? You can link interpolation with up sampling
in frequency first because the change is actually minimum, right? Only the frequency constraint.
And now some of you may realize that I also have a scaling factor here, right, the C. In practice,
you can't have a scaling factor, you don't have to make the C equal to 1. And the reason of doing that
is actually, sorry, is actually one to, wait, did I see this?
So, so in fact, right, if we have a scaling factor and it can be proven that if this
scaling factor is set to be I, same as there are some up sampling factor, right, your output
version of YM will equal to the X up sample version for all of these numbers exactly, right?
So the normal choice for the scaling factor is actually C equal to I. This is also easy to
memorize because you want to make sure the energy is conserved. You have to kill, you know, actually
n minus 1 number of images. Of course, you have removed some energies. In other words, you want
to make your low pass filter to compensate those energies so you do a scale up, right?
So the normal choice is to make the C equal to I and a column frequency equal to pi divided by,
right? This is the common choice. Okay, but now that's all, that's also only the frequency domain,
right? We also have to talk about the time domain. So remember, for all of the four alerts today,
you have to do frequency plus time, right? So the time domain, these kind of, you know,
process can be represented as a convolution operator, right? So basically what you're doing here
is a convolution between the H and V. So H will be your low pass filter, V will be your up sample
version of your input, right? So filtering can be always interpreted as a convolution. So in
time domain, this is what actually happened. And, but this VK will be zero except for the
multiple time of I, right? Remember, VK will have a lot of zero inserted to the middle, all right?
So in other words, VK will only equal to XK when the V integers, index equal to K times I in this
case, right? So these will be the mathematical expression of the time domain operation, what
happened for interpolation, okay? Oh, sorry. Here, okay, I should have one more line here, right?
So basically if you, you have to change the K to K times I because only the K equal to multiple of I,
maybe let me clear this eraser, right? So, so mathematically this is actually what happened
as a convolution, right? But these V is as something special. Remember, V will have a lot of zero in
between in two adjacent kind of samples, right? So only when the K equal to integer amount of
times I, they will give you non-zero variable. So you have to change the K here as the K times I to
avoid the zero, right? I mean, this is also true, but it's going to give you some duplicate term,
which is zero, right? Okay, but actually this 3.6, this is actually the time domain
representation of the interpolation process, all right? Okay, so, so, so far we are done with
up sampling and interpolation. We learned that up sampling straightforward, you just need to
change the rate to a faster rate and adding zeros, but it gives you images in frequency domain. To
avoid images, you have to do another low pass filter and together, up sampling with low pass
filter together, this is called interpolation. So we actually have these two pair of concepts,
right? Up sampling, interpolation. Now we have the counterpart, right? Which is actually making
the rate lower slower, right? You can, if you can increase the rate, you can also decrease the rate,
right? So decreasing the rate of your signal, this is referred as, first, refers as down sampling,
all right? So down sampling will be denoted as an arrow downward, you know, pointing to downward,
this is down sampling, and you will also have a constant beside it, right? So this constant D
describes how much you want a down sample, right? If it's two, it's going to, every two measure,
you might, you actually sample one time, right? So together, this is actually a down sampling operator.
So normally you will have something like this, you have input signals, down sample would give you
an output signal, right? So in the time domain, if this is your input signal, and we want to
down sample this by three times, that means, so every three measurements, you sample one time,
right? Every three measurements, you sample one time. Every three measurement, you sample one time.
So all of these samples will be uniform distributed, but it's like every one measure for three samples,
right? Okay? So this is actually what happened in the time domain, and in the time domain,
the mathematical description is also very simple, right? So you have input, which is the x, you want
to generate the output, so you want to make sure that your output only measured at, you know,
D number of samples, right? Every D number of samples. So this is actually the time domain
representation. And also I want you to kind of look at what happened visually in the spectrum,
right? So this is actually quite different from the interpolation we just learned, right? Remember,
interpolation what happened is that you are shrinking the axis, right? You shrink the axis,
but the waveform are actually the same. You are not distort the waveform, right? But down
sample is slightly different, okay? So let me explain this in a first way. So here, this is
your input, right? Which is the x omega x versus omega x. x omega x versus omega x. So we stick to
the original frequency, which is omega x, right? Now if you don't change the frequency, we still
stick to the original frequency, what happened to down sampling, let's forget about decimation,
right? Only down sampling here is to kind of something like adding duplicates uniformly
within the 2 pi range, okay? It's different from up sampling, right? Up sampling is like you don't
really insert things, you are actually shrinking the axis, right? Remember, this is not shrinking the
axis, right? Remember, originally these two waveform are far away from each other, but we're
adding the same replicates within them uniformly, right? So in other words, if you are up sampling
by three, you have to make sure originally there's only one measure within the 2 pi range, now we
have three measures in the 2 pi range, okay? And then, you know, this becomes the measured
spectrum of the y in the original omega x, okay? Why I keep saying it's original omega x? Because
actually the omega y will have different scale as the omega x. So this line describes the
relationship between omega y and omega x. So in other words, originally omega x is 2 pi,
after down sampling, if you switch to the y kind of domain, your frequency axis will be no longer
2 pi, but 2 times d times pi, right? So in other words, you are not just inserting kind of,
you know, duplicates, you are also expanding the axis, right? From 2 pi to 2 pi times d, basically.
So in total, this is the phenomenon. You are expanding the waveform and you are adding
the duplicates in between. Okay, so I pose a little bit and you think about whether this makes sense to
you, all right? Okay? All right, so because of this kind of phenomenon, right, you probably realize
something. This is the same reason that we have aliasing in the sampling process. Okay, if you
will still remember, we talk about aliasing when we talk about sampling, right? We say, well, there's
sometimes you could have the overlap between two waveforms. That's how you can get aliasing, right?
So here, there's also a chance that this added duplicates could have overlap with your baseband
signal. And this happens when your baseband signal itself, the spectrum range is too large.
Okay, or maybe your d is actually too large, right? So either way, somehow when you create
these duplicates, there could be an overlap between your baseband signal and your replicates.
So just like the aliasing we talk about in the sampling here, if you are doing the
down sampling too aggressively, you may also have the aliasing due to this overlap here.
Because once they overlap, you have to only represent the summation. You cannot unmix them,
right? You cannot get back. So this is also a similar distortion about these different names,
right? Aliasing is due to over sampling, sorry, is due to the sampling, it's kind of not fast enough.
Here, this overlap is due to the rate conversion, it's due to the down sampling. But similarly,
you need to make sure your baseband spectrum is limited to avoid this kind of distortion.
Okay? Just like the way we do this for aliasing, right? What we should do to make my baseband
signal more limited? If I want to do something, right, what do you think I should do to make my
baseband signal? For example, here, this is my baseband signal, right? If I don't do anything,
I just directly down sample by three, my first replicates will overlap with my baseband signal,
right? This is something I don't want to see. Now I want to avoid this. What should I do?
A simple operation, what should I do to avoid this overlap? Any suggestions?
Think about how we deal with aliasing, right? Because aliasing is very similar here.
So what do we do to avoid aliasing? Do you still remember?
There's one simple operator. We call it anti-aliasing stuff. Do you still remember? Like lecture one,
right? First lecture, we say, if you don't do things carefully, you can get aliasing, right? But if we
do something beforehand, we can get rid of aliasing, possibly. What have we done there?
Low pass filter, right? So anti-aliasing filter is a low pass filter. You have to make sure
these components, which is beyond the risky part, are being removed. Remember, right? So what we did
for aliasing is that before sampling, we have a low pass filter to constrain the spectrum within the
safety region. Remember? Anti-aliasing filter, right? Think about it, right? Anti-aliasing filter
is a low pass filter before sampling. Okay? Here, very similar idea. You want to avoid the overlap
here. You need to apply a low pass filter before done sampling. Makes sense? And how to determine
this? I mean, so first, I hope all of you agree that a low pass filter is needed.
Low pass filter is needed to get rid of the possible overlap. And actually, sometimes we
also call this anti-aliasing because if you treat that as aliasing, right? The role of this filter
is also anti-aliasing filter. So anti-aliasing filter is necessary not only before sampling,
but also here before done sampling, right? And this is actually why we always need a low pass
filter before done sampling. Okay? Together, the two together, this is called decimation.
Okay? Just now I said that up sampling plus low pass filter before, sorry, after is called
interpolation. So here, low pass filtering plus a done sampler together is called a decimation
operator, right? So decimation equals to anti-aliasing or low pass plus a done sampling, all right?
So done sampling is part of the components in the decimation process. If you only do done
sampling, you have the risk of aliasing, right? But if you do decimation properly, you won't
have aliasing because of this anti-aliasing filter before, okay? So order here the matter,
right? Remember, interpolation, low pass filter is after the up sampler. Here, the decimation,
low pass filter must be before the done sampling for the same reason as we learn for in the
sampling process, right? Okay? So together, this is called the decimation operator. And in this
case, right, your YM, of course, is going to be distorted because the low pass filter will also
making the signal losing the high frequency component, but you will not get aliasing, right?
You lose something, but you won't get aliasing artifacts, right? So the frequency in the low
range have been preserved. This is the good part because it only sacrifice the high frequency,
but you kind of save for the low frequency range, right? Whatever within the low pass
filter will be safe. So this will most likely, I mean, think about the natural signals, right?
Most of them are low frequency, so you can contain or you can preserve most of the information of
the signal, even if you apply a low pass filter, right? So mathematically, like I said, we have
to learn two things, right? Frequency versus time. So let's do frequency first. In frequency domain,
when you apply the low pass filter, it's very straightforward. An ideal low pass filter will
be something like this, right? It's going to be one within the cutoff frequency and zero elsewhere,
right? So this is the mathematics description. So the cutoff frequency will be pi divided by d,
right? For the same similar reason I could talk about in the interpolation, right? Because
when we talk about the adding the replicas, we're adding actually from one to i in the
two pi range, right? So every kind of a, you know, baseband will share only pi divided by d
range here. So this is actually the cutoff frequency we wish to preserve before down sampling. So in
this case, the low pass filter will have one as the passband between zero and pi divided by d,
okay? So this idea, of course, in practice you cannot get this, but ideally it's one versus zero,
right? So they are going to eliminate all of the spectrum outside this range from d divided,
pi divided by d to pi, right? And this is basically what happened as the anti-aliasing,
right? So the output of the filter, again, you know, a filtering in a time domain will be convolution,
right? So in the time domain, it's corresponding to a convolution between the h, here's a lower h,
which is the time impulse response, convolved with the input x, right? And this is actually,
you know, so for a similar reason, your x will be first down sampled to the v, right? In this case,
you will not have none zero for any sample, right? In practice, you have to make sure your x
has been down sampled as well, which is actually m times d minus k, right? So without it, it's not
down sampled, whether it's actually down sampled version of your decimation process, right? So the
entire time domain relationship is the following, right? This will be your time domain relationship
for decimation process, right? So two things, right? d will depend on your down sampling factor,
h will be depends on your color frequency, right, as the low pass filter. So two things will decide
the time impulse response of h, right? So just now was the time, right, time domain relationship.
And okay, here is actually the reason why we're saying that once you involve the down
sampling operator, the system is no longer time invariant, okay? It's still linear, but not time
not time invariant. Why? Because if you are somehow, I mean the fact is that your x
produce y, but if you get a time delay in the x, right, due to the time delay, you will not be
equal to y m minus n naught. I mean, this is also very simple, right? Think easy to understand.
You have a signal, right? You have this down sampling. So maybe the first time you pick
x0, x3, x6, but once you shift it sometime, you will pick x1, x4, and x7, right? So because of this
off the grid effect, if you have any time delay that is not equal to the factor of a down sampling,
you will not get the same result because when you sample that, you kind of change the measure you have,
right? So think about this down sampling process. So, but the key point is that once we have the
multiray in the system, you will lose the property of time invariant. Okay, so don't assume this when
you solve any questions. It's no longer true, okay? So, okay, that was the time, but again,
we have to talk about what is the frequency domain representation, right? So from the time domain
representation, we can actually, so this was your time domain representation, right? You can simply
do a DTFT to get the time domain representation, sorry, frequency domain representation, right?
And this is nothing but a multiplication between your spectrum of the, sorry, the low pass filter
point wise multiplied by your spectrum of the input signal, right? But of course, you have to
talk about the down sampling. So once you do down sampling, you're kind of a, how to say,
expanding your frequency spectrum by D times, right? Remember, just always say that
here, right? Originally, I'm talking about omega x, which is 0 to 2 pi, but once you do down
sampling, you are equivalent to expanding the frequency axis from 2 pi to 2 pi times D, right?
So you will have this expanding artifacts in your frequency spectrum, and this is handled by dividing
your omega by a D here, right? The D factor here. So D factor will be something like expanding your
frequency axis by D times. And this expanding, remember, we always first do down sampling,
followed by, sorry, we always do low pass filter followed by down sampling. So the convolution
happens first, down sampling happens second. So this kind of expanding artifacts will be
happened to both your H spectrum and the X spectrum, right? Because that happens for
after you have already do the low pass filter, right? So both of them will be expanded. So there
will be a D factor there, and then you will have this, you know, kind of a point wise product
together to form your final spectrum output, right? This is how you get it. And of course,
you need to properly design the HD such that AD is in can be eliminated, right? So if this is
eliminated, you will have the spectrum to do something like this, right? This will be the
corresponding spectrum. All right, but this is like a point wise product here, right? And you only
represent the frequency that is between 0 and pi, right? Because that's the baseband signal. You
can forget about the other kind of outside the baseband range, okay? All right, so here's actually
another illustration of what happened when we do decimation, right? Decimation means down sampling
plus the, what is that, the anti-aliasing, right? So originally, this is my X, right? Like I said,
you can, when you do decimation, you can first imagine, you know, your baseband is kind of here
and here, right? But you're going to make, in this case, four measures, four waveforms within the
2 pi range. So in other words, this is like a down sampling by four, right? I hope this is obvious
for everyone, like, because when you do down sampling by four, you are making four waveforms
within the 2 pi range uniformly, right? So basically, you know, there will be k1, k2, k3 as the replicates
of my k0. So, but still, we are talking about the original frequency axis, which is the omega x,
right? But another thing you have to do is kind of expanding the axis, omega range from original
scale to omega times the down sampling factor, right? In this case, it's four. So the actual
range, well, now becomes between zero and eight pi. In other words, two pi times four, right? So this
will be your final spectrum of the down sampling, right? You have to do two things. First one is
adding kind of components into it and then scale or expanding the axis, right? Because that's what
the mathematics means, but you have something divided by d, right? This is how you do it. So
these will be the corresponding y components. And normally, we only keep the free form within
zero to two pi, right? If you keep it, this will become your corresponding base band waveform of the
output, right? Because other will be just, you know, repeating itself, right? Okay? But you need to
know visually how I go from here to here. So I do two things, right? First one is creating
replicates. Depends on how many, what is the factor of down sampling, right? The second thing is
scale the frequency axis similarly by d times, right? Here's four times. So pretty much every
frequency is multiplied by d here. And then you only represent one base band range, which is from zero
to two pi. And that's enough. Okay? You can also derive this from the mathematical expression. So
I skip that part. I direct to tell you the visual change, but you are more than welcome to derive
it, right? Because I guess some of you should be able to do it because, you know, mathematics is
very clear, right? You have something divided by d, you are expanding the axis, right? Okay?
So this is what happened. Okay. So right now, we have finished actually the, I mentioned the four
major basic components of my multirate processing, right? Which are up sampling followed by
interpolation, right? The only difference is you have another low pass filter after the up
sampler, right? And the third thing is down sampling. But we say down sampling, you could have
aliasing. So you need an anti-aliasing before it. Together is called decimation. So we have learned
the four, all right? So this is a summary of the four, you know, on the left-hand side, right?
This is something we call the block diagram. We're going to see this many times. But block
diagram, you should know how to represent up sampling and down sampling, all right? And
interpolator will be up sampler followed by a low pass filter, right? But the key is that you have
to figure out what is the factor of your up sampling and then what is the color frequency of your
low pass filter, right? And there's an intermediate output, the ux, the xu, this will be your output
of up sampler, okay? Similarly for decimator, it's going to be first low pass filter with some
color frequency followed by a down sampling operator, right? So together this is actually a
decimator. And then like I mentioned, you need to know both the time domain and frequency domain
representation, right? So here, xu, this is a time domain representation of the up sampling,
right? xu is here. xu is before low pass filter, right? So this is the time domain of the
up sampling, all right? This is a time domain representation of the interpolation, all right?
This is the frequency domain of the up sampling in Z transformable. You can easily convert it to
omega if you want, right? And then this is the frequency domain representation of your interpolation.
Okay, so I just give you a summary, but I strongly encourage you to try it and see whether you can
end up with something similar, right? If you can, you should be fine with everything, right? If you
get something stuck, you can ask me or you can just try it again, right? But this is really important
because we're going to play some tricks there, right? Later we'll move on to more complicated
scenarios. So similarly, right? For decimation, you also need to know what is the time domain,
what is the frequency domain, right? And importantly is that you don't mess up with the,
you know, every time when you do, you know, an interpolation, you have to think about like
shrinking, right? Every time when you do up sampling, we have to think about the, sorry,
when you do decimation, you have to think about the expanding axis, right? So don't mess up the
scaling, right? Scaling actually matters here, right? But I think this table gives you a good
summary of the four things we have learned in the first part of the lecture, all right? Try to
digest it and we will do, let's say, a 15-minute break and we come back for the second part,
all right? So we're going to resume around 7.50, okay? All right, thank you. So let's see 15 minutes.
All right, let's continue and I will try to also finish the class around 9, right?
If possible, I actually, okay, but before that, right, I got some questions just now from the
many students talking about this visual example, right? Where is it? Okay, here, right? So this one,
so many of you do really understand where this comes from, right? And I just want to maybe
repeat a bit, a little bit to explain this part. So, you know, all of this visual example, right?
I have one for decimation, I have another one for interpolation. So all of this is just for you to
easily interpret what happened in the spectrum, right? But both of them are actually following the
exact frequency relationship, right? So the math is always true, right? But how you interpret the
change in the spectrum, it depends, right? You have multiple ways to implement that, right? So,
for example, here, if you truly want to understand what is the change or what is the
modification, right? From the X to Y after you do decimation, you have to go back to the frequency
relationship, which is something here, right? So this is actually our spectrum change. And the
spectrum here, with the Y here and also the X here, okay? So if you look at that, the difference
here is actually by scaling of the omega of D, right? So what does this mean? If I have a function,
originally it's X as a function of omega, now I have X function of omega divided by D, right?
What actually happened, if you think about it, is actually an expanding of your function, right?
So you can imagine in this way, like, how should I say, your omega is triangle, right? Okay,
maybe I just draw this. So imagine that your X is originally a triangle, right? And for example,
this is my zero, this is one, this is minus, so originally X is like this, right? So suppose this
is my X omega, right? Now I have X omega divided by two, right? So here I just let D equal to two.
How does the waveform of this guy look like? You can just check, for example, here when omega
equal to one, I will get zero, right, at this point. Now if my function changed to X omega divided
by two, which means I need to have an omega equal to two to reach, sorry, to reach the zero, right?
So in this case, the waveform will be something still a triangle, but the cutoff frequency becomes two,
right, in this case, right? Make sense? Everybody agree? Right? You just find some key points,
right? You find out, okay, if I reach this point, what should be the corresponding value, right?
If I divide it by two, I need to pay two times to reach the same index as the one here in my input,
right? So when you divide it by two, you are basically same waveform you're expanding the
waveform by two times, right? This is another way to interpret the change, okay? I'm just talking
about math, right? Does this make sense for everyone? Like, okay, simple math, right? Any function,
you have a variable divided by two, you are basically expanding the function by two accordingly,
right? Okay, now if you agree with that, right, we go to the visualization we just talked about here.
Here, right? Another way to interpret the change, suppose this is my original x,
I'm talking about a y, which is equal to one divided by d, x omega divided by d, right?
This is what, this is actually my y, okay? So what I'm actually doing here is a stretching of my
current waveform, right? So basically I'm saying, well, initially I'm ending here, but right now,
I should somehow goes to something like this, right? Make sense? Okay, but you know, there's another
way to interpret that because if you do the same thing here, right? You end up with something
quite similar as this one. And no, wait, wait, where is my,
oh no, I mean, I should use another figure, right? So there's a figure shows the,
hey, wait, wait, I think I have a figure with the change of axis, right? Where is it?
Or maybe after, right? Okay, right, this is, okay, this is a good example, right? So previously,
I'm saying that you can view this as adding components and then changing the scale, right,
to from 2 pi to 8 pi, right? But the equivalent to that you can also think about, okay,
forget about changing the axis. I'm using the same axis here, all right? So for example,
this is my x, I'm going to change this to y, which is equal to x omega divided by 4, right?
This is by 4. So what I'm actually having will be the same axis, no change of axis,
still between 0 to 2 pi, right? I'm just expanding this function to something like this, right?
So here, this was originally let's say k, so I will end up with 4k, right? Some number.
All right, I'm expanding my function. So similarly, there was another, there should be another waveform
here originally something like this, but I'm just expanding that to something like this, right?
So in this case, you can also get the same thing, right? Because if you compare this one with this
one, it's the same, right? I got the same result, but I'm interpreting this down some point or
decimation in a different way, right? But both of them are for the same math equation.
You have a different way to interpret the change, but either way is okay, right?
Because they are basically just doing this, this one, right? Just doing this kind of frequency
domain relationship, all right? I hope I didn't confuse you more, but I hope I clarify this a
little bit, right? So my point is this, there's no unique way to explain what's happening in the
spectrum, right? You have your own way, but in the end of the day, all of these interpretation is
just to explain what happened if you have a change in the frequency expression, right? As
long as you stick to that equation, you are good. I mean, you get the same results, all right?
Okay? If you're still confused, you can ask me, right? I'm happy to explain, right? But this is
what happened, but in the end of the day, I hope it's kind of convinced you the change in the
spectrum by looking at the equation in the frequency, right? But the frequency change,
this guy is what truly happened, right? So you have to really understand, you know, or maybe even
memorize this and this equation. This is what actually happened in the frequency, right? Visual
example is just a plot in the spectrum, right? All right? Okay, good. So with that, I'm actually,
this is actually the table summarized all of the equations you need for basic components, right?
Integer factor of up-sampling, down-sampling, interpolation, decimation, this is all you need,
right? And basically the main points we talked about so far are the operations we need in time
domain, right? For decimation, what we need for interpolation and what are the spectrum before
and after the interpolation decimation, right? That's what we just showed. And for decimation,
we need to understand why anti-aliasing is needed, right? So anti-image is the post, you know,
the post-processing for interpolation, right? Anti-aliasing is the pre-processing for down-sampling,
all right? And you must be able to correctly plot the spectrum achieved before and after this kind
of process, which was just covered just now, right? So you may have some examples, some questions
in homework, in exam, ask you to plot the, you know, spectrum roughly. You need to know how
these are expanded, shrinked, how the access are changed, right? Once you get those clear,
you have no problem doing the questions, all right? Okay, so that's all for the basic component.
But those things I learned so far, we learned so far can only deal with integer, right? Integer
factors for up-sampling, down-sampling. But I said that one can also do non-integer scaling,
right? You can do like 1.5 up-sampling, you can do 2.5 down-sampling. But how can we do it, right?
How can we implement that? It's also very simple because we already know, right, so this is actually
changing frequency by a factor of ratio, okay? A more general case, right? But the way to do that
is by using both up-sampling and down-sampling. Why? Because let's say 2.5, right? You can do
five times up-sampling followed by two times down-sampling. This is how you achieve, you
achieve 2.5, right? 1.5, you do three times up-sampling, two times down-sampling, right? You can always
use a fractional number, right? Like here, ratio to achieve any real number, you know, real number
kind of rate change, right? But the key here is that if you want to do it, make sure you always do
interpolation first, followed by decimation. That's the principle. Okay, why? It's very easy, right?
Interpolation, you don't lose anything. You add in zero. Decimation, you are going to lose information,
right? Everybody agree, right? So you definitely need to want to add things first and then removing
things, right? The whole idea is to make sure the information loss is minimized, right? To this end,
if you need to do a fractional factor which is non-integer, if you have to use some down-sampling,
up-sampling, make sure you do interpolation first. Always up first and then down. All right, this is
the principle. So a general pipeline for conversion will be the following, right? You will have an
interpolation in the first place and then up-sam- sorry, a decimator in the second place.
And if they give you the i and d, you can compute the factor conversion here, i divided by d,
right? You can use your own i, your own d to design a specific rate. Okay? Make sense?
All right. So now, like I mentioned, you must do interpolation before and then followed by
decimation. This is to preserve the design of the spectrum characteristics, right? You don't want to
lose things first. You want to gain first and then lose, right? This is the principle.
So both operators, right? Both filters, hd and h... Okay. The interesting part is this. If you do
interpolation first and decimator first, you will find that actually these two guys,
are actually one after the other, right? These two filters are next to each other. In other words,
there's no rate change in the filtering process. You have two filters, no rate change, and they're
just one after the other, right? So it gives you some idea that it can be combined, right? You have
two low pass filter, one after the other, right? So what's the point of apply two times? You can
apply one times, right? You know, if they're both ideal for filter, right? You can just do it one
time. So in fact, that's always what we do, right? So we're going to do a combined filtering, which
is before the down sampling and after the up sampler, right? This is going to replace the two
together, right? This is actually anti-amidgen. This is anti-aliasing. You just need one filter
to get rid of both. But these combined filter must capture the highest sampling rate in the system.
So in other words, if you have, let's say, you know, two filters, right? I don't know, one, let's say
one is actually, how should I say, pi divided by i, the other one is pi divided by d, right? If i is
not equal to d, you must pick the one, for example, i and d, which is actually larger, right? i and d,
either one, if it's i is larger, you have to do pi divided by i, right? If d is larger, you have to do
pi divided by d, right? So this is also easy to understand because you have two low-pass filter,
right? You have two plus low-pass filter multiplied together, always the narrow passband will wings,
right? So in other words, either way, d or i, you take the maximum and you can compute the overall
color frequency, right? So after merging, you're going to have a pipeline like this, right? After
sampling, low-pass filter together combined and then done sampling, right? So this will be the
overall pipeline and make sure the color frequency for this guy will be the minimum of the two,
right? In other words, if you have a pi divided by, you know, something, let's say n, right? So n will
be the maximum of the, you know, i and d, right? So maximum i and d, right? So whatever color frequency
is smaller, you stick to it. The other one doesn't matter, right? Okay? So in this case, right? So
in the, let me see, output of the, oh, okay. So if this case output of the op sampler here,
this guy will be, let's talk about the time domain frequency, time domain, right? First, right? We
go through every step, right? So the v here will be, apparently, for, we followed the op sampler,
right? Like the time domain representation like this, right? And after the low-pass filter,
so this step, right? Low-pass filter itself is actually a time invariant process. So we take the
output of the v and pass through a low-pass filter. In time domain, this is a convolution, right? You
convolve your v with h. And if you write down the convolution, this will be the form, right? Following
form. But of course, your vx, or in this case vk, will not be nonzero everywhere, right? They will
only be nonzero when the l is integer of the i, right? So in this case, you can change the variable
from k to ki, right? And only the ki will give you nonzero output. Other one will be zero,
so they can be killed, right? So the output time domain after the low-pass filter will be
this 4.3, right? So let's stick to the time domain first. Later, we'll talk about the frequency
domain, right? And then, you know, down sampling will be something very straightforward. You can
just, you know, output down sampling by scanning the index by m, right? So this one will give you
the final output in the time domain, right? So there's also some kind of factoring, how should I
say, in my original slides, there's adding some of the factor like you'll get a zero, get some kind
of off-the-grade elements. I remove it because I don't want to bring your troubles, right? But
mathematically, this is the form. You don't have to deal with those off-the-grade effects. I won't
give you the test on that. But I wish you to understand how from time domain we go from all the way
here to the end, right? This is something you need to know. From step to step, right? How the
up sampling works, how the low-pass works, and how the down sampling works, all right? Mathematically,
now we want to look at visually, right? Visually what happens? You know, you should be able to do
this because this is nothing but a combination of the visual change of the interpolation plus the
decimation, all right? So let's take this example where you have a two times up sampling followed
by a low-pass filter and followed by a down sampling of five, right? So initially, this is my x,
right? My input spectrum. So I want to get the spectrum after the up sampling. So what should
we do? Remember for up sampling, what should we do? So for up sampling, what we actually did is
actually adding the components, right, to the... Wait, why? This is increased. Let me see.
Wait a second. Why? There should be adding some components to it, right?
Oh, because this is... Okay, so this is actually... Okay, I was wrong. This is before the anti-image
filters, right? So ideally, if you're doing this, you should add components to the middle, right?
But here, this is actually the images. I haven't get rid of images because this is actually without
applying anti-image filter, right? So this is just up sampling. But after that, you need to design
this guy very carefully, right? So this is actually the spectrum of the filter. So the
filter must be capturing the anti-image filter from this guy and also the anti-aliative filter
from this guy, right? So now you have a factor of two and a factor of five. You need to make a
decision, right? What is the color frequency of your overall low-pass filter in the middle,
okay? So we say that the principle will be taking the minimum, oops, where's my mouse,
taking the minimum of the two, right? So in other words, you need to compare the i and d,
right? In this case, your i is two, your d is five. In this case, your color frequency must be
maximum of the two, right? So in other words, it must be pi over five, right? Because pi over five
is smaller than pi over two. So your color frequency must be pi over five here. So you need to have a
low-pass filter that's satisfying not only the anti-image filter, but also the anti-aliasing
filter, right? So in this case, make sure your combined filter will be limited to zero from zero
to pi over two, pi over five, right? But of course, as you can see here, this is not an ideal low-pass
filter, right? This is actually slightly not ideal filter. But anyway, it is still within the pi
over five. So you can apply this filter to the original input here, right? And by doing so,
anything within here will be killed, right? So only in this part will it be limited to
pi over five will survive, right? This is actually a filtered image here, right? Filter signal here.
And now because it is band limited to pi over five, now if you do a down-sampling or a decimation
here, it will be safe because already this is pi divided by five limited. So when you create, let's
say, five replicas in the middle, you will not have overlap, right? So this is actually the final
output we have, like here, right? But the important part is this filter. You have to make sure this
filter is properly chosen, right? And the color frequency must be the minimum of the two from the
down-sampling, from up-sampling, from down-sampling, you compare the two,
whichever give you the smaller kind of color frequency, you use that one, right? This is actually
how you can design it. But this figure shows you a pipeline, right? Gradually going from the input
all the way to output and they give you the visual change, right? Okay? All right, so be
prepared for some questions like this, you know, and make sure you know how to choose the, you know,
the color frequency, right? I may not give you something very obvious, but you should use this
principle to make a decision, okay? All right. Change bias. Oh, of course, you know, here you
can actually scale it, right? But for this case, it doesn't matter, right? You can use one. The more
important thing is make sure the waveform is not distorted, right? But in principle, you can also
use a constant scanning, not necessarily one, right? Okay, so this will summarize, right? So far,
we have learned three cases, okay? Three different cases. Decimation, interpolation by integer, right?
Just one component, we'll do. Basic component. By combining the two, you can also implement a
fractional of the change, right? And you can do a interpolation followed by a decimation
to reach a ratio of the integers, right? So in principle, you can do any rate, any rate of up
sampling or any rate of down sampling, right? By designing the ratio property. And you need to
understand how the things are changed, right, in time domain and also in the frequency domain,
right? And for decimation and interpolation, the order is different, right? Decimation, just like,
okay, just now I was talking to some of the students, right? So you can actually refer this back to
the lecture one we talked about, right? If you remember lecture one, we say this is actually
the pipeline for sampling. And if you remember the sampling pipeline, I'm saying that we will have a
sampling stage and the reconstruction stage. And in fact, this sampling stage is very like
the decimation we're talking about, right, if you remember here. This is the decimation we talk
about here, right? And the pipeline, I think it is in followed by down sampling, is very similar to
A2D process. Why? Because you can actually view analog signal as a discrete signal with
infinity large rate, right? Just make the points very dense. It's going to give you something
like a discrete signal. So this kind of risk is there, right? Both in the sampling and down
decimation, if you are decimating image or the signals too aggressively, right? In this case,
not high enough sampling rate. In the decimation case, too large ratio when you do down sampling,
right? And correspondingly, the reconstruction stage is very similar to the interpolation stage
here. If you treat the analog signal as a super high or infinity large sampling rate, rate of
discrete signal, interpolation is just like reconstruction, right? You are going from lower
rate to higher rate. So you can actually relate that to, right? That will help you to memorize why
filter must be before or after the operator, right? It's the same principle, okay? So, but
basically, for today's lecture, you have to be very sure about the order and you have to be very
sure about the relationship not only in the time but also in the frequency domain, right? So both
of them you must be able to derive and use, right? And the filter, right? For both scenarios,
the filter matters and the filter color frequency will be in terms of the sampling frequency
for decimation and output sampling frequency for interpolation, right? So you have to be able
to determine the color frequencies. And when we talk about the conversion of the ratio, right?
These in needle filter, you have to check which one give you a smaller color frequency, right? In
other words, is D larger or I larger, right? You pick the larger one which gives you the smaller
frequency and that one becomes the overall color frequency amongst the two, right? So it's going
to be minimum of the two, determining the low pass filter in the middle, right? So this is like a
summary so far but if you know the three cases, you are all good for multi-rate processing, right?
Not by design filter but by, you know, formulating the mathematical relationship, right? It should
be fine, right? Basically, you can do anything, all right? So make sure you know them. Let me say
this again. You will have a question on this part, you know, for sure. So if you're not familiar with
that, you know, better check it or you can ask me, right? I'm happy to take any questions. Okay, now
the second part of today's, actually the third part for today's lecture is that
now we know mathematically how you can do up sampling, you can do down sampling, you can do
any rate. Now how can we implement this in the system, right? So what is actually the
way we should implement that? Just like when we implement the filters, right? We learn the
ideal path filter but we say, well, to implement that, we need to do FIR, right? So here, if we want
to implement a multi-rate system, what should we do in practice, right? So in practice,
you know, when we design that, you have to think about efficiency, right? Efficiency is always the
consideration for actual implementation. So if you stick to very high rate, because we're going
to change the rate from time to time, right? If you stick to the high rate, there is a need to
have a faster DSP, right, in principle. In other words, you have to pay more for the computational
resource, right? So actually, if you want to do the same thing, right, deal with like very high rate
without paying too much or in other words, less computational complexity, right? You actually
need to minimize the cost for the acceptable performance, right? So basically, you have to
control the rate. On one side, you will have implemented the desired multi-rate system. On the
other hand, you have to accept doing some minimum rate to get the acceptable performance, right?
So this is actually the design principle. So if we consider the pipeline we just look at here,
normally the way you do that is by first increase the rate by i, right? And by doing so, you have
to somehow implement insertion of i minus 1 0s. Remember, we are talking about adding 0 to 2
adjacent measurements for my input, right? So that's how you can achieve the signal after
up some point, right? But eventually, you need to do down some point, right? You eventually have to
remove the numbers, remove the elements from the input signals, right? So this one gives you some
kind of inefficiency, right? Because anywhere you are going to remove it, why do you need to add
things in the first place, right? So just like if you think about FFT, right, when we say FFT can
speed up the DFT, it's the same principle. Sometimes you have to do some repeated computation.
That's where the redundancy comes from. And if you can identify that kind of space, it gives you
some room to improve, right? So similar here, if we know that we're going to remove some elements
eventually, right? You don't have to maybe you don't have to insert too many 0s in the beginning,
right? This will give you some room to improve. So in this case, where you think this is actually
very inefficient because only one out of I input is 0, right? Because here you actually
have sampled I time. So in I adjacent elements, only one is nonzero, right? This is actually one
of the inefficient parts. And also consider the output stage. Out of D filtered output,
only one is going to be output, right? So you actually take only one measurement,
out of D adjacent measurements. So in this case, even though you don't really need a signal in
such a high rate, you have to somehow operate everything in the highest possible sampling
rate in the system. So this is actually the place where the redundancy comes from, right?
And the design is actually trying to find the efficient implementation, right? To reduce the
total computational complexity while preserving the accurate output, right? This is where the
efficiency comes from, right? So the solution for that, I mean not only a solution, but one of
the solution for it is to introduce so-called multi-phase filter structure, okay? So let me first
explain what is polyphase, all right? So we talk about multi-rate, okay? Multi-rate is up
sampling, down sampling, right? That's like how fast you are processing the signal, okay? Now
polyphase is different from multi-rate, even though this sounds very similar, right? But it's not,
okay? Phase is not equal to rate, okay? Phase, think about, we talk about signal,
z-transform, right? Phase shift, okay? I hope you still remember what is phase shift, right? Phase
shift is nothing but z to the power of minus 1 or z to the power of minus 2, right? You have some kind
of a change of the phase in the frequency domain, right? If you shift the phase to some kind of a
delay, it's going to give you a phase change, right? So here the polyphase filter structure is
saying that we're not going to only do one branch without any phase change. We're going to do multi-
branch and every branch with some phase change and together they can implement a multi-rate system.
But every branch, due to the phase change, I don't have to run in an extremely high rate,
right? This is the principle. You kind of divide and conquer. You have to, you originally have to
do a very high-rate processing, but you divide that into multiple phase versions of the signal
processing. Every branch hopefully can lower the rate, all right? So this is where the polyphase
come from. So mathematically, right, the polyphase processing structures the following. So consider
let's say I have a filter, right, which is Hn. So I originally, I have to implement Hn in the way
that, you know, you have to, you can actually generate, let's say maybe an IR or FIR in the way
of representing this in the transfer function, right? This is my original transfer function.
So I hope you still remember what is transfer function, right? You do a z transform of your
impulse response because, you know, the transfer function. Originally I have to do, you know,
maybe a rate is very high, but I can actually decompose it into, let's say, not from,
they say zero order, first order, third order. I will do zero order, then directly M order,
and then, you know, two M order, something like that. So now you see that the number of measurements
here in every term becomes lower, right? So in other words, originally it's actually H0,
H1, H2, all the way to HM. Now I only sample at H0 and the HM, right? So in some way you are lower
the rate in this term, right? Let me just use a pointer. So no, actually the pointer here. So
this term alone, right, I'm separating only sample at M number of lower rate. I separate that,
this color, like a zero phase term, I will have a lower rate kind of a filter, right? But of course,
I have to deal with other term. So the second term will be sampled at H1, HM plus one, maybe H2M
plus one, something like that, right? But of course I need to make a phase shift beforehand.
If you multiply this in, this one gives you the first order term, right? This one gives you the
M plus one order term, all right? But I can take it out. I will have a correspondingly a
down sampled version of my impulse response, okay? I hope this makes sense for everyone, right?
So by doing so, you can do this for, let's say, z to the power of minus one, z to the power of minus
two, all the way to z to the power of minus M minus one, right? You extract that into M different
branches, okay? Every branch becomes a lower rate processing, okay? I hope, I don't know whether this
confuses you or make it clear, right? But basically, I'm doing nothing but separating all of these
components into M groups, all right? So every line is a group. So every group will have fewer
number of impulse here, exactly one over M number of impulse. So it's actually lower rate because
you're processing this every M, you know, impulse, right? But you are going to do M groups. So it's
not only one group, but M groups. So it's going to divide the entire high rate processing into
M number of lower rate processing. This is what the polyphase is doing, right? So in this case,
you are formed the corresponding representation of the polyphase structure mathematically, right?
And you can actually, the components P here. So let me see, okay. So this is original form, right?
But if you look at the expression every, in every term, right? This is corresponding to the subsample
version of your initial, sorry, it's not subsample version, but it's actually a version that is
lower, right? Remember, if you do a down sampling, it's the same as you change the variable to Z to
power of M, right? If you're doing down sampling M times. So you can view these four filter in every
branch as a corresponding filter P, let's say P0, P1, P2, P3, but down sample version, right? So this
is your M down sample version of the filter P0, P1, P2, then sum them together. Okay. So basically,
I'm just changing the variable. I'm just calling the whole thing here as the P0 Z to power of M,
right? The second term here as the P1 Z to power of M. I just give the name, right? But every P here
corresponding to every branch, right? Every face. And here the PI is defined as the following, right?
So every PI is called a polyphase component of the entire polyphase structure, right? So I index
which branch you are talking about, right? And this can be obtained by down sampling a delayed
version of the original HN, right? I already mentioned to you, right? Because here the coefficients
are all coming from impulse response of my original filter H. But I down sample that, right? So I
sample like every M elements, right? H0, HM, H2M. So every PI can be treated as a down sample version
of the delayed original filters, right? Impulse response. Okay? So as you can see, here's where the
lower rate come from because I'm doing down sampling, right? I can achieve a down sample
of the version of the filter that may be high rate in the beginning. All right. So by doing so,
let's give you an example, right? M equals 3. I'm able to represent the original, let's say this is
my original filtering, into a polyphase structure, which is going to be three terms, not only one
term, but three terms. Every term corresponding to one polyphase components, right? So this actually
P0 is actually corresponding to the first term, right here. So I can do P0, P1 and P2, but of
course there must be a delay here, right? Phase delay here. And actually you can even extract
the common factor Z minus 1 and group the next two terms, right? So why are we doing this?
So if we do this and the correspondingly, if you remember the block diagram we talked about before,
right? You can have a block diagram where every branch corresponding to one component of the
polyphase, right? So the first component, well, take care of the first branch. So no delay,
just a P0. This is my first branch, okay? The second branch you need to add a delay here, right?
So this Z1 delay will deal with the second branch and this is my P1, right? And then you do another
delay and the P2, right? This is my P2. So you can actually decompose a single branch high rate
processing into a multi branch lower rate processing, right? This is what the polyphase is doing,
okay? So in this way it's going to, I mean, of course, this is not the only way, right? So
this is the block diagram directly derived from my expression. But I hope you still remember that
we can actually use the equivalent form to implement the block diagram, right? So by doing so,
you can actually get from here to here. So going from here to here is just like the transpose,
right? If you remember, you change the input and output, you can get the transpose, right?
And also you can, how should I say, you can actually, let me see what happened here, right?
So he's first doing the transpose and let me see what, why he can do this one?
So this is my P0, right? And then this is my P1. So he do a P1 and then, oh, he's doing time delay
afterward, okay? Which is also fine. I mean, he just changed the order, right? So he's moving the
time delay to the, you know, P1 but afterward and then he's doing the time delay two times. So he
has to group the two and move it here. But anyway, so eventually the point is that you have multiple,
equivalent way to implement the original polyphase, right? But you can always start from the direct
way, right? You can just represent everything and make it a multi-bridge. But equivalent form
doesn't really reduce the computational, right? It's still the same computational,
but you can actually interchange between two equivalent forms, right? To implement that.
But the principle, the basic idea is that they give you a way to lower the rates, right? And in this
kind of a signal flow graph, it's going to give you a set of, they can always represent it in set of
branches and nodes, just like when we do the block diagram, right? So here when we say branch,
we are basically talking about, you know, this is actually called one branch, right? Everything is
actually one branch. And nodes normally define the connection points of the branches in the structure,
right? So we use nodes to describe the connection points. And we are going to use some of the
components like this. So we have learned some components before, right? Addition, you know,
splitting points, we also learned what is the delay, right? But now talking about the multi-rate,
we're going to have something different. So we may see something like a down sampling, right? You
should, you know, once you see a down sampling with D, you should know that it's a D number of kind
of reducing the rate. And also there could be up sampling, which is I, right? Input output, these
are pretty standard. But these two components are something new. Only appears in a multi-rate system,
right? And this is a page where I show you that it's possible to manipulate some of the, you know,
components, right? If you want to change the order. So I quickly go give you some idea, but
feel free to read them more details, right? So for example, if you have, let's see,
up sampling by L, right? And down sampling by also L, these two can cancel each other, right? I
hope this makes sense to most of you, right? You have up sampling and you down sampling. So if
it's the same rate, you can cancel each other, right? Do I need to explain this? I mean,
it should be very straightforward. You're adding zero and then you remove zero, right? You got the
same thing, all right? Same for, but, okay, if you do up sampling first and down sampling,
they can cancel each other, all right? But if you have down sampling first and then up sampling,
all right? This you have to be very careful, right? Because you may get some zeros, okay? Why?
Because you see, you are losing information first and then you're adding zero to it. You cannot get
back to the original signal, right? So you have the same rate, but there will be many zero in between,
okay? So this is also the idea when you do like a fracture of the rates, you have to first do
interpolation and then decimation. If not, you're going to end up many zeros in between. So by doing
so, combine the two, I'll give you only non-zero, only one at the point where n equal to the integer
number of n, right? It's not equal to the original signal, right? This is the rate you have to be
bearing in mind, right? And the other thing is such as if you have down sampling followed by another
down sampling, you can combine the two, right? This should be easy. And the combination is by
multiply the factor, right? Up sampling is the same. You can multiply them together. But I mean,
I won't go through everyone, but you just check them one by one. But these are some of the common
operators that you can apply and play with the block diagram which involves multirate processing,
right? Make sure you are convinced by everyone, okay? You may need to use it. But I want to really
emphasize the following things, right? This is called noble identity, okay? This is the most
important identity we are going to introduce because very likely we're going to use them
anytime to, you know, get rid of this, you know, different kind of a rate conversion, right? So
what does that mean? It basically means we want to prove the equivalence of the left figure. So
here. So what does that mean? So it means I will, if I first do down sampling followed by a filter,
right? I mean, this is not a conventional way. Conventionally, we have to do anti-aliasing first
followed by down sampling, right? But if we have a down sampling first followed by a low pass filter,
right? You want to make it correct. You want to change the order to make it low pass first,
down sampling second. How can I make the two equivalent? So you can swap the order, but
the low pass filter must be changed the rate. Okay, you can see that the difference here is
originally this is my HZ, right? This is after the down sample version. But if I swap the order,
I still have a low pass filter in beforehand. But if you see that the rate of my low pass
filter has already been D times. Okay. All right. So you can prove it, but I give you some intuition,
right? So you have a filtering filter, which is in the low rate version of the signal.
Now I have to do a equivalent filtering in the high rate version of the signal,
which means if you want to do the same thing, you have to make the low pass filter also high rate.
You have to match the rate. So in this case, every time if you want to bring
beforehand your low pass filter across the down sampling, you have to increase the rate
of your low pass filtering, which is by changing the Z to Z to the power of D.
Right? Remember, if you do Z to the power of D, you are enlarging the omega by D times, right?
This is how you modify your filters. Okay? And similarly, if now I want to do the same thing
for the up sampling, right? We just learned that for up sampling, the entire image filter must be
after the up sampling operator, right? But somehow if your filter is before it,
and you want to bring it back, bring it forward to the afterward position, you also need to change
the rate. Why? The similar reason, right? Originally, I'm doing the low pass filter in the low rate
version before up sampling. Now I want to do the similar thing in the high rate version.
I have to increase my filtering rate correspondingly by eye time.
Okay? Let me repeat, right? So the novel identity tells you the way to make the equivalent filtering
if you want to swap the order between up sampling, down sampling, and the low pass filter. It gives
you the guidance. If you want to swap, how can I change my filter accordingly? So they won't be the
same filter, right? The only change is the rate of the filter. So if you want to bring the filter
to the in front of the down sampling, you have to increase the rate. Similarly, if you want to bring
the filter after the up sampling, you have to increase the rate. The rate will be correspondingly
to the up sampling and down sampling rate because the whole idea is to match the corresponding
rate of the signal, right? Every time you do rate change, the signal rate will be different.
Your low pass filter will also be the matched rate. So this is the corresponding scaling, right?
So this will be, if I ask you, right? If I ask me, this is the most important property to play
with the Bloch diagram. So make sure you know it. If you can, you can prove it. So I won't really
go to the proof, but you can check them if you want, right? Basically, you can mathematically
derive, right? If you change the order, what happened? But I kind of give you some idea, right? If you
want to memorize it, what's the right way to memorize it, right? The idea is to match the
rate. You don't change the waveform of your low pass filter, but you have to scale your passband
accordingly, right? This is the principle, okay? But make sure you know how to bring it back,
bring it down, you know, back, forward, and how to change the rate because I will give you some
tests on that, right? Just a warning. I mean, homework, you will see some of the questions,
right? And later you will see what I'm talking about, right? So, but if you see that's such a
little question, like changing order, swap the order, this is the weapon you need to use, okay?
Or maybe plus some of the property here, right? Some property here. So this table and this
identity is the weapon you need to use, right? So if you get no ideas to do the homework,
check the slides here, okay? All right, so almost the end, all right? So,
observe the response of this. Okay, so in this case, right, you can actually tell that the
decimator, in fact, can be viewed as a transpose of the interpolator, right? And that's why we see
that decimator is the due of the interpolator, vice versa, right? Because if you still remember
the, what is that? The transpose structure, right? You have a block diagram, you want to transpose it.
Previously we say that, you know, you can actually change the adding, adder to the, you know,
splitting point, right? You can also revert the order, order of the signal flow. But if your
block diagram involves the rate change, you can consider the down sampling as the transpose of
an up sampling, right? Because they are the exact due operator. So that's why, that's why how you can
do a transpose, which involves also the rate change, right? So according to transformation,
right, it can be achieved by changing the input to output. So for example, if I want to find the
corresponding transpose of this guy, I can actually simply doing the opposite, right? This
will be the due of it, right? Similarly, if you want to change the up sampling to it, you can
actually, so you actually find the due of it. You change the order and you flip the sign of the
up sampling and down sample, right? This is how you can achieve it. Oh, sorry, from A to B, sorry,
from A to B, you change the order, right? Output becomes input, input becomes output,
down sampling becomes up sampling. So A or B will be equivalent, right? And C and D will be equivalent.
This is how you do transpose to get the equivalent kind of block diagram, right?
So I think that's all I want to cover today. Again, you know, I strongly encourage you to
derive this one, even though I don't really go through it, but I strongly encourage you to derive
it. If you really cannot do it, at least memorize this one, right? How you change the rate, okay?
The idea is to match the rate before and after down sampling, before and after, you know, up
sampling, right? But if you can, I strongly encourage you to derive it, right? It shouldn't be
very hard, but you have to sit down and work out the math and make sure the filter is matched
before and after the swap, okay? But with that, this is what I want to cover for the basic
multirate processing, right? It's not the end. So next, do I have something? Okay, no. So next week,
I'm going to talk about like how to implement the filter, right? Just like the way we implement
for single-rate processing. I'm going to say a few things about how to use polyphase filtering
to implement the multirate processing, right? But for today's lecture, right, the takeaway
will be the following. You need to know first why we need to do multirate processing, okay? We talk
about the reason of different source of the input. We talk about the same input may have
different module of the processing module, right? They may have different rates. And we have four
basic modules, right? Up sampling and it can be evolved to interpolation. We have down sampling,
it can be evolved to the decimation. So you need to know the difference between the two,
all right? The difference will be the additional anti-aliasing, sorry, anti-image filter.
The additional will be the anti-aliasing filter, right? And make sure you know the representation
in both time and frequency, all right? Not only time, but also frequency. You need,
every operator, you need to tell me in time how the input and output related,
in frequency, how the two are related, right? And also how to design and manipulate the rate,
sorry, sampling conversion system, right? So you have ratio of the factor, how can we design an
interpolation followed by a down sampling. So you can actually use this kind of i divided by d to
reach any ratio, right? And now the second part is become the polyphase structure. So you should
understand why polyphase structure by using multiple branches. Every branch can possibly reduce the
rate. In other words, reduce the computational resource, right? Computational complex. But of
course there's no free lunch. You have to do multi-branches. So understand how this multi-branche
is derived from your multiple terms of the transfer function, right? You should be able to
decompose it and draw the block diagram, right? And in the end, given the block diagram, I may
ask you to manipulate it, right? Moving the filter forward, backward, find the equivalent kind of
identity. So noble identity is the most important thing you need to know, right? We're going to
keep using that for many of the questions. And also, you know, this table, these are some trivial
kind of equivalency. Make sure you know what they are and make sure you can use them. We won't be
able to prove them, but at least you understand why there's some kind of a change possible, right?
Like cancellation each other, why you have to do up-sumpling first, followed by down-sumpling.
The other way will not be exactly equal, right? Make sure all of these are convincing to you,
okay? For that, I think you should be no problem dealing with this part, all right? But, you know,
look forward to the homework. So with this knowledge, you may need, you may be able to do the first
one or two questions, all right? The last question you need to wait until the next week and maybe the
last week lectures, okay? So the homework will be announced, I think maybe Wednesday or Thursday,
okay? So I will make an announcement and you should be able to find that in the homework,
all right? Okay, so thank you so much. That's the end. So, yeah, hope to see you next week.