So it's good to have proper lectures for the first hour and then we will do the quiz
after the break.
So everyone come back by 7.50 and for those who are not here, anyway, they will not be
able to get my message until after the quiz is over because it's a video recording, not
the online lecture.
So anyway, I can assure you the quiz question will not be too difficult, probably compatible
with previous years and there are also probably one or two so-called Song Feng tea.
So I will see if the students make mistake on that very simple one then I think probably
it will be, I will see actually we are fighting out students who did not do well if the students
like those under AW from certain university then we will consider raising path.
So I hope everyone, I mean not only for yourself but for your previous university because it
may affect the so-called names.
So this is some side story because I'm your provident, I'm one of the program directors
so we are looking into this particularly since August this year we have many more students
so I think this semester will be a so-called benchmark because we have more students then
I hope the performance will not drop that significantly.
Okay.
Yeah, actually we will do some groupings later but I think some of you took my course in
the next door, LT19 last week so today I will show you I will do a better job to see you
properly.
So we are going to that later on as I say we still have some lecture not finished yet
chapter 3 and I'm not rushing to do all the remaining part because we only have about
one hour.
Anyway, next week we will still, you see have time to finish the, just leave a little bit
of chapter 3 more of the application or some methods.
So I think this is week 12 and no choice I have to finish grading your marking your
quiz within one week so hopefully next week I come back the final lectures I can also
discuss briefly.
Particularly the so-called Song Feng Ti Wui, any student cannot do or make a serious mistake
or not.
So anyway let's see later for the 7402 they are in general okay but they are, I can say
for quiz there are at least two or three student fairs, I mean below 40 marks out of 100 so
so I hope you can do a better job here okay.
So let's, so last week we start from the power spectrum estimation.
So this course if you look at the lecture note it's not that many pages but the contents
quite things and also requires not just math, statistics also signal processing like DSP
and so on and yeah but as I say for quiz and final exams will exclude certain difficult
parts such as IRR, Wiener filter which is most difficult one.
So let's have a very quick review I won't go into detail but I would like to perhaps
give more overall pictures here.
So let's see, power spectrum estimation is just like you see if you are learning DSP
you have the frequency response you see and you have time domain given some time domain
signal speech or deal because here our course is not like image where most students still
based on like 1D signals which is the basic and the starting points and then we, let's
see here given the signal in time domain actually I hope that your level MSE or yeah some PSD
or so you should have much better understanding why do we want to go to frequency domain because
in time domain sometimes you know if you have two signal which is very, looks very similar
in the waveform and noise sometimes very heavy then very hard to look from time domain to
separate the signal.
So frequency domain is at least in some sense you see if you have signal with periodic signal
from different frequency then we go to the frequency domain you can look at the different
frequency component can even tell which one is the stronger signal and so on.
So this is one very basic of the motivation and DSP is mostly for deterministic and for
so called maybe signal in noise but not really looking at the signal itself range but in
the advanced level like this course in the 7402 we are also looking at even useful signal
but they are ranked them in some sense such as here we have so called sideways but it's
not totally deterministic in part of the primary typically like the phase it could be ranked
them and in such a case how are we going to handle to detect this kind of harmonic or
sideways or you know and that's also similarly we have the frequency domain approach by taking
say Fourier transform but here since we involve random signal so we cannot just simply like
in the time domain we directly take the Fourier transform and look at the spectrum.
So here we are looking into higher level like the second order statistic which involves
starting with autocorrelation as you do autocorrelation cross correlation and there are that why because
children may ask why do we go through that? Actually we are looking more carefully doing
autocorrelation it's reduced or at least it gets some more deterministic features from
the random signals. It's kind of taking the average in some sense so after that we can
take the Fourier transform and we get the spectrum information and it's more reliable.
So that's the similarity and difference taking this advanced DSP assuming probably this most
of you you took the DSP. So and then we start from the motivation you see because finite
duration and noise so there was one of some of the main reason we're looking at that and then
there you can see these three measures they are closely related but in a different way.
No parametric it's just a directory work on the given signal to extract the spectrum
information from there. So this is more classical and easy to apply but the result for unless
for very simple and clear signal otherwise it's not I would say very classical. It's also the
earlier and the other day we moved to parametric. In fact it's to somewhat closely related. We
should say we start with a more traditional parametric which is like AR model. We look at
rational spectrum starting from rational function and then estimate those coefficient. So and
they are moving on this is eigen and energy is considered relatively modern although it also
has been several decades at one time is a very popular research topic in the early years for
those before I told this course for me for five or six years but before that this was not in part
of the curriculum so I think eigen energies is quite useful because you can apply to some of the
even more recent research direction such as at one time quite popular like the compressed
same things and actually even nowadays subspace analysis even in image analysis you see are
doing clustering this subspace concept is very very useful. So I will say this is part of the
parametric but it's a more elegant approach and then it has a wider application but given this
limited hours or weeks and then including we are doing the quiz in part of the course here. So the
introduction would be rather brief so but the the the maths there also a little bit complicated
because in both you know magic theories and also we include like complex complex variable
in into into discussion because in some of the methods once you involve Fourier transform as
you all know you are going to the frequency domain which you involve complex number so you can
really avoid that. So I hope you maybe also learn you know how to handle complex number and so
on. Okay so yeah so very quickly you go through some of the maths background which I already did
last week but I will highlight the more important or more difficult one I think square matrix which
you can get the eigenvalue eigen vector I think this one should be very very basic requirement and
then in particular if for low dimension low mean two or maximum three I think three by three
matrix as you can see some of the past year papers not every year but it does appeal so you
need to know how to be able to get the determinant you see here you Kramer Kramer Lu is you see you
want to get this determine you take any one row one column okay say one row then first element
then cross out then look at this determinant two by two then two by two matrix everyone know how to
get the get a determinant cross multiply subtract cross and then multiply and then the next one which
you change the minus sign and then also do the same cross out this then you will get the determinant
and the better and this one usually you'll choose one has at least probably one zero like this at the
first one they don't need to you don't need to calculate this on your g low multiply anything
become g low so you only have two okay in this case you can also do some simplification first yeah
yeah that's how I even get get the stats so it's on plus this one you have the star with a minor one
and no include this one this minor one except it's already there so you need to add another
multivibrant minor one expand and then it become a third order polynomial then make it equal to zero
or do the factorization and so on and then once you'll get the eigenvalue you can start to get the
eigenvector so this is a little bit more difficult because you will need to be familiar with solving
system of equation because one of these become zero three that also tells you the very concept about
the ring of matrix eigen for eigenvalue once you're putting the end them in this
matrix it reduces the ring by at least one so typically reduce one become two so two ring
matrix among the three rows two and most two of them are linearly independent so you can
just take any two and then you see you have you have two equations three variable so one of them is
redundant so you use that as you know it's a free parameter and you can solve so this you know some
students find it difficult to solve but try try your best to yeah review so once you solve then
there you see this is a so-called free parameter then there are many many choice you can scale this
vector as long as no zero but they have to too many how are we going to choose
normalization that's right this is also you know some of the some of the steps you use are very
common across different subjects different areas such as in you are doing machine learning your
wrong neural network normally you cannot just get any data then putting you have to do some
pre-processing and normalization is a typically one requirement normalization means you see here the
norms will be normalizing to one so remember we're dealing with probably a complex value also so you
you need either take absolute value or you need to multiply a complex number with the complex conjugate
in order to make it into into the so-called positive positive value okay so I will go into that later
in some of the examples yeah so I think these are very clearly stay here and then unitary
metrics also very important because that involved also go now you see if you have two two two vector
they are also go now so yeah then if all the either all the column or all the rows they form an
orthonormal set then you will have this nice property because you know no singular
metrics you can you always have inverse of course assuming here we are dealing with square
metric one matrix multiplied by its inverse become i but taking the inverse big very very
troublesome particularly for big metric so so this a matrix you take the Hermitson Hermitson
means you because here remember we are dealing with complex number so you'll take the complex
conjugate conjugate is you'll keep the real part unchanged then the imaginary part you'll change
the side maybe yeah and then after that for matrix you also need to do the transfer
so these two operations combined together with Hermitson yeah let's see where this
is
definition
okay yeah basically you yeah you will be taking the
transfer and at the same time take the complex conjugate so this one is illustrating
about if you have the some useful properties so for example if you are having a Hermitson
matrix where here we are talking about eigen eigen value eigen analysis so must be a square
matrix if you are doing singular decomposition you'll allow a no no square metric so so this
property let's see we start with this and then we have eigen vector which is normalized UK and this is
eigen value we already know you can always find the one but then for Hermitson
matrix that means satisfy this they have some very useful property so maybe one of them is
you'll see the all the eigen value they will be rare as if for
a channel in channel you you may have some complex eigen value let's see with this one
okay
okay so let's maybe maybe quick
derivation and explanation about how you handle like complex or what's mean by complex conjugate okay so
uh
to to start with if you all look at just a very simple say say two by two if I have one plus two
j for example
then you also maybe for the diagonal element I make it clear and then you will have one
uh
minus j one plus j so so let's look at this
this matrix versus complex so if you all if you all just do a simple
uh
transfer as if so there will transfer of course you all know diagonal element you'll you'll keep the same
but the off diagonal in this case two by two then you'll just uh change uh exchange this at this position
okay so after transfer these two are not the same okay however the Hermitson you see if I
now if I start with the same the same matrix one minus j one plus j and then three if I take this
Hermitson operation uh it going to mean you're you're doing the two operations at one after
you can do transfer first okay uh okay and then uh after that you'll do the complex
conjugation uh you these two operations you can do complex conjugate first and then do the transfer
is the same you can uh exchange so we already done this you'll transfer you'll get this uh and then
after that you'll do you'll do one more step by the by the conjugate you see then after taking the
conjugate you you'll uh become you see the conjugate is the real part is the same as one but the
imaginary part you'll change the side and similarly similarly this one
okay so so in this case you can see uh this given given matrix here if you take transfer
only it will not be equal to itself but if you take transfer and then follow by the uh conjugate
that's we call the Hermitson Hermitson operation then it become become itself
okay beautiful complex and and that's a very very important property to hang those
complex number complex matrix okay so this is uh at first thing you should be familiar
with this because we talked about a lot the Hermitson operation here and the I think the
lecture note here is not not very clear about uh is it given this one we can let multiplying this
from both sides uh and then uh here I want to explain the meaning of this you see this if I have uh
you okay and then remember for uh a vector a low vector when you take the Hermitson operation it will
become a low vector and at the same time you also need to do the conjugate operation so for example
if uh if this is uk here okay then you you uh our uk uh h you will become uh first you'll
you'll uh do the transfer so uh column become a low and now with that this is the first operation
is very easy things look column and row is just simply uh you know graphically you can see and
now there you'll you'll take another complex conjugate if if there are complex elements
so one question is if all the elements are real of course the real you're equal to itself you see
because uh if you don't have the imaginary part you don't need to change the sign I mean it's zero
so that's how this is done here so uh and then uh follow this uh the uh ebio
to this operation uh vector column vector uh multiply from the left hand side by this uh
uh Hermitson Hermitson operation then you uh in this course I since I only teach half so I did not
spend too much time talk about this uh block block box box method I think uh I mean uh just very briefly
it's it's quite useful very often you're if you're dealing with a matrix you don't need to
most of time you don't need to write down the actual element you know very often you'll you'll just
give the size give the block uh like how many num rows how many columns in in this way then it's
very clear you can you can see in this case it will become a scalar you see this is uh you know
row vector followed by a column vector it will become a scalar uh okay and on that thing if you're
doing uh other way around uh actually not here but just a side side product if you do to this way
you'll just start with a column followed by row then the matrix will be will be totally different
you see you'll end up with a very big square matrix in in such a case okay so this is the two different
operation and anyway this this is very often we're also writing in writing this form is
is uh uh early on we talk about the the l2 norm uh and then the for if you uh take the
l2 norm you will need to take take the square root because this is a one by one a scalar a positive
value uh but then uh quite often we taking square root is a very inconvenient so we square it uh
then there will be the operation sometimes we're calling it as a inner product because
you're multiplying the vector and the her mission transform itself you will be able to so the meaning
of uk you know this double vertical bar and num2 we're taking the l2 norm or it's related to the
distance if you are looking into the 2d space or in the nd nd space okay so uh
so therefore this this part is very clear if you multiply this one uh there of course the
matrix you cannot take out but you'll make reviews of this property okay you're doing there and then
a scalar you can take out so therefore your nwc this part is not
not very clear we want to we want to derive and make good good use of this property from here
and then to see uh you see somehow we are taking the conjugate of this of this icon
icon value uh because we uh we don't know in general the icon value may be complex so how to
how to uh how to verify that there are there are several ways to do the the easiest way to use is
uh you see here uh since we want to look at the so-called conjugate you see conjugate and then
also nwc we multiply with the same norm uh we we want to derive this uh from here
uh into this so so to do that the one way to do as I say here there are several ways by the way
we look at uh one of them this is the given one you see the lambda k uk this is by definition if I
take the take the Hermitian of of both uh when you are dealing with equation you see you do one
operation on the left hand side make sure you do the same on the right hand side so that they were
they will still be equal okay and then let's look at the look at the left hand side uh your nwc
uk uh Hermitian any operation if you apply to a product of two metrics uh always make sure
you break down uh you will uh uh if you have two the the the right hand side one you have to
bring it bring forward uh then it applies to you're taking the transport taking the inverse and so on
so same with this Hermitian you see your uk Hermitian first then followed by the m also
also Hermitian you see so this is from the left hand side that there's no problem because this is
where uh doing the using the basic rule it works for any vector metrics and so on and how about the
right hand side uh because the right hand side one of them is a scalar once you have a scalar
multiplied by a vector or by a matrix you uh you don't need to change the change the order because
a scalar multiplied with a matrix or a vector you can always put your left or right you see
there but as long as you're a vector or magic you cannot okay so let's look at this uh if it will be
namda k hermitian and then also i have the i have the uk transpose here okay
then uh what next we want to uh we want to create something relative to relative
create this okay then naturally you'll be you'll be thinking uh for this one is uk transpose m and
then this this uk so this one will be modeled by left left hand from this side then why don't i do the
one from the right okay so i i multiply uh
uk uh from uh a vector from the right hand side then your n-tab with uh this uk h uk right correct
okay so this one is what we are calling is the norm as we already defined
defined early so now we uh in this way the right hand side we we create this one all right okay then
early on we already derived here equal to equal to this so the only difference is the middle of
m h here where this is m but we already know m equal to m h so so therefore this is equal to uk h uh m
uk and this one uh also where we didn't know is equal to lambda k uh without h uh uk h uk okay
so this one is the same uh therefore uh if uh a scalar
multiplied by this no zero no zero positive value and if this scalar take the scalar you'll take the
Hermitian it's just simply just do the complex conjugate you see uh then they are they are equal
so this uh lambda k must be real so you can i think this is uh uh probably
so if i ask you to verify in the final step i think you should have everyone can do that yeah
right if not then you'll start with the definition of the complex conjugate number okay so from here
you can you can conclude this lambda k must be real because our lambda k is just any eigen
eigenvalue okay so this is the one you can you can you you can be right by doing this kind of
simple property and operation similarly this uh if the two eigenvalues are not the same then
you can you can be sure this the corresponding eigenvector they are uh they are also going to
uh each other so that means this uh in the in your product of the two different vectors
it will be equal to zero so again you you follow a similar argument uh starting from the definition
of eigenvalue eigenvector uh then you can operate and you will surely get get a conclusion this one
must be equal to uh equal to zero so this is a very important uh in in both concepts if we
denote this in in matrix uh now assume uh all the eigenvalue they are real because we're property
one for Hermitian matrix they must all be real and then if they are all different so they will be
very good you put all these eigen eigenvector one by one to form a square matrix and these are the
corresponding diagonal diagonal uh matrix then you can verify this and can be decomposed in such a way
you and then this diagonal and this is you of you of edge so this is uh a very very convenient way
okay and that's uh a very useful property is positive definite
definite matrix and uh i think most of you should be familiar with a real if the matrix is a real
then you can uh you can just take uh no zero no zero vector a real and then multiplied by its
transfer you see but the same property you can extend into complex complex complex matrix but
but make sure these low matrix you have to do the conjugate so that uh in the end this becomes a
scalar you see if you if you are not sure why the vector matrix you multiply become a scalar as you
again if you use this simple box box measure you you just write down the the dimension as you hear
to be compatible this one must be uh you see the number of column must be the same as the number
of row here then in the end this product it will be it will become a one by one matrix which is of
course a scalar so being a scalar uh in general if you're doing uh habitually choose some vector and
matrix complex then you may end up with a complex number or you end up with a negative value or
may end up with a zero value but if you have this spatial matrix for whatever is it so this v is not
just if you verify just with one is not enough you'll have to exhaust you know search of course
theoretically you can it will be very difficult you cannot do even now they very powerful computer
no one is going to do that because this this kind of no zero vector is infinitely many so there are
ways to test but i won't go into detail here but yeah just the definition is yeah you can yeah if you
satisfy that then there will be a positive definite matrix and because of this property any
assume this one is it doesn't satisfy the commission you can do some operation to make it
commission so i think we will not do go through this kind of kind of step actually is easier we
assume any positive definite matrix you just assume will be a commission already satisfied the
commission commission matrix so these are the ways to so-called convert we will not go into that
okay so these are the very useful and then now you can explain this eigenvalue decomposition into
singular value decomposition actually singular value decomposition is equally powerful or in
something even more powerful because it works for no square no no square matrix of course
singular value decomposition based on eigen eigenvalue decomposition you'll need to learn
eigenvalue decomposition you need to have eigenvalue decomposition in order to apply to
singular value decomposition so so so the way to do is for any no square matrix you can
also do the decomposition but only difference here the diagonal element is the same you know it
looks like they are all positive but all depending on the ring if the matrix of ring
are then you have out of them not equal to zero they are actually positive but the
left matrix and right right matrix here there are both unitary unitary matrix mean all the columns
of rows they are they are orthogonal and but they are they are in general different different in
both in size and also they are not having the same element not the same matrix in eigenvalue
decomposition you have the same matrix just take the commission but here they are different okay
then you can yeah you can also for for special square matrix which is of ring r in this case
semi positive definite being you don't need to be greater than zero it can be greater or equal to zero
and not necessarily full ring also it can be smaller ring compared to this then this way the
corresponding singular value decomposition see here it becomes like the very similar to our
eigen decomposition except here the diagonal element is always you you you are square you see
you are always once you're square will be always always positive but then it allows to have some
zero singular value because the ring is only r so so it's and typically we all the the largest one
first and then sequentially going down okay and then the ring to equal to r so you will stop at this
after they become come zero that's right semi definite now we want to relate it to our what we
learned about you see the auto correlation matrix which is very useful in signal processing in the
random signal or statistical signal processing so so again here we are in general dealing with
this positive possibly complex value so remember what I say here this is column vector first
followed by a row vector so it's an outer product it will be become square matrix you see
other way around it will be in the product and then because they are random you see so we
take the expectation and and so you see here auto correlation is somehow you're
you're take using expectation to reduce the randomness and become a
metric here which is in Hermitian it could be positive semi definite semi positive definite
sometimes it's a positive definite sometimes it could be just semi positive definite it's not
not free okay then you'll pay some the definition and this expectation as you hear the
outer product you become matrix but to take expectation you need to know the
PDF for building the function of this of this data then multiply and then do the integration
usually this become a bit complicated and based on this property we know this metric is
Hermitian because you can take the operation of the Hermitian operation on this so
satisfy this furthermore if you now we have this matrix so our definition want to see whether
is semi positive definite you need to multiply need no zero vector which is not random you see so this
x of n is random this w is not random you see so one from the right then there is it could be
complex from the left then you're parking and do a little big simplification n dot with this is again
positive value is a norm 2 you see greater or equal to zero then this kind of integration
you will always n dot with greater or equal to zero because of this property
okay now we move one step further to a more practical setting and we did that for many times
in the chapter 2 and for those taking 7402 this is also a very basic assumption signal or
in noise okay and yeah and this is and here noise we just assume is like white noise of
of variant go to sigma w power 2 then both are statistically independent so this is very important
let me you don't have the you you are not give give a constant because when you
multiply you see plus you make it multiply from as a even outer product is similar to the
to the square square link operation so from two term your n dot n dot is four terms so
that means you have a two cross term here but because of this statistically independent
it will the cross term will become become zero so you only have the signal the so-called
or auto correlation of the signal auto correlation of the noise to accept and and this one because
white noise and then you n dot with this very special noise covariant matrix and this is in
general for the signal we can't say much okay and because it's permission and semi positive
definitely in general then based on what we learned can decompose into this sbd in this way and
it has this eigenvalue up to here then this np is the ruin of the is okay and then
because the noise covariant matrix at this very space very special structure so
you can verify very easily once you do the singularity commotion for the is by adding this one
you you will still n dot with the eigen eigenvector of this ix and the is x and is at the same
but the eigenvalue will be different or the singular value because here this is the singular
very difficult you are basically just adding up the noise and the noise is white so it's cross
all over the place or all the you see so every diagonal you just add this and so that's easy to
verify and then you can see some property also here this r of x this is dealing with the signal
noise no singular if we have noise so so that's why in some applications adding noise is useful
because noise helps you to make the matrix from the from a singular to become become like a full
ring in in this case and then the is is different eigenvalue but the same eigenvector as this is
because of course we assume the noise is white so here this property otherwise if it's not white
then you cannot have this and for the more if we assume we have the
you know lambda of k is the case eigenvalue then those are beyond this np plus one and so on they
are all equal to the noise the eigen the value of the noise and that's equal to the to the minimum
singular value of this rx because remember we all the the value from largest all the way to
the smallest one so therefore this is one way if you all you don't know this noise
value but you are able to get this rx then you can do a singular value decomposition and then
from the smallest eigenvalue of this rx you can you can file assuming of course the the n the number
of sample you use to measure is greater than the ring uh than the yeah than the than the range of this
this is the the signal n typically this refer corresponding to the independent
source signals we are assuming like for example sideways which is what we are we are discussing
so this is a very important concept signal and noise subspace this is what i told you earlier is
subspace and it's very important so how are we going to
to look into this okay remember we already know we can do the singular value decomposition of this
ix and then you're based on the singular value you see we we start from the larger one
uh number one is the largest all the way up to np and so this this is the first term
now that there will be the k from np plus one all the way up to n is another one
so therefore this uk here is the case of the column vector of this also normal for complex
we call it also normal real is also gonna also normal
matrix of this u then it satisfy this you know also normal is if l and m are not the same then
it will become zero this is delta function m you got the l of course you got the one so you'll have
this property and therefore uh this is very useful the two subspace they are mutually orthogonal
you see so that means if this this one from one all the way up to np this is what do i call
signal subspace you have a vector and if you have one vector you'll explain one vector like most
of you are still explaining the one dimension that you can multiply for any no zero value
making infinitely long but a long one vector if you have two you know two vectors as long as they are
also they are even they are assume orthogonal then you'll explain into two d space where it is
playing if you have three three d space and so on so I mean spain mean you'll you'll you'll make the
make the space bigger and bigger and the dimension will be equal to np so this is for the signal
then for noise you use those those uh column vector starting from np plus one as in those
corresponding to this smaller uh single value they'll expand and these two subspace they are also
mutually orthogonal to to each other so this is very important okay and uh let's look at the signal
model so they at least you're linking to our application here assume we are dealing with
sideways but this is not just deterministic sideways because typically we we can assume
and in some application it does the the phase here they are they're random but uniformly
distribute because phase is two pi t or other so over this minus pi to pi uniformly this
distributed but other parameter aka and the frequency they are they are not random they are
deterministic okay then this these are two ways to write typically we know the in real life our
signal is the real in sign cosine but in the analysis just like you are doing Fourier transform is
easier to introduce uh complex sideways or we call it complex exponential exponential signal
and using error formula you can uh any real sine or cosine real signal you can always like
as a sum of two uh you know complex exponential in conjugate okay so so that's why this is up to
if you're p the np will be twice two p if you're yeah big and and also the relationship this uh
amplitude here is a half uh and the amplitude here is uh is an even function so they are all equal
phase is and it's an all function so you'll change side and so on and uh frequency of course we're
assuming but looking to negative frequency so you have this uh okay so that means effectively only
the positive one are useful but you can expand into this and then uh this is a typical uh like
simple case and this uh is if you have a sum of two uh side uh complex exponential signal okay
then if the signal is say delayed by one sample delayed by two sample you can uh you see this is
useful property in the time domain you'll delay in your n-dark ways in the frequency domain you'll
you'll become some phase chip and that's precisely here because uh you can see uh all of these two
are related to this s-n s-n is this so we only need to write down this uh basic uh you know the
the signal without without delay and the other you will be uh this one one of course is
you will be accept then the other one you're every time you have the
shift delay by one you'll get some phase delay delay by two your n-dark ways another one
so this is the one here and then in general from this example you can uh extend it to the general
expression s-n you're you're doing this way this is uh uh you're in total how many you see n-p
uh exponential complex exponential signal here with different frequency and this Q here is the
one you're considering those delay time so now if you want to take the you see we are still looking
at the signal we don't consider noise here i-s equal to this uh uh you take expectation
uh since this is not random you see it doesn't involve time it doesn't involve the phase you see
so uh so uh this Q you can pull it out and only this part can become like random you have to
still keep the x-fone name uh expectation here
and then uh i think i finished this part then i take a break uh we can denote this you see again
this is and then the n-case element of this matrix uh you can work out the it will be a product of
this and remember it could be complex then we need to take conjugate and then you'll put the
n-p-dew out first then these are the uh so-called phase term you'll multiply and this is involving
n is the signal itself n is like the timing deck and then if n-eco to k you'll be looking at the
diagonal element then uh of course uh e of this you are just taking the taking this part then
then of course because the other one become become zero uh then you are taking the absolute value
raise the power of two of them uh now for n-eco to k you can taking expectation and then uh you will see
you see those not random you take out those random ones you keep it here okay and
and then according to our formula and also again now if you're depends on whether n equal to k or
not uh you or c here e of this uh it will be uh k equal to k minus uh m equal to p you see it could be
could be uh equal here we are talking about remember when we explain we will be cross over to the other
half so so therefore this will be equal twice and this is different and not n k minus uh
n not equal to p then they will be independent and either way you can see when you take expectation
uh you you uh it will become zero you can refer back to our early exercises for that so in the end
therefore our is magic will be equal to q then this is a very special diagonal diagonal matrix
and multiply that is and in this way because this is diagonal you can explain into this way so and this
q m uh here is the k column vector of the q you'll divide you'll divide early and then this q
metric is a random matrix and has a ring of minimum and n or np normally we assume n is greater than
np so therefore this is this is matrix is always always singular so yeah therefore you can reduce
this into uh if you add noise this will be the noise and again here this very important important
result this uh the uh signal subspace and the noise there will be there will be orthogonal to uh
also normal to each other if you're dealing with complex and uh yeah so this uh also uh yeah you can
see it derived from this property so it's uh it's the right time to take a break here we have uh several
uh like uh icon decomposition measure applying to uh spectrum uh power spectrum estimation
we will leave this into next week with uh we will go through that and now is 7 36 uh usually
it's the right time we take a break about just uh 14 10 to 14 minutes so everyone come back to
here uh come back to here before uh 7 4 50 you need to take a break I also want to do
show you the how we do the do the grouping uh because this time I like all the name here
hope this is clear because uh last time some student uh anyway we are not very clear later you can
you can come up to have to see uh so basically we do the grouping according to your surname
alphabetical order and uh last week for the other call there are many students a bit confused
they have the same surname li and they don't know whether they belong to group one or two so so now
very clear and then there are many one as you also uh you know this time all the one are here
all the lead they're only this lead lead zongda will be the second group and how uh I designate the
the area uh later let me show you here uh typically group one three okay so you look at that group two is
let me see all now the all the chair cutler uh okay uh xin zhang here there's my this this
is an student so you so you see here don't yeah then the I think group one uh group two is a little
bit larger so um maybe I want more role so so make sure yeah so group three will be this uh
lady student from here or after xin zhang even know her uh all the this area will be group two
okay so you take a rest then you take a look at the name yeah I think the name probably not
large enough to see I am a emphasize uh in large the first each group the first name and the same
so so remember here yeah so group one here group three here according to the name basically
your surname is a small letter group one like Chao Chao xin zhang and those are zhang or whatever
will be group three those are in the middle like uh uh Liu Wang will be group uh group two okay
because easier for us to check and to and to collect the uh the paper
so
I can come to take a look at your young supi I think near the yeah a group three is here yes
oh yeah okay very very good yeah so uh you are very good one and let me see I
I locate each of you you can I think the the other group that uh if she can other than I think
there at the Ha Ha Ha Ha you'll be group one in charge of this uh you'll be in charge of uh
three
shang
three shang
and you come the other two and you uh let's let's see the other uh okay so maybe I can yeah I can
write down here to make it uh very large so that the other side uh group one uh
group one is from uh I just write down the surname I think it's uh
bang bang all the way until uh most of the li okay li li zhi li then the only
the only li starting with uh li zhong uh
ta you will be group two leading group two after that all the if you're last name is uh
you'll see li plus something or li li and so on uh all the way up to the last one will be one
all the one if you are surname the first letter is smaller than WNG uh like t or whatever it will
be group two then last group three is starting from we surname is wei okay then uh greater than
that one because it will be wu or whatever x xiong yang or all the zheng uh chu whatever
there will be all the way until until the last okay so that one I hope it should be it should be
clear uh to you yeah which one is group one is here group three is out the the other one and group
two is uh in the middle uh the just now yeah the the the lady standing there is towards n the last
several row because it's it will be both sides group two is a larger one so it could be uh the
last one so so make sure the ways are the two to student uh uh let me call I have their their phone
uh they are yeah you for them they they gave me the uh let me call them first
you can help to check uh yeah make sure student group eight will be will be sitting this
group two is at the back the the last
are you doing are you doing
so today I make you in charge of the group then you will be somehow the last several
from both sides you are you are you are you are you are okay very good in charge of group
three later I gave you a picture just follow me I bring up all the net and then also show the
so uh again you can yeah contact the paper yeah just make sure they see in the in in right place
Hannah you're a good one so uh so again here
okay uh so it should be very clear because we want to make it easier to later to check the
your uh maturation card and also collect the the paper group one is those surnames are starting
you know alphabetical order with a small one your first letter bang you know the small is one then
all the way up to uh most of the Li Li Ziyi will be group group one is a region one here group three
is here both are later you know Zhang or whatever Yang will be always here so where is the the division
I think yeah it can be can be here okay so so group one is all the way up to here group three is
this side up to here and group two is whatever in the last several rows here can be can be both side
okay you either follow the larger one but not detail all the small one you go you go there to
at the double check okay so I want to make sure everyone follow because easier to easier to check
and easier to collect the paper then I do the yeah I do the marking and then you also sit one next
to the other with a empty seat in the you know between you not to sit next to each other at least
one yeah I think you already know yeah like the the current practice so so make sure because later
if you don't follow later when we check you will be asked to move then it calls you some
inconvenient uh also yeah okay so Liu is here whether Liu should be the we have the
many students call either Li or Liu or Wang Wang also in group two okay so the this several surnames
many students here I I think here okay so anyone stand up clear if you're not clear you ask
you ask now we still have a few minutes before we start to distribute the paper make sure you'll
follow if you don't are not sure you can tell me your your surname just just name because mostly
we base we based on surname okay
good one here so good one is on my side right hand side up to here yes yes although yeah
uh not particularly yeah yeah no no no nobody gives you very hard to follow see you you're going
front there are several empty seats yeah normally our class size is nice it's where
where enough every student you'll leave a empty seat yeah yeah typically group two they think double is
some students sitting here only but they should be either going to group one or group three because
group three there's very many empty seats so but the size about the same group two a little bit more
students so okay so should be clear I think Yang is a group three yes yeah so
any any student not very sure Zhang you're also group three because yeah Zhang is a regular those are there
uh from we own what w e i and then all the all the way to the end and yeah so so however this is
very clear okay
all uh more problem
any
more
If any student is wrongly, you are asked to move to the right.
You are also late in your lecture paper.
You can also go to take a look to see whether they sit properly.
There are still quite many MDCs here.
Also later when we distribute the paper, you can count the number of each row,
then give the correct number, ask them from past from one end to the other.
If they are young, you are more experienced.
You are taking care of the last two.
Then you can look at the left and right and do one.
They will be faster.
The left is fine.
The right is fine.
Then you give five papers.
Then you go to the next row.
Let me double check.
Are you all in correct order?
As I said, if you sit like last week wrongly, then I will ask you to move to the right group, right region.
Where do I sit last time?
Are you in group 2 or 3?
Group 3.
Group 2.
Yes.
So very clear.
De Yang, can you come here to help?
You can just stay here.
So make sure any student beyond this point will be group 2.
Group 2 is your surname.
Start from Li Zhong Da.
That's only Li in group 2.
All the other Li will be group 1 here.
And all the way up to all the Wang.
I divide into this way.
So that's why a little bit more student for Wang.
All the Wang up to group 2.
Then beyond that, WTI will be group 3.
Sorry, group 2.
Sorry, group 3 is here.
Group 2 is here.
They confuse.
Group 3 is here.
Group 3.
Group 2 in the middle is here.
It's on both sides.
Okay?
So clear.
I think we can start to distribute the paper.
Also, another important rule is very similar to the final exam paper.
You all know, I think for new students, you also is a practice.
In the final exam paper, the last 15 minutes, you cannot leave the hall.
You cannot submit paper.
So you either submit 15 minutes before the ending time for the exam.
But for this one, since we only one hour, I give you 10 minutes.
So that means if you finish early, probably not many students can do it within 15 minutes.
There are quite a few sub questions.
So probably majority will take the full Wang out.
But once you're beyond 8.50, you cannot say, I want to submit in the middle.
You either submit early before 8.50, then you can leave early.
You want to take the pass or you can leave early.
But once you're after 8.50, the color of your, you have to stay until we collect all the paper.
Okay? Fair.
So I make this announcement.
And then each student will have a double side quiz paper.
Let me see with this.
Okay, so...
This one.
Okay. I think it's fine.
We already announced that then later, I will try to see whether I can find a similar...
Okay, I think we start to distribute the paper.
I give you a few more extra minutes.
So next week, in case not enough paper, because I do not have some spare one here.
So you're for...
Group one, you keep this.
Then later, you check you give the paper first.
And later, yeah.
So as I say, you give count number.
Okay, then you will be...
The young, you can group two.
So you ask the student or you already know who's there.
It's the same thing you can do later than right after group two.
Then, you'll be the last one.
This way is on the right side here.
This one is later to check their magic.
But it will be easier.
No, no, no.
Six thousand meters.
They are free seating as long as we do the reason.
Because it cannot...
They have to follow.
As long as they are in the same reason, it's fine.
So you'll count the row how many.
Then you'll give the first one.
Ask them to pass.
Starting...
For example, here you have four.
You'll give four paper to the student to pass.
Then I'll check your name.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, help them.
And then the second one, five.
So one student take one paper in case you miss out
or you have more, you'll give back to me.
If you don't have, you'll let me know.
You'll follow the correct...
What's your name?
Li.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
There should be no group one is here.
Yes, right.
Anyone who is not clear, let me know.
Those lay comeers, I asked you to come before 7.50.
But there are always some students coming late.
Lay comeers, you'll let me know.
Raise your hand.
Don't sit at the wrong place.
Then, yeah.
Okay, okay.
Are you okay with those?
Yeah, get the paper.
You can take a look and write your name.
Make sure it's clear.
Write the name clearly, because we have some students.
Not the same name but very close.
So, yeah.
Write the name clearly.
And...
So...
You should get enough space.
You answer at the brain page below.
Try to write clearly.
Also, in case you...
make mistake, you can close up or use
another extra brain paper.
I bring some brain paper for you.
But most of the students can finish.
Can do it.
Some questions are very easy, but write carefully.
Make the...
Okay, I think you can...
If all done, any...
You're enough paper to distribute?
Yeah.
You also?
Okay, very good.
Yeah, extra, okay, very good.
Keep...
Bring enough.
Okay.
Okay, very good.
So, you can...
Almost you can start to...
In case...
You're not gonna...
Okay.
Please, take another question on the reverse side.
It's a double side.
Question one has three sub-questions.
Each are quite simple.
Question two, two sub-questions,
a little bit of calculation.
Let's ask you to bring the calculators.
The pre-season can be...
Let me see.
Three digits after the decimal point.
Yeah.
Okay.
One of the questions is some numerical calculation.
Is it one student can relate?
Or no?
Okay.
It's a close book, so...
Okay, nothing I forgot to remind is...
Turn off your mobile phone or at least make it silent.
Please do so.
If not, then the ring suddenly on.
It will be some penalty to impose
because it causes trouble to other students.
Okay.
So, you're all listening to me clearly now.
Turn off your mobile phone or at least make it silent.
If you are not done so.
Okay.
Good.
Let me start, too.
Okay.
Come over here.
Go from here.
Where we take the
Okay, now it's 8.30, you still have half an hour to go.
But if you want to submit and leave, you do it in 20 minutes.
8.50, you can submit one student just submit.
Otherwise, you will remain here.
You will not leave the LT between 8.50 until your paper is collected by the student assistant.
Okay, in front of you.
The cutoff is 10 minutes before the exam ending time.
But you can still do until 9.00 p.m.
Half an hour to go.
In case you need extra paper, you want to submit, you write your name and matriculation number on the blank paper.
If you're using two rubble, no need to submit, it's fine.
You will not be marked.
Also for students who are not very sure about the answer, you try to write something.
I will give partial math what you write makes sense.
Okay, the only totally blank will be zero mark for that sub question.
Yeah, just let you know.
That's the policy of the exam in general.
If you want to submit and leave early, make sure you pass the paper to one of the student assistants here.
Otherwise, you'll remain seated.
Okay, so you're going to submit to the exam.
Okay.
Okay, for those who have not signed me,
you will stay on until nine then we will do the exam.
And then we collect all the paper.
You have ten minutes.
Take your time.
Yeah.
Sorry.
It's a better.
Yeah.
In this way.
Okay.
Time's up.
So you stop writing or collect the paper.
You just sit there waiting for us to collect the paper.
Then, yeah.
It should be very fast.
I have two.
You just put together.
If you have two paper, make sure you write the name, name and matriculation number on the
rank page.
Any student use additional paper.
You want to submit, write your name and matriculation number.
Then submit the two pages together.
You wait first.
Wait until all the paper being collected.
It should be very fast.
Not many students here.
And that's the same practice.
Later you'll go for the final exam very soon.
Okay.