I think the question is, how do you start with the announcement again?
I will also send an end-to-learn announcement and also to the post.
So I think the quiz will be here next week.
Actually, maybe I want to get your feedback whether, because for my other course, 7402,
it will be this week, week 11.
So perhaps, do you feel, now it cannot change, but just say in the future,
I'm thinking about bringing to week 11 maybe better because we also finished the first two chapters.
There is a time.
I also want to make it clear if, since this quiz day is being set from the very beginning.
So if you are going for say job interview or some other reason you should arrange it on another day.
So don't use that to, and it's very late to change.
Anyway, week 12. There's no much time left.
So other than the contents which I already narrowed down somewhat,
we'll see perhaps end of today or leave some time for consultation for some students who still have some difficulty.
And then I add two more things which is applied to the other course.
So there will be the quiz question, not difficult.
I can show you.
There's no multiple choice.
There will be short answer or draw some program which are considered simple or some simple calculation.
But there will be some simple numerical calculation, not very complicated, but some numerical value.
So you'll need to bring calculators, probably just summation or those simple ones.
Anyway, same as you go for the final exam, so you also need to bring this.
So bring your student matriculation card with you.
I have a few student helper systems to check.
They will sit every alternative seat, not next to each other.
The LTE has enough seats for the whole class.
Also try to come before 7.50.
For those already attending the first lecture, there will be no problem.
And broadcasting for the other students who are not here, then you'll have to make sure we will be one hour sharp.
So that's about the quiz will be next week.
So today we will still go for the normal lecture.
We'll continue with the last chapter which probably similar to chapter 2.
I will try to make it easier to understand.
In the lecture now I also provide some spec ground for the part.
So we'll go into that later.
So today we cover maybe 2.30 of the chapter 3.
But before going for that, I want to discuss a little bit on the IIR filter.
So this is...
Let me use the 2.1.com because I have some hard copy with me.
So this one I can show the lecture notes which can explain better.
Let's turn on this one first.
Okay, so let's move on to this.
Also this IIR filter, I am not included in the quiz.
But I should say this part is probably the most difficult part.
It combines most of the ingredients in this part 2 into this example.
So if you try to understand this part better such as weekly, stationary,
and also the conversion including the IIR filter and impulse response,
cross correlation, auto correlation, and even in the sense a little bit about power spectrum density.
Because we did introduce in chapter 1.
So that's part of the basic but not the estimation.
So let's see what we can do here.
Because this part, to be honest, I also spent quite some time to digest this together.
Go back to the understanding of this one.
The winner of the equation here is similar to what we derived earlier for the IIR,
but now we extend it to infinity.
You see, because IIR has an infinity impulse response.
If you look at the edge of k here, you will need to have infinity of many of the parameters.
That was why IIR filters, in general, you will be much more difficult.
Also in some parts, it's efficient.
Actually in this case, when IIR filters later, you will see if you restrict it to be causal.
But here I also clarify the concept of being causal or not causal.
If being causal, then IIR filter has infinity many tabs,
but in the end it turns out to be just a little bit better than ever.
So allowing it to be no causal, which is not included here,
but if you go to the book, you can find out it will be much better.
Also, no causal in real life, you cannot do it in real time.
So you can do it offline, just like you are doing neural network machining,
you can do all the data that you are doing offline processing.
Coming back to here, we now extend this.
The main difference is, once you have infinity many equations, infinity many parameters,
you cannot use a metric for finite number of equations,
theory is very powerful.
That was my next chapter.
We will talk about some finite number of equations using metrics analysis.
But here you have to extend to infinity.
Then the mean square value of the arrow is the same way as the desired value of the one.
Even if you have infinity IR filter, you still cannot get to the desired level.
The estimate cannot, so there is always an error.
So I am here to minimize the so-called mean square error.
Then it is the same as before.
So we end up with this set of linear whole equation.
Then, assuming this is solved, then we can also get the corresponding minimum MSC.
Because we are dealing with causal, that is the difficulty here.
They will require the impulse, infinity impulse response is only from zero to the right half.
If you allow no causal, then you will have the equation here, finite infinity to infinity.
Then there is a match where the Z transforms.
So it is much easier to get no causal inner filter.
You don't need to go through all these difficulties.
So here, there is a problem here, so we cannot take directly using the Z transform.
So therefore, this is why, you see, last week I already discussed part of it.
So you see here, for the inner filter or for even no causal filter, you see we don't need this part.
From hn is given, the measure data, then this is the desired level one.
So we can get auto-correlation, function, power spectrum and so on.
So it's easily solved.
Cross-correlation can also get.
But however, the problem here is, as I already mentioned, the equation is only restricted to be causal.
So you cannot use the FIR filter approach nor the no causal IR filter.
And that was right here.
It's also very good because you learn better about why we introduced this innovation representation.
Because we follow this, you see.
hn is the one we measure.
It's a weekly stationary, sometimes we call it white-sink, stationary written process.
So from here, we introduce this inverse filter because this one is generated by white noise
go through this, go through a filter.
Then the inverse is if you look this as input, you will generate this WAN using an inverse filter.
So this concept turned out to be very useful in injecting this white noise so that you can consider
you have overall system because in Z domain, you all know your cascade tool subsystem.
So this is overall one, then overall one.
You also have the, because we assume the filter here, all the these two filter, they are all causal.
So this is the corresponding impulse response.
And then from here, you see, because the D and W, this white noise, W32, you can consider this as input-output relationship.
So this is input.
Then goes through this impulse response.
Just like a filter, you will generate this.
So therefore, in order to get this, we apply what we learned before, also going to be principle.
Then you also set, you have the similar equation which satisfies that.
There's no problem.
And here, the important one is this one auto correlation sometimes you use 1W, and I use 2W.
So that will be the same.
It's a unique impulse function.
So from here, we already simplified.
You can work out because there are infinite many terms, but only one of them, not zero, equal to one.
So you pick up this.
So that means this QM happened to be equal to this causal relation.
So therefore, our QZ, you see, is the one, you will be the impulse response.
Once we assume we know QK, then you can get this.
And we already know the relationship of this QK and this.
And then, so this is another very important concept.
Auto correlation or cross correlation, they are always two-sided.
Even if you start with sequence, you see, for example, input sequence X of n, the input signal,
from zero to infinity is equal to zero for negative n, so-called causal signal.
But then, if you do the auto correlation, the auto correlation function will always be symmetry.
You will always go to two sides.
So do a convolution with two causal signals or the signal combo itself.
You will get the causal signal output.
That was why, sometimes, as I told you, I'm teaching the undergraduate signaling system,
so students always confuse these two.
They look very similar, but the results are quite different, particularly involving causal and no causal.
So therefore, this one will require the filter to be causal,
but the cross correlation of these two signals is always no causal.
It will have two sides.
So therefore, we will get the Z-transform of this, but only take the causal part.
So now, the next thing is, we can just similar to the FIAR filter one.
We can get this cross correlation of D and X.
That's available, but not this one, because we don't know the...
You see, we have D, but the Y-noise, we do not have direct information.
But however, you see here, this is the beauty of the innovation representation.
We know this X-n.
From X-n, we do the power spectrum factorization.
We can get the GZ.
So that's why this one we can derive from X-n through this inverse filter.
We know GZ.
Then one of the GZ will get this.
So at least in the Z domain, we can do it very easily.
So why here the lecture note, we do not go into detail.
We just say because this part again involves a few more difficult derivations.
So this one in the end, it turns out to be related to this DX through this GZ-n.
So very briefly, you may think about...
Also, it's not exactly the same.
You may think about this is we want to know the causal relation between these two,
but we already know this part.
So you may think about this one from here to here,
it could be just something like the product of this one,
not about this one, so that you can divide in the same this part.
But it turns out to be very close to that,
but you divide G to the negative power.
Your inverse filter also changes the argument.
So let's see this part how we are going to derive.
So I can show you here.
Okay, so because it may take quite some time to write,
so I prepare this one here.
So this is the part where...
You can see it clearly or not.
So this is a continuing from this page.
One...
Do I get it right?
Yeah, one should be 126.
Maybe using a different...
I'm using a different version.
So anyway, it was...
Okay, should be right.
So 126 is this one.
126 is equation one for five years.
Okay.
So how do we derive that?
We can divide here.
You see this is the one over here,
the inverse filter or y turning filter.
So we call that as V of Z.
Maybe I...
I think here.
Yeah, okay, you see better.
Yeah, V of Z equal to one over there.
Then this is also a filter, you see.
We assume this is a minimum phase.
Then you can also...
It's a causal filter.
You can explain to that.
Right?
So therefore, from the...
to the white noise related to this,
because here we consider X,
if you look at the diagram,
the X of N is the input signal.
We generate this WN filter
through this transfer function, you see.
It's inverse.
So therefore, this is the convolution,
filter convolution.
And then based on the cross correlation definition,
you see, this is the one we are going to get.
D, we got cross correlation though.
All the will be different.
If you start with D and W trade though,
you will be 50 N.
And then this one, assume it could be complex.
So you take the conjugate
and the delay will be N minus K here.
Okay.
So therefore, from here, this is the expectation,
leaving a random signal.
And then you substitute this.
You see our W trade though, you see.
This is a convolution.
From here, you put in N.
And then also remember,
you need to minus K here.
So and the index will change to...
Yeah, this index will change to M
to not confuse with K.
So this...
Okay.
And then after that, we can see
now this is the cross correlation between D and X,
because we already have X.
And then now, but the argument is K plus N
because you are N minus K plus N.
So from here,
we know this is the...
still in the time domain, the sequence.
And as I say, this one is...
the cross correlation is from mining 50 to infinity.
So you can take two sides, Z transform of that.
Okay.
All right.
You'll be doing that.
Let me see whether my...
can use this to...
So this one I shift continuing.
The Z transform.
It's a rather long...
Okay.
I think that...
Yeah, that's the work.
And then...
Now from here, you see?
So the Z transform, you put...
This is the cross correlation.
Okay.
You'll put the D and W,
and then you put the Z.
Parking in.
You...
Yeah.
You do this, the Z transform.
And this is in the...
in Z domain, you see?
Because that's the definition of two-side Z transform.
And after that,
now you have to be careful
because there are two summations.
I can...
I can switch the double summation.
Now I make this M, the summation M, outside.
But because this part is in both M, you see?
So you cannot very easily break into two.
Then you will have some problem.
So as long as you have this argument of this...
It's depending on the index, you have to put break.
So I emphasize this is the whole thing.
Okay.
And then I do a variable change, you see?
Because we want to make this K plus M,
I call it K prime.
Okay.
Then if your case change this,
it will not affect the sum
because infinity to infinity,
whether you add or subtract, you know,
find a number, it will not change.
But however this K change, you see?
Okay.
Now I want to change K to K prime.
So that you have this.
Now this is very important.
This one, I want to get the proper J transform of that.
You have to remove, I mean, in the exponent, the summation,
you can make it a product.
So minus and minus becomes Z to the power K.
So this one I can take out of this
because this part is independent of the K prime.
So whenever you do the summation manipulation, always check.
That was in the 7402, the assignment sum,
student make this kind of mistake.
So therefore if you do that,
now properly JM, you bring outside.
So what led this is a proper J transform, you know?
And this one now, this whole thing is independent of M, you see?
You already managed.
You cannot bring the M from here
because that's inside argument.
So you need to change the argument and then J of M is a multiplication
you can bring out.
J of M is independent of K, you bring out.
So now once you bring out this, depending on M, this depending on K.
So it becomes a product of the two.
And it's just having to be nice.
This is the J transform of this, but the J is to,
not to the minor negative power, but positive power.
So you will have to change argument to J to the power minus one.
Because our definition is your argument J corresponding to J to the power minus one, minus two.
So it's out of the round.
So therefore this is one part.
And this one is just nice.
It will be what we already, we can get this.
There's no problem.
So therefore we get this.
And so therefore finally this is one we are going to have.
And it will be related to G by one of the J.
But now J is the argument is changed to J to the power minus one.
So therefore this one you know, this one you also know.
So from here you can get this.
So you can see this whole derivation involved.
So almost all the ingredients that we have learned across correlation, spectrum factorization,
and minimum phase, causal filter, and so on.
So this is finished this part.
So I hope you can follow.
And then you can see also the example we already showed.
But actually one student asked this question.
I think it's interesting, but it's important to highlight here because we say in this case,
I think we involve J and J to the power minus one.
You have to manage to separate into some of two.
One is the causal factor.
One is involving totally J is the anti-causal.
Usually it will be very hard if you are in the signal processing operation,
you either do the causal filtering or anti-causal.
It's totally non-causal.
So therefore these two parts are different.
You have to do it separately.
But one student question is mathematically by multiplying this by J to the power minus one.
That was asked by a student.
Then this one becomes, you see here.
That's why sometimes when you try to get both in zero, you are not doing processing.
Then it's quite good.
You always change the J to the positive power and you solve the equation.
But it will be confused if you change the J to the power minus one.
Then this one also becomes a causal factor.
That's why I prepare another two slides to show this, to see the difference.
From here you also probably will get a good understanding of the causal, no causal factor
because that's part of our requirement here.
So this is the question I think.
Can I just do the simple multiplication numerator and denominator
then change into this new filter?
I simplify because this one involves this coefficient and this is J.
I make the example very simple.
So we look at this case to see why we cannot do that.
So this is the other part here.
If you consider that as input-output relationship, you see.
So you see here.
J to the power minus one is a delay.
But if you add J to the positive power, it will be the forward operator.
That means the corresponding difference equation related to input is WN.
Not necessarily not it can be anyone.
So the output will be XN.
So this is a simple recursive filter.
So normally to verify is converged and stable you can see here.
Say I make the input to be a delta function.
This is a zero equal to zero and then equal to one equal to zero.
Otherwise up to date equal to zero.
So therefore we also assume the initial condition because this we are dealing with an anti-colder.
So we are moving from zero to the left-hand side.
Therefore if you start the recursion which is typically in signal system you verify by doing.
It value a few values.
So in this case the operation the filter link is from zero to the left-hand side.
And then you can see the result is converging.
You see here.
I continue.
Okay.
So say see here is it will be in the end you are related to the initial value it will be equal to this one.
And remember the power with the negative end so it's minus end become positive or you take absolute value.
So therefore there is no problem you converge in that direction.
But however what happened now if we if we you also think knowing this case the poles is exactly equal to three.
And for anti-colder filter is opposite.
For colder filter all the poles must be within the unicycle.
Anti-colder filter is opposite.
All the poles must be outside.
Maybe two greater than one.
So therefore this is corresponding to a stable one.
But now if you do by multiply z to the power minus one from numerator to denominator.
So what do we get?
The poles will not change.
So I say when you get the poles you don't do that you can do this but it will be easier.
So the pole location will not change.
But now this filter is a colder filter.
You all know if z equal to three you will have unstable filter.
And to show why you can again change the recursive equation and then look at the input output.
So here the now is for colder filter you start from zero and then move to that direction to future value based on past value.
And then of course you see here every time you multiply by three it will grow up.
So this becomes unstable.
And to conclude the difference between colder and non-colder or to be more accurate it's anti-colder.
It will be one in that direction.
The zero here is a reference point.
It's like the starting point.
For colder you start from here to there.
And for anti-colder no colder you start from there.
And that will be the way you're doing operation.
And you cannot say in this case I multiply.
I change this no colder part into colder one.
You do that you introduce a unstable one and also confuse because this is the truly stable and colder part.
And this is stable and no colder part but we don't need here for our IRR filter.
So we chop this.
Okay.
So that's somehow I hope it clarifies and make the concepts also career to understand.
That could be considered as a nice summary of the Pemidar pass-through chapter before we start the new chapter.
Any questions so far about the first two chapters?
This is more or less the contents for the quiz and also for the final exam which by the way the final exam paper for course also start very early.
I think the first Saturday exam start on Friday.
So the second day for the for the exam.
Okay.
So now this power spectrum estimation is considered is not totally new because I believe in DSP or DSP cause you're even in signaling system.
We already know how to get the frequency response.
You see of a given filter then you can draw the magnitude response and phase.
Yeah.
So the power spectrum estimation here is roughly corresponding to that but for the digital spectrum analysis normally we refer to the deterministic signal and the filter we desire those high pass low pass those you use for handling sideways or deterministic signal.
Not involving much you know the random signal.
Of course noise is okay.
No is assuming your noise is somewhat separate in the frequency.
Frequency don't make like the signal is a low frequency noise is high noise high frequency noise then you can apply that.
But now here we will be also applying to random signal.
So that's why we need to relook at the problem to see what is the limitation of the traditional methods and what can be done here to improve or at least hinder this problem.
And in fact you can see our assumption here is also dealing with so called sign signers.
So you see is consists of those harmonics like sign function cosine cosine functions in the sense about but then waiting this sign cosine as we already discussed early.
It could be some of the parameters they related to random signal.
No or maybe either phase or magnitude of the frequency here.
But in any case the main problem here is the noise and if the noise is white noise and dominant.
So you will see this will cause problem particularly if you have a finite number of data samples.
So that's why in this context we will not directly use the Fourier transform of the major data instead you do the power spectrum estimation here.
Okay so that's the WN here.
Yeah it's noise and usually it's the statistical independent of this.
Our signal could be random signal also in general.
Okay so how are we going to do?
We want to estimate some frequency and there are some questions we can ask like how many frequencies underlying this major data.
It could be one, it could be several.
And then the main concern is we want to see how many frequencies from here and then the value of this such as the high frequency or low frequency.
And sometimes even the amplitude here or the phase.
So the more important one is frequency and the value.
What's the frequency?
The value.
So of course the application you can as long as you are handling harmonic, sine wave, cosine and so on.
Such as space, multimedia and telecommunication and so on.
You can find those applications.
So let's look at the way we start ways.
We are familiar with the DFT or DTFT which you already know to handle.
We still assume discrete time signal.
Not continue your Fourier transform.
So B mean discrete time.
DFT or DTFT.
And then for DTFT which assume you have infinity many sample.
Then you take DTFT you will get this in the frequency domain.
It will be just two very nice impulse which happen to be the frequency.
For frequency we always talk in the real life it is positive but in mass in Fourier analysis we will get the negative frequencies.
It's positive, negative.
So that will be very nice.
If you are the signal is just cosine signal you do very simple to Fourier transform your DTFT.
You will get these two infinity.
And here this is continue in the continue domain to add.
So you see the two infinity.
Very high peak.
But there are some practical problem.
The first limitation is if we are only have finite duration.
For example you have two n, two k-p-n samples.
So you use this is like a window function.
And here if we don't care about causality.
So you have from minus negative n to positive n and of course it should be have one in the middle zero.
So it should be two n plus one.
This is just estimate.
But then the problem is if we have very long duration n is very big is fine.
But if n is very small.
For example two to the power four 16 data sample you will see the big difference.
This is very big n and this is finite n.
So you will see not the very sharp peak but you have also some other peak.
Also those peak are not very high but sometimes you may get confused.
Particularly if you are adding some noise later we will show.
And there is another problem is if now in real life you may not just sing one frequency component.
You may have two frequency components.
They are different but the difference are very small.
So that means if you plug it out in the spectrum you will be the two of them very close.
But again if you have infinity or very large number of data sample you can still resolve these two.
However now if the sample is very small only the example here is two to the power four.
Then the two peaks you will just the resolution.
As we say if you have a poor resolution you will see just one.
That is a more of a problem.
And then there is the one we mentioned is finite number of data.
I call this problem.
And then adding another problem is if you now add some white noise other than just again a simple cosine plus noise.
Then coupling together with finite data then this is very hard to differentiate whether this peak and those peak.
So this is still a bit higher than other but you will not be sure whether these are the low peaks.
They are lower than that but it may be signal, may be noise.
So that is something very uncertain now.
And that was why we cannot directly use the traditional method to do it.
So one way to do is since after now we have learned the autocorrelation.
And then since we have noising for here.
Here we assume with the cosine.
Actually for this cosine signal we already show even if the phase is random but uniformly distributed phase.
When you take the autocorrelation it will become a proper cosine signal that you will remove this randomness.
And the same is if the phase is a fixed one then that is even better.
So in any case we assume the autocorrelation of taking this cosine.
It will give you this cosine function which depending on the lag of the delay of the L.
This is L. It's like the N. It will be the time delay.
And I think this one, this type of error, this will be also L because we are changing it to N is the time delay.
L is in the take autocorrelation.
They refer to the like along the way I try to correct some like typo errors even some of the early part.
So always use the most uptake one. I may not announce every time.
So particularly between now and next week the quiz you try to get the latest version.
This one I will change but it will affect only the final exams not for the quiz.
So therefore now if the nice thing is you know why noise you take autocorrelation it will become a delta function.
That means the only when L equal to G low and the value is no infinity last because we are dealing with discretizing them.
It will be just equal to one and the noise power is always finite.
So it will be mean you only have in terms of autocorrelation take the no zero value here otherwise become G low.
So you will have this part.
And then even better is now if you take the Fourier transform apply or DTFT into this autocorrelation.
Not to the major data directly. So what do we see because this is still cosine signal.
So once you take DTFT you will get the two delta function and this delta function infinity high peak value theoretically.
And furthermore this is a delta L delta function.
Once you take DTFT you will be just being a constant independent of the frequency.
That means you have these two peaks there and you add on this DC value.
So you only raise the floor.
It will not affect the you will not create some pseudo peak as we see early.
So that works much better by applying the DTFT into the autocorrelation rather than the major data except.
So that's the motivation of introducing this going through autocorrelation and then doing the DTFT.
So that's what we call power spectrum estimation.
We are doing the power density but then since we are dealing with finite data so we need to estimate.
So that's why N double is the power spectrum estimation and estimate of the true power spectrum density.
This is the one assuming infinity many value where this one is finite data.
So in general here there are two different approaches to this PSC.
So one is no parametric.
That means you do not model just similar to neural network machine learning.
You are using data driven just based on the data you don't assume a RMA model or some linear model.
So then directly you estimate the autocorrelation function then compute this DTFT.
Parametric one is you try to model the signal using some model.
Typically here is the rational function like what we learned earlier, the rational spectrum.
So based on the IRR filters for example RMA or AR and then we estimate the model parameter such as those coefficient A or B.
Then once you got to do that you also need to base on the major data.
Then from there you can from the model you can compute the DTFT or the estimate power spectrum density based on that.
So that's the two approach we will be discussing.
So we start with this no parametric method.
It's easy to understand also the result is later you will see not very satisfactory.
So that's why this is not used very often.
Particularly it will require higher resolution.
So let's just go through this quickly.
In this topic there are mostly the very traditional method because very limited scope to do research along this direction.
So for example this Jenkins and WOS estimator is being there for 60 to 70 years because it was developed in the 1950 or 60.
So that's more than half a century ago.
But the idea here is also based on the autocorrelation but assuming now you only have finite data sample here.
And then because assume we have a total of NG sample then for the autocorrelation we need to get a delay time.
So the way to do for even theoretically or mathematically is the same is you fix one then you can take conjugate either this one or that one.
It will not affect because they all belong to the same X input signal.
And then one of them is your fix because that's the summation index N.
Where the other one you how much the N is determining the other signal, the finite signal you're going to shift and then multiply and then sum together.
But when you shift away then since we only have capital N sample the overlap number of points will keep getting smaller when N increase.
So therefore you need to normalize.
For example you are summing up instead of capital N sample you only summing up capital N minus small m.
So you to normalize you divide the number of terms you are summing.
So that's how this this method it also makes sense.
I sum how many terms?
Say 10, 10 terms then you divide by 10.
If you are summing up 5 terms you divide by 5.
And then the estimate we also assume is symmetry if it's complex if you're dealing with complex signal then you will take conjugate also.
Then outside this window you cannot do anything because you don't have beta sample shift so far away.
So we just assume this is zero.
So a little bit like you are applying a window function to take this part.
And then to do the performance analysis we're not going here but just show the result.
There is expectation equal to the true one.
So that's unbiased.
And the variant which the formula is here is a little bit complicated but it shows the formula is somewhat related to the true one and the shift product and so on.
So we see with n if you have the number of sample going with it then the variant would become zero assuming this m is a finite one and also is an energy sequence.
So that part will not go into detail but then the estimate will have a large variant.
If you have finite data sample and the leg parameter is large so that's called some problem.
That's why this Schuller's estimator is also very long time ago about the same variant.
It somehow tries to the formula is similar but just instead of dividing the denominator the previous formula it will get smaller and smaller.
It just doesn't matter.
Independent of how many times you sum I divide into the capital N.
Because this n usually is bigger than n minus small m.
So in this case you can also see you can use a vector to represent because you are dividing to the same n.
So you see here if I pack zero on left and right then you can rely this as like an inner product of this one with shift the other without shift.
But we have a problem here because so by what you know if you divide this factor is unbiased.
Now you divide n of course it will make a difference so it's very easy just based on the previous one you will see the estimate will be biased and bias term is equal to that.
So in the case of n very big and the small m is not big then you can see this bias term will be getting smaller or close to zero and go to infinity large.
That's quite okay.
But however if the capital N is finite and small n approaching n then you can see the bias will be very big.
The good thing for this estimator is the value will be smaller because it divides by large n always.
So you get the smaller value in this case.
And then you can also analyze we n goes to infinity and bias and the value goes to zero.
And yeah so also both of them you can see here they they here consistent estimate of this.
That means as long as n go become very large you will approximate this one very well.
Based on that we can get estimate of this.
This is the one the power density power spectral density the one we are going to theoretically this is the autocorrelation with infinity long data but since now we have finite data and it's also estimate.
So what we have is we do the estimation of that based on finite sample and this is the estimate.
So yeah this is what we have but surprisingly it can be proved the estimate of this is not a consistent estimate of the true one even if you have longer data.
So that's yeah that's causing some problem.
I think the main reason is you're not doing the averaging everything enough.
So that's why some method proposed to chop down into a few data segments and then do the average.
So I think this topic we will not go into into detail.
We are showing the limitation if you take sample and this is a true power spectrum.
The AR2 is not as smooth only one.
Then this is AR4.
There will be two peaks here and then if you use these two methods we introduced early what you get the estimate quite quite noisy.
The true one is smooth but what do we get is some very rough approximation.
There are some other methods which we will not discuss here because it's yeah.
So for no parametric method we just get a very brief idea without going into detail.
And for that reason usually this in the past years and also should be the same as I normally I just exclude this no parametric.
I exclude it for the final exam paper and that's why if you look at past year paper there were no questions on those no parametric method.
Although if you explore there are some topics but they were to limited time to be more focused.
We will spend more time on the parametric method.
But the no parametric one we not to discuss the two methods but the power spectrum estimation for the MA or AR or AMA model that either is FIR corresponding to FIR filter,
polynomial only or pole only corresponding to AR or a proper rational function.
That power will be doing the you know the spectrum computation and so on that will be still considered within the scope.
Anyway for this chapter 12 we will discuss more after next week's quiz.
We still have next week's 12 so we still have the final week 13 which yeah.
So let me let us take a break short break now so that now is 7.36.
We come back at 7.15 according to the clock to continue the parametric method.
Okay.
See you shortly.
Any questions you can come.
Thank you.
Okay.
So let's continue into another method which we call parametric method.
we consider the PSD, one is a function of the frequency variable F, this is the one,
the frequency, the main one. And then we try to represent that as a parameter vector theta,
it could be, you know, the numerator coefficient, denominator coefficient if you are using a
rational function. So that therefore in this case the parameter vector may take different
values. So we are trying to determine the optimal theta, called theta optimal based
on our major finite major data here, such that in this case the estimate one will be
closer to the true one as much as possible in something, usually is least squares and
so on. So that's how this part is again is quite closely related to what we learn in
chapter one and chapter two by considering this white saying, stationary process, yeah,
discussing chapter one and then some of the techniques such as how to get the autocorrelation
coefficient and so on, we discuss also in chapter two. So we want to see how we can
be applied here. So remember if we consider the more general model, AMA model where you
have the MA is the numerator part, the one corresponding to this queue, the order is
queue, where AI is the one corresponding to the denominator. So we consider the P and
queue may be the same, may be different. So in general we use P for the denominator,
the AR part, where queue for the numerator and then these are rational functions which
will be easier because rational function you have a finite number of coefficient or
parameter so we can put them together as a factor. And if you do not know the noise
value because here in this model we assume it's generally from the white noise so that
we call the W. And here by the way some students ask the process we are discussing here WSS
is for white noise is always assumed to zero mean. And zero means process you go through
filter the WSS process you generate, you also have zero means. So if I do not specifically
mention the means of the random process it will be zero means. Okay, that's by assumption.
And yeah, okay. So I take this opportunity to also discuss here. So you can also derive
from input output relationship by just similar to if you are going through filters and so
on. Okay, so in this context let's see what we can do here. So you can see if you are
using system base or model base power spectrum estimation or star is stage one which is to
select models. For example you can consider different model structure such as typically
here we have AR, MA or AMA and then also the orders if you are limited to rational functions.
And then we do the model estimation because what is model is finite number of parameters
to estimate such as what we just show early. And then after that you need to check whether
the candidate model is suitable based on the performance. You may need some data to do
the verification. So in this saying this is quite similar to machine learning that you
do the validation and also the model you choose may not be the same as the model which
generate the random signal because you are based on the major data but you do not really
know the process from the white noise how the white noise generate. For example the
white noise stationally process. So you may that's why later we also discuss how to choose
the proper order. If the order is not accurate you may need to redo it again and that's why
the model is satisfactory or not if not then you will go to another cycle to either choose
another structure or change all the and here the model is suitable for your application.
So that's how it is. Okay so now we next discuss how we can based on the different models we
how to do the model estimation and PST estimation. So the very popular one and common one is the
AR model and actually among the three models AR model is somewhere in the middle is MA is more
like the FIA filter is simple but not the modeling power is a right not a limit because
particularly you cannot model those are sharp like high-picking so because if you are estimate
sideways harmonic you tend to see some peak and MA model you will need very high order. So AI is
the compromise because you can do a good estimation and furthermore as you see in the chapter 2 you
see formula you have some analytical nice method to do it to do the magic you know computation
which is quite convenient also. So we'll spend more time on this AR parameter estimation. So
that's why here you only involve those AK estimate and also if the noise variance you do not know
your estimate is also. So in this case you know the optimal parameter assume we get the optimal one
then this is the vector parameter we need here and there are several methods to do that we will
briefly discuss. So one of them this Euroworker method this one is very critical but it's quite
well known and also for AR parameters it's very convenient you see if you go back to chapter 2
where already introduced this this method and here if you know the auto correlation coefficient or
if you estimate this one here first then you'll get you use the estimate value you will be able to
estimate the AR parameters A1 auto update and using this matrix equation okay so that's that's
you're just solving the linear matrix equations here okay so that's the way yeah you can do
and then once you estimate this you can also estimate the noise variance by because this is the
AR model you again use the equation and this one is achieved you know or the estimate value so you'll
do the using this formula you can also do it so in this way you are doing it in two steps estimate
the AR coefficient and then after that you estimate the noise variance or you can put together into
one larger matrix equation you can but yeah it should be able to solve yeah we discussed that early
okay so because we here we we do not know the true auto correlation so we use some of the early
estimator measure to do it but you can try to use other other methods also and then the estimate of
this auto correlation matrix in this case will be positive definite so therefore our AR model
will be a stable one and using this method the matrix is also satisfy the top of this form top of
this form is the one along the diagonal element it will be taking the same same value and then you
can we can also use the levion soon to bring a rhythm to solve that but as I as I mentioned early we
were not focusing on these recursive methods yeah so yeah and then there is another method if you are
using the lattice filter we discussed early then you can use the following cell all the recursive
equation to do so the way to do your start from the initial value which is given given signal and
out of that your recursively get from lower the go to higher one and at the same time in terms of the
time you also use the immediate previous value and the current value and depending on the previous
yeah the current order previous order but the but the value it could be at this at the same
index or previous value so so based on that you're doing recursively in terms of beta and also in
terms of the order and then as we discussed early to do that you'll need to know this KM which are
called reflection or partial coefficient and that's related to the filter coefficient and our filter
here is our our our mar coefficient here so you you can pay some this equation to get that then
and then you here in order to minimize the mean mean mean square arrows we can also choose the
optimal coefficient yeah one by one by by minimize this and then you'll see you can get
coefficient from because the KL they also stays by stays so you need to do get one and then
up a day you'll get you'll get a second one based on the recursive equations early okay so yeah
they're doing I to one two three and so on where this noise here is estimate using this
the last one is it the last last stage will be P so you're using that okay so from there once we
get this you can get the power spectrum density using the formula 160 and this
at the bottom of this burger measure to estimate this AR parameter is equal to high frequency
resolution because the power density spectrum here based on the lattice is less sensitive to the
error in this then if you use the AL the estimate coefficient directly that's being already being
showed by lattice filter is less sensitive and then furthermore because here AR model
corresponding to IR filter so we need to ensure stability but if you are using the lattice filter as
long as you the constability condition very easy to check even if you're a high order because every
time you're you'll make sure the coefficient magnitude if it's complex or yeah the absolute
value is smaller than one then you will do and it's computationally efficient so this is one of
the measures quite often used in practice also and then you can also use unconstrained least
square measure because least square method is also very popular and easy to easy to use so yeah so
so the way to do is you you can consider model that as unconstrained least square algorithm to
determine the AR AR parameter and then for the last stage of the lattice filter we can we can
mainly just estimate is finer optimal value rather than if you are doing that state by state
previously which will give you a suboptimal because you need to assume the previously is not so but
if the previous one creates some some some error they will accumulate so here is we just directly go
to the final stage and then using least the square to do the optimization there so that's
yeah so whatever you do once you get this so-called optimal parameter value which
corresponding to the I get here where still in the AR AR model then you're substitute into the
rational function and from there you can get the estimate PSD here and yeah normally as I
mentioned earlier using AR model is you it's quite good to model those peaks in the power spectrum
so that from the peaks you you can also try to estimate the frequency for example if the you see if
the the peaks if they are very close to the unit circle you see if you go to the jet jet domain
then you can get the poles of the AR model since these are just you know the polynomial in the
denominator okay and then to to be stable you have to ensure this lose must be within the
unit unit circle but if the poles is very close to you know the the magnitude of poles very close
to one that means very near the unit circle then you will see the power spectrum have a peak at
that at that frequency which is very close to this you see to this frequency because if you
all draw the in the complex plane you'll draw the unit circle there and to get the frequency
respond to get the true one you will need to evaluate that jet by substituting e to the power j
and phi and the phi here is corresponding to the frequency by 2 pi f phi is the digital frequency
you see here you go by one circle it will be it will be 2 pi but typically we only keep we use
the the first first quadrant and then once you get this radiant frequency you can you can divide
by 2 pi to get to get a frequency this is what we yeah we are we are looking for so so of course
if the estimate is not good the pole very far from the unit circle then you may not see the see the
very good peak yeah that's that's right that depends on you know you are a model and the
parameters you will be you'll be choosing so another very important important step is because
you all know the AR model order you got determining how how sharp the the peak you will see then so
we need to to do the selection of the order order p this is another important steps we need to do and
in general days days days a guy like if you choose the model is a very low order then you you can see
the spectrum looks very very smooth so you may not see the proper peak and that that defeated the
purpose of doing the frequency estimation but yeah on other end if you select the p the order very
very high then in general you will get to produce a more like a higher resolution but you know like
just like machine learnings if you use the model to to complex and then do not do it properly or
the data you use to learn is very limited then you may lead to this overfitting and in this
spectrum estimation you may introduce spurious low level peaks I mean you may see many peaks rather
than the true one you may just have a few so so that could lead to another extreme so so therefore
to given some data find a number of sample it's very important to to select the AR models
order property and that that's again is being done by some researchers many years back so so
there are several criterion you can use so that's one of them is called finite prediction error
criteria so the way to do is in order to select the proper order then you minimize this index the
index is defined in this way so this one you will be because by choosing different order you
will the estimate why noise it will also also change okay so typically the higher order you may
get a smaller noise here then you'll now you look at this look at this ratio you see here and
gang is a given data so that one is a fix so so if for example if you increase p so this so this
ratio will be will be bigger am I right increase p the denominator increase then the denominator
decrease denominator is the one below so p get bigger this one small the numerator increase so
therefore the ratio the ratio will will increase but then at the same time this noise variant
reduce so you'll need to compromise as a product to see which p will give you the smallest this overall
as a product so this is one way to compromise you may start with lower order and then increase to
see until when then then you you're raising minimum and then again get larger so that's that's a
the point where you can stop another way to do is this this is also very famous are kiker
kiker information criteria so again you'll select choose this p then minimize the following
following index here so you'll see here it's always the compromise between this you see
because depending on p you will you will have this estimate noise term and this term so you want to see
the compromise if p here if p increase so this part will increase where again similar to the other
one this one were were were chopped so you have this one gets smaller this one gets larger so therefore
again you can select by starting with a lower third say two or three and then see how
this index change so normally when you reach certain numbers say p equal to five or six
you know depending on the application now then you will get the the optimal one for example in
in speech typically it's the p because I I taught the speech signal processing some years back and
now the course was not offered so we so we get some experience about p usually equal to 10 it will be a
good estimation okay then we move on to change to another process which is the MA process is
so MA is very similar to like the FIA filter because in this case the our impulse will be
finite number
so in this case what do we have here you'll see if you only have this pk coefficient
while the ak are all equal to zero so we only have the denominator because auto correlation is the
second order statistic so basically it's doing the
you know the shift and then multiplication and since our HK here is a finite time then you can do that
very easily for AR normally you don't do this because for AR model the
impulse response is infinity long so you can't exist unless you work out the analytic
solution otherwise you cannot sum infinity many term numerically so that that's the main
difference so so so assumed we starting from the estimate you see the auto correlation coefficient
which only need a finite number of them you only have a finite number of equation also this
two parameter here is not not the linear not like AR there is a cross term here
so assume by some way you can get it then the corresponding estimate MA power density spectrum
you can compute by so you see here once you have a model you substitute this then you'll get
something like the frequency response the magnitude but in this case you will you'll have this
multiplication so equal n-tag is just you know taking the
things our model is FIR filter you just take up through value raise the power up to and
and then multiply by the noise value but if you do a simple calculation substitute back you will see
here you see because for this MA model you see then this part actually is already the estimate
you see the auto correlation coefficient so for MA models we do not really need to estimate
this coefficient you can if you are using assume this MA process you can just directly using the
estimate auto correlation function to the compute which is much much easier but you cannot do this
for AR model and the AMA model because for that the even in power response is in infinity many
many values
okay so how about AR MA process which is the combination because it has
numerator and denominator so for this AR MA process we can consider that as
cascade of the MA process which corresponding to the numerator and out of that you'll get the
output from here then go through another AR process so you can consider decomposing into
two and then multiply together or in terms of the time domain sequence you will need to do the
convolution in the frequency domain is multiplication okay so therefore in this case
you can yeah yeah you can consider there is a white process and then
consider that saying as AR AR is p order because we assume the order of aj equal to p
and then we get estimate of this using this IXM so once we get that then
this being here generally is output of the system aj because here you see so you need to be careful
because so again here we are we are considering this reverse reverse process yeah you see if you
yeah if you try to try to estimate this you can follow what we say we generally we from a white
noise go through this ARP process then with this the auto correlation then we will generally this
be a this the other way yeah and then therefore in this case the sequence here the estimate one
yeah excite by this so it's going the other direction will be the estimate of the
being because we we only measure this you see we have this available so I want to
want to go back in that that direction and after that you will need still need to go the
MA part because we already estimate this so we we are considering this as our major
data or the estimate auto correlation to to to estimate this part approximate yeah okay using this
yeah so therefore the estimate the amount model for the power spectrum is
will be in this way you you're doing doing two steps because otherwise the model parameter if
you are trying to solve the equation directly it will be highly no linear so you or you can get it by
numerical measure or do the iterations so that's how this is one of the approach to do it
okay so with all this discussion we can look at some
simulation results to see how this estimation measure works and later I think next next week
we will continue into the eigen analysis approach to to see to see the difference so
so the in this new simulation experiment we we will create some data the
yeah so so the data we have is one or two sideways and then some additive Gaussian noise
and the two sideways are spaced by delta f apart we will work controls how far away this delta f
and h n r is defined as you see here we have the m is amplitude of the of the sideways
raise power of two because to measure power we use amplitude power of two to do it and for the
of course this one is the the noise yes this is the variant of the additive noise
yeah and in the case of two sideways then the amplitude are set the same we consider
the two of them are the same not not say one is larger than the other so we consider several
case case one here the result for just you know very limited data and go to 20 data points
and based on an ar4 I mean ar model is 4 and then the h n r is 20 dv which is reasonably okay
the digital frequency difference because our app is just zero to half corresponding to zero to pi
pi over two they equal to that and so here I hope you can see from the north so you there are several
several measures the truth is a Euler Walker's measure also from the equation looks looks quite nice but
experimental result not very not very good here the two peak the two peak here but other measures
both is and least square are very close so but this measure not not yeah not very good because
it's a very very broad broad spectrum and small peak so it did the correct number of frequency but
accuracy rather poor where the other two measures are much better than this
yeah the LS seems to be even a little bit better compared to the Berg's measure
and if you further reduce this the spacing of the two frequency to reduce that and then the
Euler Walker's measure it can't solve at all resolve these two frequencies now the frequency I think the
scaling may be different here so you see it's one it's similar to the no parametric measure
become very broad you you even don't see the two peak so yeah so for short data this
Euler Walker's measure is not good because it based on the true the accurate auto coordination
function but if you have finite data the error may be already large there
so now we look at this case two here we only have one frequency component to underline the
rank them process and the frequency the digital frequency here we're looking at all these narrow
range 0.26 which is here and then in this case we will be considered the effect of additive noise
on the estimate and then we illustrate just use the least least square measure because this
measure tend to be better than the than the other one so from this you will see here if the hni is
large like 20 dB then again this is 20 20 poise and has and at two poles so so you'll see a very sharp peak
if it reduced you will get smaller peak and then now if snr 5 dB you the the peak is more
instead but it's a little bit off already in this one this one still okay so yeah so you'll see the
it's quite sensitive to the snr here
and then the effect of field order yeah now we look at field order because just now we fix on
one order and we already say early if you change field order then you may have a different result
so here we see how it will affect the bug and the least square method here so the left hand side
here is the bug method the right hand side is least square one so yeah you can see here let's look at
the different case if you're here is six poles eight poles then is it's quite good but poles
increase so you'll see it's yeah although we only have one one one peak so you'll see it changes
you'll add some some other peak here for the least square thing to be more stable you you
it works for six four eight poles twelve poles so it all looks looks
the two method looks quite quite similar in this case where this one is a sharper
sharper peak this is broader and the case three here we show the spectrum estimate for the two
sideways in noise using ls method and here the now we change the arm arm auto which is
numerator denominator ma and the ar port and then here even for low snr you can see the
the quality looks looks quite good for this ls method so i think the figure is a very small
number here snr you will compare this to this one is a larger snr 10 db so you'll see
this one there is a very low only zero db but it's still the performance looks still quite good
the data sample is 100 so it's not it's larger than previous one but it's not very big big number so
that's yeah so that's so far we are just illustrating you know some method using simulation
which about of course if you really want to explore further you have to
considering like writing some program as in my other course statistical signal processing for the
Simon I.R. student to try out some of the implement some of the some of the methods but
since in my part here i only have the quiz so yeah so that's up to individual if you are
at time you are king you can explore that particularly if you you need that in your
project to do power estimation power spectrum estimation for example if you are doing like
speech signal processing where as i mentioned i taught the course on msc course here several
years ago so it's quite relevant this AR base is using speech signal processing because it
it happened to be this AR model work quite well to estimate some of the speech parameters so so
let's see how this is being done in this speech signal processing here you start with some major
data then you can do some pre-processing by pre-emphasis by yeah so this is the you know the very simple
simple digital filter here to try to threaten the the spectrum and after that you'll
you'll do the frame blocking which is because speech signal you can model is
why saying stationally only over very short duration so you need to
cutting to frame by frame otherwise is the to result your pie to a very long data you will not
walk so that's that's one of the the case you'll need to consider like frame blocking
and then to make good use of the data you can do the overlapping so in this case by
by overlap by by one so that means every frame you overlap is the next one with with one so
after that you'll do wing doing you see may try to reduce because you are cutting some frame so you
want to reduce the so-called you know the pseudo peak or or whatever so you do applying some
window function and after that you'll do the auto correlation so that's that's the part where we
we have done we have considered and then you can do it recursive using labing soon to being or
sure as algorithm so based on that you'll get the AR model coefficient either a k or k m which
this is relative filter now after that you'll get the APC parameter conversion to correspond to the
your speed signal that is resonant so so you're applying to that and yeah that's that's how these
are the practical post because speed signal is very easy to measure you will have microphones you can
do it simply in the lab so that's speech portion of speech signal and the psd thing using different
algorithm show here so this is a segment of speech signal so you can see here it's
very strange over time so you need to take a short segment then do the analysis and then here you'll
see the different different method we try you know the AP AP that's one of the
all poles AP mean because the notation AP will corresponding to the AR model pj is the
am I pole and jillo so that's and the other p and keel and p
could be different so this is only for the poles so so therefore if you use a PRRG which is the
low parametric measure and you'll see it's not very good I use the model base you will see
a more accurate estimation but as I say the in practice usually you'll require
higher the not just like in the simple example you have AR to AR4 so you may need like up to 10 or
even higher so yeah I think that's probably the the main part we've done then the next thing we will
discuss is more the icon analysis methods which maybe I just give some introduction on the
mass background the relative mass because we still have some time before yeah so I hope I think at
the big beginning I introduce a little bit but not not too much because here is we rely heavily on
the icon analysis so it will start with a square matrix here it could be complex so in general
see it's complex then I hope you all know how to get the eigenvalue and eigenvector of this square
matrix by multiplied by a identity matrix of the same there so it must be square and this is also
identity matrix also of course square matrix start going to equal to 1 and the size n n by n
and then if some of the value it could be complex it make this equation equal to 0 this is
the matrix this v is a vector and assume this v vector is not equal to 0 because if this vector is
0 vector of course any you are always equal to 0 so therefore if you apply a no 0 no 0 vector which
corresponding get a value lambda satisfy this they will call this eigenvalue and eigenvector
so in general think this is n by n if you make the determinant equal to 0 you will always have
n eigenvalue but this eigenvalue they could be the same some of them may be the same some
could be complex also yeah not not not unique in general yeah so if you if you see this is
an example eigenvector whatever you get the eigenvector you multiply by another coefficient
it will also no zero coefficients scalar your n dot with also the eigen eigenvector but eigenvalue
may be unique may yeah it could you could have a repeat same eigenvalue but yeah if you have a
distinct distinct say eigen eigenvalue they they are all different then you will surely have
have the unique one so so that's the simple example how how you're getting you will need to
expand this determinant so how you're able to work out that it can do it up to three by three
if you have a three by three by three matrix you'll need to expand into the sum of three
three determining of three uh two by two but in this case one of them is a zero so you only have
two and then after that you you see uh expand and then simplifying to a polynomial polynomial
equation in terms of lambda and sometimes you may end up with you know those rules which are not
reasonable number and in some case you can have complex complex rules but if the matrix is
symmetric and real coefficient you will not get the complex rules so these are the basic
yeah so and then after that the eigenvector is a little bit more difficult to calculate
particularly for higher dimension for at least for three by three i think is still manageable
what you'll do is once you get the eigenvalue then to get this you'll put this in then of course
being eigenvalue this matrix will lose the ring you can initially three by three you can
so that means the among these three equations only and most are two of them are independent so you
you only need to solve two equations with three three unknown so so that's why you say the
say the solution is not unique you once you get one one vector you can add many many vectors by doing
yeah doing scaling so here one of them is by solving that you can let this be one one here to be
any no zero number so one zero minus one this vector is satisfied and then say you multiply by two
two zero minus two also satisfied so that's that's how this is done and then you can get the second
eigenvalue which is this then your your gang you will solve but a little bit more complicated
because you have this square root of two then you you will get this again this parameter is a scalar
and for this one it's the same way you do it and then how to deal with this no unique one way to do is I
think that's in data science machine learning very common you'll normalize to normalize this
that means you'll make the norm equal to one you see so how to get the norm is very easy each of that
if complex take the the magnitude raise power to some of them then take your square root just like
our you know in vectors so you do it and once you get this one you you divide each of all the elements
so in this in this case this normalized one your angle is equal to one so the norm of the
and that's why this is a normalized vector and then you can also illustrate here so this one you
take different value your angle with different vector they're all eigenvector but once you're
normalized your the beyond one can only take this value v2 can take this of course you can
you can still multiply by minus one if you you see if you change the side you
steer the norm of the multiple minus one still give you the same same norm but here we
we assume you take one of them so so therefore this is what the normalized one would be more or less
unique and then there is this orthogonal vector let me out orthogonal is more like the
inner product if you are talking about rare vector but in in general in this part we're
may involve complex so for complex the the inner product one of them you have to change the conjugate
you see for example the row vector edge if complex you take the complex conjugate of each of the
elements then do a inner product and then if the inner product becomes zero we say that these two
vector are orthogonal just like in the 2d plane you have the 90 degree x and y okay the whole set the
vector set is called also normal if they are normalized and orthogonal so compile both
and then look at this example here you can verify so they are all the
also going to vector set that is satisfied this
and yeah also also normal because they are already normalized
and then there is this unitary
matrix which satisfies this you see and multiple yeah so remember this edge is the
you take transpose and change the element to conjugate so it's it's a if for real for
matrix you only need to take the transpose so that's so this edge is mean her mission
yeah for real if complex you will need to consider both symmetry and it satisfies the complex conjugate
also equal so it satisfies this that means the her mission matrix of this become the inverse of this
edge so there will be very special matrix unitary unitary matrix okay so therefore in this case
the column or row vector they all form also also normal set also also going to and normalize
and then if this is a real we call it as orthogonal
matrix and that's a definition of her mission matrix and so and then the any matrix you can
always create the her mission version just as we do it for symmetry anti-symmetry by
add the her mission but if this is not m is not the her mission you can add the her mission
part and then divide by two or the nt1 is nt her mission it's subtract okay so therefore it satisfies
this yeah and then the if this satisfies her mission and then you'll get eigen decomposition
and this is normalized then you have all these varying shooting property lab multiplying this by
both sides your your nt2 is this property and then for this satisfy this you can see
your yeah you already the eigen value you take the her mission in this case just conjugate because
eigen value is the number and in this case you see all the eigen value of her mission matrix
they are all real even if the matrix itself is complex so yeah and then they are yeah
they satisfy this if you are doing that and then if you put all these as long as the eigen
value are all different you you can easily put this eigen vector then this will form this unitary
matrix and you can do the eigen decomposition in in this way yeah very special and then you have the
positive definite matrix you define define this way using any no zero vector which could be complex
for complex you always talk always talk about her mission not just the transpose but also take the
complex conjugate okay if real then we do not need to take conjugate it will be just the transpose
yeah and then there's some interesting property here
yeah you can always yeah you can always convert this we are in quadratic form you can always
convert into this commission matrix so yeah so therefore m is positive definite if only if q is
eigen value all positive so these are somewhat related yeah I think we will stop here then
we can yeah those are involving more into subspace there single value decomposition then we will
need to continue into the subspace decomposition and so on so so for that part I think we
we are playing to finish this chapter in the first half of next week and then after that next week we
will have from eight to nine will be the quiz so I yeah already give the give give the scope
you know last week I made a little quite some part for chapter one which is the basic those
fundamental match and chapter two mostly I select more to the first half for the later part I win
or the orthogonal and so on there were and some of the recursive equation like burgers and the
to being the one you can also yeah leave out so the further quiz I will say the
the the scope quite narrow and the questions are
simple I should say but you'll try to memorize a few equations normally not not very complicated
and yeah so the very basic one for for the chapter one you'll at least you'll get familiar with
like Gaussian random variable and given available how to get the like means and variant moment these are
the very very basic and some of the so-called simple factor you know like previous year I see
the basic of the VS or simple error like yeah for example variant will always be positive so if you
will get a negative variant then of course must be something wrong so the simple factor like that
and also if a random variable you raise power two you know then it will still be a new random
variable and that must be always take no zero no negative value because the power two even though
the ring them so you'll see these are the so-called common knowledge you should be familiar with okay
yeah so yeah so I I will stop a little bit early I think not only nine o'clock there I can
stay on here if you have a question you want to clarify and so on you can you can stay back
yeah otherwise it's okay you do the proper preparation and I also remember maybe I again I
highlight here just yeah just just in case some of you came late or those are not here watching the
video recording so these are the important one okay and then of course the two chapter already
narrowed down quite quite quite some part and make sure you bring the student matriculation
card because I have some undergraduate TA to help to do the invigilation and calculators yeah so and
don't use mobile phone because yeah mobile phone you need to turn off or at least silence and yeah
yeah so but you can have the separate calculator don't use a telephone the telephone set the
calculator inside you bring a separate because anyway for the need for the final exam they're always
yeah not allowing you in allowing you to take the mobile phone inside but you can bring a calculator
I believe you should already verify in the in in the school the calculator those you
put the stick but I'll show you the calculation will be simple just some numerical calculation
okay and try yeah to be here yeah 10 minutes because we need to do the seating properly and yeah
all the best and okay if no question we'll stop here see you next week yeah okay thank you
you