you
Okay, so this is the outline for TS class. So first we will give an introduction for this structure from motion, this concept.
And then we'll talk about pose reconstruction.
So direction from motion is about finding the geometry
for imaging systems.
If we give an explanation, it is
to find 3D structures from images or videos.
Pose reconstruction, it is to find a position plus orientation.
It is a six dimensional vector.
For the technical details, in today's class,
we'll talk about two concepts.
One of them is called the essential matrix.
The other is called the homography matrix.
So these are two concepts for multi-view geometry.
They can connect to the images through three dimensional
space.
To find the essential matrix, we will go through one algorithm
called a point algorithm.
This means this method need eight feature points.
For homography matrix, we will use one algorithm called
four point algorithm, which requires four feature points
at least.
So this is the outline for today's class.
And for this stereo vision and optical flow,
they can be useful for robotics, but we will not
cover them in this class.
OK, in this class, we will answer the framework briefly.
This framework is used for vision based control
and state estimation.
We can start from the control object.
It can be a robot, either flying or mobile on the ground.
We first need sensors to do sensing and the perception.
In this framework, the main sensor is a vision sensor,
camera.
Other than cameras, we can also have GPS or MU, INS,
or laser, or encoded, et cetera.
So nowadays, usually for one robotic system,
there are multiple sensors.
They can increase the reliability and robustness.
If we use just one kind of sensor, for example,
only camera sensor, then sometimes for certain environments,
the cameras may not be able to handle.
So in this class, I like to use Tesla as an example.
And you know that since last week,
Tesla is under investigation by the USA government
because of several accidents with their autopilot system.
So Tesla is very innovative, using only cameras.
But nowadays, we're not sure whether cameras are enough
for autonomous driving or not.
If it can be done, definitely it is very impressive
and very innovative.
OK, anyhow, we can have multiple sensors
for a robotic system.
And then based on images, we can do a structure for motion.
We can do post reconstruction, et cetera.
OK.
So this is about the process to go from 2D to 3D.
So from 2D images, we try to figure out some 3D information.
So after all these estimation, state estimation,
geometric estimation, et cetera, are completed,
then we can use those variables or states
to control the motion of the robot.
So then the robot can do some tasks.
So structure from motion.
This was once a very hard topic in about maybe, let's say,
15 years ago.
All right.
Let's see what it is about.
Given two images of matched feature points,
so we can determine some states or variables.
Let me drop briefly two images.
So here in this class, we focus more on geometry.
And on these two images, let's assume
that we have a number of feature points.
Say, for example, four feature points.
We use 1, 2, 3, 4 to represent them.
All right.
So this is one image.
And on the other image, we also have four feature points.
So these are two images with four matched feature points.
OK, so let me write a bit bigger so that you
can see this clearly.
To find matched feature points, it is not difficult.
So we can just use some computer vision
algorithms to do it.
All right.
And between the camera poses, taking these two images,
we assume that this rotation R and a translation
X between them.
All right.
So for structure from motion, one objective
is to figure out the rotation and the translation.
That separates these two camera views.
That's one objective for this structure from motion.
The second objective is to find the relative structure
of the feature points being viewed.
These two objectives are both about geometry
in computer vision.
And in this structure from motion,
we assume that the feature points have already
been identified and matched between two views.
So that means we need two steps, feature point detection
and feature point tracking.
All right.
So for these two tasks, nowadays the techniques
are very mature.
So they can be done very easily.
And this topic is called structure from motion.
So in addition to this topic, structure from motion,
there's another topic very useful for robotics.
Slam.
If we use a camera, then we have this vision-based slam.
All right.
So for structure from motion, we only
get these two pieces of information.
But for slam, we're going to get a map of the environment
and also locations, localization.
So they're more direct towards robotic applications.
Usually for different situations or things,
we require different methods for reconstruction.
And usually these methods are linear.
So we can use some simple mathematics,
such as linear algebra, to handle them.
So this is a very brief introduction
for this structure from motion.
In this class, we focus on geometry.
So here in these three reference books,
they all have this geometry focus.
The first reference book, multiple view geometry
in computation.
And number two, the geometry of multiple images.
And number three, an imitation to 3D vision
from images to geometric models.
OK.
And why do we need this kind of multi-view geometry?
Because they kind of bridge the 2D images and the 3D space.
And in this multi-view geometry, one state to be found out
is the relative pose.
It means a position plus orientation.
Or in another way, you can just call them
a translation plus rotation.
OK.
When we consider the motion of a robot,
so usually we consider the translation,
like how much distance the robot needs to travel,
and also the rotation.
So how many angles the robot needs to rotate.
OK.
For robotic programming, there are many software resources
for us to use, specifically for structure from motion
programming.
You can use many or quite a few programming languages,
such as C++ or Python.
In terms of programming environment,
you can use Matlab or ROS for robots.
ROS1 in the past, there was ROS1, now we have ROS2.
The first resource is based on C++.
This is OpenCV.
And the third one is from Matlab.
And if you like to use Python, you
can also find some Python-based toolboxes.
There are a lot of these kind of toolboxes online available.
A little bit history about the structure from motion.
So this is about geometry.
So it has a long history.
The scientists, you can lead, or the mathematicians,
you can lead, develop the notions of perspective
and projection.
So nowadays, these concepts look very simple to us.
But in 2000 years ago, it was not easy.
And then in the next about 1,000 plus years,
these two concepts were really discovered,
especially during this period in Europe.
Relations.
So in Chinese, it is called the Wenyi Fuxian.
Just to let you know.
And then in 1913, this researcher
proved that two camera views of five Euclidean points
could be used to estimate translation and rotation,
separation of the two camera views.
So these were an early stage results for the structure
from motion.
The two key results were invented in 1981 and 1988,
respectively.
And even today, they are very commonly used.
There were many results on the structure from motion.
But these two were what are seminal work,
or the key results.
In 1991, this researcher introduced
the essential matrix and a point algorithm.
So this is what we are going to cover in today's class,
and we'll talk about the details a bit later.
Let's call this one method one.
Seven years later, these two researchers
introduced the homography matrix and a four point algorithm
in 1988 to solve for translation and rotation,
giving four co-planned points.
These two methods have different requirements.
The first method requires eight non-coplanar points.
So that means, for this eight points,
they cannot be on the same plane.
So from these eight points, the rotation and the scale
of translation can be recovered.
So here we call it a scale translation
because the absolute translation cannot be found out
due to this loss of depth information.
In method two, the homography method, four co-planned points
are required.
These four points should be on the same plane,
but they cannot be on the same line.
So these are requirements for using homography.
And from these four points, similarly,
we can also find the rotation and scale translation.
And these are in 1996 and 2004.
Two researchers introduced five point algorithms,
but they are not as commonly used as these two methods,
method one and method two.
So what are we going to focus in today's class?
OK.
For the structure from motion, it is based on linear algebra.
So now we're going to review some useful tools
in linear algebra.
The first one is called SVD, single value decomposition.
An animatrix can be decomposed into a product
of three matrices, u, sigma, v.
So this m is animatrix.
And this sigma is a diagonal matrix
with the diagonal elements equal to sigma 1, sigma 2,
and sigma n, sigma m.
It is like this.
It's a diagonal matrix.
OK.
So these are the elements along the diagonal.
And the other elements are equal to 0.
Sigma 1, 2, m are called the singular values.
They are similar to eigenvalues of matrices.
If this m, this matrix m is not full rank,
then some values like sigma i can be equal to 0.
For non-full rank matrix m, the column of v,
v is the last matrix.
The column of v corresponding to 0, single value,
is in the last space of m.
Let's say, for example, if we have an equation,
mx is equal to b.
We know m, we know b, but we do not know x.
So here we can solve x out.
x we have equal to a linear combination of x1, x2, et cetera.
So c1, x1 plus c2, x2 plus several more terms.
So this is a linear combination of some vectors.
And this x1 is x2, et cetera.
They are called a kernel, but not space of m.
So from them, we can figure out the solution for x.
So that's about singular value decomposition.
In terms of programming, this is very easy.
You just use one command, SVD.
So then you can do this SVD for matrix.
It's a first concept.
The second is called a school symmetric matrix.
In this class, we will use this a lot
in the mathematical derivation.
School symmetric matrix is actually a 3 by 3 matrix.
It can be derived from a vector.
Here we define one vector a.
a can be any vector.
It's three-dimensional with three elements a1, a2, a3.
So based on this vector, we can define a matrix.
a brackets then cross.
So this means a matrix.
It is a 3 by 3 matrix with in total nine elements.
This matrix looks very special.
Along the diagonal, all the elements are equal to 0.
And then for the other six elements,
they are symmetric along the diagonal,
but with different signs.
Here we have negative a3.
And at the left bottom side, we have a3.
You can see different signs.
And for a2, we have negative a2.
Negative a1, we have a1.
So these are very special matrix.
We call it school symmetric matrix.
And why is this one useful?
Because it can contain vector calculation
into a matrix times a vector.
A cross B, this is a cross product.
A is a vector.
B is also a vector.
If we use this school symmetric matrix, then A cross B,
it equal to a matrix.
A cross, this is a matrix times B, which is a vector.
So this will help to simplify a lot of derivations
in this class.
OK, so next I'm going to review with you briefly
cross product, because we will use this in the mathematical
derivations a bit later.
So let me first show you what is a cross product.
So here we define two vectors, A and B. Both of them
are three dimensional vectors.
A is a1, a2, a3.
B is b1, b2, b3.
So we first review dot product.
Two vectors, A dot product B is equal to a1 times b1 plus a2,
b2 plus a3, b3.
Cross product is a little bit more complicated.
So A cross B can be calculated in this way,
because A and B are both three dimensional.
So we can write them like this.
A has three elements, a1, a2, a3.
Along three directions, I, j, k.
I, j, k means three different directions.
And then for B, along the three directions,
the elements are b1, b2, b3.
So we can just construct a matrix like this.
This is A cross B. And then we figure out what this is.
This is first equal to.
So we take a look at this i.
So i times the determinant of this matrix, a2, b2, a3, b3.
And then minus j times this matrix, a1, b1, a3, b3.
Then plus k times this matrix, a1, b1, a2, b2.
So this is the definition of this cross product.
And from this, we can figure out the three elements
for the vector A cross B. This looks very complicated.
So that's why we don't want to have this kind of cross product
in the mathematical derivation for multi-view geometry.
If we use this symmetric matrix,
we can avoid this kind of derivations.
You can see if we use this A cross, this matrix,
this cross product becomes very simple.
It is just a matrix, a symmetric matrix based on A times B.
So we tan cross product into linear algebra.
So that's the benefit of using this symmetric matrix.
OK.
To introduce this multi-view geometry,
homography, and intersection matrix,
we need to define several types of coordinates.
The pixel coordinates and the euclidean coordinates
are related using the pinhole camera model.
So here, we just review this pinhole camera model
that we covered in last week.
We first define one feature point on the object.
So this is an object in a 3D space.
We define m bar equal to x, y, z transpose.
This is a three-dimensional vector representing
this point's coordinates in the 3D space.
We call it euclidean coordinates.
So this is the first type of coordinates.
OK.
And then we define normalized coordinates.
So for this x, y, z, we divide all the three elements by z.
We get x over z, y over z, and one.
So this is called normalized coordinates.
So this is the second type of coordinates.
OK.
On the images, we can also define pixel coordinates p
equal to u, v, and 1.
This is the third type of coordinates, pixel coordinates.
So from the top to the bottom, we
have coordinates in a 3D space and then two coordinates
in the 2D space on the images.
And these normalized coordinates are kind of between them,
between the pixel coordinates and the euclidean coordinates.
And the pixel coordinates are on the image plane.
We're going to put here.
Number three, pixel coordinates.
To connect them together, we can use this p equal to 8
times m.
p can be obtained from images using our camera software.
OK.
This is measurements.
This is what we measure using the camera.
A is a matrix determined only by the camera.
We call it a camera calibration matrix.
It can be obtained through camera calibration process.
OK.
And then this m is to normalize the coordinates
with three elements, mx, my, and the 1.
So to get m from images, we can just
obtain it from this equation p equal to a times m.
We move a to the other side.
What we have is m is equal to the inverse of a times p.
p can be measured from images.
And a can be calibrated through the camera calibration process.
So after we have both a and p, we can figure out
what m is, the normalized coordinates.
So this shows how these three types of coordinates are related.
So for this structure from motion,
when you want to handle the relative structure,
when you want to handle rotation and translation,
we need to use these three types of coordinates.
OK.
Some remarks about this pinhole camera model.
Number one, many estimation and control schemes
require normalized coordinates for points.
Nominalized coordinates, as we've done again,
it's m with three elements, mx, my, and the 1.
So this coordinates a kind of a bridge, the 2D image space,
and the 3D, Euclidean space, or the 3D world.
Giving pixel coordinates p of a point in the image
and the knowledge of the calibration matrix a,
we can recover the normalized coordinates using m equal to
the inverse of a times p.
Again, this a means the camera calibration matrix.
And the p means measurements.
We are a camera sensor.
Usually there is no way to recover the Euclidean coordinates
x, y, z without additional information.
This is because the depth is lost during the imaging process.
This is called depth ambiguity.
It's a drawback of the imaging process.
Usually in robotics, when you're autonomous vehicle research,
we need to handle this depth ambiguity.
So let me write it down.
So in the imaging process from 3D to 2D, the depth information
is lost.
And how to find out?
It is still possible.
So if we want to figure out what this m bar equal to x, y,
y is images only are not enough.
We need either one more sensor or prior knowledge
of the environment.
One more image, et cetera.
OK.
We use this simple picture to show the idea of post reconstruction.
And we assume that this building is an object under consideration.
We use one camera to take two images.
And this camera can be added to two different poses represented
by f star and f respectively.
This f star and f also represent two coordinate frames.
Two coordinate frames attach to projection center
of the camera.
OK.
Between these two poses, what is two coordinate frames?
There's a rotation r and a translation x.
R is a rotation matrix.
It is used to represent rotation.
And x is a translation vector.
It is for translation.
Given two images of a scene.
So let's say, for example, here we have two images of the building.
And the matched corresponding feature points.
Corresponding feature points.
For example, for this point on the top of the building.
So we can find the corresponding points in these two images.
So they're matched feature points.
Post reconstruction is about reconstructing the relative position
and orientation between the two camera poses.
That is called post reconstruction.
Post means a six dimensional vector.
Position plus orientation.
Post reconstruction can also solve for relative feature
point coordinates up to a skilled factor.
It's about relative structure.
OK.
From the next slide, we're going to see a lot more mathematics.
So that's why in the first several slides,
we were a little bit slow so that you understand what
those variables mean.
So once we know the meanings of those variables, r, x, f star,
and also the straight halves of coordinates,
normalize coordinate, pixel coordinate,
and the Euclidean coordinate, then we
can talk about the multi-view geometry
and the two different measures, homography
and essential matrix.
OK.
So now we are going to choose one feature point
on top of the object or the building here.
And this is one feature point we use auto-represented.
And two poses, f star and f, we assume that two images are
taken and they are represented by a point a and a point b,
respectively.
These two red dots.
Between f star and f, r is the rotation, x
is the translation between them.
Rotation is a matrix.
It's r is a matrix.
It's a 3 by 3 matrix.
In a very special 3D space, here S L 3
means a special 3D space.
S L 3 means a special 3D space.
Even though r has line elements, but it's not
in a nine dimensional space, because r has some properties.
x is a three dimensional vector for translation.
And here we assume that we have n feature points extracted
and matched in both images.
Later on, we'll talk about essential matrix and homography.
We need eight points and four points respectively.
So n will be equal to 8 and 4 respectively for the two
concepts.
And for this feature point, in f star and f,
we can define its Euclidean coordinates.
So in f star, we have mj star bar.
So this is the coordinate of point o.
The coordinate of point o in f star.
O is a feature point.
And f star, we use it for two different purposes,
just to reduce the number of concepts.
So we use f star to define a coordinate frame attached
to a camera at this pose.
We also use f star to represent a pose here,
just to reduce the number of concepts from two to one.
Otherwise, there are too many concepts
in this kind of multi-view geometry.
Mj bar is a coordinate of o in f.
So far, we have defined just one point and two corner frames
attached to two camera poses.
And for these two coordinates, they
are xj star, yj star, zj star transpose,
and also xj, yj, zj transpose.
j means this feature point o.
Well, the jth point.
So in total, we have n feature points.
n is the total number of feature points,
or just the number of feature points.
OK.
Usually, from one image, we can find many feature points.
But we don't need that many.
We just need eight points for such a matrix
and four points for homography.
For these two coordinates, they are not totally independent.
They can be linked up by this rotation matrix
and this translation vector.
So Mj bar is equal to the rotation matrix R times Mj bar
star, then plus the translation vector between them plus x.
OK.
So this is how these two coordinates are related
in a 3D space.
And from this equation, we are going
to find the essential matrix and the homoctah matrix
respectively.
In method one, we have to find the essential matrix
and we will find the essential matrix.
And we'll talk about this eight point algorithm.
And in method two, we'll talk about this homography matrix.
And the four point algorithm.
OK.
Before we take a look at the method matrix,
let's take a break and we'll start again at 750.
So meanwhile, if you have questions,
you can come here and ask me.
OK.
Let's continue on the class.
Essential matrix and the eight point algorithm.
So this is what method one will cover.
This method has a requirement meaning on the feature points.
So when we choose eight feature points for this method,
we cannot choose them arbitrarily.
So this should be satisfying this condition.
No four three points are co-planner.
This means any four points cannot be on the same plane.
OK.
So here we have one example.
In this picture, we have three buildings.
So from the three buildings, we pick eight feature points.
So one, two, three.
These three points are on the same plane.
And then one, two, three.
These three are on the same plane.
But we do not have any four three points on the same plane.
This is a requirement for the essential matrix method.
These concepts of essential matrix and this eight point algorithm
were first published in 1981 in this paper.
So in a journal, I believe many of you know this journal.
So it's a top journal.
So in 1991, this finding was a very big invention.
Let's take a look at the details.
Let's say how this essential matrix can be derived and how to find it.
So we have two questions in mind.
Two Euclidean coordinates, let's copy them here.
Mj bar star and Mj bar.
So they are the coordinates of the same feature point in f star and f respectively.
From these two Euclidean coordinates, we can find out the normalized coordinates.
Mj star and Mj respectively.
Mj star is defined as Mj star bar divided by the z component, zj star.
So then we get this normalized coordinate.
Similarly, this Mj comes from Mj bar divided by zj.
On slide 12, we have one equation that links up these two Euclidean coordinates.
So here we just copy them and then use it as a foundation for the subsequent development.
So we copy that equation here.
Mj bar equal to rotation matrix r times Mj bar star and plus transnational vector x.
In the first step of derivation, we just rewrite this Mj bar into zj times Mj.
On the right hand side, we can rewrite Mj bar star into zj star times this Mj star.
So it's just like a rewriting of this equation.
Next, we're going to multiply one matrix to both sides of this equation.
And we'll multiply this symmetric matrix x cross to both sides of this equation.
Let's give it a name to make it easier to recall.
So it's equation star.
Just give it a name.
So of this equation, star.
For the three terms, we're going to multiply this x cross.
And for the last term, let's have the easiest term first.
For this x, let's say what is x cross times x?
x cross times x is equal to, based on the definition, this means a cross product between x and x.
So it's x cross x, this is equal to 0.
Cross product of two equal vectors is always equal to 0.
So the last term is gone.
So here, let's write it down.
We have x cross times x.
This term is actually equal to 0.
So it disappears.
Then we have two terms.
Let's handle them one by one.
For the left-hand side, we will get...
This is what we have already.
We're going to write equation.
And next, we're going to multiply Mj transpose to both sides of this equation.
Then we'll take a look at the left-hand side.
This should be equal to Zj times Mj transpose.
Then for the rest, we just copy x cross Mj.
So that's the left-hand side.
And this should be equal to the right-hand side.
We have Zj star times...
It's a vector, Mj transpose, in terms of the next three terms.
X cross R Mj star.
So left-hand side is equal to right-hand side.
Now we're going to show that the left-hand side is equal to 0.
This is equal to 0.
Let's see why this term is equal to 0.
Because Zj is a scanner, so we don't have to worry about it.
Then for this Mj transpose times x cross Mj.
This is just equal to Mj.
Mj is a vector, a three-dimensional vector.
Dot product x cross times Mj.
And this is further equal to Mj dot product x cross product of Mj.
And this is always equal to 0.
Because we have this Mj appear twice in this equation.
Let's say this from this simple schematic.
We can define this vector x and the vector Mj.
So there are two three-dimensional vectors.
The first thing I want to do is x cross Mj.
It is a vector perpendicular to both x and Mj.
90 degrees and also here, also 90 degrees.
And this vector in blue is x cross Mj.
For this Mj and this cross product, the angle between these two vectors is 90 degrees.
So this dot product is always equal to 0.
So I have proved that the left-hand side is always equal to 0.
Because of this, the right-hand side should also be equal to 0.
So we just copy what is in the right-hand side.
This is a J transpose times, Zj star times Mj transpose times x cross R Mj star.
This is equal to 0.
On this slide, even though we have a lot of mathematics, they are all linear algebra.
And also, this is the kind of the main invention for that nature paper.
So now you can see this looks very easy to us.
So after we know the details, this looks very simple.
But it was not easy to discover this.
So you have to try many different methods and many mathematics until you reach this point.
So let's spend about 30 seconds just going through these mathematics and digesting a little bit.
And we can move to the next slide.
And this is kind of the core or the key point of this concept, the essential matrix.
It is required for this class how to derive it. This is required.
This is the key equation for this slide.
Zj star times Mj transpose times x cross is matrix and times R times Mj star equal to 0.
What does J mean here?
J means a feature point, the J's feature point.
And we will see this equation on the next slide.
This equation is, in this equation we have this term equal to 0.
So this is valid not just for one feature point.
It's valid actually for all the matching feature points under two images.
This equation is also called essential constraint or epipolar constraint.
So if you read some robotics paper for robotic motion control, you may notice this concept.
According to essential matrix, sorry, according to essential constraint or according to epipolar constraint, it actually refers to this.
The matrix E which is x cross times R.
So this matrix, this is called the essential matrix.
It contains the relative pose information.
So just from this simple definition, we can see that E has x inside.
E also had R inside.
So kind of this matrix covers both rotation and translation.
They're coupled or combined.
So that's the definition of essential matrix.
And how to find it?
Then we should use the A point algorithm.
So if we have eight feature points without four of them on the same plane, then we can calculate this essential matrix E.
And here I want to mention one more thing is that in the definition of this essential matrix E, we don't have any feature point.
We don't have J there.
So J means the J's feature point.
This equation depends on the feature point, but this essential matrix is independent of the feature point.
So no matter which point you use, you always have this, the same essential matrix.
So it is invariant of feature points or independent of feature points.
That's why this concept is useful.
How to find it?
If eight or more feature points are available, this E can be estimated using linear algebra method.
It is called A point algorithm.
Let's see some details on how to get it.
E is a matrix.
It is a three by three matrix.
So in total, E has nine elements.
E1, E2, E3, E4, 5, 6, and E7, E8, 9.
Nine elements.
So now we're going to re-organize this matrix a little bit.
We will use the nine elements to define a vector.
Lowercase E.
It is a common vector with nine elements from E1, E2, and E9.
So they are the same thing.
Matrix and a vector.
They contain the same amount of information.
To calculate it, we will use the normalized coordinates, Mg and Mg star.
Mg is equal to Mx, My1, and transpose.
So this is defined in the corner frame F.
Mg star has three elements.
Mx star, My star, and 1.
It is in the corner frame F star.
So based on this pair of normalized coordinates,
we can define a row vector, capital Mg.
So we just use Mx, My, Mx star, My star to define a vector.
Mg is equal to this.
It has in total nine elements.
So the last three is Mx, My1.
And then for the first three elements, they define that base.
Mx star times something.
Times Mx times My times 1.
And then for the next three elements, they start with My star.
My star times something.
Times Mx times My times 1.
Then for the next three elements, it's just Mx, My and 1.
So this is the kind of the pattern in the definition of this vector Mg.
Then based on this Mg, we can get one equation for this epipolar constraint,
which is Mg times E is equal to 0,
which means this vector times this vector is equal to 0.
This can also be obtained from slide 15.
From this equation, Mg transpose times E times Mg transpose equal to 0.
So we can get this Mg times E equals 0.
These are for one feature point, J.
And J is in this set, 1, 2, and here capital N.
So in total, we have N feature points.
J is just one of them.
From one feature point, we can get one equation.
From 10 points, we can get 10 equations.
So here we have N points.
So we can have N equations.
M1 times E equals 0.
M2 times E equals 0.
Here M1, M2 are both vectors, nine dimensional vectors.
And two, MN times E equals 0.
So next, we're going to combine these N equations.
We will have a big matrix.
M1, M2, MN times E equals 0.
So first matrix, we use M to represent it.
It has N rows.
The first row is M1, determined by the feature point 1.
The second row M2 is determined by the second feature point number 2.
So similarly, the last row is determined by the N's feature point.
So that's how we can get a number of equations to solve E1, E2, E3,
and E9 to solve the essential matrix.
This is called the eight point algorithm.
OK.
So just now from the feature points, we got the equation M1 equal to 0.
So from this equation, we can find what E is.
Let's assume that we already find a solution E.
If E is a solution, which means M1 is equal to 0.
So if this is satisfied, what if we have a constant C to E?
So now we'll have C times E. This will also be a solution,
because if ME is 0, the M times CE is equal to C times ME.
This is also equal to 0.
Here C is a constant.
This means that if E is a solution, then for any constant,
we can find another solution.
So this means that the solution is not unique.
So this means that this essential matrix E will only be estimated up to a scale factor.
So this is the meaning.
How to decompose E to find rotation and translation?
This part is shown in the next several slides.
I'll just talk about the main idea.
For some details, it's not required for this class,
because it is too complicated and also very long.
And I will naturally note that which part is for reference reading only.
That means if it's for reference reading, then we are not tested in the quiz
and also not tested in the final exam.
So this E is ideally X cross times R without noise and calibration errors.
So we can estimate this E.
What if we have noise and we have some errors in the camera calibration?
Then for the E that you calculated, it is not ideal.
So ideal E, if we do SVD, single-valid decomposition,
we will get this diagonal matrix, sigma, equal to either 110 or negative 1, negative 1, 0.
This is from the single-valid decomposition.
If there is noise, then this sigma will be a little bit different.
Let me show you one example.
This sigma may be equal to 0.85, 0.95, and 0.05.
So this 0 can be a very small number and a 1 can be a number close to 1, but not equal to 1.
So this is due to the noise in the images or due to the camera calibration errors.
So in practice, noise and the calibration errors cannot be avoided.
If this happens, then we have to do a correction.
The last three items are for the correction.
So how do we fix the result if there are minor errors there or if there is a little bit of noise there?
When the errors and the noises are too big, then this does not work.
If there is too much noise, then your images have very bad quality.
So we need to improve the quality of the images.
If the calibration error is too big, then we have to redo the calibration.
If the noise is not that much and if the error is smaller, then we can use this correction.
We can project our estimate of E to the closest to the true essential matrix.
Next example, if this sigma is in the next phase, the first two numbers are still quite close to 1,
and the last number is still quite close to 0.
Then we can do calibration.
We can replace this matrix sigma with diagonal 110.
This is a diagonal matrix.
This is the correction with respect to noise and the calibration errors.
So for what we just described, this contains
a many practical implementations.
Why do I want to do this SVD single value decomposition?
Because we want to find rotation R and translation from this matrix E.
And on the next slide for the details, we leave it for reference rating only.
I will still talk about it briefly so that you understand the main idea of this decomposition.
After we estimate this essential matrix E, we want to decompose it and figure out rotation and translation.
Why do I want to do this?
Because when we control the motion of a robot, we handle the rotational motion and the translational motion.
We need these two vectors. We need the vector X and the matrix R.
To decompose it, we start from this very special rotation matrix.
In this class, we don't talk about the exact details.
First, we define a simple base matrix like this.
Very special with rotation of 90 degrees or negative 90 degrees.
And from this matrix, RZ, we can use SVD to find the translation vector.
X prime. X prime means a skilled translation.
X prime is equal to a constant lambda times the real rotation vector.
Here X means the real translation vector.
And here lambda means a skilled vector.
It's just a positive number or a positive constant.
X prime means the skilled translation with a skilled vector.
It is not exactly the translation, but it is proportional to the translation.
This is for reference reading. Not required.
For the solution from the essential matrix, it is not unique.
If M transpose times E times M star is equal to 0.
If this is true, then M transpose times negative E times M star.
This is also true.
So that means if E is a solution, then minus E is also a solution.
This is similar to slide 18.
From this, we will have two more solutions.
In total, we may have four possible solutions for the post.
This is what we get mathematically.
But physically, there should be only one solution.
Three solutions will be physically impossible.
As they will require at least some feature points to be behind the camera.
So mathematically, the feature points can be anywhere.
But in practice, the feature points should be in front of the camera, but not behind the camera.
So by using this constraint, we can remove some solutions.
Also from this constraint, the number is positive and the number of stars is also positive.
So that is the constraint that we can use to remove impossible solutions.
For the structure from motion, as we mentioned earlier, there are two different objectives.
The number one is to find the rotation and the translation.
The second one is to find the relative structure.
Next, we will talk a little bit about this relative structure.
What does this mean?
Let me show you one simple example.
In this classroom, there are so many students.
Some of you are closer to me, some of you are quite far away from me.
For example, I am sitting at the back of the classroom, so you are further away.
Relative structure information means something that can roughly describe where you are.
So you will have a relative structure in motion.
We can support this structure building or 3D reconstruction.
How to do it?
We start from the equation, lambda mj equals lambda star times this.
This equation just comes from mj bar.
Let me copy that equation here.
r times mj star bar plus x.
On both sides of this equation, we are going to multiply mj cross,
which is a 3 by 3 matrix.
After we do this, the left-hand side becomes 0.
This is from the left-hand side.
This is equal to lambda times mj cross times mj.
This is always equal to 0.
The right-hand side becomes the 2 terms in the second equation.
The sum is equal to 0.
We are going to rewrite the first two terms a little bit.
We will write them into the vector matrix form for this lambda j.
The first term is lambda j star.
The second term is this times 1.
We are going to rewrite it.
This term and also this term, we take them out and put them into this matrix.
Here is actually a vector.
It is a real vector.
For this lambda j star and the 1, we put it into a column vector like this.
This second equation can be written into the vector matrix form like this.
This is for the free-to-point j.
For one point.
Since we have n-point, n-free-to-point,
we are going to get n equations.
We can combine them together.
We have something like this.
If we solve this equation, we can figure out lambda star.
Namda star means a vector consisting of lambda 1 star, lambda 2 star, and 2 lambda n star.
If we can have this vector, they will have the relative structure information.
Post reconstruction is more complicated than this.
This shows us some basic idea of what post reconstruction means.
Next, we can take a look at one example.
From two images, how can we find rotation,
secure translation, and also this relative structure information, lambda star?
In this example, we have two images.
You can see the first two images are almost the same, but just taken at different poses.
On the image, we can find several planes.
For this computer monitor, there is one plane.
Here, we pick three feature points.
The feature points are represented using some green stars, which are not very big.
I am going to circle them.
This is one at a corner, one, two, three.
There are three green stars over there.
They are for three feature points.
On the photo frame, there are three feature points.
One, two, and three.
On the speaker, there are two feature points.
In total, we have nine feature points.
This experiment was done by one of my paper collaborators.
These two images were taken by him.
He did all the programming and got the results.
This image is taken at f star.
We have another image taken at frame f.
We have two images.
Between f star and f, we assume that there is a rotation r and a translation x between them, from f star to f.
Just now, we actually selected eight feature points.
We don't have any four of them.
We have four co-planned them.
We have four on the same plane.
Just now, we selected these eight feature points.
We selected them from three different planes.
We don't have any four of them on the same plane.
This is about feature point selection.
We do this just to make sure that the condition to use the user matrix is satisfied.
If we have four feature points on the same plane, then this method does not work.
After we choose the eight feature points, we can figure out the essential matrix.
The essential matrix is E.
We decompose it using SVD.
We can get four solutions.
Actually, for these four solutions, it is more accurate to call them four possible solutions.
Because three of them will be wrong.
Only one solution is correct.
The first column is for the scale of the translation vector x prime.
The second column is for the rotation matrix r.
How to decide which solution is correct?
We will use the positive depth constraint.
Namda and Namda star should both be positive.
For both of the four solutions, we can find out that for the first solution, the depth is positive.
This is fine.
The last one is also positive.
For solutions two and three, we have negative depth information.
They can be removed.
We can remove two solutions using the depth constraint.
Next, we will use the relative depth to remove one more solution.
For relative depth, it is Namda star.
As we defined just now, it is a vector consisting of Namda 1 star from the first feature point.
Namda 2 star from feature point 2 until Namda n star.
This is a vector.
This is from slide 20.
For relative depth, Namda star, all the elements should also be positive.
Based on this, we can eliminate one more solution and find out the correct solution.
We keep solution number four.
For this example, you don't have to remember all the details.
You just need to have a rough idea what are the steps for this essential matrix calculation and decomposition.
This slide shows the final results from the structure from motion and the post reconstruction.
Solution number four is correct.
It is X4 represents the translation.
R4 is for the rotation.
It is a matrix.
This shows us how the results look like from this essential matrix and A point algorithm.
This path is for post reconstruction.
We can also find the relative structure information.
For example, here, just now when we choose the eight feature points, they are from three different planes.
Here, in the final result, we can roughly see the relative structure information of these eight feature points.
They see it's for structure from motion.
This slide shows us that using this essential matrix and eight point algorithm, we can get these two pieces of information.
Once we have them, we can build some applications.
Next, we are going to have optional exercises for you to try after class.
If you are interested in this essential matrix technique,
in this exercise, this is what you can do.
This is optional.
You don't have to do it if you don't have time or if you don't have interest on this topic.
You can take a sequence of images.
Two images would be fine.
You can do it like this.
You take one image using your camera phone and then rotate and translate the camera.
You can take another image.
In total, you have two images.
From these two images, you need to write some source code to identify the feature points and track eight of them.
You should determine eight feature points.
From these eight feature points, no more than four co-planar feature points.
Then you can calculate the essential matrix E.
From E, you can run this SVD-based composition and find rotation and scale translation.
This is the process for this exercise.
You can use either MetaLab or OpenCV for programming.
This is not mandatory, but required.
To support this exercise, we have a list of resources and reference books.
I'm not going to go through the details. You can refer to the slide if you want to try this exercise.
Just now, we talked about this concept, essential matrix and eight point algorithm.
Next, we will talk about another method called homography matrix and four point algorithm.
These two methods are comparable.
For myself, I mainly used this one, homography matrix.
The concept of homography is basically a mapping.
It's a mathematical mapping. It's a one-to-one and onto transformation, one mapping, between two sets of points.
Let's take a look at two images.
I will just draw roughly to set our future points.
For this method, we just need four future points.
There are four matched future points.
These two images, we name them as image A and image B.
These four future points are the same.
They are four matched future points.
Between the camera poses, taking these two images, there is rotation and translation.
Rotation is a matrix. Translation is a vector.
In computer vision, homography refers to the mapping between points in two Euclidean planes.
We call this Euclidean homography.
They are the mapping between points in the 3D space.
Or to the mapping between points in two images or in two D-spaces, it is called projective homography.
That's the definition of the concept of homography.
To use homography matrix, there is also a condition on the future points.
On these four future points, they cannot be selected arbitrarily.
Let's say what is the condition for these four future points.
First, I will show you two different selection of future points.
For the first selection, we have three future points on the same line.
One, two, three, and then the first future point.
This is OK.
For the second selection, we have four future points all on the same line.
One, two, three, four.
This is not OK for homography matrix.
To use homography, we need at least four coplanar and coninial future points.
Coplanar means the four points are on the same plane.
Coninial means they cannot be on the same line.
This is the condition to use the homography matrix for structural motion.
The homography matrix and the four point algorithm were first published in this paper in 1988.
For this concept, the key point is the definition of the form of matrix.
To find the homography, similarly, we're going to start from the normalized coordinates,
mj star and mj.
This mj star for future point j is defined as
mj star bar divided by the z coordinate zj star.
It's normalized coordinate in f star.
We have normalized coordinate in f, which is mj bar divided by zj.
To normalize the coordinates, they can be linked up using this equation.
m bar j equal to r times mj star bar plus x.
We can rewrite it a little bit.
First, mj bar is equal to zj times mj.
Similarly, for this mj star bar, it's equal to zj star times mj star.
We just make a little bit of transformation to get equation 2 from equation number 1.
Just now, we'll talk about this matrix.
We were a little bit slow because this is new to you.
Not because you are more familiar with these concepts.
We're a little bit faster in terms of mathematical derivation.
Let's take a look at this figure and figure out how these points are defined.
Here we have a plane pi.
On the plane, we have four feature points.
One, two, three, four.
These four feature points are on the same plane, but they are not on the same line.
This satisfies the condition to use homography, which we'll talk about on slide 29.
In this problem scenario, we have two corner frames, f star and f.
Now we're going to choose one feature point.
Here we choose this point number 2, which is this feature point.
We're going to find that it coordinates in f star and f respectively.
First feature point 2.
Now j is actually equal to 2.
Make it more general.
This mj bar is the coordinate of feature point in f.
It's three-dimensional.
xj, yj, zj in transpose.
First feature point is coordinated in f star is this.
It's this m star bar.
We have m star bar for feature point j is equal to xj star, yj star, and zj star.
We define two convenient coordinates in f star and f respectively.
Next, we're going to link up these two coordinates using this equation.
We can get this one using normalized coordinates.
Before we find the homography, we're going to match the distance from the projection center of f star to the plane pi.
This is the distance d star.
It's from this point to this plane.
This is d star.
Let's see what d star is mathematically.
This star is its distance.
This star is equal to the direction vector n star.
n star is just a vector to measure the direction of this axis.
It's just from this point to the plane pi, this vector or its direction vector.
If we have this n star dot product, this m bar star, we can find the distance d star.
It is equal to n star transpose times mj star bar.
A vector cross-products the direction.
We're going to find the distance.
Basically, it's a projection of this vector to this line, which is perpendicular to the plane pi.
We can find this distance.
This is further equal to n star transpose times jj star mj star.
We do not know this equation coordinate.
We can only calculate the normalizing coordinate from pixels.
This is further equal to jj star times n star transpose times mj star.
We need to use this equation on the next slide to derive homography.
Before we move to the next slide with more mathematics, let's take a look at the decay state on this slide.
This is the distance, which is d star.
This is probably the most important concept on this slide.
d star is the distance from the projection center of f star to the plane pi.
The plane pi is determined by the four-physicist points.
It's the plane where we choose the four-physicist points.
This distance is calculated by this vector m star bar and the direction vector n star.
We just multiply them together using the product.
You can find this distance.
From the perspective of geometry, the distance is the projection of this vector to this line perpendicular to the plane pi.
You can understand it from two different angles.
Now we have this d star.
Next, we can derive the homography matrix.
This is the key point for this homography matrix concept.
On the first slide, we have two equations.
Now we're going to combine them.
We combine them.
We will have this mj equal to mj bar divided by zj.
So that's just the definition of the normalized coordinates.
Then we're going to plug in the right-hand side of the first equation.
This gives us r times mj bar star plus x divided by zj.
Here we make a little bit change to this mj bar star.
It's r times zj star times mj star plus x divided by zj.
You can see so far, we've already done three steps.
We just transfer the coordinates to the normalized coordinates.
That's a very simple transformation.
Next, we'll see something quite tricky for this homography matrix.
For the next equation, we're going to rewrite this equation as r times zj star mj star.
Copy and paste.
Then plus x, now comes a tricky place, times z star divided by z star.
Then divided by zj.
So pretty much we didn't change the equation.
But just multiply x by z star and then divide by z star.
z star is a scanner. It's one-dimensional. It's a distance.
Once we have this, then next we're going to plug in this z star.
This is further equal to zj star.
We put this scanner first and times r times mj star.
This is the first term.
Then plus x over d star.
And for the d star in the numerator, we will replace it using this equation number two,
which is a star transpose times mj star bar, which is zj star times mj star.
And then divided by zj.
So that's the symmetric in this derivation.
And then next, we combine these two terms by taking out common factors.
This will be equal to zj star over zj.
And then for the first term, what is left is r times mj star.
And the first second term, what is left is x over d star times this n star transpose times mj star.
And this is further equal to zj star over zj times r plus x star transpose over this distance.
And times mj star. We take it out.
And for the term in the middle, we can see that it is independent of the future point.
This defines as homography matrix H. So this is the key point for this homography matrix idea.
This H is called the Euclidean homography matrix.
We can see that it contains the relative pose information and some structure information.
So r and x are rotation and translation.
n star is direction vector.
This star is the distance from f star to the plane pipe.
And in this homography matrix concept, we have a depth ratio.
Alpha j is the ratio between zj star and zj.
It is called the depth ratio.
If we compare this technique with essential matrix, we can do something in common from two images.
We can either get a homography matrix H or essential matrix E.
For homography, we need four points, four future points.
And for this E, we need eight points.
And then from H and E, we can decompose them to get rotation and scale translation.
So for these two methods, the objective is the same.
We just want to get rotation and scale translation.
So this is the definition of homography matrix.
And in this class, how to derive this homography matrix is required.
This is the key point for this homography matrix concept.
If four or more future points are available, then H can be estimated up to a scale factor
using linear algebra method, we call it the four point algorithm.
For future points, this should be coplanar but non-colonial.
Now we're going to see how we can find this H.
So things H is a super stream matrix.
It has nine elements.
So H can be written as say H1, H1, H1, H1, H1, H1, H1, H2, H2, H2, H2, H2, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3.
So in total nine elements.
The last element is H3, H3.
We can change this H a little bit.
So we're going to say we divide H by the last element, H3, H3.
So then we can get a new matrix, Hn.
In Hn, we only have eight useful elements.
The last one becomes one.
For the eight elements, H1 to H8, we can rewrite them into a vector.
An eight dimensional vector with elements H1, H2, H8.
So now to figure out this H, we need to figure out H1, H2, and H8.
To solve it, we will make use of the four feature points.
For one feature point, we can define one matrix, Mj.
Mj has two rows.
Let's take a look at the first row.
In the first row, for the first three elements, they are Mx, My, and 1.
And then for the next three elements, they're all equal to 0.
And for the last two elements, they're like a base.
Minus Mx star times Mx, minus My star times Mx.
Similarly, we have the second row defined like this.
This Mj comes from the two normalized coordinates.
Mj is equal to Mx, My, 1 transpose.
And Mj star is equal to Mx star, My star, and 1 transpose.
So based on the previous slides, now I believe that you all know how to find Mj and Mj star.
They can be calculated based on pixel coordinates and the camera calibration matrix A.
So once we have them, we can define Mj.
And Mj times H is equal to this lower case, Mj.
And this comes from Mj equal to alpha j H Mj star.
It's just now we have this linear algebra for this H.
This is for just one feature point.
Now we're going to use all the feature points.
Then we can have M1 times H equal to M1.
And M2 times H equal to lower case M2.
So this is where we gave us a bunch of equations, linear equations.
Mn times H equal to lower case Mn.
Then we can combine them together and get this equation.
So here this capital M is equal to a matrix consisting of M1, M2, and here Mn.
And smaller matrices.
For the number of feature points, N is equal to or more than 4.
That means we need at least four feature points to solve this M, this H.
This slide shows us the main idea to calculate the homography matrix.
Let's take a look at the previous slide.
On slide 31, this shows us how homography is defined.
What's the meaning of this H?
H is called homography.
It contains rotation and translation.
And here this slide shows us how to calculate this lower case H and then to recover Hn.
And eventually we can have this homochromatrix capital H.
How to decompose this Hn and the ghetto rotation and translation?
This part is for reference reading.
So you don't have to remember how to decompose this Hn.
So below this line, the container is for reference reading only.
The idea is actually not difficult to decompose H.
It's just the mathematics is too complicated.
If you take a look at the textbook or one reference book,
the mathematics can be close to 10 pages.
So quite complicated.
First decomposition, this slide is also for reference reading.
Actually the main idea.
So to decompose H, we use SVD.
Based on results from SVD, there are three cases.
In case one, sigma one, sigma two and sigma three are the same.
And for the second case, we have two pairs of singular values.
Sigma one equal to sigma two or sigma two equal to sigma three.
So this is also for reference reading only.
Case one and case two are two special cases.
For case three, it is more general and also much more complicated.
Sigma one, sigma two and sigma three are different.
So this mathematics will show you how to figure out the rotation and scale translation.
In the first case, the mathematics is about five pages long.
So first, we just need to understand the definition of a homogenous matrix.
What's the meaning of this homography?
And then the rough steps to find rotation and translation from homography.
We don't have to remember all the details in the slides for reference reading.
When we decompose this homography, we have multiple solutions.
And how to figure out which solution is correct?
We need to use this constraint.
The distance is always positive because this is a physical variable distance, so it cannot be negative.
We call this a depth constraint.
And usually in the programs for homography, we use this one to pick the correct solution.
But sometimes this is not enough.
We may get more than one solution, quite often two solutions after we use this depth constraint.
And how to choose the correct one?
This slide is not for reference reading because this is quite general for homography.
This slide covers many concepts, so it is required.
Let's say if we still have two solutions, how to choose the correct one?
So here we have three possible solutions.
Number one, you can use some prior knowledge of the thing to test N-star and the expected normal.
And number two, we can use multiple views to determine the correct solution.
For example, we can use three images from image one and image two.
We can get two solutions.
And from image three and image one, we can also get two solutions.
And then we compare them and choose two solutions that are quite close to each other.
And that will be the correct solution.
This is the second way, using multiple views or multiple images.
And the third method is to use one more sensor.
So these are three possible solutions if we cannot find the correct answer.
Okay, we will close the class of practitioner.
So after we go through one more example.
For this homogenous method, we can also recover the relative feature point of depth.
So this will be used for relative structure information.
And we will not go through all these mathematics.
Just to show you that this one can also give us the relative structure information.
Let's take a look at this example.
In this example, the most important thing is the selection of feature points.
We should make sure that all the feature points are on the same plane.
So we choose the four corners of the computer monitor.
So they are on the same plane.
From this example, we get four possible solutions.
The first matrix is this edge, the homography matrix.
And after we decompose it from this structure from SVD, single-value decomposition,
we actually have the most general case, sigma 1, sigma 2, and sigma 3 are all different.
So the next step is to determine the correct solution from these four possible solutions.
We need to eliminate the wrong solutions using the depth constraint.
That is, this D star is always positive.
So when we use it, we check this D star.
Solution 2 gives us a negative depth.
So this is wrong.
Similarly, solution 4 is also wrong.
So we have two solutions left for further checking.
Since we cannot decide which one is correct, solution 1 was solution 3.
And we took a third image.
So based on this third image, eventually we notice that these two solutions are closer.
So we choose this as the direction vector in star.
So this is how we found the correct solution from this homography decomposition.
So let's say in this class, we covered a lot of concepts.
So what is required in this class?
Number one, the definitions of homography and essential matrix.
And number two, how to derive them, how to derive E, how to derive H.
So these two points are required.
And number three, if we have multiple solutions, how do we determine which one is the correct solution?
So these are also required.
So these three points are required.
From E and H, how to decompose them?
So those mathematics are not required.
Therefore reference reading only because those mathematics are too many or too complicated.
So let's say if you want to use them in any project, you can just use the concepts and the steps
in this class to understand those mathematics and to implement them.
So this is the summary, which you can take a look at after this class.
So that's for today's class.
So if you have questions, I will still be here for about five minutes to answer your questions.
Okay, class is over.
Thank you.