Okay, hands up. Okay, hand in your paper and sign the pen deshita.
It's alphabetically ordered. Everybody, sign your paper.
Now quickly, because the student is waiting outside for the next class.
Quickly, quickly.
Thank you.
Okay.
Okay, quickly.
The language is alphabetically ordered.
Okay.
And then quickly.
Alphabetically ordered.
Okay.
So before we go through today's lecture, I would like to remind you that we have a quiz next week at about the same time.
So we're going to start at about 6.30.
Next class in this classroom.
This is today's outline.
So we will cover this vision-based control. Some people also call it visual server control.
So there can be several different names for the same technology.
For people in Europe, they use visual server.
It's also called vision-based control or image-guided control.
We can just call it visual server control. They mean the same thing.
We'll talk about two masters.
PBVS and IBVS.
Position-based visual server control and image-based visual server control.
Next, we will cover a lot of things called homography-based visual server control.
Or 2.5D.
This one is still an ongoing research topic.
So in this class, we'll cover mostly mature technologies for visual server control.
So again, let's review this framework for vision-based control and state estimation.
So for the control object, it can be a robot, a UV, etc.
What can be the control objectives?
There can be trajectory planning.
Avoidance, path planning, etc.
So we'll talk about the systems of control measures and the techniques.
So actually we can use PID or linear control, linear control, etc.
Or adaptive control, if we have a parameter uncertainty or optimal control.
So these objectives and measures are for the control part.
The estimation part is also a quite big component of this framework.
So all these blocks are about estimation.
The objective is to get some useful state variables and then to facilitate the subsequent control objectives.
So before we do state estimation, we also need to process the images.
Like I said, image processing, multiple geometry, they fall into this topic.
Another framework is camera. Other than cameras, we can also use encoders.
Or I am using IIS or LiDAR or GPS, etc.
So all these sensors can go to this block.
I will give you a little bit of introduction for this visual serving.
Visual server control, some other people also call it visual serving.
It is the use of vision or image data.
In feedback control, it is a mechanical system.
For example, this mechanical system can be a mobile robot or a robot manipulator or a UAV, etc.
Typically, when people started visual serving 30 or 40 years ago, they considered robot manipulators.
So nowadays, when people use visual serving, they are mainly handling autonomous vehicles, humanoid robots, or UAVs, these kind of machines that have proactive applications in real life.
There are two broad categories for visual serving.
PBVS and IBVS, position-based visual serving and image-based visual serving.
This position-based visual serving uses pose reconstruction methods to estimate a pose first and then use the pose in control.
Pose refers to position-plus orientation.
So currently, you can treat the camera as a sensor.
This sensor measures the pose first and then you use the pose in this visual server control.
IBVS is a little bit different.
IBVS image-based visual serving regulates an error between the current image and a lone-go image.
And this error is used to achieve control.
So you can see for IBVS, the control is down by comparing two images.
So we don't have to reconstruct three deep pose first and then do control.
So we just use the images directly.
So that's a key difference between these two methods.
These two methods have their strengths and weaknesses.
Which we'll talk about in a bit later.
We'll also show you several small videos to see their strengths and weaknesses.
IBVS and PBVS are considered as classic visual server control methods.
There are also several approaches that are built upon classic IBVS and PBVS methods.
So which we'll mention very briefly in this class.
If you have interest in this topic, you can actually take a look at the most recently developed methods.
In order to combine the strengths of IBVS and PBVS,
some researchers invented a hybrid method called 2.5D visual serving.
So this method can help to avoid some common job acts of these two methods.
But in this class, we're not covered this 2.5D method.
The mathematics is too complicated and we don't have the time to cover that.
So in this class, we'll talk about the general setting of visual server control
and also the classic control and the analysis and methods.
In this class for PBVS and IBVS, we assume that we have a camera.
This camera is mounted on a fully actuated 6-degree freedom manipulator.
So we call this an eye-in-hand scenario.
People also call it camera-in-hand.
The camera is attached to the global arm.
This is called camera-in-hand.
There's another setting called camera-to-hand.
So for this configuration, the camera is fixed.
The camera does not move together with robots.
Let's say for example, if we install a camera in this room, put it on the ceiling.
So this camera is fixed and this will be a camera-to-hand configuration.
This camera does not move when the robots move in this classroom.
So it will be different.
But for eye-in-hand or camera-in-hand, the camera moves together with the robots.
So for autonomous cars, there are all these eye-in-hand or camera-in-hand configurations.
We also assume that the goal is a constant pose.
So that is we just want to control the robot to go from one position to another position.
Then that's it.
We don't consider a more complicated time-varying pose.
And we assume that facial points can be extracted and tracked via facial detection and tracking methods.
So these are 12 standard assumptions for teaching in this class.
And this is a list of software resources for visual-serving implementation.
So the first one is for OpenCV.
It is in C, WordCVIR Plus.
Other than OpenCV, now this will also use ROS, ROS1 and also ROS2.
In addition to C++, we can also use Python for programming.
So here for these resources, some of them are method lab based.
So method lab nowadays is also becoming more powerful.
In the past, the functions in method lab can be quite limited,
but nowadays there are so many toolboxes developed for method lab.
First of all, visual-server control.
To implement it when many need to box it from two different areas.
The first one is computer vision.
That is we should know how to deal with the images.
The second topic is control.
So we need to understand the concepts of control and the main methods in control.
We can integrate these two topics together and implement visual-server control.
If you want to know more about this topic, visual-serving,
so here is a list of tutorial papers.
Tutorial paper is different from survey paper.
So in the tutorial paper, you will find more technical details.
It is similar to a textbook, but maybe only one chapter.
We will show some concepts and mathematical details for the control methods.
The first paper is called a tutorial on visual-server control.
And then the second one is called visual-server control, part one, basic approaches.
And then paper three is visual-server control, part two, advanced approaches.
So you will find the more methods other than PBBS and ADBS in these papers.
A little bit of history for this visual-serving.
This method can be traced back to the late 70s.
So that is actually more than 40 years ago, about 50 years ago.
So in the 1970s, people first started PBBS, position-based visual-serving.
This means they kind of treat cameras as a sensor to measure the pose.
So these are the early papers on this topic.
In these papers, they require reconstruction of pose.
I'll be there as started in the late 80s, about 10 years later.
So here we have three representative papers for this topic, PBBS.
But techniques in these papers, they compare images directly.
So these are kind of different ways to apply images.
Okay, I'll be there as and PBBS are classic measures.
Then in the late 90s, people started to study hybrid measures, or 2.5D measures.
The first paper is called 2.5D visual-serving, or 2.5 visual-serving.
It's basically PBBS plus IBBS, 3D plus 2D measures.
The second paper is a partitioned approach for visual-serving control.
And then in the 2000s, about 10 years later, some researchers started this adaptive homography-based visual-serving control.
And then these researchers started un-calibrated visual-serving control measures.
So that is, when there are calibration uncertainties, how can we still design control measures to handle the control of machines?
So this was mainly in the late 2000s, between 2000 and 2010.
So why would a researcher mainly study the last two topics?
Okay, so next we're going to study some basics to prepare us for IBBS and PBBS.
To build visual-serving control, we first need to define coordinates, because all the mathematics are derived based on the coordinates.
So here we can start from this image.
We take a look at one feature point.
See here, this red dot.
This is one feature point.
Okay, so for this feature point, we can first define the Euclidean coordinate, which is a three-dimensional coordinate in a 3D space.
So we use m bar equal to x, y, z transpose to represent it.
Here on this m bar, we can define m, the normalized coordinate.
So for this m, it's defined as x over z, y over z, and 1.
So we call it normalized coordinate. It's the second type of coordinate.
To find normalized coordinates, we need images.
From images, we can measure a pixel coordinate.
So this is the third type of coordinate.
These coordinates are what we can measure directly.
So that's the measurements from images.
So this can be easily obtained using images.
Mathematically, we have this m equal to a inverse times p.
This measures a is called the camera calibration matrix.
So from this p, and the p where we define it is the third type of coordinate, pixel coordinate.
So from images, we can measure this p.
And from p, we can figure out what m is. m is the inverse times p, normalized coordinate.
So now we assume that we want to control the motion of a camera to move from one place to another place.
So we can now move between two different poses, fc and fc star.
The camera will take a look at several feature points on this plane.
So here we assume that we have plane pi and there are four feature points on the plane.
And one, two, three, four, four feature points.
They are the same plane.
And here we consider the J's feature point.
So that means we pick one feature point from a group of points and then use it to derive the mathematics.
For this J's feature point, its Euclidean coordinate is mj bar equal to this, xj, yj and zj transpose.
This is the Euclidean coordinate in f.
For the same feature point, it also has Euclidean coordinate in the corner frame f star or fc star.
It is represented by mj bar star, defined as xj star, yj star and zj star in transpose.
So now we have two Euclidean coordinates.
So next we can normalize these two coordinates by zj and zj star.
And to get the normalized coordinates, based on mj bar divided by zj, we can get this normalized coordinates, mj.
Similarly, based on mj star divided by zj star, we can get this mj star to normalize the coordinates.
So what's the main difference between this slide number 10 and slide number 11 and number 10?
Because now we have two different coordinate frames, fc and fc star.
For the normalized coordinates, mj star, we have pj star equal to 8 mj star.
So this is about the pixel coordinate from images and normalized coordinates.
From the equation p equal to 8 times m, we can figure out the normalized coordinates.
m is equal to the inverse of 8 times p.
So if we want to control the motion of the camera to move between these two locations, f star and fc,
so what do we do with that?
We need to connect these two normalized coordinates, mj and mj star.
So to connect them, we can use this.
We can use an equation that we used in the past.
mj bar is equal to r times mj star plus x.
This is just about the coordinate transformation.
And then starting from this, we can rewrite mj bar as zj times mj.
Similarly, we can rewrite this mj bar star as zj star times mj star.
So now we get an equation in terms of the two normalized coordinates.
Why do we do this?
This is because we can measure mj and mj star from images indirectly.
So we measure p first and then we get f.
Okay, so here on this slide, we have the geometry roughly unconstructed.
How to get this rotation and the translation?
We can use what we studied in class number three or in week three of part two.
It's about structure from motion.
In that class, we'll talk about two measures.
Method one and the method two.
Method one is about the essential matrix,
which is represented by this e.
So that's the definition of this e.
This x cross matrix times r.
So that's how we define the essential matrix.
So here this x cross is a super symmetric matrix.
So let's just write it down again to refresh our memory.
If x is a vector, then this x cross is a matrix.
It's a three by three matrix.
In this method number two, we have homography.
And four point algorithm.
Homography is defined by this equation.
mj is equal to alpha j times h times mj star.
This h is called homography.
And mathematically it is equal to r plus x over d star times n star transpose.
So that's how homography is defined.
To find the essential matrix, we have eight point algorithm.
And to find homography, we have the four point algorithm.
But these two measures do not apply to any systems.
They need some conditions.
So let's talk about the conditions.
For homography, it requires a co-planar and non-colonial feature points.
On the plane, so here we have four feature points.
We use one, two, three, four to represent them.
For these four feature points, they should be on the same plane.
But they cannot all be on the same line.
So that's the requirement to use homography.
Okay, so just now we'll talk about the setting to use homography
and to prepare for the service we're serving.
So next we take a look at the camera background, the camera kinematics.
We assume that the camera is fully actuated.
So that is it has six degrees of freedom.
Which means the camera can move along any direction and can rotate along any direction.
So for the six degrees of freedom, three of them are for translation, three of them are for rotation.
We can use this R to represent rotation matrices.
So R is basically a three by three matrix.
So it has nine elements to present a rotation.
Other than the rotation matrix, we also have several other ways to represent rotation.
For example, all the angles, raw pitch is your angles, angle axis, theta and u.
So here theta is the angle and u is axis.
And also you need a quotient.
Quotient is basically a vector with four different elements.
So we can, for example, write it as q0 and qv.
q0 is just one dimensional, qv is three dimensional.
So in total it's a six dimensional vector.
People mainly use our quotient to avoid the singularity for satellite or spacecraft control.
In this class, when many use angle axis, this is theta u, this method.
So let me just draw it through the axis and also the angle.
So we have a three dimensional vector for the axis and the rotation angle.
Given a rotation matrix, we can find the axis angle and also given the x angle, we also find the rotation matrix.
Let's take a look at how to convert from one to the other one.
So here we assume that r is the rotation matrix with nine elements.
r11, r12 and q, r13.
In total three rows.
So this is the rotation matrix r.
Given r, we can find the axis and also the angle.
This u is a three dimensional vector for axis and theta is the angle.
The axis u is equal to one over two times sine theta.
Times this vector.
r32 minus r23, r13 minus r31 and r21 minus r12.
Theta is cosine of one half times the trace of r minus one.
Trace of the matrix r is equal to the sum of the elements along the diagonal.
r11 plus r12 plus r22 and r33.
This is how we can define the angle theta.
r cosine is just equal to cosine inverse.
So that's how we can figure out angle and axis from a rotation matrix r.
So by giving axis and angle, we can also find the rotation matrix.
This r is equal to that matrix plus u cross times sine theta plus u cross squared times one half cosine theta.
So this u cross is just this cross symmetric matrix which we talked about a bit earlier.
u cross is just this cross symmetric matrix.
So this is how we can find rotation angle and axis from r.
We'll talk about this PBVS. We need to use the camera pose.
The camera pose is the 3D camera position plus the 3D camera orientation.
The orientation is also on rotation.
So here we can use this EP to represent it.
EP is a six dimensional vector.
It is x transpose and u transpose times theta.
So 3 for translation and 3 for rotation.
We can use it as x1, x2, x3.
So this is for translation.
u1 theta, u2 theta and u3 theta.
This is for rotation.
This is x. This is u theta for rotation.
So that's how we can represent the 3 dimensional pose.
For the camera input, it is also a six dimensional vector.
We call it camera velocity input.
So it is v transpose and omega transpose.
v transpose is linear velocity for translation.
And omega velocity is angular velocity for rotation.
For this visual server control, after we design the controller,
we need to show that the whole system is stable.
There will be a bit of system stability theory.
So first, I will give a very brief definition of being stable.
So from the controller's perspective, what's the meaning of being stable?
So this is a very simple definition.
Giving bounded input output is also bounded.
But usually this one is quite hard to use.
So we use this definition to define stability.
But we don't use it to analyze control systems directly.
What do I do here is that we are going to use the approach method to do the analysis.
So this method can be used in a lot of research topics under control and optimization,
even under game theory.
So let's take a look at this method.
We consider a system with a state vector x.
This is very general.
It's a six dimensional state vector with, that means we have six.
We have n state variables.
x dot is the derivative of this state x.
To use this approach method, we will first assume that there exists a function vx.
This one is usually called a neapro function.
For a neapro function, it usually satisfies a condition.
That is this vx is a positive definite.
So there are two conditions.
Number one is that this vx is visually positive.
So number two, this v0 is equal to 0.
Only at the position 0.
It's about positive and positive definite.
That's one condition for this vx.
Another condition is that this vx dot is negative definite.
So that is v dot is less than 0.
If x is not equal to 0, and v dot is equal to 0, if x is 0, this is called the negative definite.
So we are using these two conditions only and without respect to it.
We are trying to analyze the speed of the state x.
The system is stable.
If v dot is less than 0, the system is called a symbolically stable.
So that is the state x where we bounded.
So v goes to 0 as t goes to infinity.
So this is how we can use this neapro method.
If the neighborhood is the whole space, rm, then the system is called globally a symbolically stable.
So first method, in this class we will talk about it very briefly.
Actually, if you have taken some other control class, especially for nonlinear control,
usually it will take several classes to teach the proper method.
But in this class, we just use the main conclusion.
We don't study different variations for this method.
Okay, now it's about 7.30.
Let's take a short break, about 10 minutes, then we continue.
Okay.
Let's continue the class.
So just now we'll talk about this neapro method for control analysis.
So for this method, we first need to take a look at this neapro function vx.
And I see why the ak is a positive definite.
Then we'll take a look at its derivative.
We thought I'd say why the ak is a negative definite.
All right.
So if both conditions are satisfied,
then we can claim that the system is asymptotically stable.
So next let's take a look at one which is several control program.
A camera is mounted on a control object.
So for example, a robot manipulator or a VE vehicle.
The camera can have two different poses.
The current pose attached to FC or a go pose attached to FC star.
FC star is for the go pose and FC is for the current pose.
The task of this visual survey is to move the camera from FC to FC star.
So you can have to move it from one position to another position.
And we'll take a look at this video a bit later.
So now please on this problem.
We'll first talk about the PBVS position based visual survey.
For this position based visual survey,
PBVS we first need to define the error for the control.
In PBVS, the error is defined as a pose in the three dimensional euclidean space.
So in this case, camera is more like a 3D sensor or a Cartesian sensor to estimate the pose error.
We can define the pose error as this.
This EP is the pose error.
EP equal to X transpose plus U transpose theta.
X is for translation.
It's three dimensional.
Uclidean is for rotation.
It's also three dimensional.
The open loop error dynamics can be written as EP dot equal to LP times this is theta.
LP here is called the Jacobian matrix.
And this data is the camera velocity input.
How to get this error dynamics?
You can check one of the textbooks used or just check one of the papers.
In this class, we don't have to know exactly what is LP.
Actually, the mathematics can be a little bit complicated.
This is how LP is defined.
This is for reference only in this class.
That means you don't have to fully understand what is in this LP.
If you want to use it in the future, you can just check one of the papers.
The derivation is quite complicated for this.
There can be several pages to derive this mathematics.
But in this class, we just need to know this.
We just need to understand that for the open loop error dynamics,
we have EP dot equal to our matrix times input.
And this matrix is called the Jacobian matrix.
We don't have to know what is in LP exactly.
Under this kind of dynamics, how can we design the input of theta
so that we can control the motion of the camera?
So here, I start from this error dynamics.
EP dot is equal to LP times the input of theta.
So we can design the country input like this.
We design it as negative Kp times LP inverse times EP.
LP inverse also has quite a complicated mathematics.
But this will be a full reference only.
So you don't have to be too careful.
So LP inverse is given by these three equations.
So based on this control design, now we want to do some analysis
and see whether it can make the system stable or not.
So next, we're going to combine the open loop error system and the decontroller.
EP dot equal to LP times theta.
And the controller is theta equal to negative Kp, LP inverse times EP.
If we combine them together, then we will have this EP dot equal to LP times theta.
The open loop error dynamics.
And then we can plug in the controller.
That's the controller.
Then we can cancel this LP and LP inverse.
So they will cancel each other.
And we will end up with negative Kp times EP.
So this is a closed loop error dynamics.
EP dot equal to negative Kp times EP.
So then next, let's show the result first.
Show the conclusion first.
Then we'll do the analysis.
The claim is that this system or this control system,
EP dot equal to negative Kp times EP with Kp positive is always stable.
So this means that for this camera velocity control system,
with this kind of dynamics for EP dot equal to LP times theta,
if we design the controller in this way, negative Kp times LP inverse times EP,
then the system is always stable.
So next, we're going to show that why it is always stable.
So here, to prove stability, we will use the near-proof measure.
We first define the near-proof function.
EP is equal to one-half EP transpose times EP.
So this is the same as one-half EP squared.
So next, we're going to show that this EP is always positive definite.
To show this, we need to check two conditions.
The first one is as EP.
This is the approach function.
EP is defined like this.
It's the square of a term.
So it is always bigger than or equal to zero, always true.
And also, this EP is equal to zero only at EP equal to zero.
Why we have this?
This is because this EP is a quadratic form.
It's a square term.
So it is equal to zero only if EP is zero.
So because of these two conditions, we can claim that this EP is always positive definite.
Next, we will check the derivative of this near-proof function, EP.
So starting from here, the definition of EP.
So we can take this derivative.
EP. is equal to EP transpose times EP.
Then we can form slide 22.
We can have EP. equal to negative EP times EP.
So we plug in this.
Then we got EP. equal to EP transpose times negative EP.
This is further equal to negative EP transpose times EP.
This is negative EP squared.
So from this, we can note that EP. is negative definite.
Why? Because we have these two conditions satisfied.
The first one is that EP. is always less than or equal to zero.
Because EP. is negative EP times a square term.
And also this EP. is equal to zero only at one point.
Only at EP. equal to zero.
So because of these two conditions, we can claim that EP. is negative definite.
EP. is positive definite and EP. is negative definite.
So by combining them together, we can use this near-proof theory to show that
this control system is asymptotically stable.
So that means mathematically, EP. goes to zero as it goes to infinity.
This proves the stability condition.
So next, I'm going to stop here for about two minutes.
So to let you guys take a look at this analysis.
So for those, for a very familiar with control, this may look not difficult.
But for those who don't have a control background, this may need a little bit of time to digest.
So I'll leave you guys about two minutes to go through this.
You can also discuss with your friends if you have questions on this analysis.
So after two minutes, then we continue with this EP. and also EP.
Okay.
Let's continue.
So these two papers, so published, like I said, twenty-five or more years ago.
So people use some model-based measures to estimate the post-error.
To find the post-error, CAD model information is required.
So this is an early year measure.
So we just mentioned this briefly in this class.
We're going to go through all these details.
So these are the years of these two papers.
And this measure is for reference.
Okay.
So this is the one way to find the post-error if you have the CAD model information.
So in this class, we want to focus more on homography and essential matrix measure.
Okay.
Which are reflected in these two equations.
So that's what we want to focus on in this class.
We want to focus on epipodem measures and homography measures.
Okay.
So in these two measures, epipodem, constraint or essential matrix is defined as X cross M R.
And in the second measure, homography is defined as R plus a term depending on X.
So these two measures, what do we want to focus on?
We don't want to use the CAD model to find the post.
Then based on the essential matrix and also the homography, we can decompose them respectively and eventually get the rotation and scale translation.
So even though in terms of mathematics, they look a little bit different, but the idea is the same.
Eventually we will get the rotation and scale translation.
And for all these remarks, we leave it for reference.
Okay.
So just now we'll talk about this PBS.
We'll talk about how we define the error and how we design the controller, how we analyze the stability.
So these three points are required.
So in addition, we also need to understand the main drawback and the main strengths of this PBS.
Okay.
So maybe I can show you one simulation first.
We'll talk about the strengths and weaknesses of this measure.
Okay.
So kind of in this simulation.
So there are two halves in the simulation.
The left half will show you the image space.
It shows us how the facial points move on the images, to the images.
And the right half shows the 3D space.
How the camera moves.
This one means the camera and here we have four facial points.
So let's take a look at the destination first.
Okay.
Let's take a look at it.
One more time.
Okay.
For PBS, the drawback is that facial points may move outside the field of view of the camera.
And the strengths or the good point for PBS is that in the 3D space, the camera has quite a good 3D trajectory.
Okay.
So kind of here we have the main drawback of PBS and also the main advantage or strengths of this PBS.
All right.
So after we know the strengths and the drawback of this measure, let's take a look at the simulation one more time.
Okay.
So in the 3D space, the camera has a quite a straight trajectory in the 3D space.
So now we stop the simulation.
Next we'll take a look at this PBS, this image based WISU survey.
For this method, PBS, the error is defined in the image space.
So here we'll have three images.
Let's take a look at the two smaller images.
So you can see in these two images, our object has different pose.
The rotation is a little bit different.
PBS measures the difference between the coordinates of several features in the current image and in a go image.
So even though we have two images, but actually we'll define the errors for PBS, we just use several feature points.
The camera is moved so that the features move towards their go coordinates.
And on the bigger image, so kind of these arrows show how the features move, the directions, but they just move.
To define controllers for PBS, we have started with these differential equations for PBS.
We consider a station or a point viewed by a moving camera.
The points as coordinates M bar given by XYZ transpose in the camera frame FC.
So for this, for this, PBS kinematics, it is just a given to us.
So you don't need to derive these three equations.
We don't have to remember that.
So these are the dynamic equations that we start to design the controller.
So for this XYZ, when x dot equal to this equation, y dot z dot equal to these three equations respectively.
And we can reorganize these three equations a little bit to get this x dot y dot z dot equal to functions of the velocity of the camera.
Here for the three terms, omega x, omega z, y and omega z.
So this is the angular velocity of the camera.
And for vx, vy and vz, they are for the translational velocity of the camera.
We can normalize the Euclidean coordinate and get x dot and m y dot.
m is defined as x over z, y over z, and a 1 equal to mx, myy, and 1.
So then from the first rule of equations, we can get mx dot and y dot.
So this is where we gave the dynamics to design the control inputs.
But on this slide, it's just to show you roughly what kind of equations that this coordinate satisfies.
But you don't have to remember these equations.
So next, for one feature point, we can get the dynamic equations.
I'm x dot, I'm y dot.
So from these three equations, is this matrix times a six-dimensional velocity control input vector?
The three is for translational velocity and three variables are for rotational velocity.
This matrix, we name it as LIJ.
J is the J's feature point.
This LIJ has a name, it's called Image-Jocopin, or Interaction Matrix for FACET point J.
So similarly here, you don't have to remember the detailed mathematical equation for this LIJ.
But you need to understand here that if we want to control p, p, v, s, what are we controlling?
We're controlling this velocity input.
This is the dimension vector, so you understand this.
And also you should know that roughly this mj dot is equal to a matrix times the input.
I understand this basic concept.
But what is in LIJ, you don't have to remember.
So you can need it in project, you can still check the mathematics.
Now based on this dynamics, how can we design the camera velocity input so that we can achieve heavy vs?
So this part is required.
How to design control once we have the dynamics?
From one feature point, we have mj dot equal to LIJ times the camera input zeta.
And now you will have n feature points that will get n different dynamic equations.
m1 dot equal to LI1 times input, and mn dot equal to LIn times input.
So we can combine them together and get a matrix LI with a i2 represented.
i2 means image, ibv as image-based basic solving.
Our freedom is the camera velocity input.
That's what we can design.
If n is 3, this LI is a 6 by 6 matrix.
If n is bigger than 3, this LI is a 2m by 6 matrix.
Then we can take the pseudo-universe if needed.
Sudo-universe ii plus is defined as li transpose times li inverse times li transpose.
So making it easier for you, usually we just use square matrix and use the normal inverse.
But if it is not a square matrix, then you can still use pseudo-universe.
For ibv, the error is defined in the image space.
It is the difference between the current feature and the goal feature locations.
Mathematically, this area ei is this vector m1, m2, mn.
The minus this vector m1 star mn, 2 star, 2mn star.
The second column, this is a constant vector.
The goal feature locations is a constant.
The first column is called current feature locations.
It is time-varying. It changes along with time t.
This is the image space error ei.
For this ei, the open loop error dynamics is ei dot equal to li times zeta.
What is in li? You do not have to remember this.
But the mathematics can be found from slide 4 to slide 5.
The control objective here is to design zeta to make this error ei go through zero.
That is the objective.
How to design this error and how to make sure that it goes through zero?
This part is required.
The control design is on the next slide.
Based on this open loop error dynamics, we can design a stabilizing proportional feedback controller
with zeta equal to negative ki times li inverse times ei.
This ki is a positive skin again. It is just a positive control parameter.
Next, we are going to show why this one works.
From the error dynamics, ei dot equal to li times the input zeta.
Also from the controller that we just designed, zeta is equal to negative ki li inverse times ei.
We can combine them and figure out the closer loop error dynamics.
This ei dot is equal to...
This is a typo. We do not have an active ki yet.
This is equal to li times the input. We plug in the input.
Next, we can take out this control parameter ki and we can combine li and li inverse.
The case which are there and gives us an identity matrix, then the rest is just equal to negative ki times ei.
This is a closer error dynamics.
ei dot equal to negative ki times ei.
For this, we can claim that this is a stable system.
How to show that it is a stable system? Then we can use this neoprofit method to do it.
Here, we first define a neopropath function.
vi t is equal to one-half ei transpose times ei.
This is equal to one-half ei squared.
This is always a positive definite neopropath function.
Why it is positive definite?
Because vi ei's function is always either positive or equal to zero.
Because it is a quadratic term. It can never be negative.
In addition, this vi ei is not always equal to zero at any point.
It is equal to zero only at one position.
Only at ei equal to zero.
Because of this, then this is a positive definite.
This is a positive definite function.
Next, we take a look at the derivative of this neoprofit function.
vi dot is equal to
From this definition, here, this is equal to ei transpose times ei dot.
So you take this derivative.
So based on what we derived in the previous slide,
this ei dot is equal to
negative ki times ei.
This is a closed loop aerodynamics.
So we can plug this in and we can figure out that this vi dot is ei transpose
times negative ki ei.
This is from the closed loop aerodynamics.
And then we can figure out that this is equal to negative ki times ei squared.
We can prove that this vi dot is negative definite because
vi dot is a quadratic form.
So it is always less than or equal to zero.
And the second, this equal sign is valid only at one position.
Only at ei is zero.
So this shows that this vi dot is negative definite.
So we can combine them together.
Where is possible definite and where is negative definite.
We combine them together and we can claim that this system is always
asymptotically stable.
But it is only a local result, not globally.
This is different from PBVS.
Okay, so why is this only locally asymptotically stable but not globally
as unstable?
This is because of this matrix Li, which we will show on the next slide.
Because this Jacobian matrix or interaction matrix Li can become singular.
So it's inverse.
It's not always defined.
It actually depends on the feature points.
So for some feature points Li can become singular and then results
just locally asymptotically stable.
If li is not singular and the goal mt equal to m star.
So then it will be not singular in a very small neighborhood
around this goal position m star.
But there is no way to guarantee that it's always not singular.
And also we cannot decide how big the label for this.
So that's why we only claim that the result is locally asymptotically stable.
So this is also a drawback of PBVS in comparison to PBVS.
So just now we have used the square matrix Li and we use n equal to 3.
So if n is bigger than 3, then we don't have a square matrix.
The matrix becomes 2n times 6.
So for this case, we can use the pseudo-inverse of Li.
Li plus.
So then the controller can be changed to negative Ki times Li to the inverse times Yi.
The analysis will also be a little bit different.
The difference is mainly with this.
So we don't have Li plus not just an added matrix anymore.
So let's take a look at the simulation and see what is the stress and the drawback of this PBVS message.
Okay, so here we also have two halves on the simulation plane.
The left half is for the image space and the right half is for the straight Euclidean space.
So now we can see that on the image space, the result looks very good.
The feature points are always inside the field of view of the camera.
So this is the good thing.
So that means the camera will not lose sight of the feature points.
But the drawback is actually in the straight Euclidean space.
So now in the straight Euclidean space, you can see that for this trajectory,
the motion trajectory of the camera, it can be very long and looks very weird.
It's not that straight.
The camera actually goes for a large round and then comes back.
So this is the big drawback of the PBVS image-based visual server control method.
So on the images, the trajectory looks very nice.
But in the real 3D space, the camera motion based on the PBVS can look very weird.
It's sometimes not even reasonable.
It is like, let me show you one example.
It is like we want to go to Canon B, but actually we go to Canon A first,
then come back to Canon B.
So this is a kind of similar idea for PBVS.
So that's the drawback.
The drawback is that the actual trajectory of the camera may be very long.
Alright, so that's the drawback.
And the strength of the good thing is that the feature points are always inside the field of view of the camera.
So these are two classic measures for visual serving.
Position-based visual serving and image-based visual serving, PBVS and IBVS.
So in order to avoid the drawbacks of these two measures, researchers in the past 20 years have done a lot of research
combining these two measures, hybrid measure, switching measures, or 2.5B homography-based measures.
So all kinds of measures to combine the strengths and to avoid the drawbacks.
Okay, so let's have a quick comparison of these two measures, IBVS and PBVS.
PBVS position-based visual serving is globally asymptotic stable.
But IBVS is only locally asymptotic stable.
So this is because the image of a Corbin, this LI, may be singular for some feature points.
There's no guarantee that this LI is always full rank.
So that's where this drawback comes from.
So PBVS, the position error strictly decreases in the 3D space, and as I said, the robot follows least distance path to the goal.
So in the 3D space, the camera or robot will have quite nice trajectory for PBVS.
But for IBVS, this cannot be guaranteed.
The 3D trajectory may look very long for IBVS.
For IBVS, the stress is that image error strictly decreases.
The feature follows least distance path to their goal coordinates in the image space or in the image plane.
So on the image plane, the trajectory for IBVS looks quite good.
And the feature points will always be inside the field of view.
So we can use these two images to summarize the drawbacks and the stress of PBVS and IBVS.
So for PBVS, the drawback is mainly in the image space.
Now this EI square means the image space error.
It may increase and then decreases so that on the images, PBVS may have very weird, very strange trajectory on the image space.
But for the error in the EI space, for this EP, this error decreases very well.
So in the 3D, in the Canadian space, PBVS will have very nice motion trajectory physically.
So that's the stress.
For IBVS, it's actually different on the image space.
For this image space error, EI, this error decreases
very quickly.
So in the image space, IBVS can generate quite good trajectory on the 2D space.
But the drawback is with the 3D EI space.
In this 3D space, the camera may have very long trajectory.
So that's the summary and also for this class.
So if you have any questions regarding this class, you can still come here and talk to me after the class.
And also again, so next week, we are going to have the quiz.
The quiz may cover topics from week number 8 to week number 12.
That's this class.
Okay, so for the time that we still have, so I'll be here just to answer questions that in each of you have individually.
Okay.
What kind of practical questions?
What are the examples, please?
Okay, I'm afraid that it would not help.
You can just use the next notes, which are called for for the quiz.
Okay.
So the ways to use the quiz are different.
Next, let's have IBVS with the same hair as the image from this graph.
We get the same hair, this next, low-mass coordinates.
Yes.
So for IBVS, we actually use the rotation and translation.
Oh, and it's just for the photos.
Yes.
Is it for camera rotation?
Right, right, right. Camera rotation and camera translation.
So you can see.
So one of the questions is why does the quiz have a full hand here?
It's just a jacobian matrix.
Oh, okay.
Okay, even though they all called it jacobian, but the meaning is a little bit different.
So the quiz is just developed based on the differential equation.
So that's the equation.
No, no, no, it's different.
I was curious.
The controller is actually designed to give us this kind of structure.
Okay.
So how to get the object from there?
This actually is designed based on the actual method.
So usually for this, the approach is the design.
So the approach function first.
The approach function first.
And then we design the controller to meet the certain...
...comment.
...stability.
Right, right, right.
And to design the controller to meet the stability of the solution.
So just...
Okay, just no detail.
It's just very...
Okay, so this is already the detail.
So let's say for controller design, of course it takes some kind of practice and also experience.
So let's say why we're designing in this way?
Yeah, yes, yes.
Yeah, this is because eventually one of these aerodynamics to be like this.
E.P.Buy in the negative, E.P.
Yes, yes.
Yeah, so because for this kind of form, we know very well that it's going to be stable.
So we just make the controller to that, it equals to...
Right, right, right, right.
Oh, okay.
Okay, same thing.
Yes.
Yes, pro.
When this pose, I would say it doesn't...
...desired...
Oh, okay.
It can also be...
Yeah, so for this one, this E.P. and E.I. are different.
Next, say for E.I., you have the current pose of...
Sorry, current image and...
...did that image, right?
Yeah, and minus time stop.
But this one is...
This is just the translation.
This is the position.
This is difference.
Next example, if I want to move from here to here,
if I go from this place to this place,
this axis is already the difference between them.
So there's no axis stop.
But is it also a function of time?
Yeah, it's a function of time, yes.
Because one of them can move.
The other one is fixed.
So it's already different.
And how about...
What is the meaning of reference and what is examable?
Okay, for reference, we're not hasty in the presentation.
But in the exam, we should remember something like this velocity open.
Yeah, you just remember it's roughly the dynamics of the dynamics to the light.
You can tell the input of a matrix M input.
But you don't have to know that what it's...
...now, P.
Because this is where we have our party to remember.
Yeah, so don't need to remember it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Okay.