.
Okay.
Good evening, everyone.
So in the previous week, actually, we have studied the supra-learning,
and actually we have designed different types of classifiers.
And actually all these classified designs are based on the label training data.
Okay.
So of course, in this framework, supra-learning, based on the label training data,
and we have studied two main problems.
One is the classification problem.
Okay.
Classification, that is to categorize the samples, to assign the sample to different classes.
So the label, right, label training, the data label here is just the class label.
And another problem is the regression problem.
Okay.
And then for each sample, we have a target value.
Now in the classification problem, the target value is just the class label.
Okay.
But here, actually, in regression problem, actually, the target value is no longer a class label.
Instead, it is a real value or numerical value, actually, a target variable.
Okay.
Numerical value, target variable.
So this is the supra-learning.
And today we are going to study the unsupervised learning.
Supra-learning is based on the unlabeled data.
So in supra-learning, actually, the supra-varyon signal is just the class label, right?
So we learn and adjust the parameters so that actually the response of the model could be very close to the supra-varyon signal.
So that is the target variable, the class label, or the numerical value, not target variable.
Okay.
We have a supra-varyon signal.
So this is supra-learning.
The unsupervised learning is the data unlabeled.
So we no longer have such a supra-varyon signal.
So that is the reason why this kind of learning is called unsupervised learning, right?
Because we have no label.
We have no supra-varyon signal.
So this kind of learning is called unlabeled.
Unsupervised learning.
Okay.
So this is actually a category, unsupervised learning.
We have two main topics.
One is the clustering.
Clustering is just a group of the data.
Okay.
And then another problem is association analysis.
Association.
Okay.
So actually in this course, of course, actually we focus on the clustering analysis, clustering of the data.
And I'm not trusting this course, actually.
In the landscape of the machine learning, in particular the unsupervised learning, the focus is actually just the clustering analysis.
Okay.
So association analysis is just attached a bit.
And okay.
So of course in this course, actually we focus on the clustering analysis.
Okay.
And the clustering analysis also have many applications.
And some example applications include actually the marketing segmentation.
Okay.
In marketing, right.
And we can actually group the customers, right.
And then actually, you know, we know, you know, for different groups of customers, you know, we can adopt different marketing strategies.
Okay.
So this is a marketing segmentation.
And then another such result group.
Okay.
You can search.
You can get a lot of results.
And then you can group the result, right.
And in the super-added learning, we put the result normally into different categories.
But here we don't have the concept of category.
Instead, we have the concept of cluster or group.
Okay.
So we into actually group, actually, or cluster, actually the session result.
So this unsupervised learning.
Actually, in many applications, actually, you know, to solve one of the problems, we need to use both super-added learning and unsupervised learning.
Okay.
And the progress, actually, I remember I talked about one example, right.
For example, actually, you know, one bank or insurance company launch a new program, insurance program for insurance company or bank insurance.
And maybe a launch a new fixed deposit, actually, you know, scheme.
Okay.
And of course, actually, you know, a very smart way for marketing is that, actually, we can collect, you know, we can select some of the customers, right, from the very big pool.
The pool could be, you know, easily over a few million, right, in Singapore or small country.
The population, the number of customers in a bank could be thousands of millions or billions, right, could be that, actually, scale.
Okay.
So we can randomly, of course, we can select, no, we can select a small group of customers and then we can counter them to get their response, to see whether they are interested in the program or in the scheme or they have no interest.
So we can, these are interests or no interest, just a label, right.
So we can collect such label, then we can train a model, right.
So then we can use this model to predict the interest of other customers.
Okay.
So, so these are the three problems here until now, three is a super learning problem, right, because we collect the response of the customer.
So this is a label.
Okay.
Then, actually, we use the label to learn a model, right.
So other classification model or sometimes regression model.
And then we, we learn a model.
Okay.
So this is super learning.
But the problem here is that, actually, you have a very big pool of customers, millions, thousands of millions, billions of customers.
So how to select a few thousand, for example, two thousand customers, how to select a few thousand randomly.
Okay.
And of course you can do randomly, but randomly selection may not be a good, actually, selection scheme.
And actually we know, you know, the model performance, actually, largely depends on the data, right, the data quality.
So one of the aspects of the data quality is the representativeness of the data.
If the data tree, the training data, span the whole space.
The whole training data, the training data are representative of all the data.
And then the model, then, based on this training data, even a small number of training data, couldn't generate well.
Okay.
But we use randomly a small group of, you know, customers.
And maybe, you know, this customer cannot be a good representation or good representative of all the, you know, customers.
So in such a scenario, the model we built will not generate well.
Okay.
So here how to select these, you know, a few thousand customers and to, and to, and to label them, right?
This is a key issue.
Actually we can solve this problem using the so-called unsupervised landing.
Okay.
And then we can group.
We can cluster, actually, the millions, or down the millions, or billions of customers.
Okay.
And we can put them into, for example, two thousand groups through the so-called cluster analysis method.
And then, you know, from each group we select one as a representative.
Okay.
If we select, you know, customers and then label them in such a way, and then the training data will be representative.
And then the model built upon this representative data will generate well.
Okay.
So you can say, you know, in this, you know, problem, actually, we use the boot supervised
landing and unsupervised landing.
Okay.
So this is the application of the unsupervised landing.
So let's talk about some basics of a cluster analysis.
Unsupervised landing, normally when we see unsupervised landing, normally we refer to the cluster analysis.
Clustering.
A group of the data.
Okay.
And so roughly speaking, a classroom procedure yield data description in terms of cluster
or grouping of groups of the data.
Okay.
Description.
So that's reason, unsupervised landing is quite often called actually description landing.
Right.
And actually, throughout the landing, you know, we have a description of the data, or the data has some groups, right.
And the group of the data, we have a description of this.
So unsupervised landing is also called actually, you know, descriptive landing.
And then unsupervised landing is also called actually predictive landing.
Right.
We predict the class label.
We predict, you know, the numerical value, you know, target variable.
Okay.
So this is the, you know, the cluster analysis.
It's about the grouping of the data.
Okay.
And of course, the grouping of the data actually is not arbitrary.
You cannot see all these, you know, samples should be put in one group.
This sample should be, you know, put in another group.
But we should be based on some criteria, right, when we group them.
Okay.
And the criteria here is that the samples within the same group should have strong internal
similarities.
Or within group similarities.
Okay.
And, you know, in panel classification, you know, quite often we see, we hope actually
the data could have a strong and within class similarity, right.
And we could have a strong, between class, this similarity.
In unsupervised landing, there is no concept of class.
There is a concept of group.
Okay.
So actually the criteria here is that actually the samples within the same group or cluster
should have strong internal similarities.
Okay.
So here we talk about similarity, right.
So how do you measure similarity?
Similarity.
Okay.
And actually here, the grouping, group the data and then we should have some, show strong
similarity, right.
And the grouping of the data here we see, we emphasize the natural grouping.
You know, actually see, oh, those, those should be belong to one group.
Based on your, you know, arbitrary criteria.
This grouping should be natural.
Okay.
So what does this mean for natural grouping?
So this is one issue.
So what do we mean if we see natural grouping?
Okay.
And then another is how to measure the similarity.
In what sense the sample in one group shows strong and within class or within group similarities
or the strong internal similarities.
So in what sense?
In other words, how to measure the similarity?
Okay.
So these are the two issues actually we need to further explain.
So actually the similarity measure actually similarity can be measured using the distance.
The distance, right, the distance.
In the space, in the feature space actually every point, every sample is a point, right.
And of course in the feature space we can calculate the distance between any point.
So actually this distance actually is a measure of the similarity between the two samples.
Okay.
You can imagine if two samples are very similar, an extreme case is that the two samples are exactly the same.
Then in the space they correspond to the same point, right.
The distance from the same point, the point to itself, right, is zero.
Okay.
In other words actually we know the similarity can be measured using the distance.
And the smaller the distance actually the greater the similarity.
Okay.
So this is the measure for similarity.
And we use the distance.
Distance, okay.
Of course actually this is not the only metric that we can use for similarity, right.
I think another that we commonly use actually, simulation measure is the, normally the correlation.
Okay.
And what is correlation?
Correlation actually basically something like an inner product of two vectors.
Each sample is a vector, right.
So there's a correlation between two vectors.
And, but we need to normalize this correlation.
Okay.
So we need to normalize this correlation.
And normally this should be the inner product of these two vectors divided by the norm of the two vectors.
And actually this is actually a correlation, a normalize correlation.
It's also called cosine similarity.
Cousine similarity between the two vectors.
Okay.
And the, gemetrically the cosine similarity is just a cosine of the angle between the two vectors.
We have two vectors, right.
Of course actually there is an angle between the two vectors.
So the cosine similarity actually is just the cosine of the angle between the two actually,
the two vectors.
And you can imagine, right, if the two angles, if the two samples, is that the same?
And then the two vectors, you know, overlap, right?
So the angle between them is zero.
Then cosine zero is one.
Okay.
So these actually, cosine similarity can be used as a, actually, metric for the evaluation
of the similarity between the samples.
Okay.
And so here actually, but I think frequently, I think in different applications, and for
example, in much, you know, left-hand angle processing, and quite often actually we use
the, like, cosine similarity between two, you know, representations of words or representation
or sentence.
We use cosine similarity.
Okay.
And by the most applications, we use the Euclidean distance.
Later we will see, now that we're Euclidean distance, we have a few, we have a few, we
have a few types of distance.
Okay.
But Euclidean distance is just the most commonly used one.
So this is the metric.
This is a similarity measure.
Okay.
And then that's actually, we have another issue, right?
So natural grouping.
What does this mean, natural grouping?
Actually, when you put them into one group, right?
Actually, this natural grouping means that we, within the group, and the samples should
show strong similarities, or within group similarities.
And between groups, the sample should show strong, between group, actually distance,
or dissimilarities.
So this is called natural grouping.
Okay.
So natural grouping here, I have a tool, an S-pad, right?
Why is it taught about that?
Within group, within group, within cluster similarity.
Okay.
So this diagram just shows this.
All the red samples belong to one group.
Okay.
We can see the distance between the samples, actually, they're relative small.
And, okay.
And so here, the blue samples also belong to one group.
So the distance between the samples is relatively small.
But the distance between the groups is relatively big.
Okay.
So this is called natural grouping.
We cannot see, oh, I put this sample, and this sample into one group.
You define that group, but that group is not the natural grouping of the data.
Okay.
Collagen analysis tries to find the natural grouping of the data.
After grouping of other classrooms, within cluster, the sample should have strong similarities
or small distance.
Okay.
So these are the two cons aspects of the natural grouping and also for the evaluation of the
similarities.
Okay.
So these actually just now talk about the distance, right?
So here, we have a very general form for the distance.
Here, we have two vectors.
One is x, another is x prime.
Right?
So how to find the distance between actually the two vectors, and we have this very general
definition.
Okay.
So the care, right?
Because the vector has many elements.
Okay.
So the care element, the care element in the two vector, the difference, and then power
q summation, and then power 1 q over q.
D here is the denominator of the vector, right?
How many elements in one vector?
So this is called the D. Okay.
And this is very general, right?
Minkowski distance.
Okay.
But actually, we have normally, we use a special scenario, right?
When q equals to 2, so this is just the commonly used actually, including distance.
If you didn't write it, we have the elements, corresponding element, different square,
that's summation, square roots.
So that is just an including distance.
Okay.
And so this is the case when q equals 1 or 2.
When q equals to 1, this distance is called actually Manhattan distance or city block
distance.
Okay.
And for example, actually, no, for example, the Euclidean distance, for example, from
me to this student.
So this is just an equal distance.
Okay.
This is the distance.
And actually, the city block, that means actually we have a lot of blocks, there are buildings,
and we cannot go anywhere, right?
And so we need to go this way first, horizontal axis from here, and then go vertical axis.
So this is called x, actually, the city block distance.
So distance, actually, along the y-axis, then plus the distance along another axis.
So this is our city block.
Okay.
Because actually, we cannot go, I cannot pass through the table and go to the student, right?
This is the distance.
I need to go this way first, and then horizontally and then vertically.
Okay.
So this is called, actually, the city block distance.
And remember, actually, in the feature subset selection part, and we use, actually, a distance
to evaluate the goodies of the feature subset, right?
And actually, we try to eliminate the redundancies.
Okay.
So that is the Mahanobid distance.
So progress, it will be used Mahanobid distance.
Okay.
Actually, you can also use the Mahanobid distance, actually, to know for, as a metric, and for
the similarity between the samples.
Okay.
And another is the Kusang similarity, right?
Actually, already explained is Kusang similarity.
So these are the, you know, so city block distance, you clean the distance, and the Mahanobid
distance, and the city block distance, and so forth.
Kusang similarity can all be used, actually, as a metric for the evaluation of the similarity
between the samples.
Okay.
Samples within one cluster, the, or samples between clusters.
So these are the dysnometric, which can be used as a mirror for the similarity.
Okay.
And then we talk about the types of a collaterial algorithm.
So there are four types of a collaterial algorithm.
The first part is called central-based collaterial algorithm, central-based collaterial method,
central, okay.
Central is just a center.
We assume there is a center.
Okay.
And this method is also called a partitioning method.
And we partition the whole space into many parts, and each part has a center.
This center is a representative of that, you know, of that group, of that cluster.
This center is also called a non-class center.
Okay.
It's a central-based method.
And then another method is called hierarchical collaterial.
Hararchical.
And then that type is called a G, a G non-disruption-based collaterial.
The final one is called density-based collaterial.
Okay.
So that's our first briefly talk about each of, you know, the basic ideas of this, you
know, four types of collaterial method.
And then after that, from each of these four types, we select one algorithm, and then to
study the details of that algorithm.
Okay.
So we first look at the central-based method, central-based partitioning method, right?
And then we look at the central-based partitioning method, actually, through the whole space.
Is the partition divided into many parts?
And each part actually have one center.
So this is a central-based method, right?
You can divide the whole pool of the customers into many groups, right?
And each group, you can select one representative.
Okay.
Actually, I think this representative, actually, the class center is a good representative,
right?
Yeah.
Okay.
So this is the partitioning method.
And actually, the very famous K-means classroom algorithm actually belongs to this type,
central-based method, okay, or partitioning method.
We assume there is a center.
There is a center.
So this center is also a centroid.
This center is also a representative of all the samples in that group.
Okay.
And then the second type is hierarchical classroom, actually, hierarchical.
And actually, hierarchical classroom were produced actually, a dendrogram, which is a tree-like
structure, this, like this, okay.
And actually, previously, we studied the classification tree, right?
From the rule node, and we asked one question using a tree based on one specific feature,
right, or attribute.
And then the data is divided into two parts, okay.
And then from the left branch or right branch, actually, we can ask another question using
maybe another feature.
Another divided is a further divided into two parts, right?
And then this is a tree.
We could group the tree.
So this is a tree, okay.
So here, similarly, right?
Okay.
And the data here, you know, can be considered, we have a whole data, and the data divided
into two parts, okay, into two parts.
Okay.
And the two big groups.
And then for each of the two groups, we can further divide them into two groups.
And then for them, and then we further divide them into two groups.
Okay.
So this is, like, I know, just very similar to the classification tree, okay.
So this is the hierarchical classification, and this is actually a diagram, and it is
called a dendrogram.
Dendrogram, okay.
And this dendrogram, actually, shows the similarity of the samples.
And the samples could be hard to know, right?
And normally, we cannot visualize the data directly in the space.
You cannot visualize, then it is hard to visualize the distance between them, right?
But actually, this is a hierarchical classification tree, the dendrogram, actually, gives us a
visualization of the distance, the similarity between the samples.
Okay.
So actually, now you can see the dendrogram, you draw a line, right?
Actually, the height of the line, actually, the proportional, actually, the similarity
or the distance, actually, between, actually, the samples.
Okay.
You can see, like, okay, so these are two samples combined, right, into one cluster.
And this distance, this height here, right, is small.
This means that these samples, two samples, actually, are very similar.
And in this diagram here, we see these two clusters are combined.
But actually, this distance is big.
So this means these two samples, actually, are very different.
They're very different.
Okay.
So this is the dendrogram, the height, actually, the proportional to the distance between,
actually, the clusters.
Okay.
So this is the hierarchical clustering.
Then we have a distribution-based clustering, distribution-based.
In the distribution-based method, actually, we assume the data actually comes from certain distributions.
Of course, actually, the most commonly used distribution is Gaussian distribution, right?
It's a multivariate normal distribution or Gaussian distribution.
Okay.
So actually, we can assume this, and then we can actually try to model the distribution of the data,
try to model, right?
And actually, I think, if we assume the data for a normal distribution,
and then, actually, this is a method, just Gaussian-Mittscher model, right?
Gaussian-Mittscher model, actually, remember, is used in the first part, right?
When we started the business decision rule, we need to build the class conditional probability-dense functions.
Okay.
In some scenarios, the samples in the same class are from different distributions, different Gaussian functions.
So we use the Gaussian-Mittscher model, right?
And to model the class conditional probability-dense function.
Okay.
But actually, that's for superheated learning, right?
We know that sample belongs to the same group, a same class, right?
So for class one, class two, then we use the Gaussian-Mittscher model.
But in the superheated learning, we don't have the concept of class, right?
But actually, we can just put all the data into one group.
Okay.
Then we try to build, actually, the data, actually, using the Gaussian-Mittscher model.
We can build the distribution, or model distribution of the data using the Gaussian-Mittscher model.
Okay.
And then after we've, you know, actually, you know, after we have got this model, and then
actually each Gaussian function correspond to one cluster.
Okay.
So in this example here, we have three Gaussian functions, and then we have three clusters.
And then for Gaussian function, we have the mean vector, right?
Actually, the mean vector is just a class center.
So later, we will look at this again.
Okay.
So this is the distribution-based cluster.
Another is density-based cluster.
Okay.
And actually, in the central-based cluster, if we normally assume the distribution of
the data is like a sphere, like a ball.
Okay.
And by some scenarios, actually, this may not be true.
And so actually, to address, actually, arbitrary shape, actually, a distribution, and then
we can use density-based cluster.
For example, right?
The data, the arbitrary shape, not like a sphere, right?
It's an arbitrary shape.
Okay.
And so for such a kind of data, and the, the, the division method, you know, the, you know,
the, the partition method may not work well.
Okay.
But the, actually, the density-based method actually could work well.
For arbitrary shape, actually, in the distribution, we can use a density-based cluster.
Okay.
So later, we will also, you know, select one density-based method and then start the detail
of that method.
Okay.
So this is the, okay.
Then a brief introduction of the, the, the four types of cluster method, right?
So, that's actually, you know, we will actually study it through one example, you know, algorithm
from each of the four methods.
Okay.
So we first look at the central-based cluster, central-based.
That means that we assume that the data is a centroid, a center.
Okay.
And so not also we assume that the distribution of the data has a shape of a sphere, a sphere
shape, a distribution, like a ball.
Okay.
A ball, of course, that is the center.
So this is the basic assumption.
Okay.
And of course, if this is the assumption, it's not actually, it's not met, right?
It's not satisfied.
And then this is the central-based method may not produce the best result.
And then we need to think about some other methods.
Okay.
So that's the reason, you know, for any classification problem, we need to study different methods,
right?
Because there will be no one single algorithm that performs the best in all applications.
So every time, actually, we need to try all the algorithms, then we find the best performing
one.
For class, we're the same.
So that's the reason why we study different class, you know, method.
If the data follow, actually, this kind of a distribution, right?
A sphere-shaped distribution.
And then the central-based method may produce the best performance.
But if this condition is not satisfied, then this is actually a method.
We are not producing the best performance.
Then we should try other methods.
Okay.
So, okay.
So you can see, actually, here, all the data belong to one group.
You want to another group.
You want to each group have a center.
Okay.
And actually, the most commonly used, actually, you know, central-based method or partition
method is a K-means classroom.
Okay.
Actually, you know, this is the most frequently used method, classroom method, K-means classroom.
And this K, okay, is a hyperparameter.
So, later, we are, you spend this further.
Okay.
So, we are geometry, you know, we have a data set D. And the data set consists of X1, X2,
and Xn.
Okay.
In Schubert's learning, we have the training data.
We are testing data, right?
In the, in the, in the, in the Schubert's learning, we don't have this concept.
We don't have training.
We don't have testing.
Because testing, even for testing, we don't have a label, right?
We don't have a label.
You don't, you don't know.
We also don't have the validation data.
We just have some data.
Then you just put them into different groups.
Okay.
You provide the distribution of other groups.
So, that is just the, you know, classroom analysis.
Okay.
We don't have the concept of training or testing.
So, here, we just have such a data set.
D is a continuing example, X1, X2.
Okay.
And then our objective is to divide them or partition them into actually case subset.
And this case subset should be disjoint.
So, be disjoint.
Right?
That means there are no overlap.
In other words, no sample beyond two or more actual groups.
Okay.
That means no, no overlapping, right?
So, disjoint.
Okay.
So, our objective of classroom is to divide the data into case disjoint subset.
D1, D2, and then DK.
DK.
Okay.
And then, of course, this division or partition of the data are not actual, right?
And actually, we should follow the so-called natural grouping principle.
Natural grouping.
Okay.
So, after you divide the data into case subset, then within each subset, the data should have
a strong internal similarity.
Okay.
And between the subset, the sample should estimate a strong dissimilarity.
So, this is the between group dissimilarity.
So, within group similarity, strong internal, within group similarity, or within class similarity,
or between a strong, between class disimilarities.
This is the principle of natural grouping, right?
Natural grouping.
Okay.
And actually, you know, here we also need to define actually a function, a optimization
function.
Actually, I repeat this a few times, right?
Actually, machine learning problem, like supervised learning, right?
So, we start from some, you know, understanding or some ideas about pattern classification.
And then, you know, we convert this into, or we formulate this into an optimization problem.
You remember, right?
In the suborbital machine, you know, we formulate this as a constant optimization problem.
Okay.
And in the future linear demagneticism, and we also formulate this as a maximization
problem, maximizing the ratio, right?
Fissure ratio, the ratio between, actually, the scatter, the ratio of the, you know, between
class scatter, you know, over the, you know, within class scatter.
So, it's an optimization problem.
And actually, the classification problem can also be formulated, actually, as an optimization
problem.
Okay.
So, here, and we want to derive this, actually, in our criterion, the loss function.
So, that minimizes the loss function.
Okay.
And so, here, actually, we define this, you know, which we call, this is actually a criterion,
or loss function, is called, within class, sum of squares, sum of squares.
This square, I mean, the square distance, square distance, or distance squares.
Okay.
Sum of, you know, within class, sum of square distance.
So, here, actually, we assume, you know, for each subset, and we have a mean vector, right?
We have a mean vector.
Okay.
So, this is just the mean vector.
And then, of course, within the same class, each of the samples are distant, and two of
these are no center vector, right?
Center vector.
Okay.
And therefore, each of the class, and we can calculate within class, get, within class,
within class, actually, sum of square distance, within class, okay?
So, for all the sample in the class, the DI, actually, we can calculate the distance to
the center vector, MI.
For all samples, within class, I, okay?
We can calculate the distance between each of the samples in this cluster to the center
of this cluster.
And the distance, the square distance, we get a summation.
Okay.
So, this is just for, you know, for class I, actually, we have more than one cluster,
right?
We have a class I, class I, and your class K. Okay.
So, then, we get a summation of the within cluster, sum of squares for all the K clusters.
So, from one, see, from one to K. So, here, yeah.
So, this is WCSS, within cluster, sum of squares.
And these are actually something similar to the, you know, within cluster, within cluster,
right?
You know, within cluster scatter.
But here, we don't have cluster.
We call it within cluster.
Okay.
So, this is WCSS, within cluster, sum of square distance.
And, of course, actually, you know, when you actually, you know, the data divide differently,
right?
And here, we have some of the D1, D2, DK, right?
If you D1, DK, you are rendering the data in different groups, right?
You have a different division of the data.
And also, for each of the data, you have different, actually, MI, right?
So, then, the WCSS would be different.
Would be different.
Okay.
And, actually, we want to find, actually, the division of the, or partition of the data.
And also, actually, find this MI so that, actually, the distance WCSS could be minimized.
Minimized.
Okay.
So, the central base cluster here, you know, through some analysis.
Again, this is summarized, actually, as a minimization problem.
We want to partition the data.
Okay.
And so, that, actually, the, within class, the sum of squares, this actually functions
minimized.
Right?
So, again, the machining problem is not coming into a minimization problem.
Of course, actually, this is different from, you know, maybe you just have knowledge of
mathematics, right?
Like, or machination.
But you have no idea about classroom.
We must have some idea of classroom first.
And then we can summarize this into, formulate this into an organization problem.
Okay.
And the criterion function has a simple interpretation.
For every given cluster, the mean vector MI is the best representation or representative
of the sample in this center.
It's the mean class, the mean, the mean, right?
And you have groups.
Okay.
So, what value should be the best representative of that group of data?
Read the mean, the mean vector.
Okay.
And if you think about that problem again, right?
You want to select, you know, like, two, a thousand customers from the pool of millions
or billions of customers, right?
And how to do that?
Actually, what we need to do actually is to select representative customers, right?
Actually, here, we can also, like, divide the whole, you know, pool of the customers
into D1, D2, and DK.
DK here could be 2,000, right?
And then from each of the, you know, the subset, or from each of the groups or cluster, and
we can have select actually the representative customer, right?
Finally, we can select actually 2,000 representative customers through this cluster, the classroom
analysis.
Okay.
So, the, actually, the mean vector is the best representation or representative of this,
you know, sample in this cluster.
Okay.
So, after the call, eventually, we have this concept called class center.
Class center represents the sample in that class.
Okay.
So, this is a center vector.
It's also called a prototype.
Prototype.
Okay.
So, it's a representative.
So, the optimal partitioning is the one that minimizes WCSS.
So, as I mentioned, actually, our objective here is to minimize WCSS.
And in the K-means classroom, actually, we have this K, right?
And actually, this K should be preset.
And actually, so, this actually K is a hyper parameter.
Actually, in many machine learning, you know, all of them, we have a hyper, the so-called
hyper parameter, right?
Previously, when we started the support by number machine, right, you remember, actually,
for inseparable samples, right?
Now, we, the loss function contains two parts.
One is above the norm of the square norm of the W, right?
And then another part, actually, is the summation of the select variables.
Then we have a C, the C.
So, this is a hyper parameter.
Okay.
We need to actually select this hyper parameter, right?
So, this hyper parameter normally is not actually selected directly, you know, from the, not
directly submitted from the data.
Instead, actually, we need to determine the value based on the data, but not directly
estimated from the data.
Okay.
So, this kind of parameter called hyper parameter.
Many models have this parameter, right?
Hyper parameter.
Okay.
And in the regression, we have the lambda.
So, we also have, you know, this lambda is also a hyper parameter.
When we build a classification tree, okay, and we also need to balance the accuracy on
the training data and the model size.
Okay.
So, model size, maybe, you need to have a weightage, right?
When you combine with the prediction area from the classification tree.
So, this also, again, is a hyper parameter.
We need to determine this hyper parameter based on the performance, based on the performance
on the validation data.
But here, we don't have the concept of validation data, right?
But we still can determine this K value.
Okay.
But when we talk about K means classification, so normally this K, when you execute this
K means classification algorithm, this K need to be preset.
Preset.
Okay.
And, but actually, we have measured, so determine this value of K. So later, we will talk about
this.
Okay.
So, this is the K means classification.
So, what kind of a class, you know, problem, we are suited to WCSS criteria.
WCSS criteria, here, we assume there is a center vector.
There is a center vector.
This center vector is a good representative of all the samples within the cluster.
So, we have this concept, right?
So, if the data follows this kind of, or satisfies this kind of assumption, then actually, you
know, this matter will perform very well.
Okay.
Otherwise, actually, we are not performing very well.
So, here, now give some example.
Okay.
And this is known, we see that data distribution is like a sphere shape, right?
Like a ball, right?
This is data from here.
Like, the distribution of the data is like a sphere or like a ball.
Okay.
So, this kind of, then for each of the cluster, actually, we can find the center, right?
This center could be a good representative of all the samples in that group.
So, this is actually a scenario and well-suit, actually, the chemist's class, you know, all
good.
Okay.
But now, we have another scenario.
In this scenario, of course, the data here, right?
The data here, actually, like ball shape, right?
Sphere shape.
And of course, for this part of the data, the chemist's class organ should perform
well.
But if you look at the data here, this is like an S, right?
Like a ship of S, right?
It's all, this is actually irregular shape, not a sphere shape.
Okay.
And then, the chemist's class organ will not perform well.
So here, we assume there is a center vector.
This center vector is a good representative of all the samples within the cluster.
Okay.
And for this, I think for these two, actually, clusters, there will be no problem.
But for the data here, right?
For all the data here, you find, if you want to find the center vector, the center vector
may be here.
This is the position.
You get a mean vector, right?
The mean vector, maybe, you look at the, maybe the mean vector is just here.
So here, if this position, the point here, certainly, it is not a good representation
or representative of the sample in this cluster.
And then, we should know, you should not use the chemist's classroom.
Okay.
So here, we, although we have not talked about the details of the chemist's classroom, but
we have talked about the criterion, actually, that, you know, minimized, right?
So in this criterion, actually, we have assumed that this mean vector is the best representative
of all the samples within the cluster.
Okay.
So as long as this condition is satisfied, then we can use the chemist's classroom.
If this, like this scenario, right?
This scenario.
But if the data, actually, does not follow this assumption, right?
I do not satisfy this assumption.
And then, we should not actually use this chemist's classroom.
We should not use.
Okay.
So here, you know, we, based on the criterion, right?
WC, I said, within class, the sum of square distance.
Okay.
And, you know, we have talked about the advantage, disadvantage, and disadvantage.
And when this chemist's classroom can be used, and when it should not be used.
Okay.
So, next, actually, we have a brick after brick, actually, we talked about how this
tree, you know, chemist's classroom algorithm works.
Okay.
So, next, actually, we look at how this chemist's classroom algorithm actually operates.
And actually, the chemist's classroom algorithm consists of iteration of two main operations.
And the first operation is to assign the sample to the nearest cluster.
Okay.
Nearest cluster.
Nearest, that means the distance, right?
And to the cluster is the, nearest is the minimum.
Okay.
Actually, each sample, you know, could have a distance to all the clusters.
I mean, the cluster here means the center of the cluster, right?
From any sample to a center vector of a cluster, right?
Actually, we can have a distance.
Okay.
We will assign the sample to the nearest cluster.
So, this is one operation.
Okay.
So, after assignment of the samples into the clusters, and then we need to calculate the
new cluster.
And actually, we need to, you know, repeat these operations by many steps.
Okay.
So, this is the chemist's classroom algorithm.
And actually, the beginning, actually, we have no idea about the cluster, right?
So, we can randomly generate, okay?
We can randomly generate the cluster, and then, based on that, we can calculate the distance
from all the samples to the initial, the random, initial random generator, center vector,
right?
And then, we assign them to the corresponding clusters.
And then, we calculate the new, the cluster.
This cluster is not random generator.
It's based on the assignment, actually, of the samples to the different clusters.
Okay.
So, after we get a new cluster center, then, again, we will repeat our program, calculate
the distance from each of the samples to a new cluster center.
Then, we actually reassign, actually, the sample to different clusters.
Okay.
So, we will perform, actually, repeated operation of these two.
So, this is a procedure, right?
The first step, actually, we need to set the K to the number of clusters.
So, this K already is playing.
So, this is a hyperparameter.
Okay.
And so, later, we will talk about the method to determine this.
But in the K-means classification algorithm itself, this K must be preset.
Okay.
And in some scenarios, actually, now, this K depends on, I think, our requirement, right?
For example, if we want to select 2,000 customers from the millions of customers, and then,
you can just, actually, assume there are 2,000 clusters, and then, you assign the sample
to one of the 2,000 or 2,000 clusters, right?
So, finally, you send the, find the center vectors.
So, then, this number of clusters is determined by you, right?
You determine the number of clusters.
But sometimes, we need to determine to discover how many groups are underlying the data.
Okay.
Then, we need to spend effort to find the value of K. Okay.
So, here, we assume, actually, now, we assume this K value is known, is preset.
Okay.
Set the value.
And then, actually, we need to look at the first operation.
Okay.
And then, to care for, no, not, okay.
Then the step two, we need to generate the center vectors.
Because, actually, if you look at the two operations, right, the first one, assign the
sample to the nearest cluster.
So, if we don't have this, you know, step two, we run and generate some class centers.
And then, we don't have a basis, right?
We don't have a foundation to do the first operation.
Okay.
We don't have the center vector.
How to do the assignment?
Okay.
So, at the beginning, at the first step, the initial step, right?
Actually, this is no, center vector could be randomly generated.
Random generated by two ways.
First, actually, we can randomly, you know, actually, generate the center vector from
the samples.
You can randomly select some of the samples as the center vectors.
So, this is the initial center vectors, right?
We can randomly actually select samples.
Another is that, you know, in the range of the data, or in the space of the data, right?
And we randomly generate the center vectors.
We randomly generate, actually, the numerical vectors.
And then, randomly generate the numerical vectors.
In the future space, you know, I can't see that as the center vectors.
Okay.
So, then, two ways to do that.
So, we have the step two, and we have created the initial center vector.
And after that, actually, we will repeat these two operations, right?
The first operation.
I assign the sample to the nearest class test.
Okay.
So, these are all the samples, right?
And then, we randomly generate.
Okay.
So, these are the randomly generated, actually, point or data point, which we have been using
as the initial center vectors.
So, here, we assume that k equals two.
Right?
There are two clusters.
And then, we create the two, you know, generate the two random vectors.
And these random, two random vectors are just the initial center vectors.
Okay.
After this, actually, we calculate the distance.
For each of the sample, right?
For each of the sample, we can calculate the distance to the two, to the center vectors,
to the initial class centers.
Okay.
And then, we can compare the distance, right?
For example, after example, here, right?
And then, once I'm, we do this for every sample.
Okay.
For this sample, we can calculate the distance to this class center.
We can also calculate the distance to this class center.
And we find this distance is smaller, right?
And then, we will assign this sample to this cluster centered at this initial center.
Okay.
So, for each of the sample, we do this, we calculate the distance to the two cluster
centers.
And then, we assign the sample to the closest or to the nearest class centers.
Okay.
So, this is the result, actually.
After, actually, you know, okay.
So, assign to this result.
So, this is actually all the, you know, the sample here, right?
All the sample actually are closer to this one.
All the blue samples that we hear, sorry.
All the blue sample here, right?
Actually are closer to another center vector.
Okay.
So, this is the, you know, actually the assignment, the assignment or the sample to all the,
you know, to the cluster.
This is step three.
And then, you know, after that, we will, based on this new assignment to create a new center
vector.
Actually, the first step, the center vector, actually, is random generated.
But now, based on the assignment, you know, of the sample in each of the cluster, then
we create or generate a new center vector.
New center vector is just the mean vector for all the samples here, right?
For the red sample, you know, we get a random vector.
For all the blue samples, actually, we get a mean vector.
So, this is the new center vector.
Okay.
So, this new center vector certainly is much better than the initial center vector, which
are generated randomly, right?
You can see, indeed, they are closer to these samples and they are located around the center,
the central region of this, right, of all the sample in each of the cluster.
Okay.
So, after this, we will repeat this operation again.
For each of the samples, we will calculate this into the new cluster, the new cluster.
Okay.
Then we look at which one is smaller, then we assign this sample to the nearest cluster.
So, we will repeat this operation until, actually, the stopping criterion is satisfied.
The stopping criterion could be no change in the centroid, no change in the centroid.
Of course, in such a scenario, there is also no change in the assignment of the samples.
Okay.
So, then we can stop.
So, this is the final, you know, collection result.
Actually, now, from this example, as you can see, just through a few steps, right, and
then the sample actually can come to this, actually, in the center vector.
Indeed.
Okay.
And actually, if you program, if you do some real data, you can find it.
Maybe in most applications, maybe just like after 10 or 20 iterations, then the collection
process is completed, just about 10.
Right?
In this example, actually, just after one or two rounds, right, actually, we can get,
actually, very good collection results.
But in general, actually, when there will be no change in the class center, or if there
will be no change in the assignment of the sample to different classes, right, is the
sum of the sample to the cluster, and then we can stop.
Okay.
So, of course, I know this is just for visualization purpose, right?
In space, hard-enlarged space, you cannot see the data distribution.
But from this, actually, we should have confidence, right, to the chemist's classroom algorithm.
Even if we cannot see the data distribution, we believe or trust the algorithm, actually,
to find the center of the clusters, of all the samples in that cluster.
So, this is just a centroid of the cluster.
Actually, it is a mean vector.
Okay.
So, this is a chemist's classroom algorithm.
So, this is the most popular classroom algorithm, most popular.
Okay.
In any package, right, when you talk about the classroom, so, they always know that the
chemist is the first choice.
Okay.
It is the most popular method.
So, that is actually, I think, a very important issue, the determination of the care value,
right?
Chemist's classroom, this is care.
You assume we know this care when we actually perform chemist's classroom, right?
We assume we know this care.
But in practice, actually, normally, we don't know this care, right?
Then how to determine the super value of care?
Okay.
And actually, no, we can actually use the trauma and the error method.
Trauma and error, right?
Actually, we can set the care to different values, starting from one.
Even you can start from one, right?
K equals one.
That means, one, that means all the samples belong to one cluster, right?
Then the cluster is just the mean vector for all the samples.
Okay.
You can start from K, right?
And then, actually, we can, based on this center vector, we can evaluate, we can calculate
WCSS.
You remember, we see chemist's classroom trying to minimize WCSS within cluster sum of squared
distance, right?
Certainly we can use the WCSS to evaluate the classroom results, right?
So when we set K equals one, we can calculate the center vector and we can calculate WCSS.
And then we can actually set K to two.
We assume there are two clusters, right?
Then through the chemist's classroom, actually, we can get the classroom result.
We can get the centroid, and also we can get the assignment of the sample to each of the
two clusters.
Okay.
So based on this, we can calculate within cluster sum of squared distance, WCSS.
So this is for the WCSS, right?
Then you can set K to three, K to four, K to five.
So I don't know you have done all of these, right?
Then you can actually plot a curve.
This curve, actually, this curve, actually, for each of the K, we calculate the WCSS,
right?
Then we plot a curve of WCSS value against K values.
Okay.
So just this.
And actually, you can know the tree from here, right?
And previously, now we see, now we have like a hyper parameter, and actually we can determine
the value of hyper parameter based on the performance of the validation data.
Normally, we are training, we are validation, we are testing, right?
But in the classroom, we don't have the validation data.
We don't have the validation data.
Then how to determine the hyper parameter?
Actually, we use the training data.
Here we only have the data, training data, right?
We don't have the testing, we don't have validation.
Okay.
And for the training data, the more class that we use, the smaller WCSS.
You can imagine, right?
If each of the sample is, if the number of class are equal to the number of samples,
then each sample belongs to one class, right?
Then the center is just a sample itself.
The distance of the sample to the class center is zero.
Then WCSS is zero.
Okay.
So these are extremely key, right?
So you can imagine tree, the WCSS actually is decreasing with the increase in actually,
you know, the care value.
Okay.
Certainly, we cannot determine care based on the minimum WCSS.
We cannot determine care based on the minimum WCSS because when the care equal to the number
of samples, these value will be the minimum.
Okay.
Because it's on the training data, right?
On the training data.
Okay.
And actually, they have to determine super value.
Actually, we can use this so-called Able method.
Able, right?
So from here, right, just like this, the tree, the drop is very fast, right?
But after Able, this slope, just like this, right?
Significant drop at the beginning.
So after a certain point, critical point, actually, the decrease is slowed down.
So we can just based on that Able, right?
Just like this Able point.
Very fast, then very slow.
This point.
Three.
We can see that.
From here, you can see when a number of classes set to one, then the WCSS is around 8,000,
right?
So if we set class in the 2, 2, then the WCSS is nearly 3,000.
Okay.
So we increase the number of classes by one, then the reduction of the WCSS is nearly 5,000.
So this is a very significant reduction, right?
Then we continue to increase the class number from 2 to 3, then the WCSS is dropped to around
maybe like 800 or 900.
Okay.
Then we can see from 2 to 3, just one increment of the class number, right?
But the reduction of WCSS is from 3,000 to 800 over 2,000, this is a reduction, but just
at one class center.
But after 3, right, if you continue to increase the class center to 4, and then the reduction
is not significant, right?
From 800 probably to like 500, something like that.
The reduction is only like 500.
It's relatively small.
Okay.
So based on this so-called Able method, Able method, we can determine the suitable value
of k.
Okay.
And actually this Able method not just used here.
In many applications, if you want to determine the value of hyperparameter based on the training
data, always we can use this.
Okay.
And actually in classification, in regression, the larger the model, the more complex the
model, right?
Then the smaller the training area, smaller the training area.
So normally we don't use the training area to determine the value of hyperparameter.
We use the validation data, right?
But actually we can also use the training data to determine the hyperparameters.
But just similar to this, we use the Able method.
Able.
Okay.
So then after a certain point, drop is slow.
We'll just use that point.
Okay.
So this is the determination for the k values in the k-means class.
Able method.
So this point, the sharp point of the band of the plot, it can see that's the best value
of k.
Okay.
So this is the k-means classification.
Next, we talk about another second method, hierarchical classification.
Actually, as I explained before, actually, hierarchical classification produces the so-called
dendrogram.
The dendrogram, actually dendrogram, actually provides the visualization of the similarities
between the samples.
Okay.
Of course, in the original space, right, we can look at the distance between the samples.
We can look at the location of the samples in the space.
Then we can determine whether the two samples are similar or not.
Okay.
But actually, this space is low dimensional.
We can, right?
But if the space is higher than three, we cannot visualize the data distribution.
Then, of course, we cannot see the location of the data.
Again, we cannot see the similarity between the data.
But the dendrogram provides such a visualization.
Okay.
And for the distance between the samples.
So the hierarchical classification, and we already have seen this kind of tree-like structure,
right?
So this is the dendrogram.
And here we have a sample, ABCDEFGH, right?
And then, actually, we can see the combination of the samples.
Okay.
And B and C combination from one cluster.
And the CD combination from one cluster.
And then finally, ABCDE, actually join, join, right?
Actually, combine, actually, to form one cluster.
Okay.
So this is actually the hierarchical tree.
And actually, if you look at the tree, then we can interpret the tree from two different
perspectives.
The first perspective is from the division perspective, the top down.
Okay.
Actually, we can see the data from the very top, right?
The data is divided into two parts.
Just like classification tree.
Now, we have a rule node.
But here we don't have a rule node concept.
But here the data, right?
Actually, divided into two parts.
This part and this part.
Okay.
And then the data is further.
For the lab branch, right, the data in this subset, and then the data is further divided
into two subsets.
This is one subset.
And this isdu subset.
Then for each of the subset, the other two subset.
So this is, like, a, you know, like a, a division, right, a division of the whole data set into
two parts.
Then for each of the two parts, we divide them into two parts.
Then for each of the parts, we divide them into two parts.
Okay.
Finally, each sample corresponds to one cluster.
At the beginning of the order, this
have been onto one cluster.
We divide them into two clusters.
Then for each of the two clusters,
we divide them into two clusters.
OK, so this is a kind of a division.
From the full dataset, we divide them into,
to know, finally, we divide into n, actually, no, groups.
n here, in number of samples.
Each sample corresponds to one group.
So this is an interpretation of this dendrogram
from the division perspective.
Another perspective is from the group, the combination.
And that is the bottom up method.
From the bottom up, in the bottom up,
actually, each of the sample here is considered as one cluster.
And then we merge the clusters.
We merge, actually, the sample A and B merge together.
C and D merge together.
F and G merge together.
Finally, all the samples are merged into one single cluster.
So this is another perspective.
So based on these two perspectives,
and they have developed two different methods
for constructing such a hierarchical tree.
And so the first one, actually, I just
talk about the divisive algorithm.
So it's a top down.
Divide the data into two.
This is quite like the group of the classification tree,
the group of the tree.
And then the second method, I just
talk about is a generative algorithm, also known as bottom
up.
It's a combination, merging, the merge of two clusters.
Then another two clusters merge together.
So finally, all the samples merge into one single cluster.
So one is the divisive method.
It's a top down.
It's a divisive process.
Another is a generative method.
It's a bottom up.
It's a merging process, merge the clusters.
OK, so actually, in this code, we just
look at the generative algorithm,
which is the so-called bottom up method.
So if you have an interest, actually,
you can search on the internet about the divisive method
for hierarchical class.
And we look at this algorithm.
Actually, the algorithm actually started from,
OK, here we look at this example.
Through this example, I explained the procedure
of principles in this agglomerative algorithm
for hierarchical clustering.
And here we have six samples, S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6.
So we have six samples.
Each sample tree is denoted by four attribute, right?
a1, a2, a3, a4, a4 value.
In other words, each sample is a four dimensional vector.
And so how to combine them?
They're just the data.
How to combine them?
From here, you cannot see how to combine.
It's very hard to see how to combine.
But actually, in the agglomerative algorithm,
actually, the first step is to calculate the pairwise distance.
Pairwise.
That means sample number one, sample S1 to S2, S1 to S3,
S1 to S4, S1 to S6.
Then S2 to S3, S2.
So this is a pairwise distance.
So first, actually, we need to have such a similarity
matrix.
So a similarity matrix can see the pairwise similarity
between the samples.
And of course, the similarity measure
can be based on the Euclidean distance.
So here we use Euclidean distance.
In other words, actually, we calculate the Euclidean distance
between the samples.
Then we can have such a metric.
This is actually an S1, S2.
And actually, you can see that this is a metric, a 6 by 6,
because we have a 6 sample.
And we have 6.
It's a 6 by 6.
And this metric is symmetric because a distance from S1
to S2 is the same as a distance from S2 to S1.
So these are symmetric metrics.
And also, we know that all the elements on the metangular
are zeros.
Actually, all the elements mean the distance from sample
number one to number one itself, S2 to S2 itself.
I'll call the distance zero.
So the elements on the metangular
actually shows the distance from the sample to itself.
So this is the first step in the agglomerative algorithm
is to obtain such a promiscuity or similarity metrics.
And of course, we can use different metrics
for the similarity measure.
But here, we use Euclidean distance.
OK.
So this is a distance.
And I suppose you know how to calculate
the distance between the sample, Euclidean distance.
You know how to do that.
And then, actually, we need to start the merge process.
Actually, in the agglomerative algorithm,
at each step, we merge two more similar clusters.
And in the first step, at the beginning,
each sample is considered as a cluster.
Each sample is considered a cluster.
In other words, actually, in the first step,
we merge two more similar samples.
Because each sample is a cluster.
So actually, this is a special case.
So if you look at this, actually,
there's a distance between the sample and the sample.
Look at this, actually.
There's a distance of metrics or similarity metrics.
And you can find which distance, which value is the smallest.
And then, this distance, actually,
corresponds to two more similar samples.
So from here, you can just inspect the values, right?
Actually, two points something.
And then, we have one is 1.29 something.
Another is 1.288.
Actually, the 1.288 is the smallest value, right?
We exclude a zero line.
Because the zero just represents the distance
to the sample itself, right?
We don't need to know this point.
So 1.288 is the minimum value.
And actually, this is the distance between S5 and S6.
In other words, S5 and S6 are the most similar samples.
And then, in the first step, we merge these two samples.
Or these two clusters.
This is the first step.
OK.
So we merge these two.
S5, S6.
So because these samples, S5, S6, are more similar.
And after merging, we get a new cluster, right?
Initially, we have two clusters, S5, S6.
Although they are not two samples,
we can get two clusters, OK?
Special key.
Then we merge these two clusters to obtain new cluster.
We name the new cluster S5, S6.
So then we link them, right?
We just link the two, connect them.
But the height of this, right?
The height should be proportional to the distance.
Proponent to the distance.
So later, when you see, or the distance is small,
you know, or the two samples are quite similar.
If the distance isn't very big, then you
know the two samples are very, or two clusters
are very different.
OK.
So this actually, basically, this height
is measured between cluster distance, right?
Between cluster distance.
OK.
So this height should be proportional to the distance.
You just get 1.288, right?
S5, S. So after the merging of these two clusters, S5, S6,
we obtain actually five clusters, S1, S2, S3, S4,
and S5, S6.
We have five clusters.
OK.
And then we should repeat the process, right?
Among the five clusters, so which two clusters
are the most similar?
Then we should merge them, right?
Then how do you evaluate which cluster is the most similar?
Then we look at the distance.
The distance.
But then one issue comes, right?
If one sample to another sample,
we can easily calculate the distance.
But now you can imagine the cluster.
Even each cluster contains more than two samples,
more than one sample, right?
How to calculate the distance between two clusters?
That's an issue.
So after the first step, each cluster just
has one sample.
We don't have this issue.
But after the first step, actually, we
have one cluster that has two samples.
So how to calculate the distance from cluster S1 to cluster S5,
S6.
S5, S6 have two samples.
How to calculate the distance between these?
And actually, we have a different definition here.
And here, actually, we have the distance between two clusters,
right?
And here we have the so-called single linkage method.
Single linkage for the distance between two clusters.
Each cluster contains more than one sample.
So we look at this.
So there are two clusters, right?
Sphereship cluster.
Each of the cluster has multiple samples.
How to calculate the distance?
How to define this distance between the two clusters?
In the single linkage method, the two nearest samples
in the two cluster, right?
So these two samples are the nearest sample
in the two clusters, nearest between cluster, right?
Between cluster, not within cluster.
Between cluster, these are the two nearest samples.
Then this distance between these two nearest samples
is defined as the distance between these two clusters.
So this is a single linkage.
Single linkage.
Of course, actually, you can have a different definition,
right?
So that is the other kind of linkage.
But in the single linkage method,
the nearest samples is defined as the distance.
The distance between the two nearest samples
is defined as the distance between the two clusters.
OK.
So now if we go back to the original, right,
to the symmetric, now S5, S6 are one cluster.
If you think about distance from cluster S1 to cluster S5,
S6, S5, S6 contain two samples, right?
So we can see S1 to S5 distance is 3.263.
Distance from S1 to S6 is 2.651.
So certainly, S1, this sample, S6,
these are the two nearest samples in the two clusters.
Then this distance should be defined
as the distance between cluster S1 and cluster S5, S6.
This method is the single linkage method, right?
So based on the single linkage method,
the distance S1 to S5, S5, S6 is 2.651.
OK.
So this is the distance.
So now actually we see the single linkage, right?
So for example, we think about the S3 and S5, S6, right?
Actually, we look at the distance between S3 and S6, right?
Distance between S3 and S5, then we
look at the minimum value, right?
Minimum value.
So this is 3.111.
1.311 is considered the distance between the cluster S3
and the cluster S5, 6.
OK.
So the distance between two nearest samples
in the two clusters is defined as the distance
between clusters.
If this is a case, my single linkage is used.
Single linkage.
So besides this, actually, definition
of the distance between clusters,
we have another distance definition.
So this is called complete linkage.
Complete linkage is the furthest neighbor.
I think, yeah, so I think this looks at that, right?
So these are the sample in the two clusters.
And then we look at them between the two clusters.
Which two samples are the furthest, right?
So then this distance is considered
the distance between two clusters.
Just different measures, different measures.
Sometimes, actually, we are very conservative, right?
Or you say they are very similar.
No, I want to look at the nearest.
Sometimes, the furthest distance should be considered
the similar distance.
Right?
So yeah, sometimes you may evaluate something.
Maybe you say, OK, how about this student?
He's very good.
He's one of the course, he's known as like a hundred marks.
Sometimes, actually, you just based on his lowest result
to judge a student, right?
Although, no, this is not right.
We should not judge a person based on this, right?
But just this example, right?
So he's not that good.
He's called Jessica 16 marks.
You're based on the worst result to judge a person.
So this is just a different kind of method, right?
But they are all reasonable method.
So this is a method called complete linkage.
Complete linkage.
And then if a complete linkage is used,
then again, we look at the example S3, S5, S6, right?
Then we should look at the maximum distance.
And then the distance is 1.3165.
OK.
And then in the next week, when we talk about the evaluation
of the clusters, and basically the cluster evaluation
is also based on the concept, right?
Within cluster distance and between cluster distance.
OK.
But actually, we have a few evaluation metrics
for cluster evaluation.
And all the evaluation criteria is based on the concept,
like within cluster similarity, between cluster similarity.
And if we use the distance, how you
measure the between cluster distance?
Just like the same case, linkers,
the different kind of linkage.
We have different ways to evaluate the cluster
within cluster distance.
We also have different ways to evaluate the between cluster
distance.
And then we combine these two.
Then we can have a different metrics
for the evaluation of the cluster result.
OK.
So these are all reasonable, right?
We just have a different measure.
Different measures from different perspectives.
They are all reasonable measures.
They are all correct.
OK.
So here, this is the complete linkage.
And then, next actually, it's called the central linkage.
Central linkage.
So just now, we see, oh, you think by the distance, right?
So actually, we know the centroid actually
is a representative, right?
It's a representative of all the sample in each cluster.
So why not use the distance between the two centroid
as the distance of the between the two clusters?
Yes, I think that's reasonable, right?
So that is just the central linkage.
OK.
We use the distance between the two cluster centers.
So from this code, from here, you can also see there
is nothing to see.
Oh, these are correct.
Other, not correct.
We cannot see that, right?
We have just have different ways to evaluate, different ways
to describe.
All correct, right?
So these are all very reasonable, right?
You look at the distance between the two cluster centers.
OK.
So this is called central linkage.
Central linkage.
And then, it's such a scenario.
And then, after you do the cluster, right,
you merge the cluster, for example.
Then you need to look at the distance, the centroid
of each of the cluster.
Then, based on the centroid, you calculate the distance.
And for example, I'm doing here, and we have no S5, S6, right?
Then when the two clusters or two samples
are merged into one single cluster,
then what is the centroid?
Centroid is just the average of the two clusters, right?
Or the two samples.
Just the mean vector.
The summation of the two vector divided by 2,
then we can get this C S5, right?
So this is the central of the cluster, S5, S6.
And then, we can use the distance between S5 and S6.
Basically, I use this to.
So this is the transport.
I want to actually use this as a transport.
It's an inner product of the two vectors, right?
So these are just the inner product of the two vectors.
And then transport.
Then we have this metric, the distance between the two vectors.
So this is just a calculator, the distance
between the two vectors, right?
The inner product of the two vectors, right?
So this is the distance between the cluster S3 and S5,
6.
This is a central of this method, right?
We use the C S5, 6.
So this is the.
Then the next method is called the average linkage.
Every linkage.
What's the basic idea of the average linkage?
In the average linkage, right?
Actually, we specifically calculate the pairwise distance
from the.
We use this diagram, right?
For the sample in this cluster, we calculate the distance
from all the samples in another cluster, right?
We calculate the pairwise distance between the two
clusters, right?
Finally, we take the average.
So this average is used at distance between the two clusters.
So this is also a reasonable measure, right?
For the distance between the two clusters.
So this kind of method is called average linkage.
Every linkage.
So in the average linkage, and the average,
we calculate the pairwise distance between the sample
in the two cluster, right?
Then we take the average distance.
So the average distance is considered
the distance between the two clusters.
So this kind of linkage is called average linkage.
So in the above example, and actually the distance from S3
to S5, right?
Because in class S3, just one sample, right?
And the class 5, 6 has two samples.
So we have a pairwise of two pairs, right?
S3 to S5, S3 to S6, OK?
Then we have this distance.
Then we take the average of the two, right?
Summation divided by two.
This distance is defined as distance between these two
clusters.
So this is called the average linkage.
OK.
So we have different linkage methods.
And then actually, we have different metrics
to evaluate the similarity between actually the two
clusters.
OK.
So now, as you might say, the single linkage is used, right?
If a single linkage is used, then actually,
after merging, right?
After merging, we have five clusters.
And then we need to list these metrics,
similarity metrics.
This is the similarity between the five clusters.
And initially, it's the distance between the six clusters,
right?
Actually, it's between six samples, actually.
But now, it's the distance between the five clusters.
OK.
So from each of them, S1 to S2, right?
We have no change, right?
But S1 to S5, 6.
Because S1 to S5, 6 have two samples.
Then we, based on the single linkage method,
we look at the nearest sample, right?
Then we get the distance.
OK.
So we get these S5 by 5 metrics.
And then the next step, actually,
we need to identify which value is the minimum value, right?
That means these two clusters are more similar.
So from this, actually, a metric,
we can identify the minimum value is 1.28, right?
1.294.
1.290, actually.
1.290 is the minimum value, right?
Minimum value.
Actually, this is the distance between S4 and S1,
or S1 and S4.
So in the next step, actually, we
should merge these two clusters, S1, S4.
So every step, we merge the two clusters,
the two more similar clusters, right?
So from here, we identify, actually, S1, S4
have the minimum distance.
And then we should merge them.
And then we merge them and name the new cluster S1, 5 and S1, 4.
OK.
So then we have this.
You also sketch this dendrogram.
And actually, you look at the height, right?
So this height S1, 4 is certainly
no higher than the S5, 6.
So this means that the distance, actually,
between S1 and 4 is larger than distance between S5 and 6.
OK.
So you must draw this, actually, in a proportion
to the distance between the clusters.
OK.
So these are the two steps.
And then we have, actually, up to the four clusters, S1, 4,
S5, 6, and then S2, S3.
OK.
And then, actually, we need to perform another merging,
right?
Another run, actually.
This run should be merge the two more similar clusters.
Before that, certainly, we need to have these similarity
metrics, right?
And between the four clusters.
OK.
So this is the similarity metrics between the four
clusters.
And if the single link is used or complete link is used,
actually, you don't need to do calculation, right?
You just need to inspect which value is bigger, which
value is small, right?
Then you can get these metrics.
OK.
Because we don't need to carry the centroid.
We don't need to carry the average.
OK.
So now, we look at the similarity metrics
between the four clusters.
And then we see, actually, 1.3.
1.311 is the minimum value, right?
And actually, the 1.311 is the distance between S3 and S5,
6.
OK.
So the next step, we should merge S3 and S5, 6.
Because this distance is the minimum.
OK.
Then we merge.
S3 and S5, 6.
But the height here should be proportional to the distance.
The distance here, actually, is 1.311.
So we draw this.
And then we name the new cluster as 356.
OK.
So up this step, we have three clusters, right?
Again, we need to obtain the distance
metric for the three clusters.
S14, S2, and S356, the three clusters.
OK.
So this is the distance metric.
And then we look at the smallest value, right?
2.29.
So that's the distance between S14 and S356.
Then we should merge them.
OK.
So S14 and S356 are merged.
And after this step, actually, we just
have two clusters, right?
Certainly, we should merge them.
OK.
And here, we still need to get the distance metric.
Because we need to know the distance between S2 and S13456.
Because we need to know the height should be proportional
to the distance between the two clusters.
OK.
So after this, we still need to get this metric.
The distance metric is between the two clusters.
Actually, we know this is 2.327, right?
So then, actually, when we get the dendrogram,
the height should be proportional to this.
OK.
And finally, we have the result.
All the data points are merged into one single cluster.
So that is as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
So this is a new cluster.
So this is the process.
From bottom, right?
From each single sample.
Of course, each sample is considered as a cluster, right?
This sample is considered as a cluster.
Then we progressively merge two clusters at each step.
Finally, all the clusters are merged into one single cluster.
OK.
Then the whole process is completed.
So this is a hierarchical tree, right?
The agglomerative, actually, in the augurant.
And for the construction of this hierarchical tree,
classifying tree.
Sorry.
No, classifying tree, right?
The classifying tree.
And I already mentioned it, right?
So this tree, distance tree, give us a good indication,
visualization of the similarity between the samples.
No matter what the denominator of the sample,
even a high-demonar, we don't care.
Because here we just show the distance between them.
The distance between them is a scalar.
We don't need to show the original adrenal feature space.
We can still visualize the similarity between the samples.
OK.
So this diagram shows another scenario, right?
And the tree we see, S5, S6, S3, right?
So S5, S6, merge, right?
As then merge with sample 3, they have a cluster.
Then the distance between them is 1.4.
1.3.
This is a relatively small value, right?
And then another scenario, S1, S4,
is merged into one single cluster, right?
And then, OK.
So then when these two clusters are merged together,
you look at this, the distance, right?
Changed from 1.3 to 2.2.
This means that the cluster 3, S5, this cluster, and 1.4,
this cluster, are very different.
Because the distance is very big, right?
You can see it's very high, right?
They're very high.
This means that they are very different.
OK.
Very different, actually.
Then, actually, when you see when you merge them, right?
So this means that when we see the natural grouping, right?
From this diagram, roughly we can judge,
at least we see S1, S4, and S5, S6, S3 should not be one cluster.
Although in the hierarchical cluster,
we're finding all of them merged together, right?
But if you view from here, actually,
diagram, you can roughly judge how many clusters
underlying the data.
3, 5, 6, very similar.
We can put them into one cluster.
1.4, very similar.
Can put in the cluster, right?
OK.
And then, actually, 2 maybe can put into another cluster.
So this, actually, is a data diagram.
It shows a lot of information to us, right?
And actually, in my lab, actually,
we can use this function.
Actually, I don't require you to know my lab.
I just want to show you that it is not a software package,
right?
And we can use some of the functions
and to construct this hierarchical tree, right?
And so we use linkage, this function.
Then we have the data.
Then we have the single linkage or complete linkage
or we need to specify what linkage we use, right?
Because this will determine the distance between clusters.
And then the next distance.
What distance we should use?
City block, monobis, Kuna similarity,
all the, you know, the, the, the, the, including distance.
OK.
We also specify what distance we use, what linkage we use.
And then, actually, finally, then we
can have this kind of tree.
OK.
Then you can plot, right?
Dendrogram, this cluster.
You can just get this plot.
OK.
So this is the, you know, hierarchical tree,
hierarchical cluster.
Finally, we have one, actually, you know, the dendrogram,
which can, which shows, actually, the similarity
between the samples.
And also from this dendrogram, we can also roughly
judge how many natural groups are underlying the data.
Natural group means, actually, between groups,
between clusters, actually, that should be a big distance.
Within clusters, that should be a small distance.
OK.
So roughly, you know, give us such information, right?
About the natural groups underlying the data.
So this, actually, the hierarchical cluster,
I think, is very useful.
OK.
So, OK.
Yeah, this is a summary, right?
Summary of the hierarchical cluster.
And, yeah, I think, or this is plainly the precept, right?
Every step, actually, we should start from the, you know,
distance metric, right?
Then we identify the closest clusters.
OK.
Every step before merging, right,
we all need to have the distance metric between the clusters.
OK.
So, OK.
And finally, all of them are merged into one single one.
OK.
So this is a generative organ for hierarchical cluster.
So, necessarily, we have a break.
After break, we will actually talk about other two types
of cluster, distribution-based cluster,
and also the density-based cluster.
OK.
Right.
And next actually we look at the distribution-based cluster.
And so in this matter, actually, we assume the data tree
generated from different distributions, right.
And often, we assume, actually, each of the clusters correspond
to one Gaussian function.
function. And then overall, the data actually is from multiple Gaussian functions. Then
we can use the Gaussian-Mister model to model actually this function. This is actually the
data, right? So this is a division based on a cluster. Actually, we use the Gaussian-Mister
model. And actually, the basic idea of the Gaussian-Mister model is to, I think, to,
actually, this is the same as the other type of class-candino probability function using
one single Gaussian function. Actually, we try to actually, you know, maximize the likelihood
of having this kind of set data. And actually, we can have different, we can have multiple
actually Gaussian functions with different, actually, the center vector and the correction
matrix. And we want to find this value of the current matrix and also the center vector
of the Gaussian-Founder mean vector so that the data we have has the maximum likelihood.
Okay, so this is the basic idea of the, for the parameter estimation for the Gaussian-Mister
model. We maximize the likelihood of having this set of data. Okay. And, okay, so we have
the, and so then the data distribution, right, we assume it from multiple, actually, you
know, the normal function. And here, I mean the normal function, normal or Gaussian function.
And each Gaussian function has its own mean vector and the current matrix. Right? Okay.
So assume, totally, there are m Gaussian functions. Okay. And this m is also hyper parameter.
We don't know the m value, right? And actually, we assume there are m clusters. So this m
should be known, right? And each of the cluster, cluster to one Gaussian function. So we use
the m Gaussian functions to model actually the data distribution. Okay. So, and for each
of the cluster or each of the Gaussian function, we have a corresponding weight, alpha i. Okay.
So, so this is the, so this is the, you know, the Gaussian-Mister model. And so once this
model is aligned, right, once this model is aligned and we know, I do the mean vectors,
right? And then I treat them, these mean vectors are just the class centers, class centers,
right? Then based on the distance, then we can calculate the distance from each of the
sample to each of the, you know, the class center, right? Then finally we can determine
the class, the, the, the, the class, which class is the belongs to. Okay. So this is
the Gaussian-Mister model. And of course, actually, you know, to estimate the parameters,
actually the mu i, sigma i, and alpha i, I think it's quite challenging, right? Although
the principle here is to maximize the likelihood, but the process, I think, is not, is not a
trivial. And we need to use the expectation-maximization method, right? Expectation-maximization. Okay.
So in this expectation-maximization, you know, we need to actually perform two steps. One,
a step, we call that the expectation step, right? Another step, we call the expectation-maximization
step. So we wrote this argument called expectation-maximization method. So if you forgot that, then you
can go back and look back at our previous material on the Gaussian-Mister model, right?
But here I also treat, you know, maybe copy some of the slides, and then we look at this
again. Okay. So we set the number m. So this m must be preset, preset, right? Because
this m is just the number of class tests, because we assume each class that corresponds
to one Gaussian function. Okay. And then we need to set the initial values, right? Initial
values for the alpha i, and then, and also the sigma i, the, the, no, mu i. Mu i is the
mean vector, right? The sigma i is the current matrix. Okay. We need to give the initial
values. Okay. And then based on these initial values, okay, we estimate the, no, parameters,
right? The parameters like a gamma, you remember, right? A gamma, okay. And then, so the next
step, actually, based on the gamma element, then we can carry with the mean vectors and
the current matrix, even the alpha values. Okay. So we need to repeat this preset, right?
So, and here actually, you know, actually, you know, this actually is a preset stabilized,
stabilized, okay? And actually in the, in my lab, we have this function, a fit, fit gm
like Gaussian-Mister and DIST, this function, okay, to fit a Gaussian-Mister model. And
this function, right? So you can just actually use this function like this, fit gm, so we
are doing this, DIST, fit gm, DIST, data, then the number of clusters, right? So this is,
I think the, yeah, the main lab for us to solve this problem, right? You can, the other,
now package, probably you can use other functions actually to find the Gaussian-Mister model.
Okay. So once this Gaussian-Mister model is determined, then you can know the class
and test, right? You know the class and test. Okay. So, so these are the examples we have
used before, then we have 40 samples. So, so if we assume there are two clusters, right?
Then we use this function, F-R-T-G-M-D-I-S-T, right? So we are missing D-I-S-T. And then
actually we are, the result is this, the G-M-M actually, there are two components, right? Two
Gaussian components. And here the list actually, first actually give the alpha value, this
alpha value, the missing proportion, 0.49 something, right? 50% or half of that, right? So then this
is the mean vector, this is the mean vector, okay? And also for component number two, they
also give this, you know, the mean vector, the mean vector, right? This is the mean vector.
And also give the proportion, 50% something percent. Actually the two, no missing proportion
summation should be one, should be one. Okay. So like if you use two clusters, actually each
cluster has around 50%, 50% of the data, right? And so this is the case when M equals two.
So, and then this is the position of the two, Gaussian-Mission model. Indeed actually the
Gaussian-Mission model, indeed can find the center, the centroid of the two clusters. Okay.
So this is the cluster result actually, the center vector and for the two clusters, the
center vector, we assume M equal to two. And then actually for another scenario, right?
And so of course then we assign them to the closed-class center, right? Then the black,
or the blue or black sample to this cluster, or the red sample to this cluster. Okay.
And then if we assume M equal to two, right? Three. Because we have no idea whether or
not it should be two or two, three, right? Then we should also look at the three. And
then we have the three components and the proportion and also the data percentage, right? And also
the center vector, the centroid for each of the three Gaussian components. Okay. And then
if we sketch this, if we plot this, right? So these are not the class center. These are
class center. These are class center. The three class centers. Okay. So from here you can see
actually the, the, no, the two of the clusters we center are very, very close to each other,
right? And also actually one of the clusters.
One of the class actually, you know, two of the class actually have this actually like
very close to each other, right? And then they have the, one of them also covers small number
of samples. Actually if you see them, right, it's a, it's a 15, right? Yeah. 15 percent.
Okay. So then let's look at the density based method. And of course you practice, I think
it's very hard to determine the suitable value of m, right? But here again actually, you know,
after you get the m value, and then actually you put the sample to different clusters. So again
actually you can calculate the WCSS, right? The WCSS. And then again you can use actually
like the Able method, right? To determine the suitable value of m. But you can, some actually
previously, when we talk about the Gaussian feature model, how many m we should use actually,
some scenarios, the alpha value is very small. Just cover a few number of samples, right? A few
number, just a few, right? And, but sometimes actually, for example, in this scenario just now
it's 15 percent of the data is covered by that. So it's very hard to see, you know, we should
remove this cluster. We just have two, right? It's hard to see. Okay. So I think in practice the
determination of the number of clusters, I think this is a challenging issue. In particular,
there are no ground truths. There are no ground truths. There are no actually, you cannot
wither the data. Because it's hard to see, right? So it's very hard to see that. Okay. So it's quite
challenging actually. Okay. Okay. So, so let's actually look at the density based cluster.
Density based. Okay. Actually, you know, in the previous method like, you know, KMS
classroom and also the hierarchical classroom, we assume, you know, we have a center vector,
right? We have centers. And so this works very well. But for some scenario, either data like this,
actually two scenarios. One is an arbitrary shape, arbitrary shape, right? So even this, right,
this is actually arbitrary shape. Okay. We cannot, this is not a severe shape, right? So this is
actually not a severe shape. Okay. So arbitrary shape, irregular shape. Okay. And then actually
some scenario we have noise. We have noise like this. We have noise. Okay. And then actually,
this is all know, you know, input problem, right? Or bring problem to the KMS classroom. In the
KMS classroom, actually every sample is assigned to one cluster. And the cluster center is
average, the mean vector, right? So the noise that also actually contribute to the calculation
of the mean vector, right? So in other words, the mean vector will be affected by the noise.
Okay. So this means that if we have these two issues, then the KMS classroom, even hierarchical
classroom, will not work well, very well. Okay. Certainly for the Gaussian-Mister model,
it will know if we are not very well, very well, right? Actually, when we assume we can use a
distribution based method, we can assume they follow Gaussian distribution. Certainly Gaussian
distribution is a more like shape. Okay. So this actually, if we have such kind of
distribution, then the previous problem that we, you know, the method cannot solve this kind of
data well, right? So here, actually, now to address this problem, they have proposed a
so-called density-based method. Okay. So this is a very famous actually method called DBSCAN.
Okay. DBSCAN is a spatial classification of applications with noise. Then the short name is
DBSCAN. These are very famous algorithms. Okay. So this is now the density-based method.
And this DBSCAN algorithm actually can cluster the sample with arbitrary shape distribution,
just like the one I showed you, right? And also, it can handle the noise problem, the
auto-lias. Okay. And actually, okay, so here, actually, the DBSCAN algorithm has two main
parameters. One parameter actually is called M-I-N-P-T-S, the minimum points. Okay. And
actually, another tree is Epsilon. Okay. And actually, in the DBSCAN algorithm, they have the so-called
neighborhood. Okay. And Epsilon actually defines the neighborhood size. Okay. And for each sample,
now we can, of course, have a neighborhood, right? Based on the Epsilon, we can define, we can have a
neighborhood. Okay. And within the neighborhood of a sample, and if there are many samples, for
example, if the number of samples is, you see a certain value, a threshold value, for example, this value
called minimum point. And then this point actually could be called actually a core point. Okay. So if the
number of points within the neighborhood is less than a certain threshold value, and then it could be a
border point, or outline, yes. Okay. So this is actually just actually the three, the two parameters, the
neighborhood size, and also the number of points within the neighborhood. These two parameters determine the
three levels of data point, the core point. Okay. Even in the neighborhood, okay. And the number of
points, you see the minimum point, right? Then this point is called a core point. A core point. Okay. So I
just show you this. Okay. So here, actually, for example, this is one point. Okay. And based on the Epsilon, we
can define the neighborhood. So this is a neighborhood. You can just draw a circle, right? In a hard
amount of space, this could be a sphere, right? Okay. And then you can have a neighborhood. And then you
can call it a home sample within the neighborhood. Of course, in practice, you don't really need to draw this
neighborhood, right? You don't need to check actually how many samples, you know, have a distance less than the
Epsilon, right? Less than the Epsilon. Then you can find the home, you can find this, right? Whether this
point is a core point or not, right? For every point, actually, you can keep the distance to all other points,
other samples, right? Then you can find how many samples, you know, have a distance less than the threshold value Epsilon.
Okay. If this number of points, actually, is greater than these minimum points, then this is called a core point.
Okay. So this is a core point. Another thing is called a border point. Border point. And the border point is
actually a point which has a few minimum points within its neighborhood. Then this is called a border point.
Okay. And for example, and we have one here. Okay. And then you can draw on all the sphere. And then within the
neighborhood, only one sample. So then this point, actually, could be called a border point.
Okay. So based on the neighborhood and the number of samples within the neighborhood, and then we can define the
points as a core point or a border point. And then the type of point is called a noise autolyze.
A point which is not a core point or border point. And then it is called actually a noise.
Okay. For example, for this sample, right, for this point, each point is a sample, right? Actually, you can also, you know,
based on the Epsilon, you can find how many samples are within the neighborhood, defined by the Epsilon.
Even no point, right? Even no point within the neighborhood. Okay. And then it's not a core point, right?
It's not a core point, right? Then here, actually, these are autolyze. Okay. So that means, actually, this point is far away from other
points. Okay. A core point, actually, that means, actually, this part, actually, you know, is a, you know, is a, the data is densely, actually,
you know, disputed. Because within the neighborhood, there are a lot of points. Okay. So the border point, actually, also, actually,
maybe the density is not as high as actually, you know, this is actually that part, actually, that's a core point, but still have some number of
samples within the neighborhood. Okay. So this is actually the, you know, the three types of points. So next, actually, we have some other
tree, like a concept. Okay. So like, you know, a visibility of connectivity. Okay. So visibility, and here we have three types of
visibility. Directly, okay. Density, actually, reachable, and density reachable, and density connected. So these are the concepts in this
DPSN algorithm. Okay. So what is the directly density reachable? Okay. So we look at the scenario. Okay. A point, P, is a direct reachable,
density reachable from point Q. You P is within the neighborhood of the core point Q. Okay. So here Q is a core point, core point,
right? So that means within the neighborhood, the number of samples is greater than the minimum point. Okay. So if the number of
minimum points is five, right? So within the neighborhood, one, two, three, four, I think five, right? Greater than or equal, okay. So this is actually, so P, Q is
a neighborhood, is a core point, and P is within the neighborhood of Q. Then we see P is a, is a not directly density reachable from P, Q. So this is
a kind definition, right? So any point within the neighborhood of a core point is a density, directly density reachable from the core point.
Okay. So this is the, this is the, the, the, the, this concept, directly density reachable. Okay. So another type is called actually density reachable. We don't have it directly, right? So that
means actually the point, actually, if P is a density reachable from Q, if there are a set of a core points leading from Q to P, okay. So here we can see, okay. So Q here is a, is a core point, right?
Core point. And this P is not within the neighborhood of Q. Q here, the neighborhood is, you know, is just a circle here, right? So P is an outside circle. So P is not directly reachable from Q. Okay. But actually from here, actually, P is the
direct reachable from O. O is a center core point. Within the neighborhood, it has a very point, right? So P is directly reachable from O. Okay. And O is a direct reachable from Q. Then we see the Q, P is a reachable from Q.
Okay. So here actually, P and Q are linked, right? Reachable, reachable through two core points. One is P, Q, another is O. Okay. So P is the direct reachable from O. O is the direct reachable from Q. Then we see P is the reachable from Q. So this is a, you know, a concept about the reachability, density reachability.
Okay. So this is the second type of the relationship, right? Between those points. And then the next type is called density connected. Two points are called density connected. If there is a core point, then the both points are density reachable from the core points.
Density reachable, right? First, actually, the highest level is the directly density reachable within the neighborhood. But if through a few, through a few, you know, core point is a density reachable, you know, directly density reachable, right?
But now we have that, actually, concept, density connected. Okay. So if P and Q, right, and the two points are called density connected, right? If there is a core point, then the both points are density reachable from the core point. Okay. So from here, right, actually, we know that we have O here, right? We have O here. And actually, the, you know, this point is density reachable, direct reachable from Q.
And this Q is direct reachable from this point. So we see that Q is reachable from O. Q reachable from O, right? And similarly, and at this point, it's direct reachable from this point. P is reachable from O, right? So finally, we see our Q and P are actually density connected.
So your points, two points are density reachable from the core point. Then we see, yeah, connected, density connected. So these are the concepts that we're using in this, actually, the density base classroom, density, right? So actually, these are the different names that just say, on this part of the region, actually, the data actually densely distributed.
Okay. And some of the part of the data actually, actually, sparsely distributed. And then, you know, that means that there is a new cluster from there. Because from dense area to another dense area, there must be some region where the samples are sparsely distributed.
So sparsely distributed is just something like a boundary between the two clusters. Okay. So these are the concepts we're using in the dB scan algorithm. And so these actually, we talked about the parameter settings.
Okay. So here we have two parameters, right? One is the neighborhood size, the epsilon. Okay. Another is the number, the threshold, minimum number of points, right? Okay. So the mean number of points actually should be, normally, I think, should be at least actually the d plus 1, d is the denominator of the data, the denominator of the data, right?
Because each data, each sample is a vector, right? So how many elements in the vector? So this is the denominator of the data. Okay. So this d plus 1, the minimum should be at least d plus 1. And also, this number should be at least 3.
Okay. So at least in the region, there are three samples. Then we see this, actually, this part, actually, then we can determine the core point, right? Then we see, oh, this part, the data densely distributed. At least there's 3.
Okay. Normally, it should be d plus 1. Okay. d is the denominator of the data. d equal to 4 dimensions, right? Then this mean, I answer, be like, greater than or equal to 5. Okay. So this is the minimum point selection. And also, actually, in practice, the larger value, are you really better for data set with noise?
Noise. Right? Sometimes, actually, we have few points. And they are very close to each other. They are all noise, the otlias. Okay. So if this number is too small, right? Then we thought maybe like 3 or they thought they are, this sample, actually, there is a cluster there.
Okay. So to address this problem, so in practice, actually, we can adopt the rule of thumb. That is, d should be 2 times d. If d equal to 4, right? So now this is 2 times 4 should be 8, right? Then 5. Okay. So, actually, we increase the value of this minimum point.
Because in practice, the denominator normally is higher, right? And normally, we don't have the 2-dimensional data or 3-dimensional. We have much higher dimension. So we use 2 times d. This, actually, is the minimum point. This is just the rule of thumb, right?
Then we know, see, or we must use this value. So this is, give us a card line. Okay. We should use a value that is twice of the denominator. Okay. So this is for the M-R-N. And then another parameter is the neighborhood side, right? The neighborhood, the epsilon. Okay. And how to define m- epsilon? And actually, we can, here, we also use the so-called Able method.
The value for the, this, you know, the epsilon can be chosen by plotting the distance to the k nearest neighbors. Okay. So what's the meaning of that? Okay. And so, through the k, right? The k, minimum, actually, you can set this minimum value to different value, right?
And then for each of the sample, you can calculate the nearest, actually, you know, a k, you know, samples. Okay. Then you can look at the distance. Okay. For every sample, we have a nearest, you know, the distance, right? And then, for all the samples, we can take the average. So we can get the distance. This distance is the distance of one sample to the nearest k samples.
Okay. Then for each of these unknown k value or each of the M-R-N points, value, we can get one value. Then we increase this value. For example, M-R-N equals three, for example, right? Then k equals two. For each sample, we find the nearest two samples. Then we look at the distance, right? For each sample, we have this value. Then we take the average, for example, right? Okay. Then we find the value. And then the necessary, we can also increase the value.
M-R-N from two to three, from three to four. Then the k equals three, right? Then we select the top three, you know, nearest sample. Again, we calculate the distance. We can get one point. And finally, we can also sketch, plot, actually, the sketch plot, right? Actually, it's the distance against, actually, the minimum number of points, M-R-N points. Okay. Then you can also find, actually, some A-able, right? A-able point.
Decreasing, decreasing. Then after the center point, and the decreasing is very slow. Then we can determine the epsilon based on this value. Okay. This is actually the, yeah.
Okay. Okay. So this is actually the DBSCAN algorithm. And if the epsilon neighborhood of the data point contains a more than one minimum number of points, a new cluster, new cluster, right? So actually, in the precedent, actually, if the number of samples is less than one, so, certainly, this is a non-standard.
And this is not a core point, right? Certainly, this should not be a part of the cluster. This may be a noise or something like that. Okay. Or at least this is the end of another cluster. Okay. Then we should select another point. Then we will start the process. Start the process. Okay. So this is basically, I think, the DBSCAN algorithm. And maybe we can have a look of this.
Okay.
I think this shows the, you know, it's a DB scan classroom preset.
They are connected, right?
Because the density is on the neighborhood, reachable, and then, yeah, density connected,
then they, okay.
So at the end, actually, yeah, then they start from another point, okay.
They cannot connect extra, then they start from another point.
So finally, some of the point where we consider, no connected with others, maybe we consider
noise.
So this is a DB scan algorithm.
Yeah.
So these are all in the neighborhood at some point, right?
Then they all connect them together because they are density connected.
They are, they belong to the same cluster, okay.
Okay, then we have some noise, right?
So this is the DB scan algorithm.
And actually the, the, the, okay, so necessary we look at some advantage or disadvantage
of this method.
And if you run this experiment repeatedly, actually every time, actually, we will start
from a different initial point.
And then the issue with that, actually, we may get different, actually, classroom results.
So if we look at the procedure first, okay.
This is the procedure.
Step one, we set the value, right?
This is, you know, the hyper parameter, right?
We need to set the value for this to define the neighborhood size and also to define,
actually, these threshold values so that we can define which is a core point.
Okay.
And then, actually, we, we pick randomly, pick a data point as starting point, random
point, right?
Then we judge, actually, if this point is a core point, right?
And then we just, actually, you know, then connect to other.
So we find the recursion will always density connected point.
Okay.
And then we send them to the same cluster as the core point.
Of course, actually, if this point is a core point, right?
If the starting point is a core point, and then we just, you know, connect all the non-density
connected point.
And then we put them into one cluster.
So this cluster is a core point cluster.
Okay.
And some, actually, okay, so the next step, okay.
And then, actually, randomly choose another point among all the points.
And then, actually, we don't need to know being wasted in the previous step.
Actually, we, all of them is connected, right?
If it cannot be connected, okay, then this means this cluster, you know, for this cluster,
no, is completed.
And then we need to actually find another cluster, second cluster.
So something like at the beginning, we first find one cluster.
Then the second, in the next step, we find the second cluster, actually, progressively
find the cluster.
now, right?
We find the first cluster, then other clusters.
So random is chosen.
Another point among the points that
have not been visited in the previous step.
Then we repeat this process to find all the density connected
points and put them into one cluster.
So this process is finished.
All points are visited.
So those points that don't belong to any cluster
are considered as noise.
It's just an illustration now, right?
Some of the points are not actually assigned
to any of the cluster.
They are just considered as noise.
OK, so this is basically the DB scan algorithm.
I think the implementation of this is not that straightforward.
It's not that straightforward.
And every time, because the point is random, right?
And actually, you make a different result.
So this is actually one issue of this DB scan algorithm.
If you repeat, actually, many models,
actually, we have this problem.
Even for neural networks, actually,
if you start from a different point,
I find that the values you get are actually different.
Actually, the DB scan algorithm is the same.
So the advantage is that, actually,
so we don't need to present a number of clusters, right?
We don't need to present a number of clusters.
But the disadvantage is that we still
have some hyperparameters.
In the k-means, for example, we have a hyperparameter k, right?
But actually, in the Gordon-Mr. model, we have the number m.
But in here, we don't have this number,
but we have other hyperparameters.
So this also can be considered a disadvantage, actually.
So advantage is that we don't need to present a number of
clusters.
But a disadvantage is that, actually, we
need to set the epsilon value and also the minimum point
value.
Actually, this value is not that straightforward to set.
So this is an advantage to disadvantage, right?
And also, the DB scan algorithm, actually,
is robust for other areas.
So this is an advantage, a robust advantage,
because the algorithm that we use, the DB scan,
is particular to address two issues, right?
One is the noise, another is the irregular shape.
OK.
So I think that the Australian characteristic of the DB
scan algorithm, I think it's, first, actually, irregular shape.
And then the second, actually, the noise.
OK.
So yeah.
So I think that's all for the DB scan.
And these are all for the non-antibiotic linear.
And no, no, no, actually, the next week, actually, we still
have a few slides to talk about the evaluation of the classroom.
You have the algorithm.
You have the data.
Then you do the performance classroom.
You get the result.
But how about the validity of the classroom result?
So we have the evaluation.
OK.
So next week, we will talk about the metrics
for the evaluation of the classroom result.
And so on Saturday, we have the quiz starting from 11 to 12.
And already I've loaded the file.
And then you can check the file to see which room, which
lecture data you should go to take your quiz.
OK.
And so please be seated at least 10 minutes before 11.
And to the students, helpers, we'll
start to do the quiz paper from 10.15 or 10.45.
So please make sure you are there before 10.15.
OK.
The scope of the quiz already I mentioned in the announcement.
So I think you just follow those in the announcement
to prepare for the quiz.
We could have a description question.
We could have a calculation question.
But actually, I think one hour should
be sufficient to finish the questions.
OK.
And then on the next week, I think the next Tuesday class,
I think first I will finish the slides
for the evaluation of the classroom.
And then actually, I will have a revision of all the content
in the machine learning part.
OK.
So after that, actually, maybe you
can have a Q&A session.
So if you want to ask questions, please,
actually bring the laptop.
Maybe I can, like, you know, in the Zoom, right?
You can just type your question on the Zoom.
And then I can shoot a question on the board.
And then I'll answer your question.
OK.
So that's it for the next week.
Thank you.
Yeah.