.
Okay. Hello.
First week of school, right?
So how do you all feel?
All geared up, right?
You start the semester.
Okay.
First of all, let's...
Can you hear me from the back?
No?
The microphone.
Okay, this is probably as near as it's going to get.
Can you hear me?
Is that all right?
All the way to the back, can you hear?
You know, I ever had this experience.
You know, after I finished the class, somebody told me,
you know, all along I couldn't hear you, you know.
I say, oh gee, you know, thanks for telling me.
Right?
So I have to make sure you can hear me right at the end.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay.
Are you in the right class?
I hope so, right?
Okay.
So I'm pretty sure I'm in the right class.
So this is EE6407, right?
And my name is Lim, right?
I'm Prof Lim, Lim Ming-hyot.
I'm in the School of EEE.
So my office is stated there,
but you can connect with me to email, right?
Connecting by email doesn't guarantee an immediate reply.
Okay.
There will be times where I miss out your email.
So if you don't hear anything, drop me a gentle reminder.
Just say there, I send you an email, right, about such and such.
Did you have time to look at it?
You know, things like that.
Okay.
And I think you know why, because these days we tend to be
overwhelmed by emails, right?
So try and be understanding on that count.
So email is good.
I'll do my best to handle or manage the email.
So the title of this subject, this course, is
Genetic Algorithms and Machine Learnings, right?
Now before we go any further, it always makes sense to try
and understand, you know, in a very broad sense, the title.
So one of the questions that probably occurred to you would be,
okay, look, you know, there's this genetic algorithm here,
and then machine learning.
Is it really connected?
These days, recently, I attended this conference on Artificial Intelligence.
You can sense the euphoria of artificial intelligence.
There were so many people attending.
Everybody's talking about AI, what they can do, and so on.
Okay.
So really, when you think about AI, the term machine learning comes
into the mind.
It's all about learning, correct?
Now on that basis or on that denominator learning, right,
that's why you can link the two genetic algorithms into machine
as one of the methods of machine learning, right?
So there's no doubt that you can put GA as one of the methods in AI,
if you may, right?
So later on, as you understand the genetic algorithm mechanisms
a little bit more, then you begin to see, you know,
where the aspects of learning comes about.
GA is good, right?
But it's not good for everything.
Just like machine learning may not be good for everything, right?
So sometimes maybe we overdo it.
So same thing with GA also, right?
So as the term implies, you begin to wonder how did it come about?
The word genetic probably has some natural so-called association with nature,
and we will see why, you know, that is the case, right?
So you have the term genetic algorithm.
So it's good to have an understanding of the background,
how this comes about, and so on, right?
So certainly without any doubt, it's very closely linked.
It's just another method or approach.
It's not one of the two in your bag that allows you to solve different types of problems, okay?
So that is the basis of this course here.
I think it is reasonable to assume that you will be concerned about how your grades
is going to be determined, right?
And of course exam is part and parcel of the evaluation process.
So the final exam is a three-hour exam.
It constitutes 60% of the grade.
So because I take only three weeks, I will say roughly one quarter,
so I'll contribute one question.
I leave it to you to decide whether it's significant or not.
If you feel that 25% is not so significant, you can put less emphasis.
But nevertheless, that is what it is, 25%.
So one of the questions.
Now continuous assessment is also part of it.
So continuous assessment consists of usually homework assignment as well as quiz.
So for now, for this semester, I'm just going to do with quiz.
There won't be any homework assignment.
I'm not sure you see that as good or bad.
You may shout, hey, no homework.
So nice.
But don't be too comfortable, right?
No homework whatsoever.
Perhaps what it means is that you've got to use your own initiative to practice.
Go and look for questions or problems and discuss.
So there's no homework assignment, but this is a quiz.
So the quiz I will conduct because I have three weeks of lesson.
So I'll conduct on the third week.
So this is week one, and then next week, and then the final week.
So there's week three.
It will be around 15 minutes.
The venue, I will let you know where the venue is.
It won't be in this LT because there's a bigger group.
There's another group that needs to take the quiz or so.
Timing wise, it will be the second half of the lecture towards the last hour of the lecture.
Clear?
That's how we're going to do the assessment.
All right?
So let's go to the term, let's begin by talking about genetic algorithm or evolutionary computing.
So the term evolutionary computing, computing you know, computers.
Evolutionary, there are two meanings to it.
If you look within the context of nature, all right, then so-called evolutionary process in nature comes to mind.
For example, how species evolve with time, you know, how it adapts to environment.
So there is a meaning of so-called evolution.
Now the other angle of it, you can look at evolution in a very generic sense, right?
In a sense that for example, you know, I could say things like, oh gee, you know, I've known you since like 20 years ago.
Over the years I've seen, I'm amazed at how you evolve into a perfect gentleman.
So what that means is that it is so-called a gradual development or changes over time.
All right, so in that sense there are two angles as you can see the meaning of the word evolution.
All right, so when you put together evolutionary computing, all right, computing has to do with programs.
Okay, so basically when you link the two, all it means is that you're going to use a computer.
I'm meaning through your program, you're going to code it such that the approach will be somewhat synonymous
to how evolution happens, the process of evolution.
Okay, so when we talk about genetic algorithm, all right, so in future, you don't have to, if we talk, we say genetic algorithm,
we say evolutionary algorithm, evolutionary computing, we are basically talking about the same thing.
All right, later on I'll explain a little bit clearer why that is so.
So some of you may want to know or I have been asked a few times, is there a textbook?
So the textbook I use is, the textbook I use, let's just make sure I write it now.
Okay, I use the textbook, the title, introduction to evolutionary computing.
So this book is authored by Iben and Jim Smith.
Smith is a good friend, right, so I've asked him permission to say, gee, you know, I cannot get my students to buy any of this book.
He said it's perfectly all right, right, so the nice thing is that this is available online, right, you can download it and read it,
or you can go according to my lecture and try to understand the concepts, all right.
So the best is, hopefully through the lecture, it strikes a greater curiosity and you would read further from the textbook.
So it's available online, right, you go online, it is not something that I should freely send to you or anything like that.
Okay, let's talk about, let's begin, right, by going into trying to understand the big picture of what we are trying to do, right.
So all of you are engineers, you know, what do you do?
Basically you solve problems, right, whatever you do, be it a programmer, engineer, you're given a problem, you want to solve problems, right.
So is it wrong to say that what we are doing is actually problem solving, all right.
Okay, so if you're doing problem solving, it only makes sense to try and understand the nature of the problem, all right, and I'm going to do exactly that.
So let's take a big picture look at how, what the problems entails, right, okay.
So we will classify the problems according to these four different categories.
One is the back box modeling and then the other is a search problem and third one is optimization versus constraint satisfaction.
And the last one is an NP, NP stands for non-deterministic polynomial problems.
Okay, let's try and understand what all this means.
You have a system, right, a system that you can very easily or simply be modeled as such.
You have your input, you have your output, and then you have the model, all right.
So the model is an encapsulation of the technique, the approaches on how you derive the output from your input.
Okay, so essentially there are three components.
You have your input, the model, and the output.
So depending on these three, right, what are we solving for?
Are we looking for the input? Are we looking for the model? Are we looking for the output?
That's the basis we're going to use to so-called categorize accordingly.
So the first thing we can do is take away the input.
The model and the desired output is known.
You know what the model, you know the output.
What are you looking for? You're looking for the inputs.
Quite clear, okay, you're looking for the inputs.
So then we question, okay, what kind of problems falls into this category to illustrate what this means.
So some examples, the timetables.
Do you all have a timetable?
Timetable tells you what time, the time, and the class that you have.
So of course finally your timetable allows you to go through your whole program accordingly.
But what's the process of scheduling this timetable?
So you'll be looking for a set of the inputs that fits the criteria.
Design specifications, I have a certain specifications.
Give me the design that can fulfill this, satisfy these requirements or specifications.
TSB, the traveling salesman problem.
It's classical computer science problem.
That is known to be NP in nature.
So basically the traveling salesman problem, if you talk about N-city traveling salesman problem,
basically the problem can be formulated as such.
There are N number of cities and the salesman is supposed to visit each and every city once and only once.
Such that the distance is minimized.
Then you begin to think about it, you know, looks like a toy problem or too simple a problem.
But yet from a computational point of view, we still put it as a class that belongs to the NP problems.
And you understand later what NP means or the significance of NP.
And furthermore, this is a classical computer science problem.
We started it because many real world practical problems can be transformed or mapped into the traveling salesman problem.
Every day your logistics, the transportation logistics, very similar to the so-called the traveling salesman problem.
And many more examples.
And I will use the eight queens quite a lot in this subject.
So the eight queens problem, very easy to understand.
I can spend one minute tell you and then you know what the eight queens problem is.
So let's take a look at some of these examples and talk a little bit more about each one of these.
Okay. Optimization. Let's take a look at timetable, right?
University timetable, huge search space, right?
So what are the things that you're trying to search for?
What are the constraints or requirements?
What are the resources that you have? Let's begin my next.
The number of classrooms, all right, the physical venues. What else?
The time slots. You have limited number of time slots.
Correct? All right. And number of teachers, limited also.
Or a few other constraints, the few other so-called resources available.
So what do you understand by resources?
That's what you have, right? Okay. We optimize because we have limited resources.
If resources is enough, there's no worry. Okay.
So the way you optimize because there's resources is limited, right?
And therefore you want to make the most efficient use of the resources.
Okay. So you have all these resources, classrooms and so on, right?
Now, timetable must be good. Good is defined by a number of competing criteria, right?
And timetables must be feasible, right?
Let's ask ourselves, what is the meaning? How do you define a good timetable?
A timetable must be feasible, right?
Feasible means that it must be a workable timetable.
For example, you cannot have a timetable that makes you have two classes at the same time slot.
That is not feasible. It's a timetable, but it's not a feasible timetable.
Or you cannot assign the same lecturer to teach in two classes at the same time.
So quite clearly, right, you know what the meaning of feasible.
What about the different criteria?
So in order to understand this, you must distinguish between the hard and the soft criteria or constraints.
Hard constraints must be satisfied.
Hard constraints is what makes a timetable feasible or infeasible.
As long as this hard constraint is violated or not satisfied, it's not a feasible timetable.
Now, what about soft constraints?
As the name soft implies, soft is a constraint where you try to satisfy.
But if you cannot find it, you cannot satisfy it well, you can live it.
So there's a soft constraint.
For example, let's say I'm teaching.
If I'm assigning, let's say, six classes in a row, is doable?
All right, one after another, is doable.
But do you think that's a preference?
Definitely not.
So it would be a situation where if really have to, there's no other way out.
I have no choice, you know, that would be the timetable.
But to me, that's not a good timetable.
You see the difference between the hard and the soft constraints.
And also, I also know of, let's say, some colleagues who say, hey, can you put me all my classes on the same day?
Or at most two days, so that he doesn't have to, he can have the rest of the week to do his own work.
So of course, when the viewpoint is scheduling it or planning the timetable, you will try and accede to that request.
But if indeed, because of these constraints imposed, you cannot find a feasible solution,
then you've got to relax these constraints.
These are so-called soft constraints.
All right, so now my question is, OK, optimization means you have to define what is good, what is bad.
So how do you tell how good the timetable is?
Or how bad the timetable is?
Based on the two so-called constraints category I told you, hard constraints cannot, so-called not negotiable.
But it's a soft constraint.
For example, you can have hundreds of soft constraints.
A good timetable will be the one that so-called fulfill most of the other constraints, the soft constraints.
All right, so when you talk about optimization, the question is always, OK, how do you know this is good?
There must be some measure of goodness of how good that solution is.
So there's optimization.
So optimization of satellite structure.
So when you design a satellite, there are many infinite number of possibilities of the structure.
But because of the physics behind it, certain structures will give you better characteristics.
So one way is, of course, a human would design this structure and then test out how resistant it is to vibrations.
So that's how a human would do it.
Why not use a program to evolve it?
Use a genetic algorithm or evolutionary algorithm to evolve the design structures.
Since you understand the physics of it, you can formulate it.
You can model the vibration and then test out.
So which gives you the so-called the fitness.
The fitness, I see my arrow here, but it doesn't show here.
So you can see the fitness, which is according to its vibration resistance.
So that's quite clear.
You just evolve the structures and then you measure the fitness.
Now, what is so special about evolutionary algorithm or genetic algorithm?
What's so special about doing it this way?
Many people do not realize it's the creativity aspect, the evolutionary creativity.
Let me explain what this means.
When you design, normally what's your thought process?
You have the specifications.
So chances are you look back at what are the existing designs.
And then you will tweak or make modifications or use that as a reference to come up with another design.
So not wrong to say that it's likely to be our thought process, isn't it?
So if that's your thought process, do you foresee that whatever your design would just be a variation of what is existing?
Quite similar.
You understand my point?
Because that is what as a designer, that's your thought process.
So based on existing design, so you're going to change, you're going to modify, and then you come up with something new or different.
That fulfills the specifications or the requirements.
Correct?
So chances are your design won't be too different.
That will be quite similar in that sense.
So from an optimization viewpoint, you will be searching only along a small section of the possibility.
You'll be exploring only a small segment of the possibility.
But in your genetic algorithm, does it care what the structure is?
It doesn't really care.
It will just evolve the different structures.
It will just come out with different structures, and then all it cares about is fitness.
Is it good enough?
Is it vibration resistance?
So what this means is that from an optimization point of view, in your evolutionary algorithm, it's going to search a wider range of possibilities.
That is what we mean by creativity.
So to put it another way, evolutionary algorithm allows you to explore solutions that you otherwise would never have thought of.
That's the power of it.
So this can be optimization problem.
Okay, the egg-queen problem.
How can it be optimization problem?
Well, before that, let's understand the egg-queen problem.
Egg by egg chess board and egg queens.
If you play chess, for sure you will know what this means.
But if you don't play chess, it's not difficult to understand.
A queen is a piece that commands horizontal, vertical, and diagonal.
That's a queen.
So in this problem here, the challenge is to put the egg queens on the chess board without any conflict.
Conflict means two queens attacking each other.
For example, if you have two queens on the same row, there's a conflict.
If you have two queens on the same column, there's a conflict.
Or you have two queens on the same diagonal, there's also a conflict.
So it's not difficult to understand what the egg-queen problem is.
So two queens incomplete if they share the same row, column, or diagonal.
Can it be extended to an egg-queen problem? Definitely can.
So optimization means what?
To find the best solution. What is the best solution?
When you have zero conflicts, no queens mutually attacking.
So when you optimize, you have a certain figure of merit.
You understand the figure of merit? A measurement to say, oh, this is good, or this is better than this, and so on.
How do you measure?
According to the number of queens that are not in conflict.
So that will be the so-called how you will measure the goodness of the egg queens.
Is this configuration, are there any conflicts?
Any conflicts?
No conflicts?
No? Good.
Any conflict? Any conflict in this configuration?
Yes? No? No?
Anybody say yes? Yes? Good.
Two. Two means what? Two conflicts, right?
Can you see? Oh, I cannot.
Can you see the second queen here? This queen and this queen?
This queen, this column, and this column.
What are the so-called requirements? What does it mean to be in conflict?
Row, column, diagonal. Can you see?
So you understand what the so-called egg queens problem is.
To find a configuration where none of the queens are mutually attacking each other.
So if I give you another configuration and there are four queens that are mutually attacking,
so which one do you think would be better?
Of course this one. This one, there are only two queens.
So what I'm trying to say is that in optimization, we have to have a way to ascertain or distinguish the goodness of the solution.
That's optimization.
And I think if I say objective function, if you have done basic mathematics before, you understand what that means.
So you want to try one more because I'm going to use the egg queens problem a lot.
So it's good to get really, really familiar.
So that later when we formulate it, you'll understand what it means.
So are there any valid non-attacking configurations?
Meaning like zero queens attacking?
Spend a couple of minutes. Tell me.
Let me explain what this means.
I should explain.
Okay. So when you have
three, five, seven, one, six, four, two, eight, six, four, two, eight.
So this is for the first one. Three, five, seven, one, six.
So out of this six layout of egg queens, are there any that are non-attacking?
So the first one, have you working out?
First one, attacking.
First one is no good, right?
No good means they are queens attacking, right?
Okay.
First one good, no good.
No good.
Second one.
Okay, get used to it.
So get used to it.
If exam I give you 12 queens, you know, then it's going to be very easily.
Second one.
Okay.
So be good.
Is be good?
Good.
Okay.
So be, who says is good?
Good.
Okay.
No mutually attacking?
Okay, be is good, right?
So, okay, one more, then the rest I leave it to you to do on your own time.
C, C?
C no good.
Okay.
So what about D?
Maybe let's go through D.
D?
No.
Right?
So D is no good.
What about E?
No.
Okay.
What about F?
F, good.
No good.
Good.
F, good.
Okay, F is good.
Right?
So B and F is good.
Okay.
So what do I do, right?
If I were to ask you to formulate this, right, in terms of equations, how to know,
because chances are you probably have to draw out the configuration, right?
And then to see whether it's in conflict or not.
It's very, so there's another point you need to know.
It's very easy to see that a configuration is no good, correct?
If you see one poop in conflict, you already proven that this is no good, right?
To prove that this is a valid configuration, you have to check everyone, right?
Correct?
To prove that it's valid.
So if you have a thousand queens, you do it a thousand times, right?
So keep that thought in mind later when we, so-called, let's say you have a solution, right?
How do you prove or show that it is good?
Whether it's optimum or not optimum, okay?
So think about how you would formulate it, right, in terms of equation,
meaning that if I give you a string like that, right, you can go,
based on the equation or formulation, then you can check whether it is valid or not,
whether it's attacking or not.
I mean, you know, right, if you can formulate it, you can put it into an algorithm.
That's all the idea, okay?
I will show you next week after you've tried it.
Okay, let's talk about modeling.
Okay, so we look at optimization.
Now let's take a look at modeling, right?
So based on the black box, you have three entities, as we say, the input and then the output and the model, right?
So what if you know your, you have your input, you have your output, but the model is not known?
So this course is about machine learning, right?
So later on, I think Prof. Malgatso is going to tell you a lot about neural networks and so on.
So when you do training on your neural networks, right?
So your network consists of multiple layers.
What are you trying to solve when you do machine learning in your neural network?
You're trying to build or find the weights, the connection between the different neurons, right?
So normally in your training process, you will do it iteratively.
So you will iterate until you find a set of weights that correctly associate your output and the input.
So for example, when you do image recognition or character recognition, right?
You have a set of your training sample, could be you have your inputs, which are all the images of your characters, right?
And then you would have labeled them.
Okay, this image is A, this image is B and so on.
So based on this image here, you, you will iteratively, right?
So-called find the weights that can correct correctly associate between the inputs and outputs.
That's the basis of machine learning, right?
In neural network.
So if you think in this model here, all right?
So basically what you're doing is that when you find the weights, you're finding the model for that.
Typically that is what you do, okay?
So you do it iteratively.
Can you use a GA to do it?
Yes, you can.
So you can, modeling problems can be transformed into optimization problems.
You have all the different weights, which you normally in your deep neural network, you will iteratively train it, right?
Until you get a set of weights.
You can also optimize it.
I evolve the set of weights.
I will evolve the set of weights until there is a set of weights, right?
That very closely, right?
Model the inputs and outputs.
Okay, so we can also transform it into optimization problems or so.
Now.
So that's on machine learning.
Predicting stock exchange.
In your stock market, you have historical data.
We call it the valuation of the equity.
So you have this historical time series data.
Can I build a model?
According to this historical data, right?
To find a model, right?
That will closely predict, does approximation of the trend of the stock.
Same thing, right?
We're just looking for a model.
So that becomes a model for predicting the price of the stock.
In your smart homes, you have so-called your...
Let's say your IoT, right?
Or at home, let's say your voice control.
Can you train your device, your controller, to understand certain commands?
Then, likes on, you know, then the output will be associated to a so-called switching on,
a particular switch, and so on, right?
So basically, essentially what you're doing is finding a model.
All right?
Okay, another example of model is your so-called load, not load.
Loan, loan-applicant credibility.
Okay?
So when you want to get a load, all right?
The bank is taking a risk on you.
Okay?
So the bank would...
Ideally, the bank only want to loan you if they believe that you have so-called the capability to repay the loan.
All right?
So how do you evaluate, all right?
So in the old days, I remember when I go to the bank, right, to get a loan,
you literally have a bank officer to sit down and ask you a series of questions.
And based on the questions, according to how I answer or the profile, they will give a score.
All right?
So essentially what the loan officer has is a model, all right?
They have a model to so-called determine the credit-worthiness of the loan-applicant, all right?
Now, this is, of course, a lot of it can be done by machines.
All these can be automated, all right?
So by the same token, you can also use your event-based algorithm to come up with a model for this prediction.
So to come up with a model, all right?
So you will base your accuracy on the historical data of what happens based on the profile of the different loan applicants and so on.
All right?
So this will fall very nicely into a so-called black box model where we are trying to find the model.
So the third category on your black, according to the black box, would be the simulation.
So in simulation, you have a situation where you know the input, all right?
And then you know the model, but what you don't know is the output.
All right?
What you don't know is the output.
So this is very good, all right?
To answer in scenarios where you have that, to answer what if kind of a scenario, right?
For example, in economics and artificial life, all right?
So if you are a so-called a planner, right, you are in an economic planning unit, for example, all right?
So you change a certain policy.
Do you know what the result or the repercussion of this change in policy?
You don't know because you cannot test it out.
You cannot experiment it.
All right?
So what's the next best course?
You simulate it, all right?
You simulate it.
Or you want to do a prediction on the population growth, all right?
According to the so-called different parameters or policies or texts, your text policy or text regime and so on.
So you want to find out what the output is.
So you cannot actually test it out, all right?
So what do you do?
You use simulation to do it, okay?
So you are very applicable in evolutionary economics, artificial life, right?
Or in your weather forecast systems, all right?
And also the, let's say, impact analysis on the new text systems and so on.
Let's talk a little bit about the evolving artificial life, all right?
So this book by Epstein, it's a good book that talks a lot about this, right?
If you're interested, you can look into this.
So you can simulate trade, economic competition, all right?
And then to calibrate the models, okay?
So when you think about it, it would be a situation where you cannot actually test it out, right?
In many problems, you can't actually test it out, all right?
So therefore you rely on some kind of simulation model, all right, to predict what the output is.
And then from the output, you would use it to, so-called, to calibrate the parameters, okay?
So very useful, for example, to optimize strategies and policies and so on, all right?
And the other example you can talk about from a biological point of view, all right?
We know that incest prevention keeps evolution from rapid degeneration.
We all know this, all right?
Can we test it?
No, all right?
It's simulated.
What about multi-paran reproduction?
Multi-paran reproduction makes evolution more efficient.
Can never happen, all right?
So therefore the only request is to simulate, okay?
No picture to show on this.
Okay, so we are looking at the black box categorization.
Let's think in terms of the search problems, all right?
Let's look from the viewpoint of it being a search problem.
So you can see from our earlier discussion, simulation is very different from optimization and modeling, all right?
So in simulation, all right, we actually, as compared to optimization and modeling,
you can see the difference from what we have looked, talked about earlier on.
So optimization and modeling problems search through the huge search possibilities, all right?
So when we talk about the search possibilities, you are talking about a search space.
So search space is the so-called solution, the landscape, the possibilities that is available.
So this is a collection of all objects of interest, including the desired solution.
Now the question we want to ask is how big, how complex is the search space?
So how complex, how large is the search space?
So to be able to classify this problem, that helps us to decide what is a good tool,
the tools that we can use to solve this problem.
Okay, so understanding of the nature of the search space that we are talking about,
that will help us, or that provide us with so-called information on how to deal with the problem.
All right, in our categorization also, we have this optimization versus constraint satisfaction.
So far we have looked at, basically we mentioned about objective function.
So basically it is for us to assign a value or a figure of merit to reflect the quality on a scale.
So for example, in the n-quins problem, or a-quins problem,
so the objective function could be based on the number of unchecked queens.
From the examples that you have seen, if I ask you which layout or configuration is better,
so you can tell me which is better according to the number of queens that are not attacking each other.
That will be the goodness measure of the configuration.
So we can also think of the traveling salesman problem.
The objective function of the traveling salesman problem will be based on the tour length, the distance traveled.
So the length of a tour, visiting given set of cities, what is the objective?
We want to minimize the cost, which is the distance.
That is objective function.
You clear the objective function?
It is a function to measure the figure, the goodness of a solution.
Now on the other side of it, we have constraint.
Constraint is something that is a binary evaluation telling whether a given requirement holds or not.
It is something that you can answer yes, no.
Yes means it satisfies the constraint.
No means it doesn't satisfy.
So for example, in the eight queens problem, you are finding a configuration of eight queens on the chess board,
such that no two queens attack each other.
So if I give you two queens a position of it, you can answer me yes, they are attacking or no, they are not mutually attacking.
That is the implication or meaning of constraint.
In the traveling salesman problem, constraint, an example of a constraint is you want to find a tour
with minimal length where x is visited after city y.
It is just like you are a delivery truck, so you are doing a delivery.
So your solution must be such that you visit x after city y.
Then you ask why?
Why must it be the case?
Perhaps x is a more important customer.
So you have to make sure you visit x.
After that, you visit y.
So these are constraints that can be incorporated in a practical scenario.
So between your objective function and your constraint, we can put together a simple table.
So you have your constraints in red, yes, no, and then you have your objective function.
So based on these two categorizations of yes and no for the constraint and objective function, you have four possibilities.
The first one when you have yes for objective function and constraints, you have what we call constraint optimization problem.
C O P, objective function and then you have constraint.
Constraint optimization problem.
When you only have your constraints, the first row under constraints yes and then objective function no.
That is a CS constraint satisfaction problem, CST.
And the next one is free optimization problem.
So let's think about the eight queens problem.
How do you formulate it as constraint satisfaction problem?
How does it become a constraint satisfaction problem?
The eight queens problem.
Think about the six examples I gave you.
So out of the six examples, you pointed out two are valid.
So therefore only two solutions are feasible.
The rest are not acceptable.
Why are the two, I think it's B and F.
Why are B and F acceptable?
Because you satisfy all the constraints.
So there is a constraint satisfaction.
The rest of it are not admissible.
So what about free optimization problem?
How do you formulate the eight queens as a free optimization problem?
Remember your free optimization, you only have objective function.
There are no constraints.
How do you formulate it?
Or tell me or put to me the question is what am I trying to solve for?
Or how would it be formulated?
Any thoughts?
So when I ask you, when we are comparing the layout of the eight queens,
so I ask you is this better or is this better?
So you must have a way of measuring which is better, isn't it?
How do you measure?
The what?
Last queens, max queens not attacking, right?
So they are the maximum number of queens that is not attacking.
Correct?
So that becomes your objective function.
So you may not appreciate because it's only eight queens.
But what if it's a 2,000 queens?
So you run it as a free optimization problem.
All you want is that for your algorithm just give me the maximum.
Find a configuration that has the maximum number of queens that are not attacking.
All right.
Now what about the COP constraint optimization problem?
How do you formulate the eight queens?
Remember constraint optimization, you have constraints,
you also have objective function.
Phrase it to be such that it is COP constraint optimization.
Maximum?
So why is it a constraint optimization?
So the maximum number of queens, okay, you are right, right?
But the objective function, okay, maybe I should ask you this question.
How do you formulate the objective function?
Would it be based on the number of constraints that is fine?
In other words, the objective function tells you how good a solution is, right?
So if I ask you how good it is, you say this is eight.
The measurement of how good it is, the fineness of it is eight and so on.
How do you measure this eight?
It would be based on the number of queens.
Am I correct?
That are not attacking.
So inherently the objective function is part of the constraint.
Can you make it into a more clear-cut constraint optimization?
Come, give me an example.
Stay close together.
As close like based on the distance possible, right?
Like find me a configuration, a non-attacking configuration where the queens are near to each other, right?
Any other variations?
The number of configurations?
No queens attacking each other.
So that will be a measure for objective function, right?
The number of queens satisfied?
Uh-huh.
How many parts are satisfied?
That will also be the objective function, right?
How about if I tell you, okay, can you find me a configuration where the first queen must be in column three?
How about that?
All right?
Or you could use this to your advantage if you have a 2,000 queens, for example.
I'm going to fix half of it to a certain position.
Then when I solve it, I solve a smaller scale problem.
So there's a, in a way, there's constraint.
Okay?
You may not be very clear right now, but the last thing about the traveling salesman problem.
Traveling salesman problem.
How do we go about making it into a free optimization problem?
In the context of a traveling salesman problem, how is it a free optimization problem?
Remember, free optimization problem, only the objective function.
All right?
So, you have n number of cities, right?
Find me a tour sequence.
So just to be sure you know, you are clear about the traveling salesman.
So, for example, you have, right?
8 city, 3, 6, F, G, H, right?
So, a tour sequence could mean like, say, A, D, H, F, C, G, E, N, B.
That could be a tour sequence.
All right?
So what this means is this is A to D, and then D to H, and then H to F, F to C, and then C to G, and then B, and then B.
That will be the end.
But normally when we go back to the original point, just like in distribution, you have to go back to the headquarter, right?
So when it goes back to the original, we call it a closed circuit.
All right?
So it visits each and every node once and only once, and then goes back to the original starting point.
So the cost function will be the total distance that it has to travel.
All right?
Now, so I'm asking you, can you formulate this, or what would make it into a free optimization problem?
Minimize the cost, all right?
Minimize the distance.
Free optimization, all right?
Only 8 city, not difficult.
But what if it's a 10,000 city?
You may not know what's the best.
All right?
So my problem is just find me the best.
I don't know what's the best, all right?
But I just need a good solution.
So just find me the best.
Free optimization.
Okay?
How about your constraint optimization problem?
Find specific cities.
So, okay.
Like visiting a certain city first, like what we said, right?
X before Y, okay?
So very practical, right?
Because in logistics, quite common inside that.
So find me a minimum tour, all right?
Where city X or city D must be visited first before G.
And that's the constraint.
What about CSP?
Constraint satisfaction?
If you look at the table, only got constraints.
Don't care about minimum.
Don't care about minimum, all right?
I have a certain constraint, all right?
Maybe a certain sequence of constraints.
Just find me a solution, all right?
As long as it satisfies that constraint, it's a good solution.
So it's just like your traveling salesman problem, for example,
in your delivery truck, where you have a big truck,
you want to deliver 120 items, all right?
So the way you put the items in the truck,
what will be your consideration?
You know what's a truck, right?
So where you put things, you stack things in.
So the first one you come, the first one you want to deliver, all right?
Hopefully it will be at the end of the truck.
You don't want to go all the way to the back, you know, to dig it out.
So that means that there will be a certain so-called
the way you plan your traveling, okay?
You have to consider that, okay?
So this is how we categorize according to the optimization and constraints.
Okay.
So we have, so far, just classified the problems, all right?
We talked about the different types of problems, you know,
how we can actually approach or formulate it, all right?
So we haven't talked about the problem solvers, all right?
We didn't really consider the methods of how we're going to solve it, okay?
So in order to classify it, all right, according to the MP-ness of the problem,
so we need to know the properties of the problem solvers.
So MP stands for non-deterministic polynomial.
You all know what a polynomial is, right?
For example, if I tell you fn equal to n to the power of 48 plus 72n
to the power of 7 plus 1 million.
That's a polynomial, all right?
What's the polynomial?
Degree to the power of 48.
Then you say non-deterministic polynomial.
What does that mean?
Non-deterministic.
I don't really know this.
I don't know.
Then you ask me if you have a problem to solve, you ask me,
okay, how long is it going to solve?
If I know, I can tell you, yeah, this is the worst case, right?
According to n, all right?
The complexity of this is according to n.
But if it is an MP, non-deterministic polynomial,
and then you ask me, okay, how long is it going to solve this problem?
Well, gee, I don't know, all right, because it's non-deterministic.
I haven't found a polynomial algorithm.
So that's the class of types of problems that we are talking about.
Basically, what we want to do is to be able to know how difficult the problem is, right?
Now, this is very useful.
There are two classes of problems.
One is a discrete problem, and one is a continuous problem, right?
So the discrete problems, right, the solution is in discrete spaces.
For example, the traveling salesman problem, the way we have formulated it,
it is a discrete problem, right?
It's a discrete problem.
It is a discrete combinatorial problem.
We are basically finding out from the set of finite possibilities of combinations, right?
Like the n-queens problem.
So there is a discrete combinatorial problem.
The other type of problem is a continuous problem.
For example, you want to tune your PID controller, right?
You want to set, you want to determine so-called optimal parameters, right?
So that can be a continuous problem because you are finding a variable.
The values of the so-called parameters could be 0.2178, you know, or 1.766 and so on.
So it's all a continuous space.
So there's a continuous type of problem, right?
So you have so-called discrete as well as a continuous.
Now, the theory of NP-ness is very useful, particularly for discrete type of problem.
There are many examples of discrete problem.
The two we talk about would be the so-called n-queens and the traveling salesman problem.
Now, based on NP, we can have an understanding on how difficult the problem is
or how do we so-called characterize the complexity of the problem.
So in order to categorize it, we think about so-called the problem size.
So problem size is the dimensionality of the problem I can
and the number of different values of the problem variables.
In your 8-queens problem, what is the dimension?
8, right?
The n would be equal to 8.
If it's a thousand queen, thousand, the traveling salesman problem, right?
50 city, dimension would be 50, right?
And so on.
And then we consider the running time.
There's a number of operations the algorithm takes to terminate.
So what we want to know as far as the running time is concerned, running time is concerned, right?
The worst case is a function of the problem size, right?
There's a polynomial algorithm or not.
Ideally, if there's a polynomial algorithm, that problem is easy.
For example, if I ask you to do a sorting, what's so difficult?
At most, it's n squared.
That's definitely a polynomial algorithm, correct?
Or is it a super polynomial or is it an exponential?
So in your traveling salesman problem, what's the size or what's the number of possibilities of your traveling salesman problem?
If you are looking for the sequence.
If I give you 8 city, how many possible combinations?
Let's say you have an 8 city traveling salesman problem, right?
Can you say this is 8 factorial, right?
8 times 7, 1.
You have 50 city, 50 factorial, right?
Can you see the way it increased?
It's not linear, okay?
So that's one of the reasons why it's considered as intractable, right?
As the size of the so-called problem increases.
So we consider also the running time.
So normally in an algorithm, right?
When you look at an algorithm, you look for the steps.
Usually there's a part, the iteration part that gives on repeating, right?
So you look for the most so-called prominent or crucial step, right?
Where the repetition of the algorithm, for example, may be going through a trillion times, for example.
And the third point we want to, when we talk about emptiness, will be the problem reduction, right?
So transforming current problems onto another wire mapping.
There are many problems that are already known.
We already, we have good understanding of the problem.
For example, the traveling salesman problem.
Classical computer science problem, right?
We have good understanding of the traveling salesman problem, okay?
We study it because it is very relevant to many practical scenarios, right?
So when you're out there, for example, your boss asks you to solve a particular problem or formulate a particular problem, right?
So you have all these descriptions of what the requirements are and so on.
Now, if you are so-called a programmer or practitioner, right?
So very likely what you would do is that you will find maybe a relevant, well-studied or known problem.
So let's say the problem that you have, right?
You can map it into a traveling salesman problem or TSP.
Then you can apply the method and the approaches that you already know or you already have it, right?
And then to solve the problem, okay?
So in the theory of NpNAS, right, we look for such so-called such kind of problems, right?
So that's what we call the NP completeness, okay?
So, you know, we look at the categorization on how we categorize according to the NP characteristics, okay?
So let's take a break, right?
And then we come back before 8.30.
Does that all right?
Thank you.
Okay.
We are back.
So let's pick up from where we left off.
Okay.
We are into trying to classify or categorize the problems.
So we have looked at from the angle of the types of problems that we can deal with and
so on.
Now let's take a look at another angle.
That's the NP.
What does NP stand for?
What I just told you.
NP stands for?
Non-polynomial.
NP stands for non-deterministic polynomial.
All right?
You know what a polynomial is.
Okay.
Example, I give you n to the power of 17 plus n squared.
That's a polynomial.
All right?
Now, non-deterministic means you cannot fix a number to it.
Or you can put it in this way.
If you have a problem, then you categorize it as NP.
So what it means is that if you were to ask me how long it takes to solve this problem
or how much computational resources it takes to solve this problem, if it is polynomial,
I could tell you, okay, this is n to the power of 13, for example.
So it depends on n.
All right?
Or if it's non-deterministic, I say, gee, I don't really know.
You know?
It's non-deterministic.
Okay?
So what is the kind of problems or so-called types of problems that we want to deal with?
So accordingly, we consider the size of a problem, the running time, and so on.
Now, we also mentioned about two types.
That is the discrete problem and the continuous problem.
So this NP-ness is particularly useful for the discrete type of problem.
For example, as I said or said it many times, examples, the eight queens or the traveling salesman problem.
All right?
So what we want to know is the understanding in terms of complexity based on the dimensionality.
If it is a traveling salesman problem, how would it increase according to n?
All right?
So it's certainly not linear or polynomial.
So far, I don't think we have a polynomial algorithm to solve it yet.
You can find a polynomial algorithm to solve the simple so-called problem, like, for example,
to find the distance between two points.
All right?
That's a polynomial.
But to find the so-called shortest distance for the traveling salesman problem, it's certainly NP.
All right?
Again, I put it this way.
I cannot tell you.
All right?
Or I cannot give you a polynomial categorization of it.
So henceforth, we can categorize the problem according to these classes.
So the class P algorithm.
So accordingly, it's an algorithm can solve the problem in polynomial time.
All right?
So the worst case running time for problem size n is less than fn for some polynomial
formula.
So just to impress on you a little bit.
So this fn, all right?
It can be any polynomial, for example, n to the power of 136 plus 78, for example.
All right?
Is this deterministic?
Deterministic.
All right?
You might get scared, gee, it's 136.
But really what we want is from the viewpoint of problem solving, if we know, all right,
that is what is more important.
Because if I know this is the complexity, at least I can tell my boss, you know, it's
going to take us like 88 hours just to compute one solution.
All right?
That's all I can tell my boss.
Or I could plan my computational resources.
All right?
Now I know this is the complexity.
So I can farm it out to, let's say, 10,000 computing nodes to solve the problem.
All right?
Why?
Because I know.
I know.
All right?
If it is NP, well, I don't know.
Some problems, the worst case could be some polynomial which is unknown to me.
That's where the difficulty lies.
Okay?
So there's a class of problems that we talk about.
Now, so accordingly, if you look at the class P, you can solve the problem in polynomial
time.
For example, the solving problem.
All right?
N squared or n log n.
Very easy.
Okay?
Now, the other type is our class NP, non-detonistic polynomial.
Right?
Problem can be solved.
All right?
And any solution can be verified within polynomial time by some other algorithm.
So it's a class NP.
All right?
And I say it's the kind of problem that I don't know.
I don't have a so-called polynomial algorithm to solve it.
All right?
So we put them under the class NP, right?
If, all right, if I give you a solution, you can solve it within polynomial time.
That's a class NP.
All right?
So I'm not sure if you so-called appreciate the implication of this, right?
Now, normally when you solve, for example, if I give you a solution, all right, you come
up with the so-called a figure of merit or fitness.
Now, if you compare, for example, let's say in order to calculate the fitness, all I
need to do is I add 50 numbers.
All right?
So I just add, as compared to another algorithm or another problem where in order to find
the fitness, I have to multiply the 15 numbers.
Which one is more expensive?
Obviously the one that you do the multiplication.
All right?
Remember when you solve a problem, you do a so-called, you're in the process of solving
a problem.
You will probably do it a million times or billion times or trillion times.
So that can be quite serious.
All right?
So in the class NP, we say the solution can be verified in polynomial time.
So let me give you a hint.
For example, let's say in the traveling salesman problem, all right?
I give you a solution.
I give you a sequence.
Now I ask you, is this minimum?
Can you think about it?
Is this minimum?
Do you know it's minimum?
Okay, you prove that it's not minimum.
You can, but how?
Still the traveling salesman problem, you know what the traveling TSP is.
All right?
So the free optimizer, just try to find the so-called shortest distance and so on.
Now let's take this problem, say.
So now I give you this to a sequence.
Now my question is, is this minimum?
If it's minimum, can you prove it?
So you will prove it, how do you prove it?
You can only prove it as minimum if it tests out all the possibilities.
All right?
There it goes.
Is it polynomial time?
Most of the time you can tell it's not the minimum because you know I have a better solution
so you can discount it.
But there will be cases where you know you will have to so-called literally, right, test out all the possible combinations.
All right?
So that's why in optimization, there are many benchmarks that are created.
So they create this benchmark, the best known solution is such and such.
So if you solve it, if you get a better solution, then chances are your algorithm is better.
All right?
That's the purpose of so-called benchmarks.
So the hint I give you is that definitely your TSP is not your class NP, right?
Isn't it?
All right?
So class NP complete.
Problem belongs to class NP.
This part of NP, all right?
This is NP problem.
And any other problem in NP can be reduced to this problem by an algorithm running in polynomial time.
In other words, you are talking about mapping.
In the earlier slide, we talked about mapping, right?
So we already know some of these problems.
We categorize it quite well.
For example, you are traveling still soon.
Now, here you have somebody tells you or your boss tells you, okay, this is a problem I want you to solve.
Describe to you, like for example, it's a communication problem in communication.
So the boss tells you this, that, you know, all the different nodes, right, and so on, the configuration.
And of course, you can take the problem as it is and solve it and try and solve it, formulate it.
All right?
Saying that seems easy, but wouldn't it be easier if you can map this problem into some known problems that is already well categorized?
So you map it or transform it into another type of problem.
The advantage is very obvious because it is already well studied.
We are understood.
So you can use the approach and the algorithm to solve the problem.
All right?
That's what MP complete means.
You see?
It belongs to class MP, all right?
And any other problem in MP can be reduced to this problem by an algorithm running in polynomial time.
All right?
So that means that that process of reduction of mapping, you have to do it in polynomial time.
Which I think you can see why.
If it is not in polynomial time, it doesn't make sense to do the transformation or the mapping.
So there's your MP complete.
Now, the other type is your MP hard, MP hard problem.
So we say it's MP hard because problem is at least as hard as any other problem in MP complete.
Okay?
But solution cannot necessarily be verified within polynomial time.
And that's MP hard.
Solution cannot necessarily be verified within polynomial time.
You can general the solution, but to verify it, all right?
You may not have a, you may not necessarily have a polynomial time algorithm.
So there's your MP hard.
All right?
So with this basic understanding, we can put together a diagram to see how we can, the link between the different types of classes.
So you have two figures, one on the left, P not equal to MP.
And then on the right, P is equal to MP.
All right?
So let's talk about the P equal to MP.
Meaning we say P on the right-hand side.
So in computer size, all right?
It is, has been an open problem.
So basically if you look at this figure here, what it's saying is that if, given an MP problem, any MP problem, any problem you're known to be MP.
Now the challenge is, can you prove that there's a P algorithm that can solve this MP problem?
Just for one case, can you prove?
All right?
I repeat, this is an MP problem.
So the challenge is, it's a real challenge in computer science.
So the challenge is, can you find a P algorithm to solve this MP problem?
If you can prove it, right?
Then you win the prize.
There's an open prize for it.
Now so far, there isn't any.
Because if you have proven it, that there's, for this MP problem, if shown that there's a P algorithm to solve it, then you would have proven P equal to MP.
All right?
Or P can be equal to MP.
Then this would be the figure that you see.
This is how you would draw it.
P equal to MP.
I'm just proven it.
Okay?
But so far, there has been no proof.
All right?
You can't prove it, or you can't show it.
So therefore, what is more likely is this figure.
P is not equal to MP.
All right?
So we assume P is not equal to MP.
So therefore, the way we draw or how we categorize it, we have your P, right?
So under the broad MP here, there's one that is NP-hard.
NP-hard.
All right?
And which is why we study genetic algorithm.
Because many problems, right?
They're NP-hard.
And you really understood what it means to be NP, right?
And NP-hard.
Okay?
So that means that any deterministic or precise algorithm is unlikely to perform well.
For example, your branch and bound.
Or many of your classical methods, dynamic programming, linear programming, right?
Especially for discrete problem.
They are not likely to perform well in this kind of a problem.
Therefore, right?
What's the best alternative?
P is GA.
Your method heuristics.
You understand heuristics?
What is heuristics?
Heuristics are rule of thumb.
All right?
For example, if I go in the morning to Orchard Road to downtown, all right?
It should take me much longer than I go after 10 o'clock.
That's the rule of thumb, but it's not 100% true.
All right?
Okay?
But most of the time it's true.
That's what we use.
Those are precise heuristics.
So method heuristics, the term method heuristics refers to genetic algorithm, like other algorithms
like N-colony, right?
Or B, artificial B, whale optimization, gray wolf optimization, particle swarm.
All these are method heuristics.
So you can see that many of these algorithms are inspired by nature.
So they are inspired based on the metaphor in nature or examples that you see in nature.
Okay?
So that's why we so-called study, so-called genetic algorithm presents itself as a very
powerful tool to deal with this NP-hard problem.
Now, let me use this excerpt from a classical text on complexity by Gary and Johnson.
All right?
So in this book here, it says there's a, you have, so one day you will call into your
boss office, all right?
And your boss tells you that the company is going into a bandage snatch market.
So for this reason, we need a method to determine whether or not any given set of specifications
for a new bandage snatch component can be met, all right?
And if so, for constructing a design that meets them.
Now, because you are the chief algorithm designer, so therefore it's your task to do it.
Because you are optimistic, so you go into your boss office.
Okay.
You're very enthusiastic.
All right?
After consulting with the bandage snatch department to determine exactly what the problem is,
you rush back home to your office, take out all the reference books, all right, and try
to figure out, all right, because you believe or you're optimistic, there's a way you can
solve it, all right?
So you try a couple of weeks later, you're frustrated.
Say, heck, that's just cannot find, you know, an algorithm.
But then it's time to see your boss to update.
So what do you tell your boss?
Well, you can look at three possible scenarios, all right?
So you go into your boss office.
You know, I just cannot find an efficient algorithm.
All right?
I guess I'm just too dumb.
So the scenario number one, isn't it important?
I'm just too dumb, you know, all right?
So that's as good as telling your boss I'm not good enough so you should fire me.
Now think about it, is that so-called a good thing to do?
Probably not, all right?
Or another scenario, you walk into your boss office, all right?
You say, I can't find an efficient algorithm, all right?
I can't find an efficient algorithm because no such algorithm is possible.
Hmm, your boss say, okay, I see.
What does that mean?
Does that mean you're not good enough?
So I should fire you and find another person?
They can find me the algorithm?
It's better than before but not good enough, all right?
Now you are a learned individual, you understand about complexity.
So you confidently walk into your boss office and say, look, I can't find an efficient algorithm
but neither can all these famous people.
Hmm?
So it's like telling your boss you're not going to find anybody?
You can fire me but you're not going to be able to find anybody, all right?
Is that not better?
Okay?
That's because you understand, all right, about interactability.
What does it mean when you say a problem is intractable?
Okay?
So my point is that's why it's important to understand from a complexity point of view
the nature of the types of problems that you are dealing with.
All right?
So you hopefully you have some appreciation of why we use genetic algorithm, okay?
So let's try and understand a little bit how it came about.
So we are talking about evolutionary computing.
So I will first let's talk a little bit about the historical perspective.
All right?
So we look at a historical perspective, understand some of the background very briefly,
some general understanding of the precursor to genetic algorithm.
So of course you know by now that evolutionary computing is inspired based on the metaphor in nature.
All right?
Now from a biological perspective, there are actually two aspects of it that serves as
an inspiration for metaphorical inspiration for genetic algorithm.
One is from Darwinian evolution theory and the other is on genetics.
All right?
So if somebody asks you, okay, what's the background or how is it?
Just like neural network, you know, is based on the biological brain.
It's based on the neurons in the brain and how they are connected and the firing mechanism and so on.
So how we actually come to the neural network?
Well, it's all based on the biological brain, all right?
The inspiration of it.
So by the same token, genetic algorithm, Darwinian and then the genetics.
And finally we quickly look at the motivation for EC.
So in the early years, conceptually, there have been ideas to use evolution as a method of problem solving.
In 48, 62, 64, 65, right?
See as early as 48, you have the so-called the genetic or evolutionary search.
Your genetic algorithm can trace back to 1975 based on the work by John Holland.
And 1992, COSA introduced what we call the genetic programming.
Now I want you to look at the timeline.
So compare from 1948 to between 1948 and 1975, what is likely to be the different in terms of the, I say, the situation, you know, between 1948 and 1975 from computing point of view?
When did you get the first PC?
80s also?
So the point becomes very clear in those early days, right?
It was practically not implementable on computer yet.
So what this means is that these were concepts.
The concept, people have thought about the concepts of using so-called solving a problem using an evolutionary approach.
Okay?
So until 1975 and Holland introduced genetic algorithms, right?
And after that it became so popular, right?
So although you have this different categorization of evolution strategies, which uses kind of a mutation kind of operations to generate alternative solutions, you have evolutionary programming, right?
That solve a problem based on so-called finite state machine, right?
Formulating it as finite state machine, right?
And genetic algorithm, the first version of it is binary chromosomes, right?
Just evolving and then doing swapping and mutation.
And finally the COSA on genetic programming, they evolve programs, right?
Okay?
So these days we don't make distinction between this different approach.
So quite clearly you can see there are different evolutionary approach.
But nowadays we don't really make a distinction between this.
That's why your title is a genetic algorithm.
Basically what we mean is just evolutionary approach.
Okay?
Because most of the time no matter what method you use we call it genetic algorithm.
Alright?
So there's no need to be concerned about this different categorization.
Just call it genetic algorithm.
That's fine.
But you should understand that there are these different categorization.
So Darwinian.
The Darwinian evolution.
What's the so-called idea behind the Darwinian evolution?
Survival of the fittest.
Alright?
Why?
Why is there so-called evolution or adaptation?
Because of resources.
Finite resources.
As I said before we optimize because it's not enough.
Therefore you need to optimize.
Or we innovate because we want to improve on things or because they are limited resources.
So all environments has finite resources.
Okay?
Life forms have basic instinct.
Life cycles geared towards reproduction.
That means survival of the species.
It's about so-called ensuring the survival of the group or the species.
So the idea is that individuals that compete for resources most effectively have increased chance of reproduction.
To ensure survival.
So in nature of course we say survival of the fittest.
Meaning that individuals that has the highest capability to compete for the limited resources.
Then has a higher chance of reproduction.
So therefore in the fitness, when we talk about fitness in evolutionary algorithm.
So we always have this fitness measure.
Just like your objective function when you say how good a solution is.
So that is equivalent to fitness.
Fitness in natural evolution is derived secondary measure.
We humans assign a high fitness to individuals with many offspring.
In nature fitness means higher number of offspring.
In our algorithm it is about the goodness of the solution.
What defines the goodness depends on your problem.
If it's a traveling system problem the goodness of it is how short the distance is needed.
So it depends on the problem.
Also in the Darwinian evolution we talk about diversity.
So diversity means what?
Greater variation.
More diverse.
So in the real world there is an expression of individuals.
So that expression of the individuals is what we call the phenotypic traits.
For example in humans, black hair, long hair, no hair, blue eyes, brown eyes and so on.
So those are the phenotypic traits.
So it is partly determined by inheritance and partly by factors during development.
It is unique to each individual as a result of random changes.
So in Darwinian's theory what determines the traits?
It is the traits that will lead to higher chances of reproduction.
That is the natural evolution way.
And these traits can be inherited.
And in your genetic algorithm this is a form of learning.
Those are good ones you will inherit.
So quickly we talk about so-called individuals and the population.
So in the Darwinian evolution, when we talk about the survival of the fitters,
the word fitters means that you must have a way to distinguish which is fitter.
So because there is a basis of selection.
Selection for what?
Selection for reproduction.
Or accordingly for higher chances of reproduction.
So individuals becomes the units of selection.
And when we talk about evolution as a whole, population is a unit of evolution.
Selection is the individuals, but the evolution aspect is the population as a whole.
So one aspect of the inspiration is the Darwinian evolution.
Now the second aspect of the evolution is the genetics.
So putting it very simply, all our characteristic traits are encoded in what we call the DNA.
So the DNA is like the signature of how we look.
So the manifestation of the characteristic of the DNA would determine the phenotypic traits.
So the main point to make is that the genetic algorithms, the inspiration of it also comes from the genetics part.
So in your algorithm, you use concepts like chromosomes.
So you use concepts like chromosomes and genes and so on.
So you have your natural evolution that determines the evolution of the selection of the individuals
and then survival of the fitters and so on.
Because in the genetics, it provides a blueprint for how we can actually cope these problems
based on the inspiration of the so-called genetics.
So this is from the genetics part.
So genes are encoded in strands of DNA called chromosomes.
So most cells, there are two copies of each chromosome.
So that's called a diploidy.
Now the complete genetic material in an individual genotype is called a genome.
So when we talk about the genome, it's a complete genetic material.
So for every species, within a species, most of the genetic material is the same.
So basically two points here, from evolution standpoint, Darwinian evolution,
from the genetics, that becomes the so-called inspiration for our genetic algorithm.
And we also, from the genetics point, there is also the mutation.
So mutation, random change or unexpected change, you talk about virus mutation and so on,
I think that will give you an idea of what it means.
So in our genetic algorithm, we also have implement a mutation process.
So in the algorithm, mutation gives us the ability to vary the solution.
So when we vary, we increase the diversity.
So whenever diversity, we explore more possibilities of different solutions.
So I think from this, I think the evolutionary computation metaphor,
you can kind of have a picture of what really happens in nature,
how we have brought it into our algorithm we are in terms of problem solving.
So you know, a population of individuals exists in an environment with limited resources.
So as I said before, if resources is enough, there's no need to compete, because it's more than enough.
And also the competition, right?
Competition based on fitness.
And individuals act as seeds for generation of new individuals through recombination and mutation.
So through this information here, so when you search for a solution,
you are searching for different possibilities or different variations.
So likewise, we're going to use recombination and mutation to generate that kind of diversity.
So that is like exploring the different possibilities of the solution landscape.
So you can see that if you're able to put this into a program,
and you let the process run through this recombination and then mutation and regeneration and so on,
because you have selective selection pressure in there,
because you're going to select according to fitness.
Now if you do it over many, many iterations, what you foresee will happen to the overall fitness.
Very naturally, the fitness, the overall fitness would improve.
So therefore in your algorithm, you will keep on iterating it until the fitness level reaches a certain level that is acceptable to you.
That would mean that you have found a solution or it is a solution that is good enough.
That's the idea on how we solve it in algorithm.
So in EC, it's basically a generate and test.
A generate and test, unlike for example your branch and bound.
Your branch and bound you search, and then you know what is your current bound,
and then you search until you reach a state where you cannot improve any further,
and then you branch out to another path.
So that is more like a sequential search.
But here in EC, or evolutionary algorithm, it's generate and test.
Basically you just generate the different possibilities of solutions and then you test it.
And they are stochastic population base.
Stochastic means probabilistic.
You make decision based on some, for example, random or probabilistic approach.
Or another way to put it is that if you compare stochastic to deterministic in stochastic algorithm,
every time you run it, there's a possibility you will get a different answer.
Because you use a lot of random numbers. That's stochastic behavior.
And then in EC, we have our variation operators like your recombination and mutation.
That's to create a so-called diversity.
And selection reduces diversity and acts as a force pushing for quality.
So generally you see where we are coming from.
The motivation behind genetic algorithm or how it comes about.
So let's begin to look at the GA, or what is evolutionary algorithm.
So we're going to look at the scheme of an EA and the different components.
And look at some examples and then consider it from the point of global optimization and then the neighborhood search.
This is a very good figure that put very clearly or succinctly what the process involved in an evolutionary algorithm.
And if you can see or remember this figure here, that becomes a very important baseline for you to develop a holistic understanding of genetic algorithm.
Now there are three parts, the population and then the parents and the offspring.
So from an algorithm point of view, three parts. Population, parents and offspring.
So according to this diagram here, initially when you start, you initialize the population.
How do you initialize? Random? I don't know any better. Randomly generate a solution.
How many do you generate? Well you determine a population size.
If your population is 100, so you randomly generate 100 possible solutions.
So the population is like sampling. You have a whole solution space.
So if you have 100 individuals, you are basically sampling 100 different regions.
And population also gives you that so-called redundancy. It's like a strength in number. It's like a parallel search.
So in theory you have 100 parallel search tracks. Let's say your population is 100.
So you initialize your population. Then after that you select the parents.
You select the parents. So the word selection means that to choose, right?
To choose means you have a basis for choosing. How do you choose? According to the fitness.
According to the goodness of the solution. So you choose according to the fitness. How do you know the fitness?
You have an objective function. Which in GA normally we say the fitness function.
So you have your fitness function. Which is actually your objective function?
Like the traveling salesman problem, the fitness will be the length of the tour. So that will be the fitness.
So you choose the parents. So this pool of parents, you're going to create variation.
Remember diversity? You want to create variation. So how do you create variation? You use a recombination process.
Recombination involves one or more parents. Let's say you have two parents. You're going to do maybe a swapping.
You take one part from the first parent and then the second part from the second parent.
So the idea is that because you already selected, so the parents tend to be fitter. The good ones.
So what you have done is that you have chosen the fitter one. Give them higher chance of reproduction.
So essentially what you have done is that you're passing on good characteristics. Because you select, you recombine.
And your basis of your selection is based on fitness. So you have chosen it based on the fitness. So you're passing on good characteristics.
So that's recombination. And then you also introduce some kind of random perturbation. Mutation is random.
Why you want randomness? Well, again to create diversity.
So in GA, one of the clear things you must understand about GA is there are two main operations.
One is your recombination. The other is mutation. These are the two main.
And if you look at the so-called, the whole concept of GA, basically it involves these two mechanisms to create the variations in the individuals.
So after you create from the parents through this process, you create offspring.
So you create offspring. From the parents you have an offspring.
So this offspring, different. So now you have two pools. You have your parents and then you have a pool of offspring.
Based on the parents and the offspring, you're going to create a new population. That means that it's one generation.
So in one generation, you're going to create a new population.
Now if you think about this, through this thought process here, you can imagine if you do it iteratively many times,
over time the fitness of the pool of individuals would improve.
So quite clearly this process is very intuitive and logical.
So when you talk about GA, think of this figure, this picture.
And then from this figure here, we will use it to expand further of the different intricacies within each of the blocks.
So let me stop here and then we continue again next week.
Thank you.