Okay, good evening everyone. So we start class. Okay, so from this week, week four,
we are going to start the machine learning part. And as you know, your final result actually
consists of two parts. One is of course a final exam. And then another part is a continued
assessment. And as the other MSC courses, the continued assessment account for 14 percent.
So amount is 40 percent and 30 percent is the machine learning part. And actually this
30 percent actually contains three components. Actually one is the quiz. And the quiz should
be in the last week. So actually in the past normally I arranged the quiz in the last week.
I just steal the class time. But because of the very big cohort of this year, actually
I cannot book actually three big lecture theaters for us to take the quiz. So I can only book
the lecture theaters, big lecture theaters, not this side. Because actually when you take
the quiz, at least we should have one seat between two students. So this is the rule
of NTU. So I can only book very big ones like LT1, AIT2A. So actually these rooms are only
available on a weekend. Okay, so most likely we will take the quiz on the Saturday, not
open November. Okay, so this is the weekend of the week 12, not the last week. And so I
booked the room, the lecture theater, but actually it's a pending approval. So once
the time, I think normally I think it should be in the morning from maybe like 11 to 12
in the morning. And so once the venue and also the time is confirmed, actually I will
inform you. So besides this quiz 10 percent and we also have two assignments. Okay, so
these two assignments, each of them are countable 10 percent. And in this assignment actually
I'll give you some data sets, maybe one or two data sets. And then you try different
machine learning methods on this data set and then present the results in the submitted
report. And actually I will release actually the question for the assignment number one
week six. Okay, so after week seven, there is one recess week, so you have time to work
on this assignment. And but actually we need to submit the two assignments actually together
and actually by week 10. Okay, so these are the two assignments. So two assignments together
with the quiz, so 30 percent. And in the exam normally we have four questions. So one question
from the genetic algorithm part and then three questions from the machine learning part. Okay,
so these are the assignments. Okay, so before actually we look at the content we're going
to study. So probably we first have a look of some very popular concept in machine learning
or AI. Okay, so this AI machine learning neural networks deep learning actually are very popular
words, right? So many people actually use these words exchangeably. Okay, some probably thought
AI is machine learning machine AI, AI is deep learning neural networks AI. So they use these
words exchangeably. And actually each of these four words, four terms has its own actually
school. Okay, so before we look at the content we're going to study, we first have a clear
actually understanding about the school of each of these four concepts. Okay, first we look at the
AI and machine learning. What is AI? AI actually is a very broad term, very broad. Okay, any
techniques that mimic human behavior can be considered AI techniques. Okay, you can think
about your behavior, right? Your behavior, your actions in doing or in completing a certain task.
Okay, then you simulate this process and then develop a computer program to implement this
process. Then this technique actually is AI technique. Okay, so any technique that mimics human
behavior can be considered as AI technique. So these are very broad, right? Any technique. Of
course, we kind of mimic different organs of the human, right? And we kind of mimic humans
with a system. Okay, and then we can develop the so-called computer vision, right? And also we
have mimics human behavior in the language perception, natural language perception. So this
is the amount of the field and natural language perception. And we can also simulate mimics human
movement. And then we have developed the so-called autonomous vehicles, robotics. It's just
to give some examples of AI techniques. Okay, so it's very broad. Okay, any technique. Okay,
then what is a machine learning? And actually machine learning is a subfield of AI, subfield.
Okay, actually from this diagram, we can also see machine, AI, the big pie, right? So actually
machine learning is just a part of this pie. Okay, and so actually machine learning is a
subset of AI which enables machine to learn from experience. Actually this experience means data. In
other words, machine learning, of course, is AI technique, but it is a data-driven technique,
it's data-driven. So machine learning is a data-driven AI technique. Okay, so we learn from
data. If you look at the development of AI techniques from 1950s to 1970s, 1980s, actually
the dominant technique in the artificial intelligence is the rule-based system, okay, or express
system, or knowledge-driven system. Okay, so the AI techniques, or the AI systems are driven by
knowledge. Okay, so in the past, there is one occupation which is called knowledge engineer. Okay,
so knowledge engineer is responsible for acquiring knowledge from a dummy expert. Okay, so then
the summary of the knowledge from the dummy expert into rules, if they're rules. Okay, if this
certified condition, condition one is certified, and the condition two is certified, and then we have
this action. Okay, if condition three is certified, condition four is certified, then we have another
action. So it's a rule-based system, and this rule, actually the summarization of the knowledge
acquired from the dummy experts. Okay, but now actually from 1950s, 1980s until now, machine
learning is a dominant technique. Okay, machine learning is a data-driven. Okay, data-driven, of
course, actually we need data, right, in the past probably the data is small, but nowadays, you
know, we have big data, right, and also we have the, you know, CPU, GPU to process, you know, this
big data. Okay, so nowadays, actually, data-driven technique is a dominant AI technique. Okay, so
machine learning, okay, data-driven. And then data-driven, of course, actually, when we talk about
data, right, we think about the statistics, okay, so the statistical algorithm actually plays an
important role in the machine learning. Okay, and actually machine learning actually aims to not
develop algorithm, right, but this algorithm actually should be able to enable the machine to
learn from the data, from the data. Okay, so this is a machine learning technique, actually, so the
data-driven, right, previously we have a knowledge-driven. Of course, nowadays, actually, many
systems are hybrid systems. That means they both, they use both knowledge and the data. Okay, a
knowledge, actually, what is knowledge? Knowledge is a summarization, right, summarization of the
data. Now, we can have a lot of observations. Then, from the observations, the human can summarize
the knowledge. Okay, so in a sense, actually, the knowledge is a kind of condensed data, condensed
data, right? So in some applications, maybe the data you have is very limited and it's very hard to
acquire extra data. And then, of course, just based on the limited data and machine learning
performance could be bad, okay, could be unsatisfactory. Okay, so in such a scenario, actually,
if we have ways to acquire knowledge from the expert, and then we integrate the knowledge and
data in the system, okay, and then the performance, actually, could be better, right? At least the
system could perform, outperform the data treatments only. Okay, so many systems are hybrid systems
that integrate the knowledge and the data. Okay, so now that we look at machine learning,
neural network and deep learning. And so, machine learning, so what is machine learning, actually?
Later, we will see, actually, the central task of machine learning is to derive a model from the data.
This model could be like a mathematical equation. Okay, so my equation, what I'm
about equation, this equation could be linear equation, right? For example, we have a y equals
a1 x1 plus a2 x2 plus a0. So this is a linear equation, right? s1, s2 are the features.
Where is the target variable? We want to predict your salary, right? After your MSc study, your
first job salary, okay, depends on many factors, right? Could be your CGPA in this MSc program,
certainly, to influence your salary. Your undergraduate CGPA, certainly, could have an
impact on your salary. So, certainly, y is just a salary, right? x1 is just your MSc,
actually, CGPA. And then x2 is just your undergraduate CGPA. Okay, so we can fit such a model, right?
So this is a linear model. But in many applications, actually, we need to use a tree, nonlinear models.
Okay, nonlinear model, for example, y equals a1 x1 squared, okay? Because we have a squared term,
right? Then the model becomes nonlinear, plus a2 square root of x2. Square root is certainly
a nonlinear, okay? So these are nonlinear models, mathematical equation. And of course, for nonlinear
models, we can also adopt the so-called neural network, neural network, okay? And
neural network is kind of a model inspired by the principle or the function of the human
neural system, okay? And so it's a nonlinear model, okay? And in the past, the neural network normally
is a shallow structure. That means it just has a few layers. Normally, we have an input layer,
we have a hidden layer, we have one or two layers, just two layers, okay? And it has been
proved that two-layer neural network actually can transmit actually any nonlinear function, okay?
So this neural network actually is one technique, one nonlinear model, okay? So neural network is a
subfield of machine learning, right? So neural network is a subfield of machine learning.
Machine learning can have different models, linear, nonlinear, but neural network is just a subset
of nonlinear models, okay? So certainly, neural network is a subfield of machine learning, okay?
But nowadays, actually, when we are dealing with unstructured data, such as image,
videos, time series, natural language, okay? And we normally use the so-called deep neural networks.
We need to have many layers in the neural network, okay? So that is a deep neural network. And of
course, the learning of a deep neural network is just a deep learning, okay? So in other words,
actually, deep neural network is a subset of the neural network. Neural networks can be shallow,
can be deep, okay? But deep learning of a deep neural network is just one type of neural network,
right? So it's a subfield of neural network, okay? So this is not true the relationship between
machine learning and neural networks and deep learning, right? So, yeah, this relationship is
clearly illustrated in this diagram, okay? You can see the big pie, right? It's the AI,
and then a subfield of machine learning, and then a subfield of neural network,
and then we have a deep neural network and a deep learning, okay?
And then in this course, actually, we're not actually talking about the neural networks,
including shallow or deep neural networks, okay? We will talk about other models in the
machine learning, other issues in machine learning, okay? And actually, these issues actually
can help you understand, actually, they are fundamentals. So nowadays, actually, I notice
some students actually, they learn deep neural networks. Normally, deep neural networks are
very complex, right? Normally, you just call the function, use the lab words. Some students
even don't understand what is inside the neural network. And under such a scenario,
you can use it even in your deep neural networks, but you don't really understand them, okay? You
don't really understand machine learning, okay? I think machine learning is still the fundamentals,
okay? Actually, when we, in a traditional machine learning system, and we normally have two main
parts, okay? One is called feature extraction, okay? So, this part is also called a feature
engineering, right? So, based on our knowledge and based on some mathematical manipulation,
we extract features which are the characteristics of the input data, okay? And then the second part,
actually, is the, is the pattern classification, okay? Pattern classifier, okay? But in the deep
neural networks, so the two parts actually are combined together into one single model, okay?
So, certainly, if you actually understand, actually, if you have a, actually, a solid foundation
in machine learning, actually, when you look at the architecture of the deep neural networks,
actually, it's nothing, right? It's just a combination of the, of the feature extraction part
and the pattern classification part into one single model, right? It's not so mysterious, okay? So,
I still think the fundamentals of machine learning are the most important things, all right? If you
have this fundamental knowledge, actually, this actually will, you know, help you understand
the more advanced, actually, techniques like deep neural networks, okay? So, in this course,
actually, we will focus on other, actually, areas of machine learning, okay, rather than neural
networks and deep learning. So, neural networks and deep learning, actually, of course, actually,
are introduced in some other courses, right? And also, actually, in the next semester, actually,
I have actually a seven-series, you know, seven-dontary series course for,
which is neural network and deep learning. So, we will systematically introduce neural
networks, shallow neural networks, and also the deep neural networks, okay? In the,
7207 is normally offered in semester two, okay? Okay, so, after now, we have a basic understanding
about the main concept, AIM, machine learning, deep neural networks, and neural networks, right?
And also, the scope of this course, and different of this concept. So, now, we look at the contents
of the course. Okay, so, first, I think it's about introduction to machine learning. So,
that is the task of today. Okay, so, I have an introduction to machine learning, starting from
the human learning. And then, next week, actually, I talked about the data preparation for machine
learning. So, later, you will see, in machine learning system, there are three main parts,
data. Then, the second part is actually called abstraction. Okay, then the last part, actually,
is generalization. Okay, so, data, of course, is a very important part. Okay, so, how to prepare the
data for effective machine learning? Actually, we will be, actually, it's plowed in next week.
After we have this basic understanding, then we will look at the super-hard learning.
Okay, and so, later, we will look at this again, actually. Now, the machine learning can be, actually,
categorizing into three or two or three main categories. If two categories, then it's just
super-hard learning and unsuper-hard learning. So, now, the category is reinforcement learning.
Okay, so, this course, actually, we will focus on the super-hard learning and unsuper-hard learning.
In super-hard learning, we will study different techniques for pattern classification. Okay,
and the basic decision rule, actually, is a kind of a statistical-based approach for machine learning.
So, we make decisions based on probabilities. Okay, so, the central issue is how to estimate
the probabilities. The probability of one object belonging to a certain clock. You take a picture,
okay, then you estimate the probability that the picture belongs to a projector. Okay, and you
take the picture, you estimate the probability that the picture belongs to a computer. Okay, so,
we actually perform classification. We perform decision-making, actually, based on the probabilities.
Okay, so, this is the basic decision rule, and after that, we will look at linear
digital analysis. So, this is probably the most fundamental, actually, most classical,
actually, pattern classifier. Okay, it's still effective. It's still widely used nowadays,
linear digital analysis. Okay, very beautiful ideas, actually, in this, actually, in a method.
Okay, all these methods, actually, are carefully selected. Okay, and then another, actually,
one important, actually, method is called support-wide machines. And, actually, before deep
learning, actually, support-wide machine was the most popular recent field in the artificial
intelligence. Okay, so, of course, it was popular. Certainly, it has some merits. Okay, so, we actually
introduced these support-wide machines. And then, a decision-trade, decision-trade. A decision-trade
is kind of a classifier with a hierarchical tree structure. Okay, and it can be considered as a
summarization of the rules into a tree. Okay, and after that, we will look at the
denominator reduction and feature selection. Okay, and the other course is probably you also
look at the dimension reduction. But that denominator reduction, most likely, is the so-called
feature extraction. Okay, you produce some features, but these features have lost the
original meanings. Okay, but the feature selection, we will select a subset of the original variables.
Okay, so in this course, we will introduce feature selection rather than feature extraction
as a method for the denominator reduction. Okay, and then, now, it's an evaluation classification.
So, we can learn different classifiers based on the game and data. So, how about performance?
When we talk about performance, how to evaluate? Okay, so that's the evaluation
of classification. We will introduce different evaluation procedures and also different evaluation
metrics. And then, it's regression. And super-adventure, there are two main topics.
One is classification, another is regression. Okay, but the main topic is classification.
Okay, so we also will spend probably two or three hours on the regression issue and the
unsupervised learning. Okay, so after that, we will look at the unsupervised learning.
Actually, unsupervised learning also two main issues, actually. One is classification.
Classroom is a grouping of the data, another is association analysis. But we focus on
classification, the grouping of the data. And we will introduce actually a full, typical
classification method, central-based method, hierarchical-based method, and density-based
method, distribution-based method for grouping of the data. And after you have done the grouping,
so how about the results? How about the performance? So finally, it's the evaluation of the classification.
Okay, so these are the main contents, all fundamental issues in the machine learning.
And so now, actually, we talk about deep neural networks, deep learning. And some probably,
misunderstandings, deep learning, deep neural networks. Actually, the deep neural networks are
developed to address the classification of unstructured data, like image, like, you know,
videos, like natural language. Okay, if you are working at different domain, you are not handling
actually, you know, image, you are not handling actually, you know, the natural language. You just
handle actually the data, conventional data, storing the database. This actually,
conventional machine learning, actually, matter is sufficient. No need to adopt actually the so-called
deep neural networks or deep learning. Okay, not because they are popular, and then I will use that,
not for that reason, right? Actually, for a real neural problem, actually, normally we try our best
to find a simple solution that could solve the problem. Okay, so I think this actually is still
useful. Okay, this actually, like, I'll take some reference books. So nowadays, actually, we learn
knowledge, or we learn a skill, a technique, not bit from the test book. Instead, we look for material
from the web, right? So I think there's a lot of material on the Internet about machine learning,
right? So you can always, you know, if you can understand the lecture, right? So probably,
the way I introduce this concept is not good to you, right? You can read actually,
knows all material written by others, then probably, you know, that you feel easier to follow, right?
So if you have an issue with the lecture notes or lecture, right, you're always encouraged to
read material written by others on the Internet. Okay. Okay, so that's actually, today, right,
I focus on introduction to machine learning. But actually, before that, we first look at the human
learning. So what is human learning? Okay. Learning, right? We see machine learning or AI actually,
know, maybe human behavior, right? Machine learning, we use a machine computer to learn
from the data, right? So certainly, we should mimic humans' way of learning. Okay. So before that,
of course, actually, we should understand how human conduct learning, that is human learning, right?
So in cognitive science, learning is typically referred to as the process of gaining knowledge
from observations, gain knowledge from the observations. Okay. So this is learning,
this learning. And then many of you actually are international students, right? Singapore is
new to you, NTU is new to you. I believe actually, the first day, right, when you came to NTU campus,
you probably felt lost, right? And you cannot locate the lecture data. Okay. And
but actually, by observing the surroundings, right, by observing actually, you know, the NTU,
you know, the distribution, the location of different lecture data, observing the, actually,
the maps. And then you can find this, actually, finally, you can locate the lecture data. Okay.
Actually, we learn, we gain knowledge through observations, right, for our feelings, right?
When you just came to Singapore, look at the campus, or NTU campus, they're very clean, right? Very
beautiful. So gain knowledge about, through observation, you gain the knowledge about NTU campus.
Okay. So this is the difference in learning. And also another component of the learning,
then, with more learning, tasks can be performed more efficiently. The first time, I believe,
the first time in the first week, right, on Tuesday, I believe at that time, you are not,
we're not very familiar with NTU, right? And then probably you spend some time
and to find this lecture data, FT27. Okay. But actually, from the second week, and then the
week, fourth week, I think you have no issue, right, to locate this lecture data. This is because,
actually, you have learned, you have learned through the past year from the first week, okay.
And then you can solve this problem more efficiently. This problem just to locate the lecture data
FT27. This is just one example, right? Through learning, then we can solve problem more efficiently.
So this defines the learning. Okay. So gain knowledge from observations, okay. Through practice,
through experience, our performance improves. So this is defined as a learning. Okay. And actually,
the human learning can be categorized, graded into three types. Okay. So the first type of learning
is called learning directly and expert guidance. So this is, expert here is a very general concept.
Appearance, teachers, even your peers, actually, could be the expert, right? So learning directly
under the guidance of experts. So these are first types of learning. The second type is learning
guarded by knowledge, directly guarded by experts, guarded by knowledge, okay, learned from experts.
Okay. So this is a, in my high level learning, right, high level, okay. So this is the second
type. And then the third type is called actually a self-learning, learning by self or self-learning.
Okay. So that's actually, we're looking into each of these three types of learning, okay. Learning
and expert guidance. We all have the experience, right? Actually, when we were very young, we were a
baby, right? We learned from our parents, right? Actually, our parents actually, you know, told us,
right? This is an apple, right? This is your father, this is your mother, right? This is your uncle.
This is something else, right? So actually, we learned this directly from the parents, our parents
actually are the experts. Okay. So this is when we were very young, right? Actually, and then after
these, actually, then you go to primary school, right? Then we learn from our teachers, okay. So
our learning is directly guarded by our teachers, okay. Our teacher taught us actually, you know,
the words, right? Told us mathematics, okay. So we learned directly from them. Actually, now,
even though in the university, right, we learn, even in the MSc program, right, or PhD student in
this class, actually, you learn directly guarded by the expert. So I'm the expert in the machine
learning. I guide you to learn this course, okay. So you learn directly guarded by me, okay. So this
also belongs to this category, directly guarded by the expert. Actually, you may know when you are
well after graduation, you get a good job, right? You are in the company. So normally, you are assigned
a mentor, okay. And then the mentor will guide you, right? Tell you about cultures, tell you the
skills of communication, tell you the skills of them, and some technical things, technical skills,
okay. You again learn directly and the guidance, actually, of the expert,
okay. And actually, throughout our whole life, okay, we adopt this method. We learn
and the guidance of experts. You can imagine some old people, right, old people, very old,
80 years old, 90 years old, okay. So now, actually, you start from very young, right, you use a
smartphone, right, smartphone, actually. But for some old people, actually, they don't know how to
use that, right. They learn from their grandchildren. The grandchildren is a demi-expert, is their mentor,
right. So even we, the people are very old, we still learn under the guidance of demi-experts.
Okay. So this is the, I think the first, actually, top of the learning, okay. So at the different
stage, actually, we have, yeah, okay. Okay. Then the second type of learning is a gain,
actually, guided by knowledge, actually, gain from expert, by knowledge, okay. So this knowledge,
so actually indirectly guided by the expert, right, indirectly guided by the expert,
but directly guided by the knowledge. But the knowledge is gained from demi-experts.
Okay. Some, here I also list some examples, right, examples. And I think the thing here is very
important that the knowledge has been imparted by teacher or mentor. At some point of time,
in some other context, they don't directly tell you something. They don't directly tell something,
right. Actually, they, actually, you know, they just, but you have the knowledge, you have the
knowledge. Okay. So here there is one example. So, so there are some objects in different colors,
right. If the children, one child is given, actually, these are objects, objects, right.
Now some red objects, strawberry and apple, actually, the cup, right, red. And then also some
green objects like tree, watermelon, crocodile, and the frog, right. And actually, the child,
actually, can put them into two different groups. Although their parents have never
taught them this specific problem. But with the knowledge, okay, gain from their parents,
and the God by the knowledge. So what is this knowledge? Actually, certainly,
at some other time point, actually, the parent of the child, actually, told him about the color.
He told him about the red color, you know, orange color, yellow color, purple color,
blue, green, different colors, right. Certainly, he has this knowledge. He now,
he, the child, actually, performs this task, put the things into two different groups with
different colors, right. God is by the knowledge, by the knowledge of the color. So this specific
problem has never taught, actually, by the parents, okay. But he taught something else,
by the knowledge of the colors, okay. So certainly, here, this is a higher level
learning, right. High level learning. Okay. And you learn the knowledge, right. You learn knowledge
in this course, learn machine learning. And then you future, actually. So in this course,
actually, normally, I don't talk too much about applications, okay. And actually, if you have
a good understanding of this machine learning, then after graduation, or even during your
project dissertation, right, your application, you apply the knowledge to solve a specific
problem, okay. So this kind of learning is just the second type, right. I don't directly tell you
how to solve a specific problem. Instead, I give you the general knowledge, okay. But based on the
understanding of this knowledge, actually, you can solve a problem that has not been taught before.
Okay. So this belongs to the second type of learning, guided by the knowledge. So certainly,
you know, this is a higher level learning, right, than the first type.
Okay. So this is something like you apply the knowledge, right. And actually,
learning including, actually, learning including applying, right, application, or applying the
knowledge, okay. I think this is easy to understand. Right here, you're leading to the lecture,
my lecture, right. I give you an assignment, and then you give you an assignment, you work on the
assignment. That is process is also actually a process of applying knowledge of machine learning
to solve a specific panocletal problem. Okay. So this is also a learning process.
Okay. So actually, this is actually a type of learning is basically is that is to apply the
knowledge. Apply the knowledge is a part of the learning. Okay.
Okay.
And this is another example. Okay. And then actually,
know the, know the children, right, have this knowledge, maybe from the teachers
about the different norms. Okay. Like present norm, present norm, things norm, ideal, ideal, right.
And also some verbs, some words. She has this knowledge. Okay. Learn. Okay. And now, actually,
if the child is given some words like hospital, car, mother, right. And then actually, the child
can separate the run from other words. Because he has the knowledge, a run is a verb. The other
words like hospital, mother, and car, actually are norms. Okay. Although the parents have never
taught the, or the teacher has never taught the child to separate the run from other three words.
But with the knowledge taught before, actually, he can address this problem.
So this is another example. So, you know, the, of the second time learning. Okay.
Guarded by the knowledge, or applied the knowledge. Again, actually, at some point, right, before.
Okay. So this is, you know, I think the second time, right, the second time.
So that's actually look at the learning about ourselves, right. Actually, you know,
self-learning is also actually an important way of learning, right. And of course, actually, you know,
we learn, you know, from the, sometimes we see with self-learning, right. We learn, we read the
textbooks. I think, in essence, they not called self-learning. Because, actually, you learn,
as you guard by the expert, the expert is just a textbook. Okay. So self-learning here
means actually other type of learning, right. This is the kind of learning, like when we are,
very young, right. When we are baby, we learn to walk. Learn to walk, right. Of course, actually,
maybe the parents or teachers could give some knowledge to us, right. How to stand up and then
how to move forward, right. You know, to walk. We have some knowledge. Okay. But the child finally,
actually, through the self-learning, right. And then finally, he can walk. And this self-learning
also involves, you know, like success and failures. Okay. So this kind of learning is called
self-learning. We all have these experience, right. If you have, forgot this, right, because
at that time you were very young, right. Certainly, you will remember another example, right. For
example, if you learn to ride a bicycle, right. Actually, that, actually, not maybe, yeah. So,
maybe just 10 years ago, 15 years ago, you still remember this, right. And also, you know,
basically, parents or peers, right. Friends, okay. And maybe give us some knowledge. But finally,
through our own child, right. Try many tries, fail, and success. Give many tries. Finally,
we learn, we know how to ride a bicycle. This is also kind of, actually, self-learning. Okay.
So, not all things are taught by others, right. Others are like experts, right.
Test book is an expert. Okay. So, a lot of things need to learn only from mistakes made in the past.
Okay. So, this is a self-learning. And now, this, actually, this self-learning is also, I think,
the popular. And actually, this is, I think, the idea is similar to the, you know, reinforcement
learning. Reinforcement learning also, actually, through many tries. Okay. And then, you finally get
the, actually, optimal solution. Okay. So, okay. This is a self-learning. Okay. So, next, actually,
we look at what is machine learning. Okay. So, after, we have an understanding of human learning,
right. And then, we look at the machine learning. Machine learning from human, right. Because,
actually, machine learning or AI technique is a technique that mimics human behavior, right.
You can, you can have different behaviors, right. You can also have a behavior of learning. So,
machine learning actually learns the human's way of learning. Okay. So, sometimes, actually, when
you have a project or you have an assignment, right, you have a certain task to perform. And you
have no ideas how to solve that, right. And, at least, actually, you have no ideas how to develop
a machine learning system to implement. And then, actually, you can always, actually,
you know, think about how human are solved that problem. Okay. Sometimes, actually,
based on your intuition, right. And, I just, I, even you don't think about that. Okay. You don't
need to think about the whole process, but you can complete the process. You can complete the task,
okay. Very, very efficiently. But you need to think about, you need to decompose the whole process
in too many steps. You need to think about, so, at each step, actually, what specific task I have
conducted. Okay. And then, from this, you know, decomposition of the whole process,
now, we can learn the process, right. We can learn the details of how human solve this problem.
So, at least, I think this can give us inspiration to develop a machine learning algorithm,
right, to learn. Okay. So, machine learning, indeed, need to be inspired by the human learning.
Okay. And so, let's look at the machine learning. So, do machine learning learn,
so how do they learn? Okay. And, actually, this is a statement from a very famous professor in
machine learning from CMU. And, so, a computer program machine, right. Normally, I think we
see machine learning machine in the computer. And, my computer program is set to learn from its peers
if its performance improves with the NPRS. Okay. So, here, we see this, actually,
computer program aims to solve, actually, to perform certain tasks. This task is T,
with a certain performance measure P. Okay. So, if this performance measure P improves,
okay. And, with experience. And then, we can see, you know, this computer program lens.
So, basically, this gives a definition, right, of machine learning. So, what is machine learning?
A machine is set to learn. Okay. If its performance improves with the experience.
This is the same as, you know, the definition of human learning, right. Human learning, you know,
just now, actually, in one slide, actually, we have, you know, from the cognitive sense,
what is learning, right. And, we have one characteristic of human learning. That is,
our performance improves with more experience. So, here, for machine learning, also, actually,
the machine performance improves with more experience. But, of course, the experience here
means the data. So, where data is planted. With more data, with data, the performance improves.
Okay. If the machine can improve the performance by having more data, and then, we see the machine
lens from the data. Okay. So, this basically defines the machine learning, right.
Okay. So, this, so, here, the machine can be, can it be able to gain, get the experience,
get the experience, right. The experience here normally means data. The machine can get the data,
right. And, then, the performance improves in doing the similar tasks in the future, right.
And, actually, you know, the first time you come to this lecture theater, right,
at 2027 for the machine learning course, right, on week one, right. On week one, Tuesday,
and, certainly, actually, some probably have difficulty to find this room, this lecture
theater, right. But, with more experience, right, in the future. So, today, compared with the week
one, right, in the future, you can locate this room. The same task, locate the LT27,
the same type. But, now, you can actually address this task, right, or conduct this task
much more efficiently. This is because you have the experience, right. So, this is not
machine learning, this definition is, so, basically, the same as the definition for the human learning.
Okay. But, just, you know, the experience for human normally, you know, our own personal
experience normally. Of course, it can be experienced from others, right. But, machine
learning, this experience means data. Okay. So, the passive experience normally is the data,
okay. And, so, for example, you learn to play checkers, this is the experience of playing
checkers. So, no other experience, right. So, solve this problem, our data, or our experience,
of solving the same problem. Okay. To locate the lecture theater of 27. Okay. In the first week,
now, in the week four, the same task to locate the lecture theater of 27. Okay. And, you have
the experience in the last three weeks. All right. So, certainly, today, you can conduct this task
more efficiently because of the passive experience in the past three weeks. Okay. And, in image
classification, this could be a task, right. The experience is represented in the past data
with images, having labels. Okay. If you are required to, you know, if the machine is asked to
perform a certain task, like image classification, it takes a lot of pictures, right. Then, based on
the picture and the features and the language of the picture, we want to perform classification
to see, oh, this object, I did learn to, like a projector. And, this picture is about
chair. This picture is about person. Okay. So, this passive experience means the data.
Of course, the data can be acquired by you or by someone else. Okay. So, the experience can be
your own experience, can also learn from others' experience, right. Can also learn from the data
collected by others. Okay. So, basically, you know, these are the machine learning, right. Actually,
from the machine learning, so, where the machine learns, actually, from here, we have machine
learns, we have this definition, right. Performing improves if we have more data. Then, we see the
machine learns. This is the same as the human learning. Okay. And, of course, actually, you know,
in this experience, in machine learning, means the data. Okay. So, data, that's also, you know,
in the beginning of the class, we review the different concepts, right. Machine learning
is a data driven, right. So, here, machine learning is an experimental driven, right.
A data driven, right. We need to use data. Okay. So, I think now, it's 720. So, we have a short break.
10 minutes break.
Okay.
Okay. Actually, the basic machine learning process can be divided into three parts. Okay. And,
the first part is the input data. Okay. Actually, we know machine learning is a data driven,
right. So, certainly, you know, data is a very important part of the machine learning. Okay.
So, this data could suggest a past data, right. And, of course, this data now could be later,
we will see, could be labeled or could be unlabeled. And then, based on the data, the label,
unlabeled data, we can perform different kind of learning. Okay. So, this is the input data.
And, the first part of the machine learning process. And, then the second part is the abstraction.
So, abstraction, the input data is represented in a broader way through the underlying algorithm.
So, this is called abstraction. Okay. And then, the last one is the generalization.
Generalization basically is to apply. Okay. You have applied, you have get them, you have
a lane, right. The knowledge in the abstraction part. And then, in the generalization part,
you apply the knowledge, okay, for future data. Okay. So, this is the generalization.
And, actually, the data is a very important part. And, in the past, normally, this data is very
specific, right. It's not specific. Now, we are, we are asked to solve a problem. And then,
now, this, for that particular problem, specific problem, we need to collect data.
Okay. And, we need to collect the data. And, we also need to label the data. Okay. For example,
if you want to build a computer system, right, to classify anything in NTU campus,
right. So, this is our task. And then, for this task, and then, we need to collect data. And,
we need to take pictures of all objects, right, different objects in NTU campus, right. And,
then, after taking pictures, we also need to label the picture. Oh, this picture shows a classroom.
This picture shows a canteen. This picture shows, actually, you know, the,
the student hall. Okay. So, we show, you know, we take pictures of different objects. And,
also, we label this object. Okay. So, basically, I think this is normally for a specific,
task-specific problem. And, always, if you have a specific problem, data collection normally is
is a, is a, well, straightforward process. Okay. So, nowadays, actually, if you are on some
big problem, like, large-language models, which, you know, is very popular in recent years, right.
And, GBT, you know, GBT, 4.0, and also other large-language models. Okay. And, if you, actually,
you know, want to train such a model, and treat the data collection, actually, is a, is a very big
challenge. Big challenge. Okay. So, this, actually, is the, the, the, the dependent
complexity of the problem. And, so, nowadays, if you, you know, want to propose a solution, right,
for a problem. And, then, actually, one important part is the, the design, right, or the data
collection. So, how to collect the data. Okay. For example, I have a certain project, actually,
then, then we are, I locate $100,000, and just for data collection. Okay. So, this, actually,
data collection, nowadays, actually, actually, is a, is a, is a, is a, is a, is a, is a, is a, is a,
receive more and more, actually, attention. And, this, because, actually, the linear results
normally directly determined by the quality and the quantities of the input data. Okay. So,
we need to emphasize this point. And, sometimes, actually, we are, now, given a task, the data is
provided, most likely, right. You do research, you get the data from the web, right, and the
public will have the data. The data is collected by others. Okay. You have no choice. You just,
based on this data, then, you design a machine learning algorithm to learn the model that could
perform the best. But, if you are given a task, you have no data, right, you need to collect data.
And, then, you need to carefully design, actually, the data collection process. So, you need to
think about what data should collect. Okay. In order to produce a model that could have a very
good performance. Okay. So, I want to emphasize the importance of data collection. Okay. So, nowadays,
most likely, you just use other data. You cannot appreciate the importance of the data collection.
But, actually, this is the very important part, right. Just like you cook a meal, right. Actually,
cook a meal. Actually, the important thing, actually, most important thing probably the
ingredient, right, the fresh materials. Okay. And, then, through some cooking skill, right,
then you can make a good meal. Okay. So, this is, you know, fresh food, the quality, right. Just
like the quality of the data. Very important. Okay. So, now, actually, we first look at the
abstraction. So, what is abstraction? Abstraction aims to derive a conceptual map.
A conceptual map. And, this is a conceptual map, actually, you know, it's just a model. Okay. So,
abstraction aims to derive a model from the input data. So, this is the object of the abstraction.
And, so, of course, actually, this abstraction, or derive model, should be based on certain
learning algorithm, right, learning algorithm. Okay. So, this is a model, and it could be
in different forms. Okay. And, so, it could be the computation blocks, like if else rules,
if then rules, or if else rules, right. So, this could be a model, right. Actually, abstraction.
Okay. We, just from the given data, we extract this. Okay. We extract, actually, a model. This
model is also a conceptual map. It is a kind of summarized knowledge representation of the raw
data. It's a, the model, actually, is kind of a condensed or summarized knowledge representation
underlying, you know, the knowledge is underlying the data. Okay. So, model is a kind of condensed or
summarized representation of the knowledge underlying the data. Okay. So, this actually could
have different forms. First, it could be the if then rules.
Right. Okay. And then, actually, the other model could be mathematical equations. Now,
I introduced, right, and we could have many linear equations, like y equals to a1 x1 plus a2 x2,
right, plus a0. So, these are very simple linear equations. Right. So, this is a linear model,
mathematical equation. And we could have a more complex equation, like a nonlinear function,
nonlinear equation. We could have a very complex, deep neural networks. Okay. So, these are all the
mathematical equation, model form. And we could also have, actually, a model with a tree structure,
a graph, a graph neural network, or decision trees, actually, are popular, you know, model
representations. Okay. And, okay. So, this is a model form. And actually, this is a non-model or
conceptual map. Could it be a grouping of similar observations? The grouping of the observations
is also kind of a model. It's also a model, a length, actually, from the data. You are given a lot
of things based on the color, based on the shape, or based on the other characteristics. You put
similar objects into one group. So, actually, this is the last part, actually, it's just the
classroom problem. So, this is the answer for the linear. Okay. So, we can have different, you
know, models. So, abstraction, the second component, second part of the machine-linear
abstraction aims to derive a model. This model, of course, can be a mathematical model,
can be if-then-rules, can be a classification tree, right, can be a tree, can be a grouping of the
data, different forms. Okay. So, this is abstraction. But, of course, which model form to adopt
actually depends on application. Okay. So, the type of problem to be solved
determines actually, you know, actually, the model form. And so, this is the
type of problem, the nature of the input data. Actually, in the next week, when we look at the
data preparation for machine-learning, we will know the data could have different types.
Some data are categorical data. Like, you know, for example, top of the gender sex, right, male or
female. Okay. So, this is a categorical variable, right. And even under this category, you know,
some could be ordinal, have an order, but some don't have an order. Okay. So, different,
these are different data. Some data could be continuous, real data, we think about the temperature
of the room, right. Actually, you know, temperature, there is specific real value, okay, numerical
data. Okay. So, depending on the nature of the data, we could determine what type of model to use.
And this is because for some data, for some models, they will not often assume the data
for a certain distribution, like Gaussian distribution or whatever, right. So, normally,
these assumptions assume the data is continuous. It's a numerical value, right. It's a real value
variable. But either variable is categorical. Certainly, it will not follow, it will not follow
the Gaussian distribution. Certainly, we should not use this type of model. Okay. So, the nature
of the data, the type of the data also determine what model we should use. In such a scenario,
if the data is mixed, right, all the data, you know, has a categorical. Quite often,
we use the super if then rules, we use a tree. Tree, you know, is a kind of a decision tree,
kind of a hierarchical or emulation of the trees, of the decision, of the rules. Okay. So,
this is the model, right. If the model is real values, then we can use other type of models.
So, it's kind of nature, the nature of the data. And also, some of this depends on the nature of the
domain or the problem. And in some scenarios, I think that we hope the model could produce the
best performance. Even the model predicts a wrong result. We are not actually, you know,
result in a disaster. Right. For example, we can use a tree like a web page, right.
We can look at what web pages you have seen in the past day. So, from this web page,
you have seen, you have read, and then we can predict your interest. Or your interest in news,
or your interest in sports, your interest in education news, or your interest in like food.
Okay. Even though this prediction is wrong, actually, you are trying to look for
material on the web on machine learning, right. But they recommend something about chemistry.
But then there will not be a disaster to you, right. You just say, oh, this is not irrelevant to me.
This web page is irrelevant to me. I just skip. I look at others. So, this is just some application,
right. It's not that critical. But for some applications, actually, the decision is very
critical. Okay. And then we have a CT. We have an MRI image. And we input this image,
the input data to an abstraction path, right. Then we will develop a model. And then the model,
we are now performing diagnosis of the disease. Oh, the person has cancer. This person does not
have cancer. So, this decision is very critical, right. Very critical. So, in such a scenario,
we hope that the model could be explainable. Okay. We don't only want to know the prediction result.
We also want to know how this result is obtained. We want to look at the decision process. We hope
the model is explainable. Okay. So, again, based on this requirement, based on this nature of the
problem, right. And we need to use certain types of models, like a decision tree. Okay.
Decision tree, if the data is mixed, have categorical variables. And it has actually like a real
value of variables. And also, we hope actually the decision could be explainable. Then we can use
actually the decision tree. Okay. If there is no need to know that this decision process,
I just want to know the result. Then a black box model, like a neural networks, we will do.
Right. So, this is a dependent application. Okay. So, we decide the model form.
Okay. So, let's say we look at, so, abstraction, right, to let a model, to derive a model.
Okay. And so, once the model is chosen, you decide what model form to use. Right. We want to use
a linear model. We want to use this nonlinear model. We want to use a tree structure model.
Once you have decided this, and then we need to, the next step is to fit a model based on the input
data. Model fitting to fit a model. So, what is, what is fitting a model? Actually, fitting a model
is just a process to determine the values of the parameters in the model. This just shows a very
simple example. Y equals to X, Y, X plus C2. X is a feature. Y is a target variable. Target
can kind of could be a class. Okay. X could be your CGPA. Y, whether you could be admitted to
this CCPA program, or to this signal processing machine learning program, MSC program. Y is just
such a decision. Okay. So, this is known. And the tree, of course, the tree, this Y and X feature
under the target variable is linked, connected by the coefficient C1 and also C2. Okay. So, fitting
a model is just a process to determine the values for the two parameters C1 and C2 based on the data.
Okay. Of course, actually, how to determine the value of C1 and C2. So, we have different methods
to determine C1 and C2. Actually, so later now, from week, from week six, right, from week six,
we will just study different methods to determine the values of C1 and C2. So, this is called fitting
a model. And actually, under the machine learning context or domain, fitting a model is often,
is more often, right, more frequently called learning. Okay.
So, the process of fitting a model based on the data, it also called training or learning,
machine learning, machine training, right. Actually, in statistics, statistics, right,
actually, you know, this is just called fitting a model fitting or sometimes called parameter
estimation. So, this is in statistics, in many, many, we call this as a parameter estimation
or model fitting. But in machine learning, we often call this as a machine learning,
a model learning or model training. Okay. So, because actually, we link the machine
learning to human learning, right. So, it's a learning. So, we're training learning. We use this
the worst. Okay. But actually, it's just to find the value of unknown parameters. It's just a
parameter estimation for the model. Okay. And the data used to fit the model, the data used to
estimate the parameters of the coefficient, right. Actually, I call training data.
Okay. The training data. So, now, actually, for machine learning problem, we have input data,
right. And actually, this data, of course, actually, you know, in the model evaluation part, we will
talk about the model evaluation. Quite often, we have the input data, right. We divide them into
two parts, or three parts. One part is used as a training data. Another part is used as a testing
data. Or one additional part is used as a validation data. Okay. So, not all the data, actually, you
have will be used to train the model, to learn the values for the parameters in the model.
Part of that will be used to train the model, right, to learn the parameter values. So, this part
of data is called training data, or learning data. Okay. Okay. So, this is a learning, right, learning
to derive a model. Okay. Of course, the first we need to determine the model form. And then we
determine the value of the parameters in the model. So, this is the abstraction part. Okay. So, once
we have obtained a model, right, and we need to apply the model, actually, of course, why you
develop a model, right, the ultimate goal is to apply the model for future data. Actually, this is
called generalization. Generalization. Okay. And so, quite often, when we think about machine
learning, right, within abstraction part, we learn the parameter model, value for parameters,
actually, this is just a part of the machine learning, right. Data collection is also part of
the machine learning. Then the parameters of your model based on the data is the second part.
The last part, generalization, is also is a learning process. You apply the knowledge, right. You
apply the knowledge. And then in the progress, you will know when you apply this knowledge,
and you have a prediction. And the prediction sometimes could be wrong, right. From the wrong
result, you also learn. Okay. So, you just remember, apply the knowledge is also a part of the learning
process. Okay. So, apply the knowledge is just the generalization. Okay. So, the other part is to,
to, okay, use to make future decisions. Future decisions. Okay. And so, yeah.
So, this actually, we will apply the knowledge for future data. So, these future data, actually,
are often called testing data or test data. Okay. So, quite often, I mentioned, when we have some
data, we collect some data, right. We divide the data into at least two parts, right. One is used
to train the model. Another use will be used to test the data, test the model. Okay. So, this is the
process. Right. So, the second part, apply the model to the test data is called generalization.
Okay. And actually, the model performance, the generalization performance, right, actually,
depends on many factors, of course, right. Many factors. Okay. And of course, actually, when we,
when we actually apply this to future, right, actually, we assume, we assume, actually, the
testing data, actually, are similar to the training data. Right. You have the knowledge,
right, of the location of the LT27, right. So, you land this in the first few times,
then you know, from your, from a canteen B or from your home, what is the shortest path
to this electric data, right. So, for the first few weeks, you have landed, right. But now,
if you have a task, the location, not LT27, the LT, like 1A, LT1, why is it, right. So,
your knowledge about the location of this, actually, now you are given a new task to
locate the LT1. Why is it? But actually, the testing data is very different from the,
training data. And then the performance could be bad. Okay. So, when we,
generate this model, land from the training data, actually, we assume the testing data
is similar to the training data. Okay. And when we, during this generalization process,
quite often, we could encounter two problems. Okay. So, the first problem is that the training,
the training model is aligned with the training data too much, too well. And this is often called,
actually, the overfitting. So, here I show a diagram. Okay. So, actually, you know, we have
each dot, actually, is a one sample. So, X is a feature, X, horizontal X is a feature. The vertical
X is just the output, the response variable. Okay. And so, in the first tree, roughly,
now we can see, actually, X and Y has a linear relationship. Okay. So, in the first, in the
diagram, actually, we can see the line, the three lines, it captures the train and the train,
and the line, the two variables. It's a linear relationship. But in the second tree scenario,
actually, we see, actually, we have a nonlinear curve, right, that passes through every data point.
So, the second scenario is overfitting. That means, actually, the model is aligned with the
training data too well. Okay. And why too well is bad? And this is because the data normally
has noise, right? The data has noise. You, then, actually, our model tries to capture the noise,
but we know the noise is not random, right? So, in this sample, the noise is this value.
Then, another sample, the noise could be a different value. Okay. But you assume that the
future data has the same value as the random noise, right? Could have the same value as the
train data noise. That's not impractical, right? That's not true. Okay. So, in overfitting, most
likely, we overfit the data. We fit, actually, the noise underlying the data. Okay. We feel to
capture the main train underlying the data, just like this example shows. Okay. So, in such a scenario,
when we perform generalization, the performance could be very bad. Although the performance on the
training data is perfect or very well, but the performance on the testing data could be very
bad. So, this is the more important issue overfitting. Okay. And then, another tree could be that tree,
the test data possesses certain characteristics apparently unknown to the train data. This
issue is often overlooked. Okay. So, I show what is this issue. Okay. And so, this diagram shows
some train data like the blue dot shows the train data. The black data shows the testing data. Okay.
And if you just use the train data to fit a model, right? So, roughly, probably, we know in this
range, actually, the y and the x has a linear relationship. Okay. Indeed, actually, the true
relationship may be like a sine wave or something like this, nonlinear. But in this part, in this
range, the input and output has a linear relationship. Okay. If we just use this part of data to fit a
model, and then, certainly, we just get a linear model. And then, if we use a linear model to
generalize, this linear model is generalized to the testing data, like losing the part of the
black data. The performance is very bad. And this is because, actually, the test data has some
characteristics that is unknown to the train data. Okay. So, here, actually, the one very important
issue that when you are given a task and the data collection is part of the process, okay.
When you collect the data, actually, the data, the train data should
cover the whole range of the data. You need to think about the range of the data in the future,
the whole range of the data. Okay. Then, actually, the model performance could be good.
Okay. And I know that, from what you understand, the two concepts in mathematics, like one is called
interpolation. Another is extrapolation. Interpolation is in between, right? So, normally,
the performance is good. But extrapolation, that means it's something out of the distribution,
out of the range, right? The performance normally is bad, particularly if the model is a nonlinear
model. Okay. So, here, actually, if during the data collection stage, you collect the data,
the car will cover the whole range, the whole range. Okay. And then, for the testing data,
actually, this is something like interpolation, because the data is in the range. Okay. So,
the performance normally is good. But if the data out of the range, then it becomes an extra
problem. Then the performance could be bad. Okay. So, I think, quite often, actually,
in machine learning, in the course study, in the assignment, even in your research papers,
you use some data collected by others, right? You are not understanding the issue. You are not
appreciative, actually, the challenge, you know, or the seriousness of this issue.
But if you really are not solving a problem, starting from scratch, from data collection,
okay, and you will understand this point. Okay. I think this is very, very important.
And this issue is often overlooked, overlooked, because you don't have the experience. You use
the data collected by others. Okay. So, I think, yeah, so you have a chance to solve a problem,
starting from data collection. You need to keep this in mind. Okay. The data cover the whole range.
And I just mentioned that data quality, right? Quality normally, when you think about the quality
frequently, quite often, you will think, oh, the data has no noise, no noise free, or small noise.
But actually, the data quality, not just actually about the cleanliness of the data, right? What I
think is clean, actually about the range, whether this data of the training data cover the true
distribution, true distribution, right? Cover. It's a cover range. Okay. So, the quantity,
sometimes with the quality, quantity, the more the better. But the more I treat the better. That
not mean the data just in a small range, but you have a lot of data. The more the quality, right?
That means, actually, the data cover the whole range. Okay. Sometimes,
in all the number of Hohman data points you have, it is the range of the data.
Okay. So, this is the, I think, the two issues that we may encounter. I think it's important.
Okay. Okay. So, let's actually look at the top of a machine learning.
Okay.
So, so actually, just now, actually, we see the determinant parameters, right? The abstraction.
So, our focus actually, you know, from week six, we will be the, actually, the,
just the, you know, how to determine the parameters. Okay. So, here, I think it's still some
introduction of some basic concept. But I think this concept is important to you. Okay.
And the machine learning can be classified into three categories. And the first one is
supervised learning. Supervised. Okay. And supervised learning is also called predictive
learning. So, machine learning is a class of unknown objects based on the prior class
related information of similar objects. Okay. So, this is supervised learning. Okay. This is one
type. Okay. And another type is unsupervised. Okay. Supervised, unsupervised. So, based on what,
actually, we differentiate the two types of learning. So, a little bit about that. And then,
the last type is called actually reinforcement learning. A machine learns to act on its own,
right? Learn on its own, self-learning. Right? So, I mean, in the beginning, we see the three types
of learning, right? So, last type is self-learning. So, here, this is self-learning. So, a machine
learns to act on its own. Not guided, right? By expert. Act on its own. By trial, by failures,
failures, and success, right? So, through this process, machine learns. So, this is a reinforcement
learning. Okay. Then, as we look at the details about the supervised learning. Okay. So, this
diagram actually clearly shows actually, you know, the different categories. Machine learning
broadly actually divided into three categories. Supervised learning, unsupervised learning,
reinforcement learning. And supervised learning, this category, right? And we have two tasks.
One is regression. Another is classification. So, later, we will talk about the difference between
the two. Classification regression. But actually, in machine learning, the classification is the
main topic. Okay. So, in statistics, so normally, they handle the issue of regression. In statistics,
right? They use a model to predict. Normally, you know, this is a kind of regression problem.
But in machine learning, actually, we focus on the classification problem. But in this category,
we cover both regression and classification. And for another unsupervised learning, we have two
topics. And one is the association analysis. So, this is just a small topic. And some actually,
you know, machine learning, actually, you know, papers or books. You know, just sometimes, you
know, this is actually, you know, association analysis. But this is one kind of learning.
And this could be put under this category. Then, of course, the main topic, the main issue is called
clustering, classification of data, grouping. Put the data into different groups based on the
similarity of the data. So, this is a classification, right? Okay. So, so, next, actually, we look at
the supervised learning. So, the supervised learning, of course, is to learn from the past data, right?
Actually, no matter supervised or unsupervised, we all need to learn from the data, right? So,
and based on some past information, what past information? Okay, this depends on,
this determines whether we could show you the supervised learning or unsupervised learning.
Past information, okay, based on the information.
In the context of machine learning, this past information is also the experience of data,
right? Okay. And so, for example, here, give an example, the task is to separate,
segregate or separate the images by other shape or color of the objects.
Okay. So, you buy shape, then the objects can be classified, the image, run object,
square shape or object, or irregular shape objects can be put into different categories,
right? Okay. And so, if you perform such a task, so what kind of data we should have?
What kind of information we should provide? Of course, we should provide an image, right?
Because we are going to perform image classification. We are going to perform
object classification based on the withdrawal information. So, take pictures, okay? So,
certainly, this picture is the data, input to the abstraction step, right? Abstraction.
So, certainly, actually, we should not have this image, right? So, this is the basic information.
And, okay, another, actually, the color, right? Objects into different categories, green,
color, objects, red, objects, and a blue object, yellow objects, okay? Based on the color,
we put the objects into different categories, right? And so, this is, of course, the basic
information, again, is a color image, right? The picture, the color picture, color image.
This is the basic input, basic information. Okay. But besides this information, we need
additional information. How the machine can know, or this is wrong, this is blue, this is
square shape, this is irregular shape. How the machine can know this, okay? We will perform
class field based on the color, right? How the machine can know, or this object is a blue color,
this object is a red color, this object is a green color. How the machine can know this,
okay? And, actually, this is a part of additional information, right? Additional information,
not the basic information. The basic information is just the picture, okay? The image. Now,
besides this image, we need to have additional information, okay? So, this additional information
is just color, okay? This object, together with the color, okay? This color, this color is just
a tag, right? This image with a tag of shape. This is a wrong shape. This is a square shape.
This is irregular shape. And this tag is also called label, label, right? So, the basic input
is just the image, right? Besides this, we also need to have the tag, this tag information, right?
But if we do the classification based on the color, then we should have color information
of the object, right? So, this actually is called tag, right? This is a tag. This tag is also called
label, label, okay? If an image, together with a tag or label, and then this data image is called
label data, okay? So, super hard learning is based on the label of the training data.
You take a picture, right? You want to build a system to recognize anything in NTU campus, right?
So, you take a lot of pictures. Take a picture of this building, take a picture of another building,
take a picture of a table, take a picture of a computer, take a picture of a chair, okay? Besides
this, you need to do, for each picture in the training data, you need to give a label or this
chair. And this is the computer. So, this is a laptop, right? This is a projector,
and this is a building, and this is a room, this is a canteen, right? So, you give a tag. So,
this tag is a class label, class label, okay? If a data with a tag, with a label, then this data is
labeled training data, okay? Super hard learning is based on the label training data.
Okay, now you see the super hard learning, right? Learning always, of course,
the machine learning is based on the data, right? The data could be just the basic information,
like image, okay? But besides this, we need to have a label, this label, right? Define the class,
okay? So, then the data becomes a label training data, okay? If we learn
using the basic information and also the label information, and then this learning is super hard
learning, okay? So, now actually we come to the concept of super hard learning, right? Actually,
this is linked to the label training data. In another application, for example, like a
sentiment analysis, sentiment means the person's emotion, attitude towards something,
towards a product, towards a lecture, towards a food, towards a service, and this is a sentiment.
Normally, sentiment analysis actually tries to classify the sentiment attitude into one of the
three categories, positive attitude, or you feel, oh, delicious, right? Very good, okay? And then, oh,
awful food, right? Terrible. Bad attitude, right? This means actually the negative sentiment,
neutral, right? I have a lunch in Canine Bay that I'm not sure whether you like the food in Canine Bay
or you don't like the food in Canine Bay, right? So, it's neutral. So, these are positive,
neutral, right? You want to build a model to perform this kind of classification,
okay? So, we need to collect a lot of data, some comments, okay? NTU, students have a lot of comments
on social media, right? About the triple E, about NTU, about lectures, okay? So, some of these comments,
and also, you need to read the comments. These are just a test, and then we also need to give a tag,
right? Oh, the human need to evaluate this, right? Then, oh, this student has shown a negative attitude,
okay? Then, negative. Then, we have another comment, right? Another, this comment could be just one
sentence, just could be just a few words, and then, and allowing this actually words, we could have a
negative positive attitude. So, then we have a label, positive. Then, another one, so nothing, right?
Then, it's neutral. We need to collect out such data, a lot of tests, a lot of tests, writing your
comments, and then, the corresponding label about sentiment. So, this is the label data. So, we want
to build a model to classify the sentiment, and we need to first collect some data, and then, we label
the data, and then, we input this labeled training data to the machine learning algorithm, right?
To the abstraction part, okay? Then, we can perform super learning to get a model, okay? So, this is
just actually the label training data, and also some examples, right? What is a label? Okay? The label
normally means a class, class label. Okay. Okay. So, this is just, that shows the flow, the flow,
and we have label training data, right? Because super learning, we have label training data,
then, goes to the abstraction part, right? So, through the super learning, we get a model.
So, this is just the training data, the input data abstraction, then, the last step to apply
the model, right? To predict the result of the test data. So, this is the generalization, okay?
Then, we can have a predicted result for the testing data. So, this shows the flow of the
super learning, right? Essentially, the data, the training data, the label. For each data, we have
a label. We have a class label. Normally, this label means class label. Okay? So, this label
actually depends on the problem, right? You do the sentimentality, we have a label, right? Do the
emotion recognition, happy, anger, you know, actually, you know, dislike, right? Or joy,
embarrassment. These are the emotions. Okay. So, these are the class. Okay. So, we need to
collect a lot of data. For each of the data, we put them, we think about what is the emotion.
Then, we have a corresponding label. Okay. So, this is called a labeling of the data. Okay.
So, this is the super learning. And some example of super learning is the prediction
of results of a game. When lose a draw. Okay. And then, predicting whether a tumor is malignant
or benign. A tumor, right? Malignant, then, I mean a cancer. Okay. So, benign and malignant. So,
these are the prediction, actually. And then, predicting the price of a real estate. And also,
predicting the price of a stock. Price. Okay. And then, the last one, you know, classify the test.
So, these are the classifications, right? Classified test. And actually, all these are the
examples of super learning. But actually, these examples also, we know, they are based on the
super, the label train data, right? But actually, they also have difference. They also have
difference, right? And they are not the same. They are not the same. They are not the same.
They also have difference, right? And they are not the same. Okay. And here, we give an example,
like, whether a tumor is malignant or benign. And then, predicting the price of real estate.
Actually, the two are different. Okay. And actually, the first problem, the outcome is very limited.
Just, actually, tumor or malignant benign. Just two possible results, right? Just two possible
results. And then, the next problem, predicting the price of real estate.
This value could be any value in a range, right? Could be any value in a range. Actually, the value,
and the possible values is numerous. Actually, so, actually, these two
problems, although they both are super hard learning problems, but they belong to different
categories. The classification, or whether a tumor, predict, whether a tumor is malignant or
benign, actually, is a patent classification problem. Predicting the price of an estate
is a regression problem. Okay. So, they all super hard learning, but actually, they belong to different
types. Okay. The case one is a predictor category. This category, this category, the category, right?
Benign, malignant, predict, win, lose, draw, predict, right? Get offer, don't get offer.
Actually, this is a category. Okay. So, this kind of problem is called classification.
Then, another predict a real value, another class. So, in the first case, actually,
the prediction result is limited. Normally, it's limited, right? Limited. Okay. And, of course,
sometimes, this is known, this is limited, and we see limited. We can have many possible values,
right? For example, face recognition, right? And, you know, each person could be a one class,
right? Could be a one class, one category, right? We look at the face, then we put the face into
different categories. Okay. So, this is, you know, this is limited, but how many values is
considered limited? How many values are considered, actually, numerous? Actually, this is hard to say,
but actually, sometimes, this limited value, just two possible results. But, sometimes, this could be
huge number, right? During COVID-19, I know in China, the campus, actually, you know, they all,
you know, put, actually, some face recognition device there, right? Recognize whether you are
a student belonging to this university, right? Or whether you are a staff of this university.
You are not, then you are not allowed to go into the campus. Okay. So, here we use face recognition.
Of course, the university, you know, could have, you know, like a $50,000, $60,000 student. So,
this category, like $60,000, could be a huge number, but this is still a, it's a limited number,
right? It's still a classification problem, face recognition. Okay. So, this is a free limited,
you know, sometimes, this number could be just two, right? Sometimes, this number could be huge.
Okay. So, classification.
Classification, normally, the output is limited. It's a category. The output is a category.
It's a category. Okay. So, these are the examples. Image classification, right? And we can take
pictures. I think, based on the picture, we can actually classify the object, right? This is a
desk. This is a table. This is a projector. This is a laptop. This is a chair, right? This is a person.
Different categories. Image classification. And the prediction of disease.
You have diseases. You don't have the disease, right? You're healthy, not healthy. Two different
categories, right? And then malignant, be none. So, these are the, you know, the
prediction of categories. And then, when those predictions, prediction of natural calamities,
natural disasters, right? Based on the, you know, in some of my projects, we, we, we, we
detect all, we detect an event from the, from the social media or news. Okay. Because actually,
sometimes, actually, you know, this is actually, you know, some, some person, you know, see the
happening of the event. He will publish this on the social media, right? So, we can detect the
happening of the events on the social media, right? So, basically, based on the test, okay?
So, this is a classification. Natural disasters happen. As quick happens. A flooding happens.
Typhoon happens, right? These are the events, okay? So, the natural disaster classification.
Recognition of handwritten, handwritten writings. You write something, right? English alphabet,
26, right? The digits, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 9, right? Dijit. These are all recognition,
recognition, right? This is a class-future problem. Okay. Because, you know, you recognize this
writing, right? This, other is a digit, right? 0, 1, 2, 3, and 10, right? So, it's a 10, 10.
And then, if I use a letter, right? 26. So, the category only, like, 36. Okay. So,
this is a limited category. It's a classification problem. And then, physical recognition. And
then, many applications, actually, is a classification problem. And so, I think these are
no super hard learning. Certainly, actually, no, we, we, we, I think, follow the super hard learning
flu, right? Framework. Okay. And so, here, you know, we have, yeah, okay. Again, we use input
label training data. And then, we treat the trend classifier. And then, we use the classifier
to classify, predict the label, class label, or the category of user testing data, right?
Okay. Okay. So, that's a tree. I think we are, yeah. At 20, we have a break. 10 minutes. Okay.
Okay. So, just now, we have talked about the super hard learning. And under this super hard learning,
one main type of learning is the problem, is the classification problem, right? So, we predict
that category. So, the response variable is a category, right? Good, bad, right? And
malignant, B9, right? And so, this is a category. Okay. So, this is a classification problem.
And this category is also called class. Okay. So, this is a classification problem. And this is a
super hard learning paradigm. And we have another problem that is regression. Regression, right?
And in the regression, the target variable is a numerical variable. It's a real, actually,
value variable. It's not categorical. Okay. It's not categorical. It's a real value.
And actually, in the classification problem, right? So, for example, we have a category, right?
But of course, we know the computer normally can't really handle numerical values, right?
So, this category normally needs to be encoded into numerical values. Okay. And so, part of
actually, we use the so-called one-hot encoding. One-hot encoding. For example, we have two class.
It's a two-class classification problem. Just a malignant B9 for a tumor, for example, right? And
then, actually, we can use a vector. We can use a vector to denote, actually, you know, the class
label. For example, for the B9, we can use a 01 to denote. And for, you know, malignant, we can
use a 10. Okay. So, for a two-class classification problem, we can use a two-dimensional vector
to denote, actually, the class label. Okay. And for a three-class, for example, we
classify the object into a round-shaped object, a square-shaped object, irregular-shaped object,
three-classes, right? Then, we can encode like a round shape into 100. And the square shape is
011. And then, the irregular shape is 100. Okay. So, 001, 010, 100 for the three-class.
So, we can use this vector. So, we use a one-hot encoding. But if it's a prediction class,
prediction problem, normally, this is just one scalar, a scalar. Okay. So, this scalar,
no target variable, could just be 2.3 or 5.2. Okay. It's kind of real value,
the real value or numerical value. Okay. So, we can see the difference, right? The target variable,
categories. We normally use a vector to encode this. This is called one-hot encoding
to categories. Okay. But for the target variable, if you want regression problem,
the target variable is just a scalar, scalar. And the value could be any numerical values,
real values. Okay. So, this regression problem and like a store price, temperature, right?
Temperature of the room is a real value, 27.5 degree. This is a real value. So, this is a
prediction, just a scalar by the temperature. Okay. And so, this is like one problem. We
use a petal length to predict the sample length. Okay. And so, regression problem. So, the length,
could be any real values. 2.3, 5.5, no, 1.0, some real values. Right? So, this is a regression problem.
Some example, demand for caution in details, demand for caution. Okay. Although, for example,
if you want to predict the whole many, you know, how many hand phones, right, in this certain
shop, right? So, what is the demand for the next one week for a specific model of hand phone?
It can predict like 2,000, 1,500, 1,400. So, although these integers, right, but these are
just real values. Okay. So, this value, just one real value, the scalar. We don't use actually like
like a vector to include this, right? It's just a scalar. This kind of demand, right,
obviously tell prediction for caution. And then, self-prediction for managers,
price prediction. What is the price? Okay. And good prediction in economics,
the GPT group in this year is 3.5. Okay. Last year, 2.7. The year before last year, 5.7.
This is a real value, right? Actually, it's just a scalar. Okay. In rule number,
student number, prediction in education, in rule number, right? So, every year, you know,
offer a lot of, give a lot of offers, right? But who will finally actually magically in
this program? Okay. We have prediction number. Normally, 70%, 40%. No, we have a, we have a
specific number, right? Specific number. Okay. So, these are usually regression problems.
You remember the prediction normally is just a real number, right? Although sometimes these are
integer, right? Number, right? Specific student number is an integer. But it's not a category.
This number can be just represented by a scalar. Okay. Not like, you know, like in the
Wang-Hong-Ying, the category needs to be represented by a vector. Okay.
Okay. So, this is the super high-level learning and also the two
types of learning, right? A problem, actually regression and classification. So,
next we look at unsupervised learning. Supervised learning based on the super
label change on data, right? But in some scenarios, we have data, but we don't have the label.
We don't have the label. And actually, sometimes, like, you know, like test classification, we
could have a lot of tests, right? On the web, a lot of tests on the web. But we don't have the time,
we don't have the energy to annotate. Okay. So, we label them. So, this data unlabeled.
So, actually, you know, even the data is unlabeled, we can still learn from them. Okay. So, here,
actually, the learning based on unlabeled data is called unsupervised learning.
Unsupervised. Okay. And so, actually, within this unsupervised learning, the main objective,
actually, is to put the data into the natural groups. Natural groups. Actually, when we talk about
the classification in wiki level 12, actually, we will talk more about the natural grouping.
Natural grouping, that means, actually, the data within the same group are very similar to each
other. Okay. The data between different groups are very different. So, this is called natural grouping.
Okay. And this is different from classification. Sometimes, in the classification, right, and we
use, actually, you know, classifier to separate them. But sometimes, the sample in the same class,
actually, are very different. But sample in different class could be similar.
This classification. But this is not natural grouping. Natural grouping, that means, within the
same group, the data are very similar. Between groups, the data are very different. Okay.
So, this is the so-called natural grouping. So, unsupervised learning is also called, actually,
the descriptive learning. Okay. The unsupervised learning is called predictive, right? Predict,
predict the label, predict the target value, the real value. So, prediction, right? We do the
so, predict the learning. So, here, unsupervised learning, we don't do prediction. Okay. So,
it's a descriptive learning. And unsupervised learning is also referred to the patent discovery
or knowledge discovery. Okay. So, classification is a main, actually, a top of unsupervised learning.
Classifier. I just mean, I really mentioned, actually, classification is just the grouping of the
data, based on the similarity of the data. Okay. And, okay. So, object within the same,
within the same, this diagram shows the classification, right? Actually, the similarity,
we see the object of the data, similar data are put into one group, right? So, actually,
each data normally has a few features, right? And each feature has a value. So,
these values could be used as a coordinate. Then, actually, we can have a feature space,
right? We can have a feature space. And then, each sample, actually, based on the coordinate,
it is just one data point. Okay. So, actually, in the geometric layer, each sample is a vector.
And this vector is just a data point in the feature space. Okay. And then, how to evaluate
the similarity? Normally, the most commonly used similarity measure is the distance in the space.
If the distance between two samples is very small, the extreme case, the distance zero,
that means the two samples are identical, the same. Okay. So, this distance is a measure of
similarity. The smaller the distance, the larger the similarity, right? So, just now we see,
or the object, similar object are put into one group. That means the objects in the feature space
are close to each other, small distance are put into one group. Okay. So, here, this just shows,
okay. So, these are data, right? And, actually, we can keep the distance. And then, these data are
put in one group, these data into one group. So, class one, class two, right? Class three,
so these are grouping. Within one of the same group, they are quite similar. The distance between
them is very small. So, this is called similarity, right? Based on the similarity. And between groups,
you can see that there is a gap, right? So, this gap means there is a big difference between the
data in the two groups. So, this is called the natural grouping. So, this is the so-called
classroom. Okay. So, this is the main topic, main problem of answer-wide learning.
And another, actually, answer-wide learning is so-called, actually, association analysis.
Okay. This is not a main research field, not a main research topic in machine learning.
But this also, actually, I think some are working on this because this technique can be used,
like in data mining, in the market of data, in the mining, right? So, actually, this is just
one example, a transaction ID, means a customer ID. Class number one, bought two items. One is
butter, another is bread. And then, class number two, bought diaper, bread, milk, beers. Number
three, bought milk, chicken, beer, and diaper, right? They all bought different items. But,
actually, we find, actually, when one buy the diaper, quite often you buy the beers. You can
see, you know, the second customer, right? Diper, beer, together, right? Then the customer, beer,
diaper, right? Four beer, right? This means, actually, these are the two items associated.
So, this is association analysis. That means when one customer buys this item, most likely he will
also buy another item. So, this is the association analysis. But this also is very useful, right?
In the market, actually, for example, supermarket, you put a tree, you even know these two items are
associated, right? Quite often, you have association. Of course, not every time they associate, right?
This is a perfect example. But in some scenarios, actually, they don't buy an item, don't really
necessarily buy another item. But frequently, they have high frequency. But one item, they will also
buy another item. Okay. So, that means, in the supermarket, you can put a tree, like, an item
in this side, right? Then another item just beside. So, then when the guy sees this item, most likely
he will buy another item. If this item is not beside, so probably he will not buy. Okay. So,
this actually will, I think, promote the sale of one item, right? And based on another item.
Okay. So, this is association analysis. And this is not a main topic. So, we are not
starting this, actually, we are not. In this course, we just briefly understand this concept.
We are not starting this technique, association analysis. But if you have interest, of course,
you can always find the material on the web. Okay. So, we have introduced the super-adrenaline
and super-adrenaline. Then we come to the last type, that's reinforcement learning. Reinforcement
learning, self-learning, right? Self-learning through many tries. Of course, the amount of the
many tries, some of the tries are successful. Some of the tries actually are failed. Okay.
And so, this is actually like, you know, self-learning, right? Self-learning and no teachers. Actually,
the super-adrenaline, why we call it super-adrenaline? Because the target variable, just like a teacher,
just like a teacher. So, we call it super-adrenaline. Okay. So, here, we don't have a teacher here.
We don't have a teacher. Okay. We need to learn about ourselves. Okay. So, this is self-learning.
Actually, self-learning, now you say, in this machine, it's called reinforcement learning.
Okay. And so, I think some examples are like, walk, right? We learn how to walk. We learn how to
ride bicycle. Okay. So, and actually, in this machine learning, right? I think reinforcement
learning, this is diagram. And we have input raw data. And so, here, now, this is the component
of reinforcement learning. We have an environment, right? We have an environment. And we have agents.
Normally, agents is the one that perform the environment, normally, the program, right? The
contest. Okay. And one important part is the reward. Reward. Just like, you know, when the student,
the child, right, learn how to walk, right? Sometimes, he failed. Sometimes, he failed, right?
But the parent could give an encouragement to him. And then, like, give him a chocolate, right?
And then, oh, give him a reward, right, if he succeeds. And then, encourage him to learn, right?
And then, encourage him to learn. So, this is a very important concept, is the reward.
And the reinforced millennium, I think, is often used in robotics. Okay. And because,
for example, we have a robot in a certain environment, right? And we want the robot to
go through all obstacles through the shortest path, just like you are located in, you know,
in a certain seat, in this classroom, right? You want to leave the room as soon as possible.
You want to find the shortest path, right? For machine, right? Nobody tells him where to go,
right? Nobody tells him what is the specific path he should follow. But the machine should
try many times, right? In this room, you try a lot of times, just like doing simulation, right?
I go this way, go this way, go if I go that way, then you block, right? And then, I need to bypass
this obstacle, and then find a goal, take quite some time. Okay. So, through this kind of,
through many trials, just like a simulation, right? You know, you don't necessarily really need to go,
right? To simulation. Go that way, go that way, then how many, you know, the distance I need to
go through, right? You want to leave the room, okay? You can do a lot of trials, okay? Finally,
you can find the shortest path. This is a self-learning, reinforcement learning, okay? And
so that we have a score, right? A score, okay? And actually, the reinforcement learning,
it recently is also, you know, I just mentioned in robotics, which is a popular area nowadays,
right? And also, it's widely used in the training of the large language models, LL,
large language models. And actually, a large language model normally is trained by a few steps.
And the first step is so called actually language model, right? What is the language model? The
language model is used to predict the next word. I have a very good, the next one, time, for example,
right? We use the previous word to predict the next word. So this part is called self-learning,
it's a super-learning class. It's a self-super-learning, we call it self-super-learning, okay? So we train
a model that could predict the next word, okay? And then after that, we need to have the so-called
instruction learning. Instruction learning, we have an answer, right? We have a question,
then we have answers. But the answer could be very different, right? If I ask you,
how about Singapore? You see, Singapore is in the Southeast Asia. Yes, you are correct, but this
is not a very good answer. Another better answer is that Singapore is not in Southeast Asia, right?
And then, you know, what is the, you talk about the population, you talk about the size of the
territory, you talk about the two famous universities, NETU, right? NUS. You know, you talk about more,
right? Then suddenly, this is a good answer, right? This is a better answer. And then you
even talk about more about the new groups, right? Chinese, Indian, Malays, and others, right? So
talk about more. The more, the longer the answer, right? Of course, I mean, every information is
correct, right? Then you give a high score, give a reward. So this kind of learning, so to encourage,
that's why when you ask GPT, right? Try GPT, they give you normally a long answer, right? If I
ask a GPT now, they actually say, you may see Singapore is a very long answer. Okay, so they
encourage you to try a long answer. Why a long answer? Actually, the first case is also correct,
right? Singapore is in the Southeast Asia, right? It's correct, but not a very good answer, right?
Too short. So they also use this, you know, in reinforcement learning, a mechanism, right? Give
a score, give a reward to higher, longer answers, right? They encourage the longer answers to the
question, right? So this is reinforcement learning. And then you have, it's like self-driving cars,
or I think now in robotics, so reinforcement learning. But in this course, actually, we focus on
the super-hard learning and the anti-hard learning, right? Reinforcement learning is not
covered in this course. But if you have interest, or if you need this reinforcement learning in your
dissertation, your project, then certainly you are encouraged to look for material from the website.
Okay. So next I'll talk about the applications of machine learning, right? So of course, machine
learning is widely used, right? And almost all areas, right? And then you can think about, actually,
the use of machine learning. But of course, actually, in some scenarios, actually,
we use the more advanced machine learning, like a deep learning, right? If the data is a test,
or natural language, or time-server, this kind of thing, right? But actually, in many scenarios,
the data is just a tree. You know, the data, you just use data in the database,
relational database, structured, okay? So in such a scenario, and we just use a commercial
machine learning, okay? Like the data in the banking, in the banks, right? In the banking and
the finance industry, we have a database, right? So all the information you have. And so like
some typical example, a fraud transaction detection. Actually, you know, some students actually are
working on a project like to, based on the transaction, you can predict whether, you know,
there's a possibility of money laundering, right? So this is actually, you know, prediction, okay?
In finance. Customer-churn prediction. Whether this customer-churn will select service,
leave this company, or go service to another company, right? Select a service of other companies.
So this also can have a prediction, okay? So this is a finance, banking, many, all the insurance,
and, you know, you have to care, you know. And the part often, to know, you know, a problem,
we don't just use one type of a learning. So now we talk about super-hard learning,
unsupervised learning, right? And actually, in practice, and part often, you know, for one problem,
and we need to integrate, you know, both super-hard and unsupervised learning.
Okay. So I just give you one example, right? This is a very typical example, actually.
Like, for example, a bank, you know, have a new scheme for fixed deposit.
Fixed deposit, like you save the money in the bank for one year, and then what is the interest rate,
right? So now if they have, you know, the interest rate, probably, actually, we are done, right?
We'll be done, actually, in the next few months, okay? So now, actually, the one bank, like,
launch a new scheme program. If you save, actually, like, a certain 50K, no, 50,000,
Singapore dollar for one year, and then the fixed deposit rate, right, interest rate is
4%. For example, this is actually very high, right? 4%. Okay? They have a new scheme. Of course,
actually, they can inform every customer of the bank, right? You can imagine, even in Singapore,
a small country, and a bank can easily have, like, 1 million customers in China, right?
Huge population. A bank could have 1 billion customers. Of course, you can send a message,
you can write letters, you can call them, actually, to tell them, you know, this new scheme, right?
And then you ask them whether you are interested or not, right? But you need to send billions of
messages, you need to send billions of letters, you need to send, actually, a billion phone calls,
right? So that is not practical, okay? Then how to address this problem, actually, normally,
we can use the machine learning technique, okay? So first, actually, you can select a few,
a small number of customers. For example, like 2,000 customers, okay? And for these 2,000 customers,
of course, you can call them, you can write letters to them, you can message them to see,
oh, we have a new face deposit interest rate, right? 4.0, very attractive. So whether you have
interest or not, right? Then, of course, actually, normally, we can receive three types of response.
First, the customer could see, oh, yes, I have interest. Please send more information to me,
I have interest, right? They have interest. Some say I don't have money or I don't, I have a better
way to invest my savings, right? I don't want to actually put this into a fixed deposit scheme.
So I have no interest in this. So this is a second response. And then that response, actually,
simply don't reply, okay? Call them, they don't reply, okay? Three responses, okay? So actually,
now, based on these responses, different type of response, three types, right? Of the 2,000
customers, we can build a model and to predict the customer's response based on his personal data.
Actually, the bank normally have our data, right? And normally, our age, our gender,
nationality, if you work, right, then what is your salary? What is your family size? So what kind of
apartment home you stay? Whether you have a car, what car it is, how much is it? I have a lot of
information, all recorded in the bank, in the database, okay? So based on these input features,
we can predict whether the person could have a positive response, could have a negative response,
or could have no response, no reply, right? We can predict, at least based on the 2,000
customers, we can build such a model, okay? And then we can use this model to predict the remaining
customers around billion, okay? Then we can only select those with a high probability
that could give a positive response. Then we just inform them, right? There's no need to,
with your effort, right, to call billion customers, to send billion messages, right? There's no need
to do that. So this is a smarter way, right, of marketing, right? Okay. So this basically, you know,
is a class-gaming problem, right? It's a super-high-learning problem. You collect the data of
2,000 customers based on this label data because you have the response. The response is just a label.
You can build a model. So this is a, build a patent classification model. So this is a super-high-learning
problem, okay? Then the question comes, how do we select these 2,000 customers?
This cost, or 2,000 customers should not be randomly selected from the probe, okay? These
2,000 customers should be representative, should represent those rich, you know, middle income,
right? Poor people, okay? Because I have a big family side, very big saving or less saving,
right? Because it should be representative of the billions or millions of customers, okay? But how
to, but how to select these 2,000 representative customers? How to select? Actually, we can use
the so-called answer-high-learning, the classroom algorithm. Actually, you can use the classroom
algorithm to put the data into 2,000 groups or clusters. And then from each cluster, you select
one, the representative one, okay? Then finally, through this answer-high-learning, you select
2,000 customers, right? Then for these 2,000 customers, you call them, you get the responses,
you label them, then to build a model. So in the whole process, you can see we use
more types of learning, unsupervised learning first, then followed by the supervised learning,
right? Okay, so we know different type of learning, but actually based on the nature of the problem,
and sometimes we need to integrate different techniques. Just like in the beginning, I see
the first generation of the AI is knowledge driven, right? It's a rule based on knowledge,
but rules, okay? Second generation, and then it's machine learning or data driven. But not
necessarily we need to use either knowledge driven or data driven. We can use both, we can integrate
both, right? See how they're similar? We can integrate different types of learning, right?
Supervised and supervised into one system. Okay, so this is the different applications of
machine learning. And then of course, actually machine learning, we need to machine learning,
right? Machine learning to use machine, to instruct machine. Instruct machine here means computer.
You instruct computer how to learn from the data. So certainly we need to know programming.
And remember last year, actually I gave an assignment, actually the student actually email
complaints, see? You don't tell me, you know, in the beginning, you see, you know, machine learning
needs computer programming. But if machine learning is the machine, computer learning,
if you don't know how to program, right? Don't program how to learn, how to instruct computer
to learn from the data. So we must know programming, right? Of course, actually,
we cannot use like a low level, like you can use C, Java, or you can use either more high level
language, but we need to do programming. Okay, so this is a necessary skill actually for machine
learning. Become machine, here computer, computer learning, computer, you don't know, you must
know how to program, right? Okay, so here for machine learning, I think there are three popular
language, right, common language on the pattern. Okay, these are no open source, right? No need to
pay, right? Of course, for some particular package, probably need to pay, but basically,
you don't need to pay. Okay, and also based on the pattern, we have some tools for machine learning.
So this is actually a Sanskrit language, right? So these are very popular machine learning
libraries, okay? There are a lot of functions there. All the methods we learn in this course
actually have a function in the library. Okay, so you can use actually, you know,
pattern language, and you can use these two both. So this is one popular technique pattern, right?
Okay, another actually is R. R is an even higher level language, right? And for those,
like in the business area, not familiar with computing, we are all from, many of you are from
computers, you know, background, from the engineering background at least, right? Control,
or communication, or similar area, right? Certainly, you know programming, right? So,
but for many, like in business, in banking, just now we talk about application in banks, right?
In finance industry, their background is business management, but they can also use
machine learning, so they can use R, it's like a, it's a very high level, okay? R, and then my lab,
my lab, actually, I'm familiar with my lab, but not R or Python. I started to use machine,
my lab in 1989. So actually now, how many years? When I did my master's degree in 1989, I used
a tree, my lab. So I have 30 years, right? My lab, I don't know Python, but you are encouraged to use
the, the Python to, you know, to work our assignment, okay? But of course, you can still use my lab.
Okay. So, okay, so these are my lab, the three, you know, computer language are popular, I mean,
for machine learning. Machine learning and my lab also know tour balls, even for deep learning, right?
And also for neural networks, and for statistics, he's studied it, we all have, for control, right?
We all have the tour balls, he's a professional, okay? And so you can use N.A., right? So actually in the,
you know, our assignment, actually, you are encouraged to use the Python, but any language is fine,
okay? You can use any language, actually, I give you the data, right? You, you, based on data,
you build models, then use the model to predict the result of the testing data. You can use any language,
okay? And, okay, so this is, I think, yeah, so when, when, week six, when I give you the assignment,
I'll talk about more details, okay? But at least in the past, actually, I hope the student can start
and then can, from scratch, can write some code, okay? But actually, I find nowadays,
students can use the, you know, try GPT, right? To get a code, and copy it to the assignment,
to get a high mark. So from this year, just look at your results, okay? Don't look at the code,
you can copy the code, right? You can use a machine, try GPT to generate the code, okay? So I just,
we'll look at the results, okay? Okay, that's actually like the issues in machine learning,
okay? Machine learning is widely used, right? In countries, like, in, in China, right? Now,
it's pioneering in the application of machine learning, okay? And also, you observe in Singapore,
machine learning is used, AI, you look at a lot of apps, right? But maybe it's less used,
and not come than China. But if you are other countries, I think even, I think less used,
right? So actually, these are, I think the, because actually, many, many factors, right?
It doesn't mean they don't have the technique, okay? And there are some other issues, okay? There
are some issues, right, to the law, regulation, the cultures, okay? And so there are other equal
issues, okay? About the use of machine learning, use AI techniques, okay? And some important
issue here is the, is the privacy, privacy. I think you all have the experience. I think a few
years, I do, but a few years, you know, actually, I see, you know, many people, they all appreciate
the covenants, right? Brought by the AI technique. Just appreciate the covenants. But nowadays,
more and more people talk about the privacy issues, right? Privacy. Probably you also have this,
actually, this is a nice chair, right? You have this chair, okay? So privacy, okay? And so this is
actually, you know, when we use the data, right? Actually, sometimes actually, from our machine
learning point of view, we should use any possible information. Normally for learning,
the more information we have, normally the better the performance, right? So we should
try our best to get, to collect as much as possible of the information. This could be
the personal information, right? But actually, you know, some, but in practical scenarios,
sometimes, actually, because of the law and the regulations, we cannot use some of these
information, even these information is available to us. For example, actually, like, you know,
in a bank, you know, the per day, the risk, whether there will be a default or not, the
person will not, you know, you borrow them, you lend the money to them, right? They will not pay you
back later, right? There is a risk, okay? And of course, actually, maybe there is a,
the gender make a difference, male or female. But you cannot use this information in the model.
Actually, some have these regulations, because these will create a result that against a certain,
we have a bias against a certain gender, right? So, so these are, you see, from machine learning
point of view, we try to do that, that from other point of view, from social science,
from a non, from non humanity, no, they have other considerations, okay? So, I think, so
there's no application of machine learning, the issues we need to take into account.
Okay, not just from our point of view, right? We engineers, right? Or we try to get the best
performance by the tree, we need to take other issues, editing issues, social issues, actually,
cultural issues, and into consideration, okay? So, this is, I think, one thing we need to note
to take into account, the privacy. Okay, another is that actually, even there is no breach of
privacy, there may be situations where actions were taken based on machine learning, or may create
adverse reaction, okay? And this actually, we also need to realize this. So, machine learning,
we see, or machine learning from data, some even believe machine learning outperforms human.
Indeed, in some tasks, right, in computing, for example, you might calculate, can calculate,
can outperform human, right? Yeah, certainly, machine learning can outperform human, some tasks,
right? And then, actually, they tend to believe the result of the machine learning. But we need to
keep this in mind, actually, the learning result also, actually, is affected by many factors.
First, the quality of the data, right? The quality of data, then the learning algorithm,
and the quality of the data also has many considerations,
quality of data, right? And, for example, actually, you get the data, but this data actually
just cover, you know, part of the information, part of the customer, not representative.
Just as in the previous example, I see you select 2,000 customers, these 2,000 customers should be
representative, okay? But if you happen to select 2,000 customers, even 3,000 customers,
by these three, all time, just represent a small group, a small group, right? And then,
based on the small group data, small group, not all the customers, right? Not representative,
just like very rich people or very proud people, just middle class data, okay? Don't cover the whole
range, right? Then you build a model on this, you predict the data outside, now, beyond that range.
I certainly know the prediction could not be accurate, could not be, right? So that could,
you know, create adverse reactions, okay? Adverse effect or impact, okay? So we should actually,
so it's very ethnic issues, and we should use machine learning technique, but we should not always
trust this, right? Machine learning results, the prediction from the model, because actually,
the model actually basically lend the information from the data. If the data is not representative,
and then the model certainly not can only capture that part of the information. And when it's
generalized to other part of the data, actually, certainly, actually, that could be, actually,
you know, a very big area, okay? So I think we also need to take this into account, okay? Try to
use machine learning, right? Try to use AI. Don't always try them. They are 100%, right? Don't
try them. Trust them, okay? We need to always to have the so-called human judgment, right?
Ultimately, we are smarter than machines, right? We need to have our own judgment,
okay? So these are the, so probably human judgment actually should be exercise.
So this is the order of the consideration that we need to take into account, okay? And when we use
machine learning, okay? So this is a brief summary about today's lecture, right? So today, first
about the basic learning process, right? Three parts, input data. The data is always important,
right? The raw material. Without good material, you cannot make good food, right? So the data,
the abstraction, and also the generalization. So the three parts of a machine learning system.
So then learning, data, the client data is all part of the learning, right? Apply the model to
the future data is also part of the learning. And the different learning, actually, you know,
categories, the supervised learning, unsupervised learning, reinforcement learning, right? So the
difference based on the data, right? The label training data. If we use the label information,
then it's supervised. But even the data is labeled, but if you don't use the label information,
but then the learning is still unsupervised, right? It's unsupervised because you don't use that part
of information. Then the learning is unsupervised. Although the data is labeled. Okay.
Okay. And then the popular, you know, the platforms or computer language, right? For machine learning.
Python, R, my lab. And so ethical issues. Very important. I'm going to consider this
when we adopt machine learning techniques. Okay. I think, yeah, basically this is all for today.
This is our first lecture about machine learning. So I just introduced some basic concept.
No technical details. But actually, indeed, actually, I think these issues are important.
We need to have a good understanding about these basic concepts. Okay. So that's all. Thank you very much.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.