Okay.
In the previous weeks, actually we have started a few, actually a pending classification design
method, right? And the first method is the basic decision rule. We try to actually predict
the class label based on the posterior probability. And of course the central issue is how to
model the class kind of probability density function, right? So this is the first one we
have studied. Then the second one actually is the naive base, okay? And actually naive
base is just the same as Gaussian function base, right? Probability density function estimation.
But actually we assume the features are in 30 pendants, okay? And then the second type
actually classified and then we have studied is the feature linear digital analysis. And
then the third type is the linear support random machine. And then the fourth type is
the pending classification tree, okay? So given some training data, not always we can
learn a model, right? Actually we can learn all the four types of models, even five types,
including the naive base, right? We can actually build four models or five models based on
the given training data, okay? And the whole model performance of the model, okay? I think
that's a very important issue, right? And actually I mentioned before there is no free
launch theorem, okay? There is no single algorithm performed the best for all applications,
okay? So that means actually for each application and we need to build a few models, a few types
of models, then we try to find which one will perform the best, okay? Then we will adopt
that model for that specific dataset, okay? So perform the best. This is about the evaluation
of a model, okay? So today actually we are talking about actually a few model evaluation
procedure and also the model evaluation metrics, okay? The first evaluation metric is called
the evaluation procedure called holdout method. So in this tree holdout method, so part of
the data, part of the data, right? We will be used as testing data. We will be head
off and we will be used as testing data. Then the remaining part of the data will be used
as a training data, okay? So this is the holdout method. This diagram just shows this actually
in a process, a procedure, okay? So given a dataset, yeah, we have a full dataset, right?
And we divide the dataset into two, actually, you know, subsets, okay? One subset is called
a training data, okay? And then another subset, the remaining subset is the testing data,
right? In the holdout method, then we see the holdout, right? That means this testing
data is head off and will not be used for the model training, okay? And then based on
the training data and based on the learning algorithm, right? And we can build actually
a model for the classification that is just a pen and classifier, okay? So we get a model.
And then, of course, we can use this model to predict the class labels of the testing
data, okay? And then we can compare, you know, actually the prediction of the testing data
and also the true, you know, label of the testing data. So based on this comparison,
we can give some evaluations. So that is an evaluation, actually, you know, matrix. So
later we will talk about that, okay? So the procedure is that, is talking about how to
divide the data, right? So here we divide data into two types, okay? Normally, actually,
like 70 to 80 percent of the data will be used as a training, then 20 to 30 percent of the data
will be used as a testing, okay? In other words, given a data set, okay, we randomly select 70
percent to 80 percent of the data, okay? And this part of the data will be used as a training
data to build a model, okay? Then the remaining part, right? The remaining part, actually,
will be used as testing data, okay? So the training data and also the testing data, actually,
are randomly selected, right? Randomly, actually, selected from the given data set, okay? So this
is, it is actually a whole other method and we just see, this is, now we just see that data is
divided into two parts, right? But frequently, actually, we divide the data into three parts,
okay? Training data, validation data, then testing data, okay? And then, of course,
actually, no, the training data will be the majority of the data, right? Training data,
okay? And then, actually, we will have this, actually, the validation data is used to
measure the model performance during training stage, okay? So I will elaborate this further,
okay? And then, actually, the second data, the test data is used after training, okay? So actually,
the validation data can be considered as a part of the training data, okay? For example,
in the assignment, right? I give you the training data, actually, you can use part of the training
data as a validation data, okay? And so why, how this validation data is used, okay? And actually,
this validation data is often used to determine the hyperparameters, hyperparameters of the model,
of the learning algorithm, okay? And for example, right, in the last, I think, just last week,
we started the classification tree, right? And actually, the size of the model is a very important
issue, right? We need to determine the size of the model. And normally, with no, no, either
pentacletic tree, now, we have two processes, right? Two phases. The first phase is the
construction, growing of the tree. And then the second stage, or second phase is actually the
perium of the tree, the custom of the branch, right? So that actually, we can keep the model small,
okay? And so, actually, I think one important parameter in the growing stage is that, so when
we should stop the growing process, right? We have some criteria. That is, when a node has less
than 10 data sets, for example, less than 10 data samples, and then we can stop, okay? All we know,
if the node just contains actually, no, less than five samples, then we can stop, okay? And
actually, these five, and these 10, actually, are called hyperparameters. Before, you train the model,
before you grow the tree, you need to preset these values. These kind of parameters are called
hyperparameters. And these parameters could be determined by the so-called validation data,
okay? You first use the training data to grow the tree, right? And then you determine when to stop
by based on the performance, actually, on the validation data. And another example of that,
is linear support by the machine, right? You remember. And actually, no, for in several scenarios,
and actually, we introduce a select variable, right? Then in the loss function, cost function,
and we have two parts. The first part, actually, is the square of the norm of the W, okay? Because
this part is inversely proportioned to the margin of separation, right? If we want to
maximize the margin of separation in the small one machine, and then we should keep, actually,
the norm of the W, or square norm of the W as small as possible, okay? Then we have the second
part in the loss function, if you remember, right? I see times the summation of all the select
variables. Actually, this is the hyperparameter. When you train the tree, I mentioned before training,
you need to set these values, preset these values. This is also actually called hyperparameter, okay?
How to determine a suitable value? We have no idea. Normally, the default value is one, but one,
the default value, one does not mean the one is the best, right? So that is just when you don't
know how to select, you can use these values, see as one. But we normally want to actually select
a suitable value of C, right? How to select? Normally, we want to set C to different values,
right? Then we can get a few, you know, small-watt machine models, right? Then we test the
performance on the validation data. Then we see our corresponding to which C the performance
is the best on the validation data. Then we will use the model on that C, right? Based on that C.
Okay, so this is the training, right? And also, actually, I think when we talk about the
base decision rule, and actually, sometimes we know that data is not from one single Gaussian
function, right? We need to use a few Gaussian functions to build the class-continental probability
function. And if you remember, we assume m, right? m is a number of Gaussian components in the class
kind of density function. Okay, so how many we should use? Actually, this is a hyperparameter.
Actually, before training, right, you need to give the value of m. So this is a hyperparameter.
So this hyperparameter should be determined based on the, actually, the validation performance on
the validation data. Okay, if you know, some of you know neural networks, right? And neural
networks, actually, normally, it's based on the differential linear, right? Sequential linear,
the length step by step, actually. And normally, the neural networks, like the deep neural networks,
is oversized. Okay, oversized, that means, actually, there are two successive number of
neurons or parameters in the model. And in other words, the model could easily overfit the training
data. Okay, so how to actually avoid this problem? Actually, normally, we can use the so-called
early stopping of the training process. Okay, and I want to stop. So, actually, normally, we should
determine, actually, when to stop based on the performance on the validation data. Okay, so
normally, this validation data is very important. In practice, we need to divide the data into three
parts, right? And then the proportion for the three parts, normally, you know, 70% or 60%,
70% for training, 15% to 20% for validation, which is validation, actually, which means, actually,
we use this part of the data to determine the values for the hyperparameters. Okay, and then
we use the remaining 15% to 20% esthetic data. Okay, so this is the whole automaton. And this
diagram just shows this process, right? So, first, actually, we train the model, right? We train the
model based on the training data. Okay, and then we evaluate the model performance based on the
validation data, right? And if the data, validation data, the performance is not very good. And then
probably, now, we take the model according to, actually, you know, results on validation data.
You take the model, that means, actually, you train the parameter of the model a bit. How do
you get that? That is just you change the hyperparameters. Okay, you change the model size,
and then you can get a different result, right? You change the value of C, you get a different set
of parameters for the linear support animation, and then you can get the performance. In other
words, actually, we need to actually go through a few iterations. Okay, and you want to get a good
value of C, right? For linear support animation, or get a good value of the model size in the
classification tree. Okay, all these, actually, are determined based on the performance of the model
on the validation data. Okay, so once, actually, the both-space model is selected based on the
performance on the validation data, and then, actually, we can just actually use this model
to predict the levels of the testing data. Okay, so this is the use of the validation data, right?
And then, the model training and validation. Okay, so this is the first method and the whole
automata. And in the whole automata, I just mentioned, the data actually collected randomly, right?
Randomly, okay, 70% or 280% or 70% or 60% to 70% for training, randomly selected. The random
selection remaining, actually, or part of the data is the validation, then part of the data is the
testing. Okay, and that could be an issue. That could be an issue, right? And the one issue that,
actually, in some applications, actually, some class, actually, the so-called small class,
small class, that means the number of samples is very limited for that small class. Okay, and
so if we still use the random selection, right, random selection, there is a possibility that,
actually, the proportion, right, of training data for different classes, okay, this proportion
is different from, actually, the proportion of the data in the overall data, the proportion of
the different classes in the overall data. Okay, for example, if, actually, in the full data set,
one small class, only accounts for 10% of the data. If the data is small, 10%, for example,
just like 20 data set, 20 data samples, 10%, right? And if you randomly select samples,
maybe there's a possibility, okay, only a very few, like five samples are selected from that small
class. Okay, so that means the proportion in the training testing of the small class, right,
is very different from the proportion of that class in the overall data set. Okay, and so in order
to address this problem, and we can use, actually, the so-called, actually, a stratified random
sampling, stratified random sampling, okay. So in this method, actually, the data divided into
different groups, of course, here, the data actually already divided into different groups,
right, based on the class label. For class one, class two, class three. Okay, so we want to see,
I want to see 60% of the data as a trained data, right? Then, okay, from class one,
we randomly select 60% of the data. For class two, we randomly select 60%. And then for class,
the small class, class three, for example, right, actually, we still select 60% of the data.
Okay, and then for validation, then for testing, the same. So by this stratified random sampling,
so we make sure, actually, the proportion of different classes in the training validation
testing data, actually, the same as the proportion of the data in the overall data set.
Okay, so this is called stratified random sampling. Actually, the sampling, actually,
the very important technique. And actually, you know, in the statistics, actually, there are a lot
of studies because statistics, actually, and one of the researchers, the area is like a sampling,
how to perform sampling, right? So one of the sampling methods is just called stratified,
actually, the random sampling. Sampling, I just mentioned, is important, right? Sometimes,
you watch the news, right, TV, the news, and particularly the news about the election in the
certain countries, right? And actually, before the election or during the process of the election,
right, they do some survey, and then they can get some prediction of the election results, right?
And actually, sometimes we see that actually, this result is very accurate. Why not these results
to be very accurate? Before election, we have to do a survey, right? After the election, we have a
result. So this result, actually, could be very close. This means, actually, the survey, this
process is very important. How to select the samples based on these representative samples
and to predict the result. I think this is very important, right? Sampling, actually,
need to select representative samples, okay? And actually, so that means, actually,
when we actually select samples for training, right, for training of a model, and the samples
should also be representative. Okay. And if samples are very different from the,
the training data is very different from the testing data, and then the performance could be
very bad. There's something like that, okay? So we started these, right? And then in the exam,
actually, I tested you in your network, the deep learning, right? So training, learning,
very different from the final exam, right? So certainly, you cannot get a very good result
in the final exam because actually, they are different, okay? So, so this means that training,
right, the testing should be similar, should be similar. It's very different. That means,
actually, the data is out of the mean, out of the mean, okay? Normally, the performance is very
bad, actually. Okay. So we should try our best, actually, to select the representative samples
as a training data, okay? And then the performance, the generalization performance on the testing
data could be good. Okay. So this is the first method. And then, actually, another issue with
whole the automatic is that the random selection, right, random sampling, 70%
cc panel training, then what are the different testing, right? So every time, actually, when you
do the sampling for training, what are the different testing, actually, the result will be
different. Result will be different. Okay. In particular, if the training data size is not
very big, if the data is not very big, you will randomly select. And then, actually, the model,
actually, you will get a different model. Okay. And then, which model performance should we use?
Okay. So which performance should we use to see, as an evaluation for this training model?
And, actually, we should use the so-called repeated whole the automatic. And, actually,
we should repeat this experiment many times. Then, we take the average.
I think these are actually easy to understand, right? And many of you will take the exam,
that TOEFL, right? And, I see some of you take a few times. Okay. Then, you know, sometimes,
actually, you're very lucky, right? The question you have seen in the test, actually,
very similar to the one you have practiced. Okay. Then, you can get good results. But,
sometimes, actually, you are unlucky, you get a bad result. So, which result could reflect, actually,
your capability? Actually, I think the average, right? So, I think the idea is similar. Okay.
We should actually perform the so-called repeated whole the automatic. Okay. And, so, we will repeat
this kind of experiment. Random select 70% or 60% of the training, the 25 validation,
and the 25 testing. Then, we look at the performance testing, right? And, then, we will repeat this
experiment. And, when you, in the second experiment, when you select random samples, right, from the
given, from the overall data, certainly, the data you obtain will be different from the first
experiment. And, also, the model you build will be different. Okay. Then, the performance on
testing data will also be different. Because, the model is changed. The data also changed. Okay.
So, finally, we should take the average of all performance. So, that will give a justified or
fair evaluation of the learning performance. Okay. And, actually, sometimes, actually,
we can see, like, you know, the public paper, even paper public, right? And, mainly, maybe,
right experiment for many times. And, then, they just shoot the best results. But, actually, this
is, actually, kind of cheating, right? This is not right. This is wrong. Okay. In order to give a
justified fair evaluation, we need to repeat this experiment for many times. Okay. And, then,
we take the average. Okay. So, this is just a, you know, repeated holdout method. Repeated holdout.
Okay. Okay. So, the next, actually, the evaluation method is the so-called
care food cross validation. Care food cross validation. Okay. So, this, actually, is also,
actually, I think, is a more commonly used validation method or performance evaluation method. Okay.
And, in this care food cross validation, the data is divided into care food, care or care path.
This is one food, just part of it. Right? Care food. And, normally, each of the food, actually,
have the same or similar number of samples. Similar because, for example, you have 100,
like, zero-nose samples, right? And, then, you view the care food cross validation. You divide
the data into 10, 10 food, right? Or 10 parts. And, some of the part, some part of the data will
have 10 samples. But, some of them will have 11 samples. Okay. So, basically, you know, the number
of samples in each order should be the same or similar. Okay. So, divide them into many foods.
So, this is care food. In many, care can take different values, right? Can take, you know,
five or 10, right? You can also take other integer values. But, commonly used, and then, value for
care, five or 10. Okay. And, then, actually, we will repeat the experiment for care times.
This is something like the repeated hood out method, right? In the repeated hood out, we repeat the
experiment for many times. But, here, in the care food cross validation, we repeat the experiment
for care times, for care times. Okay. And, every time, we use one of the food, actually,
actually, testing data. Then, the remaining care minus one food is the training data.
Okay. So, the experiment number one, actually, we can actually use the data in food one as the
testing data. Then, data in food number two, three, four, five, actually, as the training data.
Then, in the second experiment, we use the data in food number two as the testing data. Then,
the data in number one, number three, number four, number five will be as the training data. Okay.
So, repeat the experiment, actually, care times. Okay. And, then, we take the average,
we take the average of the care experiments. So, this average, actually, result will be reported,
actually. Okay. So, as the final result, okay. So, this is, actually, the care food cross validation.
It's a repeated experiment, right? And, repeat care times. And, each time, we use different food
as the testing data. Then, the remaining data will be used as the training data.
So, if we can actually compare this, actually, with, actually, the care and the whole automated,
either whole, repeat the whole automated, actually, each time, actually, you have a
part of the data as the testing data, right? But, before, between different experiments,
actually, we could have some overlaps. Okay. Because the sample are randomly selected, right?
And, some of the testing samples will be used a few times as the testing data. But, in the
care food cross validation, the one data, one sample is used only once as the testing data.
Only once. Okay. So, this is care food cross validation. And, so, here, I'll give one example,
like five food, five food, right? So, and so, the, either, is prime number one or,
et cetera, et cetera number one, we use this food number five as a testing, right? One, two, four,
as a training. And, after that, actually, we can have an error. We can have evaluation, right?
Of the error rate, for example. How many errors, how many samples are misclassified?
This error could be an error rate, percentage of the errors, or the number of samples that are
misclassified. So, this is the error, right? Then, similarly, the iteration number two or the
experiment number two, and the food number four is used as testing data. Then, we can also get a
result. Okay. So, that is error number two, error two. Okay. So, we get, finally, after repeats of
five, the five times, right? Then, we can get a five result, five errors. Then, we take the average.
Okay. So, it's, you know, it has some similarity with repeated care food, repeated care food.
But also, actually, it's a bit different, right? Because here, in the care food,
cross validation, actually, in each repeat of the experiments, and we use a different set of data as
testing data. Okay. No sample is used twice. None of them will be used more than once, right?
As a testing data. Okay. And, this is the care food cross validation.
And, that's actually, we will look at this, you know, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the
cross validation is a, a special case of the care food cross validation. And, in this, the, the,
the, the, the care is a care food cross validation. The care equals, actually, the number of samples.
If you have 100 samples, that means we divide the data into 100, you know, food. Each food contains
only one sample. So, this method is actually called, the one out cross validation. So, it's a
special case of the care food cross validation, where care equals to the number of samples.
Okay. So, this is a new one out. New one out. That means this one is used as testing. Then,
the remaining will be the training, right? So, we repeat this experiment n times. If then,
total number of samples is n, total number of training samples, right? n, then we repeat this
for n times. Okay. So, this is a new one out. Okay. And, I think the, the, the, the good thing is
this, actually, you know, if the data set is small, right? If data set is small, and actually,
we only use a part of the data as a training data, training data. Something like, you know,
some resources has to be wasted. Although, you know, the willow was resources are very limited.
The number of samples. Okay. In the leave out one out method, we use a, only one sample is a testing.
All the remaining, right? We'll be used as training. So, this is a good thing. Okay. And, of course,
this method normally is, this is practical. Only when the number of samples is small,
and maybe like a few hundred samples, it's small, right? Then, you can repeat 100,
a few hundred times. Okay. And, so maybe, you know, nowadays, actually, if the data is very big,
right? It's very big. And, you need to train a very big, you know, deep neural model. And then,
this method could be time, very time consuming. Time consuming. Because a training of one
deep learning model could take, you know, some time. If you repeat this for, you know, many times,
right? If the data is big, and then, I think this method is not practical. But the data is
so small, actually, I mean, we should use this method. We can use this method. Okay. Although,
nowadays, we talk about big data, right? Of course, if the data is from the Internet,
from the open source, I think there are no problems for us to collect the data. But actually,
in many applications, actually, the data is very limited. Very limited. Okay. And, for example,
in medicine, right? If you want to study a certain kind of disease, okay. First, actually,
sometimes, the number of patients is very limited. Okay. And, you don't have that number, right?
You don't have the big data. You don't have a limited number of patients. Second, actually, even
you have the number, you know, a relative, you know, big number of patients. But the collection of
the data is also costly. Very costly. Okay. And also, actually, also probably because of the
privacy issue. And some patients don't want to relate their personal data, their data to you,
right? So, finally, you only get a limited number of samples. Actually, even if I find that, actually,
this could also be the number of samples is very limited. Very limited. Okay. So, small data,
it's a very practical problem. Although nowadays, we all talk about big data, right? But actually,
many, many applications scenarios, we still have very limited data. So, we can still use this kind
of lay one out and cross validation. Okay. So, another is called a care food, repeated care food.
So, food automated, and then we have the repeated, actually, you know,
food automated for care food cross validation. And also, we have the repeated care food cross
validation. So, why we need to repeat this? And actually, we see, just now we see
all the samples, right? Compared with the food automated, actually, each of the samples is only
used once as a testing data. Okay. But actually, all the, because some of the data, but the data in
one food will be always, will always be used as a training or testing together. Sometimes,
this set of data in one food will be used as training. Okay. And sometimes, they will be used as a
testing. They're always together, right? Always together. Okay. And actually, if you,
actually, normally, you know, the division of the food, the data, based on the sequence,
from sequence number, sequence number one, number two, right? Okay. So, this is the first,
you know, care, you know, like 10 percent, if you care food cross validation, then the next 10 percent,
then the next 10 percent. So, the division of the food will be followed, will follow this way.
Okay. But if the data, actually, sequence is different, and then the, actually,
this kind of division of the data will be different. Actually, you will find that the result will be
very different. Okay. So, this, actually, in other words, actually, the testing performance depends
on how you arrange the data. Actually, something is not justified, right? It's not justified.
So, how to avoid this problem? Actually, we can use the so-called repeated care food cross
validation. Okay. So, maybe at the beginning, we just based on the given sequence of the data,
right? To divide them into, like, care food, and then we perform, you know, this,
you know, care food cross validation. Okay. And then, you know, we can repeat the experiment,
this care food cross validation, by reshuffling the data. After one care food cross validation,
we reshuffle the data, change the sequence of the data. Then again, from number one,
until, you know, 10% training, first food, and then the next, you know, 10%, 10% second food,
right? So, every time we reshuffle the data. Okay. By this way, some of the data, you know,
this problem, we mentioned before, always will be used as a training or testing, right? This
problem will be solved. Okay. And actually, if you, actually, you know, I have the experiment,
actually, I run this experiment, actually, sometimes the performance difference could be huge.
Okay. In one or ten, the care food cross validation, although we repeat care times, right? We call
this actually one care food cross validation. The result, maybe, like, the good performance is 70%.
And then in some scenario, the extreme case, actually, in another round of the experiment,
right, if I reshuffle the data, the performance maybe only, like, you know, 80%.
That is a very significant difference, 70% accuracy, 80% accuracy. This is,
really, not 10% is significant. Okay. You know, in machine learning classification, right? And
actually, if a performance, actually, the difference is like over 0.5%, this can be considered as a
significant. I remember when a few students asked me questions, or I turned this, actually,
this won't affect the performance. So, I say, you see, won't affect the performance. So, what's
the difference? Or see a difference, like, 3% or 2%? Actually, that's a very significant difference.
Okay. Now, this, you probably saw paper, right? You see my performance, actually,
is better than the state of art by 0.5%. So, 0.5% is considered a significant improvement,
right? But now, actually, because you use the data differently, right, you get a
performance difference of 10%. That's a huge difference. Okay. So, to address this
problem, actually, we can wish we repeat this problem for many times. Okay. Then, actually,
we get the average. Okay. And sometimes, actually, when you read, you know, we said papers,
you see, for example, we see, for example, right, we see the performance, you know,
some like, you know, if the model, you know, if the increase the complexity of the model,
and then we, at the beginning of the model performance, improve. Okay. After a certain,
actually, you know, point, if you continue to increase the model complexity, that means the
model becomes larger and larger, right? Then the performance, actually, we are deteriorates.
We are deteriorates, right? So, that means we have better performance, right? But the
impractical, if you just run one, actually, kind of cross validation, right, you will never see
this phenomenon. You will see the data, actually, every time that the performance increase, and then
if you change the model, maybe decrease, then increase, decrease, you know, something through this.
I see an increase, the complexity of the model, at the beginning, the model performance, actually,
improves. Then after a certain point, decrease. But if you run the, you know,
repeat the careful combination of one time, then you can observe this. This is because every
is permanent. Actually, only one is permanent. The result is a random, result random. Because the
data sequence, right, randomly. Okay. So, the result will be, actually, this result is a random
value. Okay. And so, random, this is a random value, have a big, actually, virus. Big virus,
that means, actually, the data could be, the result could be changing in a, in a range, right, in a
range, very big range. But if you repeat this experiment many times, and then the range of the
change will be small. Okay. Then you can see a smooth curve after you, actually, get the average of
many, actually, repeats of the careful square validation. Okay. So, actually, my experiment,
that if you run the experiment, like careful, like 50 times, 50 repeats of careful square
validation, like 10-foot square validation, then you can see the result. Okay. And the model
performance improved, actually, at the beginning, with the increasing complexity, then decreased
after a certain point. If you continue to increase the complexity of the model. Okay. In other words,
actually, careful, like 10-foot, you already repeat the experiment 10 times. Then repeat the
careful 50 times. That means that you repeat the experiment 500 times. Okay. Then you can get a
reliable result, reliable evaluation. Okay. So, this is a repeated, actually, careful square
validation. And so, this is just, actually, the procedure of these repeated careful square
validation. So, the first, we set the repeat equals one, then we perform careful square
validation. So, in this part, we repeat this, we actually repeat this experiment care times,
right? 10 times. And then we let the repeat, and then resharp the data. These are very important
points. Resharp the data. You change the sequence of data. And then, again, the first part, 10%
first food, then that's 10% the second food, that's 10% actually, like that food. Okay. So,
every time to resharp the data, and then, okay. And you actually, a preset of values, like 50,
say, 50 repeats of careful square validation. And then finally, we take the average of all the
repeats, and then we repeat, you know, the, actually, this average of the repeats. Okay. So, this is
the, careful square validation, and the repeated careful validation. So, given my data set, so, how
we divide the data, right? And how we use the repeated experiment. So, this is the validation
procedure, right? Performing the evaluation, and the procedure. Actually, here we can use a different
method. Hold on, very simple, right? But the result is not reliable. Normally, we need to repeat the
experiment for many times. So, actually, like, repeat the careful. And then we have a repeat
holdout. Then we have a careful square validation. Repeat the careful square validation. And a
special case of the careful square validation is the lay one out. Okay. And then we know,
you know, repeat the lay one out, right? Because lay one, every time you just have one sample, right?
Actually, this is, we are not affected, actually, not affected by the sequence of the data. Okay. So,
there are no, no repeated lay one out. Okay. But they repeated careful square validation.
Okay. So, these are known, the model performance evaluation procedure. And that's actually, we look
at the performance evaluation metrics. Metrics, that means, actually, we need to give a number,
right? Give a number as an indication of the model performance. Okay. And so, these numbers are
all defined based on the four, actually, you know, results. The first is called a true positive.
True positive. So, here, actually, we have positive and negative, right? So, normally, you know,
I think in medical checkup, you know, quite often, you know, see, oh, something, you know,
some item of the testing is true. You are positive, positive, right? Normally positive, actually,
is something of concern, is something of our interest. Okay. So, this class normally is defined
as a positive class. Okay. Then, unimportant class is defined as actually, you know, a negative class.
Okay. So, we assume these are two class, kind of a problem. We have positive class, we have
negative class. Positive class normally is a class. And then, we have a strong interest in that.
Okay. And so, here, actually, we have defined four, actually,
results. Okay. First, here, we have a so-called true positive. Okay. These are positive,
okay. It means that the predation is positive. True positive. That means that ground truth is also
positive. Right. So, the predation is positive, the ground truth is positive. So, this means that
true positive. Okay. Positive. And then, the next, actually, is a false positive.
This is a positive, means that predation is positive. But, it is false. It is false, actually.
That means this is wrong, right? This means that the ground truth is negative.
So, this is called false positive. And similarly, for negative class, we can have a true negative.
That somehow is a negative sample. And the predation is negative. And then, this is a true negative.
Okay. And then, we have the false negative. The sample is a negative sample. But, you predict
this. It's a sample. Predation is a negative. But, the true label is a positive. So, this is called
false negative. Okay. So, actually, these are the four results. Based on these four,
as you know, minors, and then, we can first, I have the so-called confuring matrix.
Confuring matrix, actually, just list these now for minors. Okay. And so, here, actually,
you can look at the top. Okay. So, this means that the actual value, the ground truth. Okay.
So, ground truth could be positive, could be negative, right? Because we have a sample from
these two classes. And then, this left hand side here, this is this part that you show that you,
this is the prediction. Prediction. So, prediction is positive. Prediction is negative. Okay. If the
prediction is positive, and also the actual value, the ground truth is positive, then this is called
true positive. Okay. If the prediction is negative, here, right, prediction negative,
and the ground truth is negative. So, this means that this negative is true, right? It's a true
negative. Okay. And then, we have this, actually. So, these are true positive, true negative. That
means that the samples are predicted correctly. The prediction is correct, right? The prediction is
correct. Okay. But if these two scenarios, like false negative, false positive, the prediction
is positive. But the actual value is negative. Okay. So, this is called false positive. And then,
this is the false negative, right? The prediction is negative, but the ground truth is positive.
So, then, this is the false negative. So, this is actually the, on the diagonal, the diagonal
means that we are classified correctly. The number of samples correctly classified. Off-dark
angle, the number, means that the number, they are misclassified. So, this is called confluent
matrix. And actually, some of those, some of them, research paper, actually, in the top,
they give the predicted value. And then, this part is a true ground truth. But that does not
matter, right? As long as you correctly label this, these are actual, and these are the predictions.
Okay. Okay. So, this is the confluent matrix. Confluent matrix clearly shows, actually,
the samples, the number of samples that are correctly classified, right? Or wrongly classified.
Okay. So, these are things, I think, from this confluent matrix, we can get a lot of information,
right? Okay. So, these are just one example, right? And so, these are actual, positive,
actual negative. And these are predicted positive. So, 85 positive samples are correctly classified.
And the non-sample, negative samples are correctly classified. Okay. Then, we have
six samples, two plus six, four, right? That are misclassified or wrongly classified.
Okay. So, this is the confluent matrix. So, based on this, you know, the four measures,
true positive, actually, you know, false positive, true negative, false negative. And then, we can
define the following matrix as a performance, actually, evaluation matrix. Okay. And then,
the first one is called accuracy. Accuracy shows how percentage of samples that are correctly
classified. Okay. So, first, we need to calculate how many samples are correctly classified.
So, these include the true positive and true negative. And then, you want to give the total
number of samples. So, this is the percentage, right? This is the ratio. It's just called accuracy,
accuracy. Accuracy is the proportion of correctly classified samples. So, the numerator part is
the total number of samples that are correctly classified, right? True positive, true negative.
And then, you want to give the total number of samples, all the data in the number of data,
you know, in the confluent matrix. Okay. So, this is, okay. So, in this example,
and the correctly classified sample, actually, number, you call it 85 plus 9, right? So, 94.
And the total number of samples, actually, is 100. So, it's accuracy is 94 percent.
Okay. So, this is one measure. And another measure is called error rate. The percentage of the
sample data are misclassified. Okay. And so, here, first, we need to find out what is the total
number of misclassed samples. Okay. And then, we look at the percentage, right? Divided by the
total number of samples. Okay. So, in this example, the two, the misclassed samples, actually, are
those off-diagonal, right? One is four, another is two. So, the summation is six. So, among these
100 samples, six are misclassified. And then, the error rate is 6 percent. So, you know,
accuracy plus error rate is just 100 percent. Okay. So, but sometimes, you know, we use error
rate. Sometimes, actually, we use accuracy. But if you know accuracy, you immediately know error
rate, right? Because this is just, actually, the summation is 100 percent. Okay. And so,
this is the one measure. Another type of a measure, actually, are the sensitivity and the specificity.
Specificity. Okay. So, these are the, another two measures. Okay. What is sensitivity? And actually,
selectivity, sensitivity, actually, is something that measure, actually, for positive samples.
Okay. Sensitivity class measure is a measure of the proportion of positive samples that have been
correctly classified. Okay. In other words, among all the positive samples, how many are correctly
classified as positive? So, this is sensitivity, right? This is sensitivity.
So, so this means that true positive, correctly classified positive samples,
over the total number of positive samples. Total number of positive samples, including,
includes those classified positive, right? And also includes those, actually, you know,
classified negative. Okay. So, it's a false negative plus the true positive. I treat the denominator
here, it's just a total number of positive samples. Sensitivity, right? So, I think it's easy to
understand this sensitivity. For example, we have one kind of detection technology for a certain
concept, for example, right? And sensitivity, that means that whether this is a machine,
this is an equipment, this device, or this measure can identify the conception. Okay. So, that means,
among all the positive kinds of patients, all the positive kinds of patients,
the percentage that are correctly detected. So, that is sensitivity, right? So, the true
positive divided by total number of positive samples. So, this is called sensitivity.
Then another measure, you know, is here is called specificity, specificity. Okay. So,
this actually is talking about the negative class. So, sensitivity about positive, right?
This is about negative class. Okay. So, among all the negative classes, the samples,
how many actually are correctly classified negative? So, this should be equal to the
true negative, right? That means that negative samples are correctly classified divided by
total number of negative samples. Okay. These numbers include two parts. One is a true negative,
another is a false positive. False positive, that means the prudential positive, but this is wrong.
Actually, the true label is negative. Okay. So, these contain these two parts, right?
False positive and also the true negative. So, this actually, the denominator here
is the total number of negative samples. And then the numerator here is the
number of negative samples that are correctly classified as negative.
So, this is a real show, right? So, in the, this example, as you can see, for a negative class,
right? So, this is a true negative. So, together, we have 13 samples, 13 samples, right? This is
actual negative, the ground truth negative, 4 plus 9, 13. But among the 13th negative samples,
only 9 of them are correctly classified. So, the specificity is a 9 over 4 plus 9, right?
So, this is the specificity. Okay. Okay, next, actually, we will have a 10-minute break.
So, at the break, we talk about the other measures. Okay.
So,
measures. And so, these are called, actually, precision recall. Okay. And then,
free precision recall are more commonly used under the selectivity, sensitivity and specificity.
Okay. And precision gives the proportion of positive prediction, which are truly positive.
You give a look at all the positive predictions, right? Look at all the positive predictions.
And then, you check, actually, whether the ground truth, actually, is positive.
So, this is the precision. Okay. So, the true positive divided by the total number of positive
predictions. Okay. So, positive predictions are like a true positive or false positive.
Okay. So, among all the positive predictions, among all the positive predictions,
how many samples, or the percentage of samples that are truly positive. So, that is the precision.
Okay. Okay. So, above example, right, we look at all the positive predictions, among all the
positive predictions. So, the prediction positive, actually, here, we have 85.
And also, we have actually the four, right? So, these are 89 samples, actually,
predicted as a positive. Okay. So, among all these, actually,
89 predictions as a positive. So, how many are truly positive? Only 85. So, then, the
precision is 85 divided by the total number of positive predictions. So, 89. Okay. So,
this is called a precision. So, among all the positive predictions,
so, the percentage of truly positive, actually, samples. Okay. So, this is a precision. Okay.
And another measure is called recall. Okay. Recall is, you know, measure the
proportion of a correctly prediction of positive samples to the total number of positive.
Among all the true positive samples, among all of them, so, how many are correctly detected?
That means how many of them, actually, or the percentage of them that are correctly predicted
or detected? Okay. So, this is true positive. This is the number of
prediction, correct, as a positive. Right. Then, you are doing the total number of positive samples.
And, actually, this is recall, actually, is the same as the sensitivity. Okay. So, among all the
true positive samples, how many are actually correctly classified? Or percentage that are
correctly classified? So, this, actually, recall, actually, is the same as the sensitivity.
Right. Sorry. It's the same as the, yes, the sensitivity. Okay. So, this is the recall. Okay.
And it's about the positive class. So, here, recall is about positive class. Right. And,
actually, the precision is also the positive class. Okay. But, actually, the precision is,
among all the predictions as a positive, the percentage of samples that are truly positive.
So, this is the precision. Recall. Among all the positive samples, the percentage that are truly
positive. Okay. So, these are the recalls. So, these are the two different concepts. Okay. And,
that's actually, actually, I use one extra example to explain this concept. Okay. So,
these are multiple choice problems. And, actually, we have four answers. Actually, our task is to
pick all the, actually, you know, the positive, correct answers from these four answers, right,
four statements. Okay. And so, the first one has a male-female student. So, certainly, these are,
I think, the correct answer. Right. These are correct statements. Okay. And then, the second,
class, the complex student from multiple countries, I think, that's also a correct statement.
Right. And, we have students from multiple countries. And, all students, our PhD students,
certainly, these are wrong statements. And, then, the last one, the two-seater lecturers
in this lecture theater. Right. These are also correct. Okay. So, we have four statements,
but three are correct. Right. So, now, our task is to pick all the correct statements from the four.
Okay. So, then, we look at what is, you know, under different scenarios, what is the precision,
what is the recall. Okay. The first case, the, so, if you pick only one answer, right, and this
answer is A, you just get A. A is my answer, right. A, or B, or D, right. You only collect
one answer. This answer is correct. Okay. Then, based on the, actually, the, based on the,
you know, the definition of the precision, right, precision, but for all the, you know,
the positive predictions, so, here, for all the, you know, picked correct answers, correct
statement. So, how many are truly correct? Okay. So, you pick one, and this one is correct. So,
the precision, actually, the precision here is 100%. Pick only one, right. The precision,
actually, is 100%. Because the prediction is one, and it is truly one, right. The prediction is
correct. And then, then, this answer, indeed, is correct. Okay. So, actually, your precision is 100%.
But recall, here, that, actually, among all the positive sample, among all the correct answers,
how many are correctly picked up? Only one. Then, the recall is one, that. Okay. So, if you just,
like, one correct answer, then the recall is very low. Then, the precision is very high.
Okay. And really, the recall, truly, is something like, to matter, actually, how much you have
missed, right. How much you have missed. The percentage of the answers, actually, have missed.
Okay. And then, actually, if you collect, actually, all the four answers, I see all the four, no, four
seem are correct. Okay. So, among these four, all positive predictions, so, how many, actually, are
correct, are correct, all right. So, then, in such a scenario, actually, the recall is very high.
Among all the positive predictions, right, and among all the previous predictions,
how much are truly, actually, positive. So, here, recall 100%. But the precision is low.
It's 375%. Okay. So, when you are, just correct, one answer, but you missed something, right.
Then, the precision is high, but the recall is low. Okay. If you pick all the answers, right,
certainly, continue all the correct answers. In such a scenario, the precision is low, but
recall is high. Okay. So, this may actually, one measure, does not see anything, right.
And one measure is not sufficient, actually, to give a fair evaluation of the performance of the
model. So, maybe we should combine the two together. Or, at least, we should look at the two, right.
Not just based on one precision, or recall. Okay. But, of course, actually, in some applications,
actually, we can emphasize one measure or another one. Sometimes, actually, we show the tree,
you know, just to get one answer. The answer is correct, right. Then, that's enough. Okay.
And, for example, you know, when one, some event happens, right, we have a lot of news
published on the website, right. Actually, maybe, if you just get one news, right,
that is about that event, that is sufficient. Okay. You just get one. That is correct. Okay.
But, in some scenarios, we don't want to miss anything, right. Then, we should actually,
you know, put more emphasis on the recall. We should not miss the information. Okay. So,
this is, but, actually, normally, the two should be used, actually. Both of them should be used.
And then, actually, if you pick, actually, ABD, all the three answer are picked, right. Then,
the precision is 100 percent. And, also, the recall is 100 percent. Okay. So, this is the best,
no. This is not the best result, right. The best result. The 100 percent for recall, 100 percent
for precision. Okay. So, normally, no, I just mentioned, we need to combine the two, right.
So, that is just the so-called, actually, F score or F1 score. Okay. We combine the two. Okay.
And, so, precision times recall. And then, divide by precision plus recall. We don't emphasize one
or another one, right. Actually, they consider them equally for the two measures, because we look at
the multiplication. Okay. One high, one low, right. Then, the multiplication, the multiplication,
per die is low. Okay. And, so, with times two, y times two. And, because of my precision, one,
recall the one, and then, divide by one times one, right. Then, you get the 0.5. But, if you
time two, then, the value will be, actually, very high, right. But, be one. Okay. So, the F score,
normally, should be in a range, maybe, from zero to one, to, if one of them, the precision recall,
one of them is wrong, right. The zero. Then, you can get a zero. So, the value should be in the
range from zero to one. The one is the best. The larger the F, the better the performance.
Okay. So, we take the two measures into one, actually, you know, matrix. Okay. So, that is F score.
Okay. So, now, you probably wish that paper, right. So, normally, we provide the result of F score.
Okay. All you provide, that both, all the three measures, right. The precision,
as you recall, and also, the F score. Also, if you just need to provide one, right, then, that is F score.
Okay. Because F score combines the two measures, right. Two matrices into one single, actually,
matrix. Okay. So, this is the F score. These are the, okay. And so, in the, in the above example,
right, just now, we have an example in case one, actually, you know, we know precision one, right,
about the, the recall, you know, one dot. Okay. Then, we have the, to the F score, zero point five,
is a low value, right. Then, the second scenario, actually, that recall is, is, is, is, is, is,
recall is high, by the precision is low, right. So, then, the result is upon eight. And then,
the, the case, actually, 100 percent for recall, 100 percent for precision, then, the F score equals
one. Okay. So, this is the largest value, actually, the larger the, actually, this F, normally, the
better the performance. Okay. The best result is F equals one. Okay. So, this is the precision,
and the recall, actually, which are commonly used, including the, actually, F score, a commonly used.
Okay. The next, actually, is called, actually, we have, we call the receiver operating characteristic,
actually, curve, ROC curve. And then, we have a matrix, that's so-called, actually, area and the
curve. They're not frequently used, but sometimes, actually, we, we, we use this. Okay. And so,
conventionally, when we make decisions, right, for example, in the basic decision rule, and we
basically put a posterior probability to make decisions, right. So, actually, we assume, actually,
we assume, actually, 50 percent as a threshold value. Okay. If one probability is higher than
0.5, right, 0.5 is a threshold value, right. And then, actually, another one will be less than 0.5,
okay, or 50 percent, right. So, so, actually, 0.5, actually, is used, actually, as a threshold,
okay, actually, so, implicitly, okay. Again, our mind, actually, we use this, okay. And then,
either, support one machine, for example, right, actually, we use zero as a threshold value. Okay.
If this, the logistic function value is greater than zero, then belong to class five, right.
The negative, less than zero, then belong to class two, or minus one, okay. So, with zero,
the threshold values, okay. But, actually, sometimes, actually, zero, or zero.5, you know,
there's a one in the middle, right, in the middle point, is not actually, maybe not be the best,
actually, the threshold value. Okay. Sometimes, actually, for example, you have a, like, a detention
of a cancer, right. For example, I need a screening of the cancer, right. And, actually,
as long as maybe you have a 40% of the probability that person may have a cancer, right, not 50%,
maybe 40%. And then, maybe, we will suggest that this person should go for further,
further examination, right. Right, now, we don't use zero.5, actually, instead, we use zero.4,
right. Okay. So, this, actually, then, so, not, actually, we should not always use, actually,
like, zero, or zero.5, as the threshold values. So, the receiver operating characteristic curve,
it just, actually, something, they show the performance, actually, when the threshold value
is, threshold is set to different values. For example, only the, you know, the, the, the
different function value is greater than 0.5. Then, you see the positive class. Okay. And,
even less than, actually, 0.5, actually, we are not considered as a positive example. Although,
implicitly, we assume, as long as the discrete function is greater than zero, and then it's
class one. Okay. So, if you use, actually, of course, different threshold values, right,
and then, actually, you can have different performance. Okay. And, actually, you can draw this,
actually, performance against, actually, performance, right, and, and the different, you know,
these are special values into, into such a diagram. And then, you can get a so-called ROC curve,
ROC curve. Okay. And, so, ROC curve, we first look at this. Okay. So, you have a tree horizontal here
is a false positive rate. And, the vertical here is a true positive rate. Okay. And, we have a E,
A, B, C, D, E, right. So, every value here corresponds to one threshold value. Okay. So,
threshold value A is set to one value, right. Then, we can have a performance of the
false positive rate. And, then, we can have a true positive rate. And, then, we, based on the two
on in it, as a coordinate, we can find one point, right. That's A. And, then, you set the threshold
value to another, threshold to another value, right. Then, maybe, you get a B. And, then,
you get a D, you get a C, D, right. So, these, finally, these are curve. These are called ROC curve.
Okay. So, these are true false positive rate, right, false negative rate. Okay. So, what are
the false positive, true positive rate? True positive rate, actually, is just a sensitivity,
is a recall. Okay. So, sensitivity recall. And, then, these are true positive rate.
True positive divided by the, all the positive. This is sensitivity. Okay. Also, actually, equal
to the recall. This value. Okay. And, then, the false positive rate, false positive divided by
total number of positive. Okay. So, these are true equal to one month specificity. Okay. So,
based on these, actually, two values, right. For every threshold value, now, we can have a
corresponding point, right. Then, we link the point. So, this point is just ROC curve. ROC
curve. Okay. And, after we sketch this ROC curve, and then, we can use the area and the curve,
AUC, as a measure, and for the performance evaluation. Area and the curve. Okay. And,
so, here, actually, an example, right. AUC equals one. Equals one. Right. Equals one.
Actually, even look at this, this rate, right. True false positive rate. So, here,
as most, actually, the value could be one, right. And, then, true positive rate, as this is the value
of one. And, then, actually, this is a square, right. The square. Then, the area of the square,
at most, actually, is one, right. At most, is one. Okay. So, one. Okay. And, then, if the AUC curve is
one, that means, actually, all the classifier able to provide, actually, able to classify the samples,
right. Correctly, no matter, actually, what actually, no threshold value you use. Okay. This is a
very special scenario. Okay. And, then, we have an AUC curve zero. The classifier will predict
all the samples, negative as a positive, and all the samples as a negative. This means,
you classify all the samples wrongly. Then, the AUC curve, actually, is zero.
Zero. Okay. And, then, actually, we normally have this, I know, like, zero point five. Zero point
five, actually, here, is through the tree. A random, a random, a random classifier, and a wood,
actually, you know, have this performance, zero point five, AUC curve. Okay. So, this is just the part.
This part, this curve, this line, this line here, this line here, right. You see this line, right.
This is a tree that corresponds to a random tree classifier. Okay. Then, you get a performance,
AUC curve zero point five. Okay. And, so, actually, the larger the, you know, the AUC,
the area under the curve, the better the performance, right. So, how can we get a larger AUC?
And, that means, actually, this AUC curve is far from the diagonal, you know, the three line, right,
far from that. Okay. So, this is something like that. So, this is a random classifier, you know,
this three line. Okay. Then, the further away from these three lines, the better the performance,
because the area under the curve would be greater, right, would be greater. If it's a line, for example,
the blue line here, right, is far away from these, you know, these three lines. So, the performance
are best here. Okay. Then, we have this green line, better, right. Okay. So, this is the, actually,
the ROC curve, right. ROC curve, yeah. Okay. And, so, also, area under curve. But, this is actually
better, not, these two, you know, ROC curve and also the, you know, the area under the curve, AUC,
actually, are not frequently used. But, sometimes, they, you know, they use, okay. And, sometimes,
when you write a paper, right, sometimes, actually, they ask you, actually, you know,
to look at this, you know, matrix and as a measure for your performance of your model. Okay. But,
the precision recall, I think, the most commonly used. Okay. Okay. So, these are the matrices we
can use to evaluate the performance, right, for the trained model. Okay. So, this is actually
first session and also until now, actually, we have talked about the evaluation of
Penn and Classified, right. And, so, this includes two parts. One is the evaluation of procedure,
how to divide the data, how to repeat the experiment, right. And, then, there's a second part about
the matrix that we can use, you know, to measure the performance of the model. Okay. So, necessary,
we will look at different topic. That is regression. Okay.
You remember, actually, you know, I think in the first class, we talked about the linear, right,
there are three categories. One is, you know, surprise, another is unsurprise, another thing,
that one is reinforcement linear, right. So, under the surprise linear, there are two that remain
some areas. One is called, actually, classification. And, then, another one called regression. Okay. So,
necessary, we will talk about regression. Of course, actually, in the area of machine learning,
the classification is a dominant topic. A regression is more studied, I think, in statistics,
statistics, right. Now, we see machine learning is an interdisciplinary, right.
It's a disciplinary. And, so, actually, many research can be considered as a work related to
the machine learning. So, regression is more studied in the statistics. Okay.
Regression is also, actually, also try to build a model and then build based on the model to predict
the values. Okay. And, classification is also the prediction, right, the prediction of class labels.
Okay. But, in classification, remember, in the class, we already talked about the difference
between classification and regression, right. In the classification, actually, the target variable
is just class label, right. The target variable class label only have limited values. For two
class class, we have two values, right. For class label, we have one opposite minus one, right.
We have these two values. Okay. And, all one are zero. Okay. So, just two. But, anyways,
these values are very limited. Okay. So, the class label or target variable is a discrete,
discrete. Okay. And, but in the regression, although it's again, it's a prediction, right,
prediction. But, actually, the target variable, actually, is a continuous variable. It's a
numerical variable that has many, many possible values. Okay. And, for example, we talked about the
score, right. Your score could be, actually, you know, it can be considered as a continuous
variable. Okay. And, then, the gender, right, the gender is just a two possible value, right.
Male or female. Okay. If we want to predict the gender, right, then this is a classification
problem. If you want to predict the score, the score, for example, the examination result,
the exam result, actually, the marks, this can be considered a continuous numerical. Then,
this can be considered as a regression problem. Okay. So, this is a difference, right. This is
a difference. The variables, the, you know, like, stop price, right. The price, you know,
is a continuous variable. Or, you see the numerical variable. Okay. So, if we want to predict this
kind of variable, then it's a regression problem. You want to, you know, predict, then it's a
Gorka variable, which has a limited number of values, right. Then, it's a classification problem.
Okay. So, previously, in the previous week, we have learned different methods of classification,
right. So, today, the next, actually, we are talking about regression. Okay. The first,
actually, we consider, okay, maybe I first go through this slide. Okay. So, regression, okay. We
have one, we have predict, right. Actually, in the classification, normally, we see we have many
samples, right. Then, in the space, we try to find a discerned boundary, right, to separate the
sampling of the two classes. What about the discerned boundary? Then, we see, oh, this sample
belongs to class one, or class two, right. Then, in the sample below this discerned boundary,
is a sample of another class. So, classification is a partition of the space into different part,
in different regions. Each part or each region corresponds to one class. Okay. So, this is
the classification. But, actually, regression is different. Regression is something like that. Okay.
We have one variable X, and we want to predict this way. Okay. And then, this prediction should be
very close to the true values, to the true values. So, normally, we see, we use this like a
diagram to illustrate the regression. Based on all the samples, we find a curve, or we find
a straight line, a linear regression, we find a straight line. And then, actually, all the points
actually are close to this straight line. So, this is regression. So, you can think about the
difference between classification, right, the geometric interpretation of the classification
and the regression. You find a straight line to separate the sample. That's classification, right.
So, here, you want to, based on a sample, find a line that passes through the samples, right.
That means that all the samples are very close to this line. This is regression. Okay. And the
regression tree, here, we can, can be linear or nonlinear. In this course, actually, we first
talk about the linear regression problem. Okay. Then, we will attach a bit of the nonlinear
regression problem. Okay. So, linear regression problem, that means, actually, we build a linear
model. So, linear model should be, this model is similar to the regression, to the classification
problem. We have y equals w transpose x plus, you know, w zero. Okay. So, this is regression.
If you look at the form, right, actually, I know that the linear equation always have the same form,
right. This is a linear equation. Okay. And, just to show you how to, you know, find the parameters,
right. Based on different problems, we have different ways to find the value for these linear
equations. Okay. And, okay. So, actually, in the regression, in the regression problem,
so normally, we have two type of variables. One type of variable called predictor variables.
So, this is just like in machine learning, these are called features or attributes. Okay. In this,
actually, regression, they are called predictor variables. All the time, they call independent
variables. Okay. Then, the target variable is called, actually, dependent variable, because
these variables depend on the independent variables. Okay. All these are called, these target variables,
or independent variable. So, these are the terms used in the regression, because these are
not regression, normally, studied in statistics. Okay. So, you know, the term, knowledge, I think,
here is different from those in machine learning. Okay. And, in the simple regression, linear regression,
we assume that there is only one variable, one predictor variable, x. Okay. And then, we use,
this is actually x to predict the y, which is a dependent variable. Okay. So, y equal to theta
zero plus theta one x plus epsilon. Okay. This theta one, just like w one, right, x plus w zero in the
classification, right. But, they use a different, actually, no, letter to denote. Okay. So, here,
we use theta zero, theta one. Okay. And, y is a target variable, or dependent variable, x is a
predictor variable, or independent variable. Okay. So, theta zero, theta one are the parameters of
this simple linear regression model. Okay. And, this epsilon here is residual, maybe the noise.
Okay. So, this is a simple linear regression. And, here, give an example, right. For example,
peasants, actually, the salary, right, could be related to the number of years of experience.
We assume there is a linear relationship, right. So, actually, we kind of, how to find this relationship,
how to find the value of theta zero, theta one, right. And, we need to get some samples.
Now, we can ask a few people, right. So, how many years have I worked in this area, right. So,
what is your salary? So, here, we can get one, two, three, four, right. And, seven samples.
Of course, just for illustration, normally, we need to get a hundred samples, right.
Based on the hundred samples, actually, we fit a line or linear equation. Okay. So, this is,
actually, the regression problem is also based on the super, is also a super linear,
because we also need to have the target value. In regression, we have no this kind of target
value, right, here, the salary. In classification, so, this is a class label.
A boot can be considered as a label data, right. So, it's a super linear.
Okay. Okay. So, this is actually a simple linear regression. And, of course,
if you know, in practice, normally, we need to use more than one per data variable, right.
Just like in classification, we need to use more than one feature. And, this feature could be,
number could be huge, right, in some applications. Okay. So, you, then, this is a linear,
multiple linear regression. That means we use a multiple per data variables.
And then, the model form, like this, y equals theta zero. There's zero, just like w zero in
the classification, right. Then, plus w y x1 plus w n2, w m xm. So, here, we use a theta to denote
the parameters. Okay. So, that's zero, theta one, and then, theta n. Okay. So, this is a multiple
regression, linear, because this is a linear equation. And, so, of course, that's just like
in classification. The central issue, the central issue is how to find the values for the parameters,
right, in the model, based on the training samples. For regression, the same. The central issue is
how to find the values for theta zero, theta one, theta m, based on the training samples.
Okay. So, in that situation, we will look at the way to find the value for these parameters,
theta zero, and theta m. Okay. And, actually, we, so, this is a method called the ordinary
least square estimation method. Okay. So, here, we assume we have n training samples, n, capital
n, right. And, so, this is actually, we have n pairs, right. So, each sample, we have the input,
we also have the target value. So, this is the, the same as, or similar to the normal
classification program, right. We have the feature vectors, and then we have the class label. So,
here, we also have the input vector, and then we have the, actually, or we see the predictor
variable vector, right. And, also, we have the target value. So, we have n pairs. Okay. So, the
input, of course, can be, you know, a vector, right. We assume, actually, the input, you know,
contains one to m variables. So, we have m predictor variables, right. Okay. So, this is xi for
sample number i. Then, the label is yi. Okay. And, then, we can write, you know, the yi in such a form
for sample number i, for sample number i. And, then, we can write this, actually, this formula.
This is a linear combination of all the variables, right, into the inner product of the two
vectors. So, this is the, you know, the parameter vector, right, theta 0, theta 1, and theta m.
So, these are the input vector. But, here, we put a 1, because theta 0 can be considered as a,
the input is a constant 1. You can consider x0 times theta 0, but x0 is just a constant 1.
Okay. Then, we have this representation, right. 1 always a 1, the first, because this corresponds
to 0. x0. Input x0, here, is a, it is 1. Okay. And, then, we have x1 and xm for the sample number i.
Okay. So, each sample, as we can be known, is in the inner product of these two vectors.
And, of course, this is theta 0, theta 1, theta m, common, right, for all the
samples. But, for different samples, we have a different input vector. Okay. So,
actually, we can summarize all these, you know, n samples into such a matrix equation,
matrix equation, right. So, this matrix equation, you can see this is, this part is still the
parameter vector, right, theta 0, theta 1, theta m. And, then, the first rule, it just corresponds
to the first samples. The input of the first sample, the input vector, right. And, of course,
we have a 1 extra 1, yeah. And, then, the second rule is the input vector for sample number 2.
Totally, we have n samples, right. So, with the nth rule, nth rule is the input vector for
sample number m, n. Okay. So, these vectors summarize all the input, the target variable,
right. So, the target variable vector. And, this is the matrix, input matrix. And, then, this is
the parameter vector. Okay. So, if we define this, you know, this actually is a y as a vector,
right. This is a matrix, phi. This is a theta. Okay. And, then, this actually, you know,
matrix equation can be expressed as this. y equal to phi times theta, actually, plus actually,
epsilon. Epsilon is also a vector. For different samples, now we have a different residual or error.
Okay. So, now, actually, we have, you know, have this expression, right. So,
necessarily, we need to find the values for this theta. Okay. And, actually, given the
training sample, the phi is known, right. The phi is known, actually, the y is known,
because, actually, these are the target values for the training sample, right. And, the phi is known,
and the theta is known. The phi is known, y is known. Theta is unknown. Okay. Our objective,
next, is to estimate the theta. How to estimate? Okay. First, we need to have some basic ideas,
right. Then, we can summarize this idea, actually, into an equation, right. This equation could be
used as a loss function for optimization. You will remember in the classification problem,
right. So, first, actually, we analyze the classification. So, what is, you know, is
expected for a good classifier. For example, in the support machine, and we show some analysis,
we show, actually, we found such a decision boundary so that the model of separation makes
a mark. Okay. Then, the classification problem is converting into an optimization problem.
We try to optimize, actually, the model of separation. Or we try to minimize the square of the
model of separation, the square of the norm, square norm of the w. Okay. Then, subject to some
constant. Okay. So, classification problem is summarizing into an optimization problem.
In Fisher linear adjustment analysis, I did the same, right. We see, oh, we want to find such a
w and so that the sample could be, have a small, actually, within class scatter, and
we're big, between class scatter. So, based on this concept, idea, then we summarize, actually,
a criterion, right. And then we try to find the parameter that could minimize, or maximize,
this criterion. Okay. So, this is a, this idea of solving this kind of question, right. For regression,
the same. So, what are the, our target? And we want to find such theta because we want to make
prediction, right. And we want to find such theta so that the prediction of the way is
very close to the true way, to the true way, right. And how close, how to measure they are
close. Actually, we can use the difference. In other words, actually, we hope that the, the, the
difference between the prediction and the, the true values of way could be minimized,
could be minimized. Okay. So, how to measure the difference? Of course, actually, we can use
the, the square of the difference, right. This is the difference. Actually, y is a true value,
right. Other way, we have theta, we, theta is a prediction. So, this is the difference.
Difference, just actually the sigma i, right. We use square. For every sample, there is a
prediction error. The error is just the, the epsilon, epsilon, right. Epsilon i is for
sample number i. We hope this error could be as small as possible. Could be as small as, could
be close to zero. Close to zero, that means it could be, actually, we don't care whether it's a
positive, it's greater than zero or negative, it's a small than zero, right. As long as it's
close to zero. So, we use square. We use square, right. We try to minimize the square of the error.
The residual. Okay. And actually, this can be just like y minus phi theta, right.
Transpose. So, this is the vector of the, the error. The residual. So, finally, you know,
through the analysis, we want to find such a phi, a sub-theta, so that this function j is
minimized. That means that the prediction is very close to a true value of the y.
So, this is the main idea, right. Prediction is very close to the true value. So, based on this
idea, we summarize this regression problem, right. And the parameter estimation problem
into such, actually, the minimization problem. Okay. So, next, actually, we will try to solve
this minimization problem to find the theta, right. So, theta should be the one that could
minimize this j function, j. Because this is the error function. Okay. So, we should minimize this.
Okay. Okay. So, theta phi, we should minimize this. And how to, okay, minimize this. I think these
are very, very classic, you know, omniscient problem, right. Very classic. Okay. And then,
we all know how to solve, right. And actually, that is, you know, the derivative of this j
with respect to the theta should be zero. Right. Okay. So, we first look at the partial derivative
of a j with respect to theta. Right. So, this is the first derivative. And then, you know,
if the theta is optimal, then this is, you know, the partial j theta, partial theta. This is the
first derivative of j with respect to theta, must be zero. Right. So, if we solve this, you know,
equal zero, we can obtain this theta cap. That means estimate equal to phi transpose phi,
the inverse matrix, then phi transpose phi. Phi is not the input matrix, right. Phi is not the
vector of the packet variable that's found truth. Okay. So, from this, actually, you know, equation,
now we can estimate the parameters. And these parameters, estimation will minimize the squared
area. Okay. So, this is theta is called, actually, the least squared estimate, ordinary least squared
estimate. This, let me, smallest squared, yeah, squared area. Okay. This means that this theta
will result in a smallest squared area. So, this estimate is called ordinary least squared,
actually, you know, estimation. Okay. So, this, actually, this solution here, you know, is an
analytical solution, right. It is an exact solution. Okay. We don't need to use the numerical method,
like training of neural networks, right. We need to do iteration, iteratively, right,
to find the parameter of the models. But here, you can just use this one step,
use this formula to calculate, actually, the estimate of the parameters. So, this is actually,
I think, very easy to implement, right. As long as you get the training samples, you put all the
input vector into a matrix, okay. You put all the target values, you know, ground truth values
into vector of y. And then you just substitute this formula to calculate theta.
Okay. And so, here, maybe I'll just show an example. And so, here, we have yx,
like, by the red color, right. And also, we have a y, is a y. And then, we want to,
there is a linear relationship between x and y. Okay. So, we are, so, this is the diagram shows,
actually, we have a 200 data point, okay. So, this is, I know that x is a coordinate, right.
Horizontal y is a vertical. Based on x and y, we have a data point. So, these are all the data
points. And from these, actually, the points, we can roughly see, there is a linear relationship
between y and x. That means, actually, we can use y equal to theta 0 plus theta 1 x, right.
A simple regression, right, to estimate the theta, right. We can solve this, you know,
a linear simple regression problem. And also, we can just use, actually,
this formula, right, on a least square estimation method to estimate the parameter of
0 theta 1. Okay. And, actually, this is a model. Because from here, we can see,
we roughly have a linear relationship. We assume we have a linear relationship.
And then, actually, we, this is a way, right, y, y, y to 200. This is a fact. And because
of this example, we just have one sample, right. Okay. One, one, one, one, predict variable. So,
from x, y, x, right. Okay. And then, we use this formula, substitute, we can calculate.
So, these are the values of theta. The estimation. This is the estimation of theta.
Okay. But how accurate is this theta? How accurate is this theta? And then, this depends on the,
the, the, the, the quality of the data. Okay. And if the data contain noise, and then, this is
fair, the theta estimate. And it could be very different, actually, from the true value of theta.
But if the noise is very small, then this estimate will be very close, you know, to the true value
of theta. Okay. So, this estimate, actually, is largely, actually, affected by the level of noise.
Okay. That's actually, I show you. And this, too, okay. So, this is the, okay. So, this is the
prediction result. Based on this, actually, we can get this straight line. Okay. This is a straight
line. And so, this is the value for theta, zero theta, one, estimated based on the 200, you know,
samples. Okay. And, okay. So, necessary, I will show you the influence of the noise
on the parameter estimation. Okay. And actually, I generate the data based on this
equation, where equal to 0.5 plus 2x plus a noise. This noise is random noise, Gaussian random noise.
Okay. And, actually, I said this noise level, I said the noise to different levels, right? Okay.
And so, I said the standard variation of the noise, you know, this Gaussian noise to 0.5,
then I generate the 200 data. Okay. Then, based on this 200 data, find the estimated parameters
of theta, zero, theta, one, right. And then, actually, I said the noise level, the standard
variation of the noise to 0.5, which is smaller, right. Then, again, generate 200 samples,
and then I estimate the parameters. And lastly, I said the noise, zero, no noise.
And then, based on the 200 sample, I say another set of parameters. Okay. So, these are the values
you can find, actually. This is the estimation when the standard variation of the noise is 0.5.
The true value is 0.5, but this estimation is 0.47. Okay. Then, the true value is here is 2,
but the estimation is 2.73. This is the case when the noise level, the standard variation is 0.5.
Then, this is 0.1. 0.1, you can see the estimation of the parameters. 0.4943. Very close to 0.5.
So, this is 2.0073. Very close to 2.2, right. Okay. So, this is the case,
noise free, no noise. Then, the parameter estimation is 0.5, too. Okay. So, from here,
you can see the noise, actually, affect the parameter estimation, right. Effect the parameter
estimation. Okay. And, of course, actually, in the application, we should always try to, actually,
to get the data clean, right, use the clean data, actually, to estimate the parameters of the model.
Because, actually, we see here, the accuracy of the parameter estimation is affected by the,
or influenced by the level of noise.
Okay. So, that's actually, we have a break. Okay. So, I'll break, we'll look at another
regression, which is called ridge regression. Okay.
So,
okay.
Okay.
Okay. So, next, we look at the ridge regression.
Okay. So, actually, if we use the on a least square estimation, we could encounter some
issues. Okay. And, this year, we listed three issues. And, the first issue that actually,
in some scenarios, actually, the number of per data, actually, could be, could greatly,
you see the number of prediction, per data variable, could be greater, actually, you see the
number of observation samples. Okay. In some applications, for example, the number of training
data is very limited. Maybe just like, you know, in medicine, for example, right, just have 100
samples, 200 samples. But, the per data variable could be huge, could be huge. Okay. And, that
means, actually, it could be, you know, more than 200, 100, 200. In other words, the number of per
data, actually, is greater than the number of samples. Okay. In such a scenario, actually,
we don't have a unique solution, unique solution. For example, we have an equation,
an equation, right? This equation is just like, I just want to have one equation, right? For example,
theta zero plus two theta one equals one. We have one sample, right? One sample normally
can only release one equation, right? But, in this equation, we have two parameters. So, this is a
case, a special case, right? Where the number of samples is less than the number of per data.
Actually, per data, of course, it's similar, one per data. But, actually, we have more than,
actually, one unknown parameter. We have two. We have two unknown parameters, but we have one
equation. Actually, we have numerous solutions, right? Theta zero plus theta, two theta one equals
one. Actually, we have numerous solutions. Okay. That means, actually, the solution is not unique
if we don't actually penalize, actually, the value of the theta, the parameters. This is one
issue that we could encounter when we apply this only to estimate, estimation method to estimate
the parameter of the model, right? So, this is a case where the number of samples is less than the
number of predictors. In other words, the number of unknown parameters is more than the number of
equations, the number of equations are called the number of samples. Okay. And then, now,
that's not really that, actually, the phase, your condition, okay? That means, a phase transpose
phase in words, or these matrices, right, is singular. Singular. Singular, that means, you know,
in words, start not exist. And then, we cannot use this method to calculate the parameter
estimation, right? So, this is a one case. Okay. Actually, when we talk about the, you know,
the feature linear human analysis, actually, we have one method to find the W, right? You remember
equals to the, in words of the, within class kinematics, that times M1 minus M2, right? If you
remember that. And actually, I mentioned, if they, in some scenario, the SW, the within class
kinematics, it could be actually singular. And then, how to address that problem? I remember, actually,
we use, actually, we add one real small real number, a positive real number to all the
diagonal elements. Then, we can actually solve this singular problem. Okay. So, here, you know,
we can also meet this singularity problem. Okay. And then, the words are not exist.
And then, another, that the OLS estimate may provide a good fit to the training data, but it may not
and generally, we are to the testing data. So, this is the case, actually, we see,
you know, the overfitting. The overfitting. Okay. And then, overfitting, I think,
all that happens, right? When the number of samples, maybe greater than the number predicted,
but this ratio is not big. Okay. Maybe, for example, we can have, you know, like a, you know, 200
samples, but we have 100, actually, parameters. Okay. In such a case, actually, although,
actually, the number of samples is still greater than the number of predicted, right? But this
number of, the ratio of the number of samples to the number of predicted is not big, only two.
Okay. In such a scenario, actually, we can have a high possibility to overfit the training data.
And then, the performance of the testing data could be bad. Okay. So, how to address these
problems? Actually, we can use a so-called rich regression. Okay. The basic idea of the rich
regression is that, actually, besides, actually, the consideration of the prediction area, we also
put a penalty on the side of the parameters. It was found, right? When, actually, the, you know,
the fair transport is singular, for example. And then, all very close to singular. Okay. Then,
actually, the parameter estimation is very big. Quite often, we hold a model, just have a small
value, like a one point something, zero point something, or two point something. Normally,
the small range of all the parameter values. But if the singularity happens, okay, and then the
parameter, all very close to singular, right? We can still have the inverse matrix, but the
parameter estimation would be very, very large value, like 100 something. If it has one, 200
something, if it has two, 500 something, it could be something like that. Okay. So, actually, from
that observation, I think it's very intuitive, right, to actually put a penalty on the side of
the parameters. Okay. So, in the loss function, so, besides this, you know, area should be
minimized. We also hope the parameter size could be not very big, could be close to zero, right?
Could be close to zero. So, we use a theta i squared, right, for every parameter in the model,
and the squared norm, right? Square norm of the theta vector. Okay. So, of course, actually,
we ought to balance the two considerations. We should put a weight here. So, lambda is a weight.
Okay. So, again, we can express this, you know, cost function, loss function into such a form,
right? So, this is the squared area, right? So, it's a kind of, where a matter of theta is just
an area, right? The area is trying to put the area. These are squared areas, this part, okay? And then,
this actually can be expressed as a lambda theta transpose theta. Okay. So, this is the
squared norm, right, of the theta vector. So, this is a new loss function. Okay. And then,
we can actually, again, use a similar, right, partial derivative of j with respect to theta,
first of all, derivative, right? Let this be zero. Then, we can solve to find the fact. And,
actually, to find the theta. Actually, this is the theta, I say. Actually, although, you know,
we have this condition, but we find that this result is so simple, right? Actually, we're just
going to add diagonal elements. Diagonal elements, right? And, for all diagonal elements, we add
one small constant real positive number, that is lambda. So, actually, even if we don't use a
regression, if we don't know the regression, we quite often, we use this technique, right, to,
actually, you know, address the singularity problem. But, actually, this is a regression,
a real regression. Okay. Actually, this is the effect of this, put a lambda on all the
diagonal elements, right, and this small real positive number to all the diagonal elements,
right, in the fair transpose of fair. It's the equivalent to put a penalization term in the
loss function. Okay. So, this is called real regression. And, actually, this technique is
called regularization in machine learning. This is called regularization, right? Regularization
is a technique to address, actually, to, you know, the overfitting problem. Okay. Quite often, actually.
So, this is called regularization. So, by the instead, it is, this is called real regression.
Okay. And so, from the regression, the consideration is to penalize the size of the parameter,
right? And, finally, this can be achieved by just adding a small positive real number
to all the diagonal elements. This adds identity matrix, right? Identity matrix. This means,
actually, we only add a small real point of lambda to the diagonal elements in this fair
transpose of fair. Okay. So, this is the regular regression. And, of course, this theta value,
this theta is a hyper parameter, right? Because if you want to use this formula,
you must preset the value of theta. But what is the suitable number of theta? Actually, again,
actually, you can actually use the so-called, actually, no, validation data, right, to find the,
know the suitable value of lambda. So, later, we will talk about the, you know, the
evaluation matrix for regression. Okay. So, we can set the lambda to different values,
and then we will estimate the parameters. Okay. And then we look at the predictions on the,
on the validation data. Okay. Then, based on this validation data performance,
then we can actually find the suitable value for this lambda. Okay. So, lambda is a hyper parameter.
So, this is a regular regression. Okay. And, also, can be considered as a regularization technique
to improve the regularization capabilities of the model. Okay.
So, this is a regularization technique in machine learning. Okay. And, so, regularization aims to
avoid overfitting. Okay. So, to improve the performance of the model on the testing data.
Okay. So, regression.
So, next, actually, we can see another regression. This is called a lasso regression. Okay. And,
actually, in the, just now, actually, in the regression, so, as you know, in the loss function,
we have two parts, right. The first part is about the, the square area, the square area,
the prediction area, right. The square area. And, then the second part is the square, actually,
norm of the parameter vector theta. Okay. Square norm. Okay. And square norm is also called L2 norm.
L2 norm. Okay. So, in other words, in the regression, we use the square norm, L2 norm,
of the, of the, of the parameter vector theta. Okay. And in the lasso, they don't use this L2 norm.
Instead, they use the so-called L1 norm. L1 norm. What is the L1 norm? L1 norm is just,
actually, the summation of all the, actually, the theta value. We don't have squares. The summation
of, of course, the value can be, the point can be negative, right. So, the absolute value
of all the parameters. So, this is the L1 norm. Given a vector, what is the L1 norm?
Right. Just, actually, the summation of all these, the, the individual element in this vector.
So, this is the, actually, then, again, we have this, you know, we need to balance the two part,
right. Balance the two part. On one hand, we want to, and hope this prediction area could be as small
as possible. On the other hand, actually, we want to know, overcome, or a reading problem,
by penalizing the value, the size of the parameters. Okay. And then, to balance the two,
we put a, a weightage lambda here. Okay. And as in the regression, lambda is a hyper parameter.
Okay. And we need to know, use validation data to determine the super value of this lambda.
Okay. So, so, actually, if we compare, actually, you know, the Lasso regression and the reg regression,
the difference is very subtle, right. It's very subtle. Here, we actually use the L1 norm of the
theta. And then the regression with the L2 norm, the square norm. So, this is the only difference.
But this is a subtle difference, actually. I have a very big, actually, you know,
difference in the final, in the result. Okay. And actually, in the previously, right, if you have a
tree, you know, this, this, actually, L2 norm, right, L2 norm, theta i squared, theta i is the parameter.
Okay. And actually, we, we minimized the theta i squared, right, the i squared. Okay. If theta is
small, less than 1, right, theta i squared will be even less than theta, right, than theta. For example,
if the theta value is 0.2, then, you know, the theta i squared will be 0.04, right, 0.04. So,
these are tree values, these are penalization could push, actually, the theta, you know,
close to 0, close to 0. But actually, it's not as effective as this L1 norm. Because L1 norm,
actually, the theta will really be 0, right. Because theta i is 0.2, then the square norm is 0.04.
Okay. But if you, actually, the value, you know, the parameter is 0.2, right. But actually, if you
use a tree, this L1 norm, L1 norm, this L1 norm, right, only a tree, when the tree, the theta is
close to 0, 0.04, then we have the c. Then this is a penalization part, 0.04. But originally,
the theta 0.2, then the consequence, in the loss function, 0.04. But now, if you use this form,
then the theta i must be 0.04, really close to 0. Okay. So, these L1, you know, this last regression
tree, actually, we will have a, I think, I think we will have a strong, actually, you know, shrinkage
on the parameter values of theta. Okay. Theta i squared also shrink the value towards 0. But
actually, this L1 norm has a stronger shrinkage of these parameters. Okay. Then what is the
consequence? Okay. If we use this L last regression, finally, many of the parameters will be close to
0, really close to 0. Okay. Close to 0, what does this mean? This means, in the final model,
this tree, the corresponding predictor variables actually have almost no contribution or very
little contribution to the prediction of the y. In other words, these variables can be removed,
can be removed from the model. Okay. So, this actually also plays the rule of select variables.
Okay. So, this is the full name of last rule. This absolute shrinkage, this absolute,
this absolute, right? Absolute, I mean the absolute of the parameter value shrinkage towards 0.
And the select, select an operator, this select, they can push many of the, actually, the theta
close to 0. And then we can remove these variables from the model. Actually, this plays the rule of
selecting actually the variables. Actually, this is the power of the last rule, actually,
regression. Not only to fit a model, but also actually select the variables.
Previous models, we don't have this, you know, this capability. Okay. But here we have this
capability. So, last rule regression, I think is often used as a feature selection algorithm.
Feature selection. Because actually, during the design stage, actually normally we don't know,
actually which variables are useful. Okay. And some of the variables could be useless.
Some of the variables could be useful, but redundant, redundant. Okay. So, through this,
you know, variable selection or feature selection, we can remove features or variables that are
redundant or insignificant. Then we can get a small model, right? Small model, actually,
normally, you know, is less likely overfit the training data.
Less likely overfit the training data. And then the generalization could be better.
Okay. So, this is actually the last rule, actually, regression. Okay. So, it has this function,
selection of the variables. But actually, because of this L1 norm, actually the solution
is not easy to find. Not easy to find. Okay. And we don't have an analytical solution. If you look
at the owner regression and also the regression, right, we have the exact solution. We have known
the formula to calculate the solution. We have the formula to calculate this analytical solution.
But for this, we don't have way to use the numerical method to solve this.
Okay. So, of course, actually, for this kind of problem, actually, you don't have a formula,
right? And we need to use some like a software, a turbo to solve this last rule. I think normally,
in the, you know, the machine learning turbo, they have the function that we can call to solve this.
Okay. Like in my lab, they have this function to solve, actually, you know, this last regression
problem. Okay. So, this is the regression. So, the choice of the non-regulation parameter is crucial,
right? And we can actually, a larger lambda value doesn't mean that put a more emphasis on the
parameter of the value of the parameter of theta, right? If a larger theta lambda will actually
lead to a larger number of zero values or close to zero values for the theta. Okay. In other words,
a larger lambda will select a small number of variables to include in the regression model.
And actually, a smaller lambda actually will actually select more variables to include in
the final model. If lambda zero, right, this is just a conventional, all variables will be selected.
Okay. So, we also always know balance the two. If lambda is too big, right, just a small number of
samples actually are included in the, in the model. And then we have a possibility that the model,
the data is underfitted. That means the model cannot capture the true relationship between
the, the predictors and the, the target variables. Okay. So, this is underfitting. Underfitting of
course actually kind of, you know, lead to the very bad performance on the train data and also on
the testing data. Okay. But if the lambda is small, we include more. And if the number of,
of initial number of predictor variables is huge, right. And then if we use a smaller lambda,
then actually the final way we will have a large number of predictor variables in the final model.
Then we have a chance to overfit the train data. Okay. So, of course, actually we should have a
balance, right. We should select a suitable value of lambda. How to select? We can look at the
performance on the validation data. Okay. So, in the regression that we can also divide the data
into training, validation, and also the testing. Okay. And then the model evaluation, we look
about the metrics. Actually the, the procedure can be similar as that, you know, the class
failure problem, right. Actually we can divide the data into training, then you use the train
data to estimate the parameters. Then we look at the performance on the testing, the validation data,
right, to select a suitable value for the hyperparameters. So, here is the lambda. Okay. And then,
we, we get the best performing model, right, on the validation data. Then we apply the model on
the testing data. Okay. Then the what metrics we can use. Actually in the regression, and normally
we use actually, this is the first, actually, the mean squared error. Actually, our goal in the
regression, right, trying to minimize the squared error, the squared error. So, certainly we can
use the squared error as a metric to evaluate the performance on the model, right. So, here we use
no average, right, because this is not the number of samples, even more, right. You can have a bigger
mean squared error. So, here we use actually the mean, the mean squared error. So, for each of the
sample, we have a squared error, right, summation, then divide them into a number of samples. So,
this is the average of the squared error, or mean squared error, MSE mean. Okay. So, this is the first
measure of metrics we can use to evaluate the model performance, or to compare the performance
between different models. Okay. And then the second one is the root mean squared error, root
mean squared error. So, mean squared error, root mean squared, the square root of the mean squared
error, is just the mean root mean squared error. So, this can be actually used as a metric for the
performance evaluation. Okay. Then another one is the absolute, the mean absolute error. We don't
use a square, right. We don't use a square, right. And we just look at the absolute value
of the error, right. So, why model AI absolute value? Why absolute? Because actually we don't care
whether why a prediction is greater than why or why is less than why. The prediction is less than
why, right. It's not as they are closed from any direction. Positive error or negative error,
we don't care. We just care they are very close to each other. Okay. So, we use absolute value,
right. Okay. Then we use the mean. So, this is the mean absolute error. So, this is another
metric we can use for the model performance evaluation. Okay. Then that's why the R squared,
R squared. This is also a commonly used actually
metrics for model evaluation. Commonly used. Okay. And actually R squared actually
it defines as the fraction by which the variance of the error is less than the variance of the
dependent variables. Okay. So, R squared defines as 1 minus RSS TSS. What's RSS? What's TSS? RSS here is the
sum of the square of the residuals. Sum of the square of the residuals. RSS. And TSS here is a
total of the sum of squares. Okay. So, RSS actually here.
Sum of square. Right. It's like in the mean and the square error, right. We divide by n. Here,
but we don't divide by n. Okay. So, this is just the sum of the square of the residuals of the
errors. Then TSS. So, here is the y bar. This y bar means the mean value of y. We have the
all the samples, right. The target value. We take the average. This is the average. Okay. The mean.
Okay. Then actually, so, so this actually when the bar minus the y i, right, this shows actually
the difference of the usual sample from the mean, from the average of the, of the, of the
target variables. Okay. Then squares summation. So, this is a total of sum of squares.
Okay. And so, this is the y bar is the mean, right. The mean for y i, the average. So, this is the
R square. R square. It's commonly used actually in the regression model at evaluation. Okay.
And this is actually, you know, we have a data, right. Where noise is data. We have x and we have
a y, right. Then we have this actually based on the, you know, the x and the y. Actually, we can have
this estimate, parameter estimate. Okay. And then, you know, this parameter estimate actually determine
a street line, right. So, from here we can see that the samples are all very far from the street
lines. But this is the best, the best estimate. This is the best actually street line we can,
we can have, right. In other words, this street line that leads to the minimum, actually,
you know, square area, minimum square area. Okay. But actually, this is because the data is very
noisy, right. And then actually we can see the model, the R square is 0.2071. So, okay. So,
this is actually the model, the data is very noisy, right. So, data noise is normally the
quality of the estimation or the accuracy of the estimation not high. Okay. Then the R square value
is very low. And then this scenario shows actually, actually we have a, you know, the noise level is
reduced, right, compared with the previous one, right. And then we can see the R square, 0.55
R square. Okay. So, the larger the better, right. This is a case, we can see the noise level is very
low, right, noise level. And then actually the R square, actually, is a high, very high value,
as you're probably not 719. Okay. So, from here, actually, we can see this R square,
you know, can indeed can be used actually as a, as a, as a metric, right, for the evaluation of the
model quality. Okay. And so, this is actually, you know, the, this is the, you know, R square,
right. We can see the different levels of the noise. And then actually we can have very different
three values for the R square. Okay. A different level of noise actually also see that the different
quality of the model, right. Okay. So, finally, actually, we have a good model and under these
low noise, then we can have a large R square value. Okay. So, from here, you can see R square
value can indeed can be used as an indication of the model performance as an evaluation matrix.
Okay. So, this is the R square. So, R square should be in a range, right, from zero to one.
The one is the best, zero is the worst. Okay. And so, how high does R square need to be? So, how big
of R square is considered as a good R square. Okay. So, these are the problem dependent, right.
And actually this is a human that we have to predict. How to predict the tree. That means
that you can still use some variables, right. For example, you can predict the salary based
on the number of years. But number of years certainly not the only, is not sufficient, right.
There's two, you know, peasants and people have the same number of years, right. The salary could
be different, right. One, you know, maybe auto-perform others, right. Then the salary could be higher.
Okay. So, these are the means, you know, if you just use one variable, then it's very hard to predict.
Okay. Of course, for human behavior, sometimes we don't know which variable we show you to
predict the human behavior. Okay. So, the example scenario, that means actually the noise,
because we don't use some of the variables, right, then the noise is considered very high.
Okay. Then the R square could be very low. Okay. So, for human behavior prediction,
actually the value of R square could be rarely actually higher than 0.5. This means actually
this model could not be an accurate model. We don't believe a model could be,
we could have a very, very good accurate model to predict the human behaviors.
Okay. So, this is the thing that's just, but in some, you know, the engineering problem,
actually this is actually the R square and could be closed over at the 0.9. Could be close to 1,
because the noise level is low, right. So, normally we are sure, okay. So, these variables,
tag variable is affected by these independent variables. Okay. Then we can use all these
independent variables to predict the tag variable. But in the social sense, right,
you will predict the human behavior. Actually, we don't know. So, what factors actually affect
the human behavior? Of course, you can name a few, right, but you certainly will miss some of them.
Okay. This means, this is equivalent to add a very big, actually, noise. Actually,
you have a big noise, actually. The noise level is high. Then the model quality could not be high.
Then the R square is low. Okay. So, this is the R square.
Okay. So, you can see the R square matrix actually also has some limitation. It's not perfect. Okay.
And so, here, this is the field. R square, we are increased with the increase of a number of
predicted variables in the model. Okay. So, actually, as you see, we have mentioned,
I explained this before, right. Actually, you know, sometimes, actually, some variables are
usually, some are redundant, right. And we should normally, should actually remove those variables
from the model. Okay. Then we can get a simple model and to avoid the graffiti problem. Okay.
But if you use the R square matrix as a measure, and if the more variables we include in the model,
then the better the performance, the better the R square values. Okay. So, this actually,
as an disadvantage, this actually is the weakness of the R square matrix. Okay. Because this R square
matrix, fewer, a larger model. Okay. Then to address this problem, and we have the so-called
address the R square at the drive state. Okay. And address the R square at this,
into account, the number of parameters or the number of variables in the model. Okay. So,
they do the adjustment. So, in other words, they penalize the number of variables in the model.
Okay. So, this is the address the R square. So, first, actually, we calculate the R square,
right. R square. Then, we substitute the R square into this formula. We can get the address the R
square. And here, a number of samples. M is the number of per data variables in the model.
X1, X2, and your XM. Right. So, these are the, so we penalize this. Okay. And so, this actually is
the address R square. And so, these are the all the matrix, actually. We can use to evaluate the
performance of a model. Right. So, we have the mean square error, we have the root mean square
error, we have the mean absolute error. Right. And we also actually have the R square or the regular,
the address R square. Actually, all that these are, these matrix I use, okay. For example, actually,
yeah, one of our research project to predict the depth of the object. Actually, we all use,
it's a regression problem. We all use these, these are known, these matrix to evaluate the
performance of the predictions of the depth of the objects. Okay. So, these are then the,
the matrix that we can use to evaluate the performance of a regression model. Okay. And then, okay.
So, this address actually penalize the inclusion of unnecessary variables. Okay. So,
okay. So, this is the summary of the evaluation matrix, the mean square error.
Actually, the root mean square error is more widely used than mean square error. Okay. So,
this is actually the root mean square error. And then absolute mean square error is also commonly used.
Okay. Then we have R square, just R squares. So, these are the evaluation matrix. And the,
the next entry is the model validation. Model validation, I think I will, yeah, talk about this
in the next week. Okay. So, given a model actually, of course, we can look at the non-evaluation,
performing the evaluation matrix, right. We can look at that. And we can also have other methods
actually to validate the model. So, that is the model validation. Okay. So, normally, we look at
the performance, look at the characteristics of the areas, the prediction areas. Okay. And
based on the analysis of the prediction areas, actually, we can validate the model. Okay. So,
we will talk about this actually in the next week. So, today, actually, we just stop here. Okay.
And, okay. So, I think that's all for today. Yeah. Thank you. Okay. Thank you. Thank you.
Okay.
Hello.
Yes.
Can you hear? Hello.
Can you hear?
I was trying to. I was trying to. Okay.
Test. Test. Can you hear? Okay. Can you hear? You tried to say something? Hello. I think you're
listening higher. Hello. Can you hear me? Hello. Hello. Hello. Hello.
Test. Test. Test. Test. Test. Test. Testing. Test. Testing. I'm not sure what it is. My voice
or the microphone? Maybe. Testing. Testing. This is fine. Can you hear? Okay. Yeah. Okay. It needs
to be this level. Your chest. Chest level.
Testing. Testing. Hello.