.
Okay, going around one. So the last week, actually, we have studied the Fisher's linear
Dismantlet analysis. And actually, the problem we address actually is a two-class classification
problem, right? So we have two classes, and we find one actually, a Dismantlet function,
and which is contained two parameters. One is W, and another is the bi-term W0 or B. And
actually, the W determines the linear classifier, actually, is a street line in the 2D space,
and all is a hyperplane. Okay. And so the orientation or direction of this in the hyperplane is determined
by the W. And the location of this hyperplane is determined by the bi-term W0. Okay. And
so, naturally, we will try to extend this Fisher's linear Dismantlet analysis from two
classes to multiple class problems. Okay. And so, quite often, the class problem contains
more than two classes. Okay. And assume the number of classes is C. Okay. And then we
need to actually solve a C-class classification problem. And then in a C-class classification
problem, and we need to have C minus 1 Dismantlet function. Okay. C minus 1, C is the number
of classes. Okay. And then in the 2-class classification problem, C equals 2, right?
C minus 1 is just 1. So we actually design one Dismantlet function, GX, which contains
one with vector and one bi-term. Okay. And in the C-class classification problem, we
need to find that C minus 1 are the Dismantlet functions. Okay. And for each of these Dismantlet
function, we have one, no, W. And also, we have one bi-term, W0. Okay. And actually,
in some sense, actually, the multiple Dismantlet analysis can be considered as a deminotent
reduction technique. Because originally, the data in the D deminotent space, right, D could
be very high. Okay. So after a project to a new space, okay, which has a deminotent
of C minus 1. Okay. Because for each of the, in each of the dimension of the C minus 1
space, actually, we have one projection, right? That is W. And also the bi-term W0. Okay.
So totally, we have C minus 1 projection and all we have C minus 1 Dismantlet functions.
Okay. So the data, actually, is projected from a D deminotent space to a C minus 1 deminotent
space. Okay. This D deminotent of the data could be very high in practice. Although,
you know, in the examples, demonstration examples, we often use the 2D, right, for illustration
purpose. But in practice, the D could be very high. In our assignment, right, the D is like
30, 32, 33 dimensions. Okay. And you see just like two or three classes, right, three classes.
Then you project the data from a high-dimensional, like, 30 dimension to a 3D or to a 2D space.
So, you know, obviously, the deminotent reduction is very significant, right, from 30 to 2. Okay.
And actually, no, previously, I probably, I think you already know one commonly used deminotent
reduction technique that is the principle of Kaupung analysis, PCA, right? And actually, PCA
is kind of unsupervised deminotent reduction technique because we don't need to use a label
information. But in the multiple digital analysis, now, we need to know the label information about
data, right? We know the data belong to one class and the data belong to another class. We need
the label information. So, it's kind of a supervised deminotent reduction. Okay. Okay. So, actually,
in the two class collection problems, actually, you know, in order to find the projection W,
and actually, we need to have the two metrics, right? One metric is called, actually, the within
class scatter metrics. Okay. Another is between class scatter metrics. Okay. Within class scatter
metrics, actually, for each class, you know, we have the samples. And actually, we can find the mean
vector of the samples. We need the same class. And then, based on the dismean, we can find the
scatter metrics for each individual class. Okay. For example, for class i, then we use all the
data in this class i. And based on the mean vector for class i, we can find the scatter
metrics for class i. Okay. And then the summation of the C classes, because we have C classes,
right? So, each class has a scatter, within class scatter metrics. So, the summation will get
SW. Okay. This is the total within class scatter metrics. Just a similar summation of the
C scatter metrics. Okay. And then, that's actually, we need to have, actually, you know,
another metric, right? That is the between class scatter metrics. So, here, this is an
within class scatter metrics. Okay. So, that's actually, we look at this, actually,
between class scatter metrics. Okay. And so, here, we first define the total mean. The total mean
here, actually, is the mean for all samples, regardless of the class levels. Okay. So, we
consider all samples belonging to one class. And then, we can have, actually, a mean vector. So,
this mean vector is called total mean vector. Okay. So, based on this total mean vector, actually,
we can find, actually, the total, actually, no scatter metrics. Total scatter metrics, right?
Actually, the total scatter metrics is all samples. So, now, for all samples, we don't think about,
we don't think about the class label. Okay. We just think they belong to the same class.
Okay. And then, we have a total mean vector. So, based on the total mean vector, we can look at
the difference from each sample in the trineal dataset, right, and to the total mean. Okay.
Then, we can calculate this ST. This ST is called total scatter metrics. Okay. And, actually,
you know, here, now, we can do some simple manipulation. For example, now, we can actually
minus MI, then plus MI, right? So, this, actually, then, then we know the still X minus M. Okay.
And then, similarly, you know, for this part, X minus MI plus MI minus M. Okay. And then,
we can separate these into two parts. Okay. So, finally, through some manipulation,
and, actually, we can find, actually, the first part is simply, actually, the within class scatter
metrics. So, the total scatter metrics include SW. Okay. And then, there is one additional part
here, right? And this part, actually, is defined as the between class scatter metrics. Okay. So,
the total scatter metrics is a summation of the within class scatter metrics and the between
class scatter metrics. So, this part, actually, so, for each class, we have a mean vector. And,
we look at the distance or the difference between the mean vector of an individual class
to the total mean vector. Okay. And then, we can calculate, actually, the
between class scatter metrics. So, this between class scatter metrics. Okay.
And so, now, we have these two metrics. One is within class scatter metrics. Another is
between class scatter metrics. So, our next objective is to find, actually, the C1,
dismal functions. In other words, we need to first find the C minus 1 projections,
W1, W2, and your WC minus 1. So, after that, we also need to find the vice term, right,
for each of these C minus 1 dismal functions. Okay.
And here, actually, we define, actually, no, this is actually
a dismal function. And, actually, no, for each, for each, here, we see we have a C minus 1
dismal function, right? Okay. So, we can put a C minus 1 dismal function into one, actually,
vector, right vector. So, we define the G. Here, I use a bone phase, right, a G to denote a vector.
So, this G is, this is actually G, actually, is a scalar, right? But this G, G1, G2, and your
GC minus 1, actually, is a scalar. But here, we put them into a vector. So, this is a dismal function
vector. Okay. And also, we put all the, you know, weight vectors, W1, WC minus 1, right,
because we have a C minus 1 projections, and into one matrix. So, this weight becomes a weight
matrix. Okay. So, here, actually, we include all the C minus 1 dismal functions into one
vector function. Okay. And we include all the C minus 1 weight vectors into a weight matrix.
Okay. So, then, we have these definitions. And then, we have this Gx equals W transpose x.
Okay. And actually, from here, actually, we can see that this is kind of projection, right?
Originally, for each data, x, and its representation is a d-dimensional vector, right? It's a d-dimensional
vector. Okay. But after projection, and we can have a new vector, right? The projection is
through this weight matrix. Okay. And we come to a new vector, a new representation. For each x,
we have a new representation. That is just a Gx. Okay. So, part often, the number of classes
is less than the number of deminality, right? So, this is indeed a deminality reduction. So,
from an original D space to a C minus 1 space. Okay. Through this projection, W. Okay. That's
the reason why we see the multiple, actually, the digital analysis is often used as a technique
for deminality reduction. Of course, this is superactually deminality reduction, right?
Because we use class label. Okay. So, now, actually, after projection, after projection,
even the data is represented in a new space with a lower deminality. And in this space,
and again, we can have a new, actually, the mean vector, right? We have a new mean vector.
This is just another representation of the original data. So, from x to Gx, from D to C minus 1.
So, in this C minus 1 space, each x is represented by G1x, G2x, Gc minus 1x. Okay. So, it's just
kind of transformation, right? It's a new representation. And in this C minus 1 deminality
space, and again, for all the samples within the same class, we can calculate the mean vector.
We use this m-tied i to denote the mean vector of all samples of class i in the new space
with a deminality of C minus 1. Okay. So, this, okay. And again, we can have a total mean, right?
We can have a total mean, this m-tied. This is a total mean vector. Okay. In the two class
kind of problem, so after projection, by this, this function Gx, and we obtain, actually, a scalar
representation for each x, okay, then of course, actually, for each class, then we can have a mean
value. Okay. But now, the projection, actually, is to a C minus 1 space. We cannot have a mean
value, but we can have a mean vector for samples in each class. Okay. So, m-i-tied, and also,
we can have a total mean, m-tied. Okay. And even, of course, in this new space, again, we can,
based on the mean vector of each middle class, then we can calculate the within class scatter
matrix in this C minus 1 deminality space, the new space, right? And also, we know we can calculate,
actually, the total within class scatter matrix, right? Total within class matrix. That is just a
summation of the C, actually, the individual within class scatter matrix. Okay. And also,
we can also have a SB-type, which is a between class scatter matrix in this new space,
with a deminality of C minus 1. Okay. Now, previously, in the C class kind of problem,
we have no, actually, the within class scatter. Within class scatter matrix, we use a standard
agent, or we use a variance to represent, right? Because it's a scalar, okay? Because the projection
is from a deminality space to a 1D space. Okay. So, the recognition, actually, is a scalar,
is a 1D. Okay. Then we can have a, you know, the scatter, actually, just an automaton, right? You
just actually, actually, in the new space, actually, just an standard agent, or the
variance can be used as a scatter. Okay. And so, this is a B, right, between class. Previously,
we can use a difference between two mean vectors, right? In the two classes, as a
measure for the between class scatter. But now, it's a scatter matrix SB between class. Okay.
And in this calculation of the between class scatter matrix, we don't do the calculation of
between M1, M2, M1, M3, M1, M4, and then M2, M3, M2, M4. We don't do this kind of,
you know, pairwise, actually, you know, kind of scatter measurement, right? Instead, we look at,
we first find a total mean vector. And then, based on the total mean vector, we calculate, actually,
the, the, the between class scatter matrix SB type. Okay. So, type, SW type means, actually, the
scatter matrix, you know, within class scatter matrix, or between class scatter matrix,
in the new space. The new space, actually, it has a denominator of C minus 1. Okay.
Okay. And, actually, what's the relationship between the new, actually, the scatter matrix,
within class scatter matrix, and the between class scatter matrix with the original,
within class scatter matrix, and the between class scatter matrix. Okay. Actually, this is the relationship.
And, actually, the new, within class scatter matrix, the new space equals W. W, actually,
with matrix. Okay. Times the SW. SW here is the, within class scatter matrix in the original space,
the D, the denominator of D, right? Or no feature space. Okay. And so, for the,
between class scatter matrix in the new space, also equals W transpose SB. So, this SB is the
between class scatter matrix in the original space. Okay. So, these, actually, two equations,
gives the relationship, right, between the new, you know, with the scatter matrix with the old,
with the original, you know, scatter matrix. Okay. And, actually, you know, the main idea,
you know, in the, in the Fisher's linear student analysis, you know, in the C class,
and we know our objective is to find the projection W. And so that, actually, the
between class difference or between class scatter could be maximized. And the within class scatter
or within class difference could be minimized. So, this is the main idea of the Fisher's linear
student analysis, right? So, this is a very good idea, right? Between class should be different.
Within class should be small. Okay. So, we try to maximize the between class difference
or scatter. Okay. Or, and minimize the within class difference or scatter. Okay. But,
finally, actually, we try to find a W that could maximize the ratio of the two, right?
The ratio of between class, actually, difference of scatter and to the within class scatter.
And, actually, the scatter, you know, is just, actually, a scalar value, right? Just a scalar value.
Okay. So, now, in the multiple Fisher's linear student analysis, we also want to find a W.
Here is no, no, no, one, actually, the Witt vector. It's a Witt matrix. We want to find such a Witt
matrix. And so that the within class scatter matrix, within class scatter could be minimized.
Between class scatter could be maximized. Of course, actually, ideally, actually, we should try to,
actually, maximize the ratio of the between class scatter to the within class scatter.
Okay. But, here, you know, we just have a scatter matrix, right? We have a scatter matrix.
Actually, when we look at the ratio, actually, the ratio should be the ratio of two scalars,
right? But, here, we have two, two matrix. One is within class scatter matrix. Another is
between class scatter matrix. So, how we can get a scalar, then try to, actually, you know,
to maximize the ratio of the two scalars. Okay. And, actually, for the scatter, right, for the
scatter, between class scatter, and, actually, we can use the, actually, between class scatter,
or within class scatter, actually, we can use the determinant of the scatter matrix.
Okay. So, here, actually, a simple measure of the scatter is the determinant of the scatter
matrix, the determinant. We cannot get the ratio of the two matrix, right? We don't have such an
operation, the ratio of two matrix. Okay. So, so, how to, you know, maximize, actually, the
between class scatter and the minima, the within class scatter. In other words, so, what measure
could be used for the scatter, given a scatter matrix? Actually, we can use the determinant
of the matrix, right, as a scatter measure. Okay. And, actually, you know, this is not the only
measure that we can use, you know, for the scatter of a scatter matrix. And, some, actually, you know,
research work actually employs the trees of a matrix, the trees of a matrix. We will talk about
this, you know, again, when we, in the later weeks, when we talk about the official selection.
During that part, we will look at these, you know, measures again. Okay. So, we will use the
determinant of the matrix as a measure for the scatter. Okay. And then, actually, our objective
here is to maximize, actually, the ratio of the scatter between class and to the, actually,
within class scatter. So, the determinant of the matrix is a measure of the scatter.
Okay. And so, just now, we already know, find the relationship, right, and between the new
scatter matrix and the scatter matrix in the original space. So, that is just, okay. So,
now, indeed, this called function J is a function of the width matrix W, right, the matrix W.
Then, actually, our net objective is to solve this homo-azision problem. We want to find the
width matrix W, and so that this JW is maximized. Okay. So, through our analysis,
through our understanding, and through our expectation of a good, actually,
projection, right, and we have the ideas of between class scatter and within class scatter.
Okay. So, through these analyses, finally, actually, the machine learning program is
formulated as an homo-azision problem, right, homo-azision. Okay. Of course, actually,
if you just have the homo-azision technique knowledge, you don't have machine learning
knowledge, you cannot formulate such a problem. Okay. But if you have a knowledge of machine
learning, and we know, actually, what is an ideal distribution, right, of the samples in the new
feature space, we have some ideas, right, that the between class scatter is maximized, and within
class scatter, scatter should be minimized. We have these ideas, and then, actually, we can formulate,
at least, the machine learning problem into such an homo-azision problem.
Okay. So, later today, when we finish this part, we are looking to the support-widen
machines. And, again, actually, first, actually, we start from machine learning concept, and what is
known, we expect from a good pattern classifier. Okay. And then, we have some conditions. So,
finally, we also formulate, actually, a machine learning problem, not a support-widen machine,
into an homo-azision problem. Okay. I think this is the standard procedure for machine learning.
You want to do machine learning research, right? You also need to have a very solid foundation
machine learning. You need to understand, right, machine learning. You need to understand what is
pattern classification. So, what, actually, distribution of the data could result in a
good performance. You first need to have such ideas, okay, and then you formulate the problem into a
homo-azision problem. Then, you solve it, and then you can get a new solution, right? Maybe
with good, actually, or better, or improved performance. Okay. So, now, actually, we try to
solve this problem. Of course, actually, I think for us, it is not an easy problem, right? And,
fortunately, and, actually, the mathematicians already have found a solution for such, actually,
a homo-azision problem. And, actually, they found, actually, the solution, right, actually,
for this homo-azision problem, actually, can be found through solving, and this, actually,
and generalized eigenvalue problem. Remember, you know, in the last week, when we talked about,
you know, two class kind of problems, so there are two ways to find the projection, right? So,
one way is to solve the generalized eigenvalue problem or the regular, the normal generalized
eigenvalue problem. And then, another matter, we use a formula to calculate directly, right? So,
there are two ways, okay? So, here, again, we can solve, actually, this problem, and by using the,
by finding them, or by solving these general eigenvalue problems. Okay. So, Sb is the
between-class kinematic, right? And in the homo-space, wi is a width vector, okay? And,
lambda i, here, lambda i is called an eigenvalue, okay? And wi is a corresponding eigenvector,
okay? So, as I said, I demonstrated in the last week, right? And in many, actually,
like, the machine learning tools, and we have functions to solve this generalized eigenvalue
problem. Okay. Or the normal eigenvalue problem, if the, within-class kinematic, Sw is non-singular.
In non-singular, then, we can multiply the, actually, the inverse matrix to the two sides,
right? And then, this becomes the, the U-roll, or the regular singular value decomposition problem.
Okay. Okay. But this is not necessary, actually, in all the tools, actually, the,
have functions to solve the general eigenvalue problem, or just the normal eigenvalue problem.
Okay. Okay. So, based on the SB, based on the Sw, and we can solve the generalized eigenvalue
problem to find, actually, the width vector, W1, W2, until Wc minus 1. Okay. So, these are the
projections for the C minus 1, you know, the Dismount functions. Okay. So, this is for the multiple,
Dismount analysis. Okay. Multiple, I mean, for multiple class.
So, that's actually, I showed you one example. And in this example, and then, we have three classes.
You can see the data, right? A label with black, blue, and red. So, these are the samples,
actually, in three classes. And each class has 100 samples. Okay. So, here, you know, we need to
design a pattern classifier, right? And to classify the sample in the three classes.
Okay. So, in this problem, the C equals 3, right? This is a C class class, and the problem C equals 3.
And then, we need to find, actually, two, right? We need to find two width vectors, W1, W2. And we
need to find, actually, the two Dismount functions, because we can only find the C minus 1, right?
Dismount functions. Okay. So, that's actually, you know, we try to find, actually, these are
the two width vectors, okay? By solving the eigenvalue problem, or the general eigenvalue problem.
Okay. And, of course, before then, we need to calculate, you know, the between class
scatter matrix and the within class scatter matrix, right? Okay. So, to calculate the
individual, the, you know, the within class scatter matrix for each individual class,
now, firstly, we need to calculate the mean vectors. So, based on the sample, we can easily
find the mean vector for the three classes. M1, the mean vector for class 1, M2 for class 2,
M3 for class 3. So, based on the sample, we just get average, right? So, this is just the mean
vectors. Okay. And, of course, actually, based on the mean vector for each of the class, we can use
all the 100 samples in each class to calculate, actually, the within class scatter matrix for
class 1, S1, class 2, S2, class 3. Okay. So, these are the within class scatter matrix. Okay. And,
so, the summation of the three is just the within class scatter matrix, okay. So, here, actually,
you can see the number, right? It's very big, right? 12,000. 7,000 something, right? Very big
values, okay. So, actually, you know, in the calculation of CROF, we try to award big values,
right? So, actually, we can do something like a scaling. You can just, you know, you see the
value too big, right? I can just divide it by all the value by 101,000. Okay. And, so, that, you know,
we can have a small, you know, all the values are established to be small. And, actually, in this
course, actually, the formula adopted from one textbook, these are, you know, it's all the summation,
right? All the data. But in some books, when they calculate the within class scatter matrix,
actually, they also actually divided by the number of samples in the class. Okay. But there are some,
just a different tree, you know, some different wiring, right? For this Fisher linear different
analysis technique. Okay. So, we can have different ways. We can do some scaling, right?
To, for the within class scatter matrix. Okay. So, we get this. Okay. So, this is the within
class scatter matrix. So, necessary, we need to calculate the between class scatter matrix,
right? Before that, we also need to calculate the total mean vector, right? The total mean vector.
Okay. And, based on the total mean vector, and also the mean vector of each individual class,
and why M2, M3, right? And then we calculate the between class scatter matrix, SW, SB. So,
this is the SB, the between class scatter matrix. Okay. And then we can solve this, you know,
generalized eigenvalue problem. SBW equals lambda SW, SW. Okay. So, actually, here, actually,
maybe I use my lab to as a demonstration lab. My lab, okay. My lab, you know, we can use it,
A and E, I, G eigenvalue, right? And then, so, this, this is in the, so, this SB and A, B,
right? So, SB, SW, you just give, need to know, input these two matrix, right? One is the left
hand side, SB, right? Another is the right hand side, SW. Okay. So, here, output have two matrix,
one lambda, another is W, okay? And, so, lambda here is a two by two matrix, actually. So,
this is a matrix, actually, has a normality of C minus one. It's a square matrix, C minus one.
Okay. And, so, actually, so, actually, this is no lambda, matrix lambda, actually, the diagonal
matrix. We only have nonzero values on the diagonal. Okay. So, actually, these values are called
the eigenvalues, eigenvalues. Okay. So, one eigenvalue is 1.41, another is 2.9 something.
So, these are two eigenvalues. And then, the W are the eigenvectors. Okay. The first column
corresponds to the first eigenvalue. The second column corresponds to the second column,
eigenvalue. So, this is 1.4155. It's just the lambda here. Okay. Then, the corresponding W,
the, with vector, could certify this equation is the first, is the first one. Okay. The first
vector. Okay. And then, the second, 2.91, actually, is a, this is a lambda. And then, the corresponding
W should be the second column, minus 0.012, 0.0585. So, this is the second column. Okay. So,
the two columns, actually, are the corresponding eigenvectors. Okay. And, actually, these two
vectors, two columns, are just the W1, W2. Okay. The projection we are looking for.
Okay. So, this is W. Of course, no, these are special cases. Right. These, no, the W is here.
Actually, the, the, the, the, the, the number of column in W equals C minus 1. But the number
of rules depend on the monality, right, of the data. In this, no, example, we have a 2D data,
right. So, there are only two rules, actually. So, this is the 2 by 2. These are very special
cases, right. But if you, the data has the monality of 30, then this matrix is 30 times 2. Okay.
Two columns, because we only have two nonzero, no, eigenvectors. We only have two eigenvalues.
We have two non-2D, we have two nonzero eigenvalues. Okay. Then, we have two eigenvectors. Then,
we have two columns. But the monality of these two, the convex vector, depends on the monality of
the data, right. So, the data here is 2D. Right. Then, we have two rules. But if 30,
and then we should have 30 rules, then the matrix is 30 times 2. Okay. Okay. So, these are eigenvectors.
Then, that's actually, we can use the two eigenvectors to construct, actually, the two
dismal functions. Okay. And, actually, the first one, and we normally, we start from the one
corresponding to the larger, or the largest eigenvalue. The largest eigenvalue here is 2.91,
right. So, we use, actually, the second column as the w1. Okay. So, we, w1, which is the second
column in this w1, it's the w1. Okay. And then, we, we put the data to the new dimension, right,
to a new dimension, g1x. Okay. So, w transpose, w1 transpose times x. For each x, we can perform
such a projection. Okay. So, this is the data of the 300 data, and the projected value. The
horizontal axis shows the index of the data, right. So, from 1 to 100, so, this, you know,
the red one is just the samples of class 1, and then from 101 to 200, the sampling class 2,
and then from 201 to 300, the sample of class 3. So, this is the joint index. The vertical value,
the vertical axis shows the projected value, projected value. Okay. So, for blues, no sample,
for sampling class 2, and the projected value normally are in the range, right. Most of them,
actually, actually, is around 0.1, right. Some could be as high as 0.2, some could be as low as
negative. Okay. So, these are the projected samples, and in the values, or in the, in this,
by this, you know, different function g1x, or by this projection vector w1. Okay.
And, actually, of course, actually, we can look at the m11, right. We can look at the mean vector,
mean values, because of the projection, by this, you know, w1x, we get scalar values, right. The
projected value, actually, for each sample is a scalar. Okay. And then we can calculate the mean
value. The mean value for all sampling class 1 equals minus 0.0051. For all sampling class 2,
actually, of the projection, right, by this w1, now we can calculate the mean value. So, that is
0.1470. For all sampling class 3, actually, you know, the mean value of the projection is minus 0.09
13. And from here, actually, we can see m12 is positive, then other is negative, right. And,
actually, the m12 is a bit, actually, away from the sample in class 1 and class 3 of the projection.
Okay. So, in this, actually, w1, our objective is to separate, to separate, okay, class 2 from
other two classes. So, here, we use w1 to separate one class from others. So, one versus the rest.
Okay. So, class 2 versus the rest, actually, is class 1 and class 3. Okay. So, as the objective
of w1 is to separate class 2 from other two classes. So, this is the w1. Okay. And, of course,
actually, we just have w1 and we don't have a bias term, right. Then we look at the projections.
Actually, we can know that many of the values, right, here, actually,
for class 2, 1, actually, is positive, positive, right. And many of the values for class 3 could
also be positive above 0. So, this is 0, right. So, for class 2, for class 2, right,
for class 1, some of the projection value could be positive. Actually, no, we need to find the
w01, the bias term. Okay. And so, that, actually, the projected value, the g1x, right, g1x,
for some of the class 2, or 2, should be positive. Then, for some of the other two classes, it should
be negative. Okay. So, necessarily, we try to find such a w01, right, the w0, okay, for
corresponding to w1x, w1. So, that the blue sample, right, actually, the values could be positive.
And then, the sample in other two classes, the projected values could be negative.
Okay. And in the last class, actually, we have a basic idea principle to follow to obtain the
w0, right. Actually, we see for the 2-clark-climbing problem, we hope the middle point of the 2-mini
vectors is on the, you know, the hyperplane, right, is on the descent boundary. That means that the
digital function equals 0. Okay. And actually, here, we can also use this principle to determine
w0. Actually, when we use this principle, actually, our basic idea is that, actually, the spread of
the, the spread or the scatter of the two classes should be similar, should be similar, right.
Even they are not similar. Then, this value formed by this w is not a good value. Okay. Then,
in the last, we are really suggesting, you know, give some suggestion, right. And we can,
in practice, we can first find this value and then we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we try other
values around this value, right. Then, to find the one that performs the best on the validation data.
Okay. So, here, the principle that, actually, the, the spread of the two classes should be similar.
Okay. But now, actually, when we determine the classes, right, so one is class two. Another
class is class one or class three. Okay. Suddenly, class one, class three, all sample from two
classes, right. So, certainly, the spread of the data should be very big. Okay. So, if we use such a
way to determine the, you know, the w zero, certainly, I think we cannot find a good w zero.
Because the spread of class two could be much smaller than the spread of class one, class three,
together. Okay. And then, how to determine such a value? Actually, you know, in practice, we
cannot determine value based on, you know, we say one class. Class one, class three, right.
Look at which class is closer to class two. We use the sample in that class to determine the w zero.
Rather than use all the sample in the remaining classes, class one and class three. Okay. So,
here, actually, from the main vector, actually, here, with the main values, we find, actually,
m one, one, actually, here, actually, is closer to this m one, two, right. Closer to this one,
two. So, that means class one is closer to class two. Okay. And after projection, by this w one.
Okay. So, in such a scenario, we use, actually, class two, right, with the class two sample,
right. And to determine, actually, class one, class two, to determine the w zero.
Okay. So, this is the w zero.
W zero is based on class one and class two. Because class two is closer,
we're class one closer to class two. We don't use the mean of class one and class three, right.
And together, right. We don't use that because the spread of class one, class two,
three together could be very big. Okay. So, okay. So, this is the w zero one.
And so, now, we can combine w one and w zero one to construct the different function g one x, right.
Okay. So, this is the, okay. So, I think this is the, let me see. So, this is the g one x.
G one x. Actually, I don't know the adjustment by this w zero. And we can see most of the data
of class two, right. Class one is below zero. More data, actually. Previously, before we used
the w zero, the bias term. Actually, we see many samples, you know, have
positive values, not represented by w one, right. But now, the adjustment by w zero,
w zero, right. And then most of the values of class one are below zero. And also here,
also below zero. Of course, not all of them are actually below zero. And also for class two,
all of them actually are above zero. Okay. So, this is because, actually, you know, the data,
actually, we cannot achieve 100% accuracy. Okay. And some of the samples have been misclassified.
Okay. And then the lesson we look at the w two, right. So, w two is the first column,
corresponding to the smaller, actually, the eigenvalue. Okay. And so, this is the projection
samples on w two. And actually, from w two, we can see, after projection, w two and w three are
almost, all the values are in this range, right, from, actually, minus zero point two five to
minus zero point zero five on this range, right. So, but actually, for class one, it seems that the
value is five away from the projection value of other two classes. Okay. So, w two will be used
to separate class one from other two classes. Okay. Because upper projection, actually,
w two and w three are always mixed. They are mixed. Because why we say mixed? Because you look at the
vertical value, right. They're almost the same. Okay. But w one, the red one is very different
from other two classes. Okay. So, we use w two to construct the g two x to separate class one
from other two classes, common class one, class three. Okay. So, and again, actually, we can know
for w two, we need to find the corresponding w zero, the bias term, right. So, we show you that
with the one that the closest to w class one. So, actually, here, actually, the class three line is
class two is closer to class one, right. So, the class two to calculate, actually, the bias term
for w two. Okay. So, based on the w one, the corresponding w zero one, w two and the corresponding
w zero two, and we have actually obtained these two different final tracks. For each x, for each x,
right. For each x, and we can substitute into g one x to get a value, right. And also, we can
substitute to g two x, we can get a value. Okay. And then, how to make the decision based on g
one x, based on g two x. Of course, ideally, we see when g x, g one x is positive, then the sample
should be classified to class two. Because g one, actually, should be able to separate the class
two from others, right. If g one x is positive, then it should be classified to class one. Okay.
And if g two x is positive, and then if g one x is negative, then, of course, actually, we should
classify them into class one. Okay. So, this is the decision rules, based on one, one, and the
and the class two. Okay. So, this is the decision rule. If g one x greater than zero, and g two
x negative, so then, we will classify them into class two. Okay. And if g one, g two x is positive,
and g one x is negative, and then, the sample should be class, class one. Because g x, g two x
try to separate class one from other two classes, right. And g one x try to separate class two from
other two classes. Okay. So, this is the g one x greater than zero, g two x negative. Okay. And
then, the message is, how about both negative? If g one x negative, g one x negative, this should
not belong to class two, right. And if g two x negative, this should not belong to class one.
Okay. Then, we should actually, assign this sample to class three. Okay. And then, there is one
additional scenario. How about g x is positive, and g two is positive? There are some possibilities,
right. Some possibilities. g one is positive, and g two is positive. g one x, or this is class one,
and g two x, g two, g one x positive, oh, we see this probably is, is class two. And g one x is
positive, and probably is class one. And then, how to classify, okay. And then, actually, in such a
scenario, we, based on which one is bigger, right. If g one x is greater, then we classify the sample
to class two. If g two is greater, we classify sample to class one. Okay. So, this is the
decision boundary, based on the, about decision rules. Okay. So, the samples in the two, three
classes, and then, I created, actually, like a 10,000 data set, data point, in this region,
in this range, right. And then, we classify each of the samples, based on these classification rules.
And then, finally, we find a region for each of the three classes. So, the yellow region,
for class, actually, the, for class two, right. Yeah. Okay. And then, the green region, and for
class one, and then, the blue region for, actually, class three. Okay. So, we, finally, you know,
we separate, or we divide, or we partition the whole space into three parts, into three regions.
And each region corresponds to one class. So, that is just classification. So, what is classification?
Classification is just the partitioning of the feature space. Okay. Into different regions.
And each region corresponds to one class. So, this is called classification, right. So,
so, indeed, actually, through this, actually, decision rules, and we have divided the whole
space into three parts. And each part corresponds to one class. Okay. So, this is a, you know,
a multiple, you know, analysis. Okay. And so, I think both, actually, you know, two class
two analysis, or multiple class two analysis. The main idea is that we try to find the W's,
okay, the weight vectors, or weight matrix, so that the, within class scatter could be minimized,
between class scatter could be maximized. So, this is actually a very basic idea.
If you answer this idea, I think, in future, in your research or in your, you know,
exploration of any machine learning project, right, actually, you can benefit, actually,
sometimes, based on this idea, you can divide your own ideas. Okay. I think this is a very
important idea in both classification, classifier design, and also the future selection. And in
future selection, we also hope to find the attributes that could actually possess these properties.
Within class, they are very similar. Between class, they are very different. Okay. So, this is actually
the very basic principle in the future, the linear different analysis, maximize, maximization of the
between class difference, the scatter or minimized, within class scatter or difference.
Okay. So, that's an afternoon break with a top of a small machine, which will have a
double different principle to find the projections. Okay. So, that's actually, we have a 10-minute break.
Okay.
Okay. So, necessarily, we look at another classifier, subordinate machines.
And the subordinate machines can be linear or nonlinear. Okay. So, nonlinear subordinate
machines also called kernel subordinate machines. But in this course, we will talk about the linear
subordinate machines only. Okay. And so, actually, this linear, right, so linear, so linear again,
of course, actually, now in the space, actually, naturally, now the decision boundary of a linear
classifier, actually, is just a straight line, right? So, here, again, we look at the two class
classroom problem. And so, our objective, of course, to find a certain boundary, right?
A certain boundary, so that the sampling of the two classes could be separated by this
decision boundary. In other words, this decision boundary will divide the whole space,
the whole feature space in the two parts, right? One part belongs to class one, and another
class belongs to class two. Okay. So, the objective of a linear classifier is just to
find this straight line, right? And, of course, this hyperplane, or this hyperplane, you know,
linear decision boundary is determined by two parts. One is W, another is a bias term, W, zero.
Okay. And so, of course, the key issue in the, again, in the linear classifier, in this linear
classifier is to find a W and W, zero, so that we can separate the samples correctly. Okay. But,
actually, we're not just known for this objective. We have other objectives. Not just
classifying correctly. We also try to reclassify the sample competently. Okay. So, here, actually,
we have known, like, three examples, three testing data, data point A and the sample B and the sample
C, right? And so, actually, of course, actually, both, all the three samples are located on the positive
side of the decision boundary, right? So, they are located on the side of the class one. So,
the three samples will be classified into class one. Okay. And, but when we classify three samples,
actually, into class one, then we have a different confidence for the three samples, right? And the
class, the sample A, you know, is very far from the decision boundary, right? So, actually, when we
perform this classification to class one, you know, we have very high, we are very confident.
We have high confidence, right? But for sample C, actually, we see it's very close to the decision
boundary, right? Although, no, we're classifying to class three, but actually, it's class one. But
it's marginal, right? It's marginal. Okay. And, actually, in the last week, we already analyzed,
actually, actually, the distance, right? And to the decision boundary. And actually, can be measured
from the GX, right? From the GX. And then, as in the last week, we already know GX divided by the
norm of W, actually, it's just the distance from the data point to the decision boundary, right?
If G, if, if this GX is very small, and then, although it's positive, but just know like,
0.1 or 0.2 or very small value, right? So, although they are positive, but they are not
positive enough, okay? So, we can already, you know, have a low confidence to classify them into
class one. Okay. And, actually, this confidence, confidence, right, actually, is a, is a, is a
distance from the data point to, on to the decision boundary, to the decision boundary. And,
actually, you know, for, for, for, for a given data set like this, and, actually, we could have many,
actually, actually, linear classifier to separate the sample into two classes. Okay. But, actually,
the data point to the difference, the decision boundary would be very different. Okay. And,
maybe, necessarily, I'll show you one example. This, right? So, these are the data, the data
distribution here, the same. Okay. And, we have two, actually, decision boundaries. We have two
different linear classifiers. One on the left-hand side, another on the right-hand side. And, for
the, on the left-hand side, actually, we can see, for this is our point, right? It's very close to
the decision boundary. Okay. Although, actually, when we classify them, as you, we know, or this
point is looking at the right-hand side, in the positive side of this, of this, actually, decision
boundary, we will classify this sample to the positive class. But, actually, this classification
has a very low confidence, low confidence, right? And, if there is a big change, if some sample,
like, this X, right, this X, if there is a small change, for example, there could be a noise,
measurement noise. And, then, this sample could be located in the negative side of the decision
boundary. Then, the sample could be classified wrongly. Okay. And, similarly, and for other samples
in the negative class, like this one, right, is also close to the decision boundary. Although,
we classify them into class, negative class, but this classification has a low confidence.
Okay. But, this one is very different. Okay. So, this is another decision boundary,
another classifier. Okay. And, we can see, actually, the distance,
the distance, right, to the decision boundary
is very big, is bigger, right, compared with this scenario. Okay. And, then, in this scenario,
not only we can classify the samples correctly, but we can also classify the samples confidently,
confidently. Okay. So, certainly, you know, the classifying the right-hand side, actually,
it's preferred. It's preferred. Okay. So, we want to find such a classifier,
and that the sample classified correctly and also confidently. So, that's, you know, some
observation from the data, right, actually some analysis. We know the classification,
not just for classify them correctly. They know the only goal, right. Another goal is that we should
classify them confidently. So, this is, you know, the objective, classify the sample correctly,
and also classify the sample confidently. That means, actually, we should find such a decision
boundary that all the samples are far away from the decision boundaries. So, this is our objective.
Okay. So, from here, you can see that this analysis, right, is from a different angle,
right. This is different from the feature linear digital analysis. Okay. In the feature
digital analysis, we try to look at the, you know, within class spread and between class spread.
But in this concept, actually, not used in the spoil and the machines, because here we are only
concerned with the points close to the decision boundary. We don't care whether someone in the
three-seem class actually are within the same class, right. The scatter is minimized or not. We
don't care about this. Instead, we just care about the data points on the decision boundary.
Actually, these points are normally the most difficult, actually, to classify.
Samples close to the decision boundary are normally those samples that are difficult to
classify. Okay. So, we only concern about this part of the samples, the data. So, that's the
best idea. I think the motivation of the support machine. Okay. Okay. So, let's actually talk about
the formulation, the fundamental formulation of the problem. And so, actually, the linear
classifier, and we have two parts, right. One is the projection of W, another is the bias term.
Okay. So, here, actually, for the convention, it's for when machine, we use the B to do the
bias term. Okay. So, this is just the W zero, right. In the previous, the feature linear
analysis, this is the bias term, constant. Okay. The W is the projection. Okay. So, and so, the
W transpose X plus B equals zero is just the equation for the decision boundary. Okay.
And in one side, and then the data points actually will achieve a positive decision
function. That means the W transpose X plus B is greater than zero. So, these are the samples
for class Y. Okay. And then, if this is negative, then this sample actually class minus Y. Okay.
In support of the machine, it's actually the class label. Normally, we don't use the class
one, class two. We use the class one to denote one class, the label minus one to denote class,
actually, class two or any class, right. So, we use the minus one or one to denote
actually the two different classes. Okay. And, okay. So, this is the, so, the classification,
right, the decision boundary. This is the same as the feature linear denomination. For any linear
classifier, so, we have this equation. Any linear classifier. Okay. We have this, okay. We have
a W, we have a B. But just the different methods have different ways to find these W and the B.
Okay. And now, actually, we need to introduce a concept which is called a margin of separation.
Okay. And so, here, actually, we have a, this is a decision boundary. This is a decision
boundary. The solid line here is a decision boundary. And actually, here, we also have two,
actually, dashed lines. So, these two dashed lines are parallel to this, actually, the
solid line which is the decision boundary. And these two dashed lines pass through the samples
that are closest to the decision boundary. Okay. You see, these are the samples, these two samples,
actually, so, this is the, this is the hyperplane, this is the line, actually, pass through this
sample. Actually, this sample, two samples are the closest to the decision boundary. And on another
side of this, this is the sample in another class, and we have one sample here which is
closest to the decision boundary. And then, we have a parallel, actually, you know, three line here,
right, dashed line. And actually, the distance between these two dashed lines is called margin
separation, margin separation. Okay. So, the separation between the hyperplane and the
closest data points is called the margin separation. Okay. And actually, the objective of support
weather measurements is to find such W and B, and so that this margin separation is maximized.
So, this is the best-posed idea. Margin separation is maximized. So, this is very different from the
feature linear German analysis, right? So, we try to maximize the margin separation. But this
margin separation, of course, determined by two factors. One is the location and the orientation
of the decision boundary, right? And another, actually, is the sample closest to the decision
boundaries. Okay. So, this is a good support weather measurement to find such a hyperplane,
a particular hyperplane, the decision boundary, as for which the margin of separation is maximized.
We want to find this. And just now, we know, we know, we analyze the scenario, right? We have
three samples, A, B, C, right? We see, oh, the sample C is very close to the decision boundary,
so we have a low confidence. But now, if margin of separation maximizes, that means the distance,
even the closest distance, right, to the decision boundary could have a higher confidence
to be classified into one of the two classes. Okay. So, here, we see maximizing the margin of
separation. Actually, also, the maximization of the confidence to perform the classification
of the sample in the two classes, right? Even for the samples, they are closest to the decision
boundary. And this margin is maximized. And we have the highest confidence to separate them,
to classify them. Okay. And under this condition, the decision
boundary or decision boundary is called the optimal hyperplane, the optimal decision boundary.
Okay. The decision boundary that has the maximum margin of separation, actually,
is called the optimal hyperplane, the optimal decision boundary. Okay. Of course, the goal
of support animation is to find the optimal hyperplane that could separate the samples
in the two classes correctly and also confidently. Okay.
Okay. So, I think in the last week, you already know, Anna did, right? So, for any data points,
actually, X, right? X. And actually, now, we can have a tree projection of this X on this
decision boundary. And we can do the projection here, just Xp, right? Xp. And actually, this
decision boundary is perpendicular to the W. Okay. And this W, if we normalize W by dividing
W by the normal W, right? Then we can get a directional vector. This directional vector,
actually, is not given the direction of W. But the length, the norm is just 1. Okay. And
so, actually, for such a scenario tree, we also analyze a tree for any arbitrary point X.
It can be represented by the Xp plus R times, R is the distance from this X to the decision
boundary, right? And times the direction W times W norm. Okay. And this W should point to the direction,
to the positive side of the decision boundary, point to the positive class. Okay. And also,
we know in the last week, we analyzed this already, right? And actually, we substitute this X, actually,
and we know this, you know, the gx divided by the norm is just a distance between the data points
and to the decision boundary, right? Data points to the decision boundary. We need to
use these results because the model of separation, right, actually, just the points
actually to the decision boundary, the distance to the point, to the decision boundary. We should
maximize the model of separation, right? So, this certainly is relevant to the distance measure,
right? For gx and then divided by the normal W, just R. Okay. Okay. So, now, for this tree,
just now, we see, you know, when we perform classification, we see for positive class,
the W transpose X should be positive greater than zero. For net two samples, W transpose X
actually plus B should be negative, less than zero. Okay. And actually, we can always scale
a W and a B and so that we can satisfy this condition. W transpose X plus B greater than one.
For example, if our W transpose plus B is greater than, it's just known that the
smallest value is zero to one. Then you times ten, ten, right? Then you can get actually,
it will be greater than ten, than one. Okay. So, we can always scale the W and the B and so that
this condition could be satisfied. W transpose X plus B greater than or equals one for all the
sample in class one. For all sample in class minus one, the W transpose X plus B should be
less than or equals minus one. Okay. We can always scale W and B and so that
these two conditions are satisfied. Okay. And let's actually have a look of the,
oh, look at this. Okay. So, this is the W transpose X plus B equals zero, right? So,
even if you scale W and B, then this is still that zero, right? Even if that means scale,
that means you times the constant to the two sides, it's still zero, right? But actually,
we can push the value, right? W transpose X plus B for arbitrary positive value. Okay. Other scale
to, to greater than or equals one, than equals one. And then here we have two lines here and all the
points on this dash line actually certify this condition. W transpose X plus B equals positive
one. Okay. And all actually, another side actually, we also have a line that is both parallel to this
hyperplane and all the points on this hyperplane certify this condition. W transpose X plus B
equals minus one. Okay. And actually, all the points that you certify this condition,
one or minus one are called support vectors. So, this is no method called support vector machine,
right? So, what are support vectors? So, these are the support vectors. All the points, right? All the
points that certify this condition are called support vectors. Okay. So, here they have this
two-sign boundary, right? Yeah. Okay. The particular data points for which the above
is certified with equality, right? Because greater than equals, right? So, certify the equality
condition. And then, so this number are called support vectors. Okay. And later, we will see
this half, optimal hyperplane are determined by this optimal, by this support vectors only.
So, here in the, in this diagram, we just have three support vectors. Okay. So, these are the,
in other words, this dissonant boundary is determined by these three support vectors only.
So, this is also the reason why this classification argument is called support vector machines.
Because this dissonant boundary, this classifier, is determined by these three support vectors only.
Okay. So, so this is not the support vector machine, right? So, those samples certify this
equality condition, actually, are called support vectors. Okay. So, necessarily, now we look at
this. Okay. And so, we, we submit that the support vectors, right, into the dissonant boundary,
into the, into the decimal function. And the GX, GX is W transpose plus B, right, equals one.
This is for positive class. Okay. And then the, the GX, the decimal function, W transpose X plus B,
right, actually equals minus one. Okay. And then the distance to the dissonant boundary for the
support vectors, right, for positive support vectors, the distance to the dissonant boundary is
one to the GX, right, divided by the norm of W. And then the distance for negative support vectors
to the dissonant boundary is minus one divided by the norm of W. Okay. So, this is the distance
from these positive, positive support vectors to the dissonant boundary. And the minus one divided
by norm is the distance from this negative support vector to the dissonant boundary. Okay. And then
the margin of separation actually is just actually twice of this, right. One divided by norm,
right. Another is the minus one divided by norm actually. So, the distance here actually is two
divided by the norm. So, this is the margin of separation. Okay. So, we want to find such a W
and so that this rule is maximized. Of course, if you just look at this condition,
they're not sufficient, right. Because actually W, if you see the norm is zero, then this is
infinity, right. But here actually, we just actually, this norm is maximized because we want to
maximize the confidence. But there is another condition, the sample needs to be classified
correctly. Okay. So, we need to combine the two. Okay. So, necessarily, we formulate support
vectors. We try to maximize this rule. Okay. And then actually, we maximize this rule, right.
Then the margin of separation. Actually, maximization of rule actually is equivalent to
minimization of the norm of W. Okay. Or actually, in practice, we don't actually minimize the norm
of the L1 norm of W. Instead, we try to minimize the square norm, the L2 norm. Okay. So, that's actually,
you know, this is the alternative. And the condition, the samples are classified correctly.
And this condition will maximize the margin of separation. Okay. And then actually,
based on this analysis, actually, we know the support vector machine, actually,
actually, it can be a tree formulated as such a constant or malization problem.
Constant or malization, right. So, given the training samples, SDI, so these are no training
sample pairs, right. We have the data, the representation of the sample, and also the class
label DI. Okay. The DI is either positive one or negative one. Okay. And the optimal value of the
width vector W and the bus B, we want to find these values, optimal values, B, W and B. And such that
they set further constraint. This constraint is just a tree. All the samples need to be
classified correctly. We know for positive samples, W transpose X plus Y should be greater than equals
one. Okay. For negative samples, W transpose X plus B should be less than or equal to minus one.
Okay. But we can combine the two conditions into one, right. So, that is just DI, the class label,
times this is greater than equals one. When DI is positive, we have no problem. This is just W
transpose X plus one, right. When DI negative, so these are less than minus one. So, the same.
Okay. So, we combine the two into one condition. Okay. Under this condition, we maximize, we minimize
the square norm of W because the rule, right, equal to two divided by norm of W, right.
Maximization of rule is equal to minimization of the normal W. But in practice, the
minimization of the normal W is a bit challenging. We minimize the square of the normal W. Okay.
So, when we have half a tree, normally we put a half because later we see when we look at the
derivative, this half will be canceled, right. So, quite often you also will see a cross-fond
line, something like a half of that. Because later, this half could be canceled. Okay. So,
this does not matter, right. Even if you don't have a half, it's also okay. So, we try to minimize
this cross-fond shape. Subject to these conditions. These conditions just for each of the training
sample, they should be classified correctly. So, correctly under this condition, we maximize the
confidence. So, this is a basic idea of the support and measures. So, you can see this is a different
from the Fisher's linear treatment analysis. Very different ideas. Okay. And actually,
before machine learning, before deep learning, right, different networks and the for natural
angular procession, for the image procession, that's as much as data. Actually, the subordinate
machine is the most popular, you know, research field in the machine, in machine learning.
So, because of the very good performance of the support and measures.
So, now, actually through analysis, right. Finally, the support and measures summarize
as a constant or malation problem. Again, you know, this formulation is a,
is a malation problem. But here is a bit different. It's a constant malation problem.
The constant here is, the constant here are from all the training sample. For each of the
training sample, we have one constant, right. The training sample need to be classified correctly.
For each training sample, we have one constant. So, the, with here, we have a total, we have n
constant. n here is the number of training samples. Okay. i from 1 to n. Okay. For each of the
sample, we have one constant. This constant, just that, this sample should be classified correctly.
Okay. This sample, W transpose X plus B should be greater than 1 or equal to 1 or less than or
equal to minus 1. Okay. So, this is the constant or malation problem, right. So, necessary,
to find the W, we should try to, our best, right, to solve this constant or malation problem.
I think for constant or malation problem, I think you already started that, right, before
and where you started in year one or year two, right. When we started calculus, actually,
we started constant or malation, right. And when we started the derivative, I think you remember,
right, calculus, actually, we learned, we have the knowledge of constant or malation. Okay. And
actually, in the NTULAN website, actually, I upload one supplementary material for the constant
or malation problem. Okay. You can have a look at that. Okay. And so, now, based on this constant
and this or malation criteria, right, and so how to solve the constant or malation problem.
And then we can use the so-called Lagrange multiplier method, right. Okay. So,
okay. And the constant or malation problem has a falling characteristic. The cost function,
Jw is a convex, convex, just like a bow here, right, a bow, actually, we can find the optimal
solution, global optimal solution. Okay. And actually, then the constant are linear in W.
So, for this kind of linear W, actually, we can use the so-called Lagrange multiplier method
to solve. Okay. And, okay. So, actually, we can introduce this, actually, the Lagrange,
Lagrange function, which contains two parts. The first part is just the cost function we try to
minimize, the half of the square norm of W. Then the second half, actually, the second part here,
comes from the constant. Okay. And if you look at the textbook or even you recall the constant
or malation method, so normally, we have a cost function and we have constant. Normally,
the constant should be something like the constant, see the Gx or Hx is less than or equal to zero,
right. Normally, we have this kind of constant. Okay. But here, our constant is here, that tree,
d times greater than or equal to minus one, greater than one, right. Of course, here, we should
formulate, we should move the one to the left-hand side. So, greater than zero. But this is different
from the constant in the conventional, you know, that the constant should be less than or equal to
zero, right. So, if we put a minus sign before that, so minus di times W transpose Xi plus b
minus one, less than or equal to zero. Okay. And then, we introduce a multiplier. Okay. So,
for each constant, we introduce one multiplier. In your previous, you know, we say, when you solve
the constant or malation problem, use the Lagrange multiplier method. Normally, we just have one
constant. But here, we have an n constant. Because for each sample, we have one constant.
Okay. So, here, we introduce n multipliers. Alpha one, alpha two, and alpha n. For each alpha,
correspond to one constant. Okay. So, we can have a one, minus alpha one times the constant.
Minus alpha two times the constant, right. So, finally, we summarize that together,
actually, the totally n constant into one, which is i from one to n, summation of all the constant,
times the Lagrange multiplier, alpha i. Okay. So, we should find such W, b, and alpha,
so that this L is minimized. So, this is our next objective, right. We should find such W
b and alpha as that, this L function, Lagrange function, right, is minimized.
Okay. So, now, of course, we have a basic condition, right, to minimize a function. Certainly,
the first orderity of this function will respect the coefficient, will respect the W, b,
alpha, should be zero, right. So, this is a condition. Okay. So, that's actually, we look
at these conditions. Okay. Of course, this alpha i actually should be non-negative, non-negative.
Okay. And, later, you will find that among all the n samples, very few alphas will be non-zeroes.
Most of the alphas will be zeroes. Okay. Only those superwaters have non-zero alphas.
All others have zero alphas. Okay. But, at the beginning, we don't know, now, in the hard
domain of space, you cannot see the data, right. You don't know which sample is a supervector.
We don't know. Okay. So, we can't, we don't know which alpha is zero, right. But, finally,
we can find, actually, the alpha values for all the samples, alpha 1, alpha n. Then, you will
find, actually, based on whether alpha is zero or non-zero, we will determine whether it is a
supervector or non-supervector. Okay. So, next, actually, we try to solve this problem. And,
first, look at the first orderity of L with respect to W. This should be zero. And, first,
all the derivative of L with respect to B should also be zero. Right? Okay. So, we differentiate L
with respect to W and B. So, the first orderity of L with respect to W should be zero. Right? This
is a condition, right? Condition. Okay. And, then, we first look at the form of condition 1.
First orderity with respect to W. This part is a function of W, right? W times W. Actually,
the first orderity of L is 2W. Then, this half could be cancelled. And, for this part,
R for i, d i, W transpose xi. So, the first orderity with respect to W will be R for i, d i, xi.
Okay. Then, the other part, actually, is a closed rate to B, right? We don't need to care. Okay.
So, from the condition 1, actually, we know the first orderity, right? Okay. W transpose W,
first orderity, actually, is 2W. Okay. And, then, actually, the second part, right, is R for i,
d i, xi. Okay. And, then, actually, now, okay. i from 1, actually, to n. Okay. And, so, this
should be zero. Should be zero. So, for this part, actually, then, from this, actually, we can obtain
result W equals R for i, d i, xi. So, this, actually, looks a bit strange, right? A bit strange.
Okay. Actually, the W, actually, is a linear summation. It's a W-summation of the training
samples. This is the support rate, right? The weight. Weight, no, it's the summation of the input xi.
But each of the sample xi has a corresponding weightage. The weight is just the R for i,
the corresponding multiplier. And, multiply the class label, d i.
Right? d i. The W, okay. I just mentioned, later, you will see, most of the alpha will be zeros.
Only a few alpha will be non-zero. So, that means, only those small number of sub-vectors
will determine the W. The linear summation, the weight-summ of the sub-vectors, is just
the weight vector W. Right? From here, no, it seems that this W is very easy to find, right?
As long as we know the alpha values, and then, we can easily calculate the W, because d i is the
class label, which is known. xi is a training sample, representation, of course, it is known.
The summation of them is just the W. Okay. So, from the first known condition, we obtain these results.
So, let's say, no, we look at another condition. Part of derivative. Actually, if we look at this
set function, right? So, the first part is not related to B, right? Only the second part,
alpha i, d i, times B. Okay. Then, the derivative, no, the B will be kind of, will be alpha i,
d i, i from 1 to n, right? So, from here, from the second condition, derivative will be zero.
Okay. And this will be, that means that alpha i, d i equals zero. Submission of all of them equals zero.
And actually, the d i, d i, you know, could be positive, right? Or could be negative.
But finally, actually, alpha i is positive. Or at least, it's non-negative. Okay. And actually,
we know some of the alpha will be zero, right? So, when we do the summation, it has no contribution.
Only the support vector, which have a non-zero alpha, right? And then, alpha i, d i, that means
the summation of the alpha of the positive support vectors should be equal to the summation of the
alpha of the negative support vectors. So, this is also a very interesting result, right? We
catered alphas for all the support vectors, for all the samples. But most of the samples, we have
zero alpha. On the support vectors, we have non-zero alpha. But the support vectors of the positive
alpha, the positive support vectors, the summation alpha of the positive support vector, should be
equal to the summation of the alphas of the negative support vectors. So, this is from condition B.
Then, we obtain these results. Okay.
Okay. So, actually, beside this condition, we have some other conditions. So, actually,
for the constant omission, actually, we can have this KKT, actually, the omission theory. And they
have another condition. That is, for the constant, right? The constant should be zero. The constant.
R for i times the constant, right? This should be zero. The R for i is greater than equal to zero.
R for i, that's a multiplier. The rock part should be greater than or equal to zero, right?
And then, the R for i times this, I know the constant. It should be zero.
Okay. And actually, if you look at this, right? And we know now for the W transpose x plus B
minus y, minus y. Okay. So, W transpose x plus B should be greater than equals to y, right?
Normally, greater than or equals to y, right? We have this, right? Greater than or equals to y.
Okay. And, or less than or equal to minus y, right? We have these results. Okay. And actually,
we'll, W R for i will be nine zero only for power point or sample, certify the equality in the
constant. If R, this actually, this is nine zero. Then, if this is nine zero, this means they are,
they are not on these two parallel, no? And on the dash, no, the three lines, right? So, then,
they are not sample vectors. And then, this R for i will be zero, right? Because the multiplication
should be zero, right? And only for those on the decision boundary should be zero. Should be zero,
right? And not on the decision boundary, on the parallel, right? The closest sample, actually,
yeah. That's the samples that certify the equality condition, right? Equality condition.
W transpose x i plus B equals minus y or equals y. Okay. So, for this part,
okay, R for i is nine zero. For others, because this part will be greater than one,
than zero, then R for i must be zero because we have these two smart applications should be zero.
Okay. So, just to see, actually, the small vectors correspond to nine zero R for i. For all other
samples, the R for i, the multiplier, actually, are zeros. Okay. So, these are the conditions, right?
So, this is actually an illustration, right? So, those are the samples, certify the equality
condition, right? W transpose x plus B equals one or equals minus one. Then, for those parts,
they have nine zero R for us. Nine zero R. Therefore, all other points, these points,
these points, right? These points, these points, they have zero R for us. And just now we see,
you know, the W is a contribution, right? Of all the training samples, R for i, D i, x i. If R for i
is zero, right? Certainly, have no contribution. In other words, all other samples here, right?
These samples, these samples have no contribution to the W. Okay. The W, actually, is calculated
based on the sub-varietars only, based on those three samples in this example. One, two, three.
And actually, in this, actually, the R, here, we have two sub-varietars, right? We have one alpha
value for this, well, we have another alpha value for these sub-varietars. The summation of the two
alpha values should be equal to the alpha value of this sample. Because in this side, we only have
one sub-varietar, right? And then we have one alpha for this sub-varietar. And these alpha values
should be equal to the summation of the two alpha values corresponding to these two sub-varietars.
This is because of this condition, right? This condition. Sorry, this condition.
Okay. R for i, D i, summation, zero.
Okay.
Okay. So, next, actually, we will, we expand this at W. Just now, we see the W, you know,
first part, actually, is a norm, right? The square norm of W. The second part is a,
is a constant termed alpha, right? For the constant, actually, we have two parts, right?
One, actually, the W, right? Another is a little b, right? And also, that part is a y, minus y,
okay? So, we expand this, we expand the L, and then we have one, two, three, four parts. Okay.
And, okay. Just now, no, based on the condition two, we have found actually the z term, summation
of alpha i, D i should be zero, based on the condition two, right? So, this part is a, a,
a, a, remove. Okay. Then, in the L, we just have three parts. The first part, which is the square
norm of W, and then this part. And then the last part is the summation of alpha.
Okay. So, next, actually, for the three parts, right? Actually, we expand the second part.
We perform expansion. Okay. How do we perform expansion? The second part here, right?
And, actually, we substitute the W. W is the summation for alpha i, D i, x, x i, right? So,
we replace W using the, to W transpose, right? Just actually alpha i, D i, x i, then transpose,
x, x transpose. Okay. So, here, we already have i. We use the j, right? j from 1 to n.
So, this part is just the W, right? W transpose. Okay. So, alpha i, D i, W transpose,
then x i. Okay. So, we just do some manipulation. Okay. And then, actually,
we can move alpha i, D i into this side. Okay. So, this, so this is the expansion of this.
Okay. And, let's actually look at another part, the first part, W transpose, W. And, actually,
here, we replace this W and also, actually, using the summation of alpha i, D i, x i, right?
i from 1 to n. Okay. So, here, the j, right? Okay. J from 1 to n, the W alpha i, D i, D j, alpha j,
D j, x j. So, this part, actually, is just the W, right? Okay. So, we do this, you know.
What? W transpose. W transpose is also alpha i, D i, x transpose, right? Okay. And so, finally,
you know, we can see, move in, right? So, this is the form. Actually, just now, we rederub this,
right? It has this form. And, for the first term. And, for the second first term,
it also has this form. Actually, so, the two parts, actually, can become one, right? Can become one.
Okay. And, actually, the first part is a half, right? Actually, so, actually, we can cancel,
cancel half. Then, actually, the L becomes this. So, this is the last term, summation of alpha.
Then, minus half alpha, one half alpha. Because, the first W transpose, W is half, right? Then,
this part is canceled. Okay. So, finally, we have this function. And, if you look at this function,
we find that G, the L contains alpha only. We no longer have W. We no longer have B. We only have
alpha. Okay. So, through many mathematical manipulations, right? Actually, from a function,
L, which contains two parts, right? One is the, you know, the function we want to minimize.
Another is the constraint. Okay. So, we have many unknown parameters, W, the B, like very
much applied, alpha. But, through many, you know, many manipulations, many manipulations. Finally,
we find another equivalent L. This L contains alpha only. B and W do not appear. Okay. So,
so, this is actually, you know, the S, I, S, J, like, actually, the training sample,
like, these are already known. Okay. So, here, actually, this is W, right? So, now,
that's actually, we try to minimize the L. Actually, we try to find alpha so that the L could be
minimized. And, actually, this problem is called a dual problem. The original problem is called a
primal problem. The primal problem, you know, the L, right, contains the, you know, W contains B,
right, contains alpha. But, if there's a dual problem, we only have this alpha.
Okay. So, this problem is called the dual problem. The original problem is called a primal problem.
Okay. So, the dual problem contains alpha only. Actually, as long as we can find alpha,
then we can find W, right? Because W is just a summation of alpha, I, DR, X, I, right? So,
and so, the B, actually, after we find alpha, then later we can find B. Okay. After we find W.
Okay. So, the most critical part of the tree is alpha. So, here, we just try to solve this
homogenous problem to find the value of alpha, I. After that, find B. Okay. But, how to find alpha?
Of course, actually, this is not an easy task. Actually, this kind of problem, actually,
of course, here is the condition, sublet this condition, right? Alpha, I,
D, I should be equal to zero. Okay. So, this is not from condition B2, right? The partial
dual L with respect to B, right? We get this condition. And also, alpha, I should be zero.
Okay. So, next, we solve this constant homogenous problem. And so, the Q could be
minimized. Okay. And how to solve this problem? And actually, this is a quadratic programming
problem. Actually, we can use, you know, quadratic programming software to solve this problem.
And actually, part of it, you know, in the conversional, you know, quadratic programming
problem, we just have a few parameters, right? A few parameters. For example, in your provisional
work, actually, you just have one parameter, right? If you have one constant, one constant,
two constant, you just have two alphas, right? But now, the number of alphas is just a number
of training samples. In practice, the training samples could be huge, right? Or a few thousand,
tens of thousands. Okay. So, in practice, actually, the solution for this problem,
or no, we do all these, like, solve problem, kind of solve one, the quadratic programming,
you know, the software, right? But actually, not so easy, you know, in practice. Not so
straightforward. If you use a QP and an algorithm, you know, the terminal software to solve this
problem is a very time-consuming. Okay. And actually, when this actually, a support-wide
machine just, you know, developed, of course, we all see the very good properties, the ideas,
but it's very difficult to use because actually, it's very time-consuming and to find, to solve
this problem. Okay. And until later, they have found some, you know, sequential method or approximation,
actually, sequential method to solve this, you know, quadratic programming problem,
which can solve the problem very efficiently. And then, a support-wide machine becomes very popular.
Okay. And remember, at that time, actually, when professor in the Taiwan University,
you know, they run the coding in C, and then to solve this problem. At that time,
and all the people in the world actually use this, that software. Okay. So later, they have
developed a new algorithm, the sequential omission method to solve this QP problem,
and then become popular. Okay. So, okay. Okay. So, okay. And that's actually, we have a break,
time-inspirited. Okay.
Okay.
Okay. So, now, actually, we can use some software to, like, keep you software to solve this,
quadratic programming problem, and to find the alpha values, right? So, once alpha values are
found, and then we can use actually, you know, the formula to calculate the w directly, right?
Actually, the w, the width vector is simply the width summation of all the samples. Okay. And actually,
we also answer, most of the samples, we have actually zero alpha, right? So, we only use the
non-zero alpha. Those samples actually correspond to non-zero alpha to calculate the w. And those
samples actually are called sub-vectors. Okay. So, alpha, r, d, r, x, i. Submission of the,
you know, this is a very interesting result, right? Submission of the input is a width vector.
Okay. But it's a width summation, right? So, I think, as always, alpha, r, d, i, it's a width. Okay.
d, i is a class label, right? Okay. And then once we find the alpha, right, we found w,
and then, unless we need to find the biotherm b. Okay. And actually, we can use the width
sub-vectors, any sub-vector to find this biotherm b, right? Actually, we know, you know, based on the,
you know, the sub-vectors, which are on the boundary, which satisfy the equality condition,
right? W transpose x plus b equals 1 or minus 1, right? Or we will type di, the class label,
then it's equal to e equals 1. Okay. So, from here, actually, we can see, you know, the b,
actually equals 1 divided by r d, i minus w transpose x, i. W transpose here, w, you know,
is found here in the previous step, right? Then we can find this b, okay? 1 over di, di could be
1 or minus 1, right? So, 1 over di is just di, not the same, okay? Minus w transpose x. Okay. So,
you know, this is the biotherm. It's just the target value, right? Minus, actually, the value from the,
the projection, right? W transpose x. Okay. So, this is the way to find the biotherm. So,
this is also different from the way, you know, to find the biotherm in the Fisher-Linus
Dismunaleses, right? Very different. Okay. So, actually, you know, once we found the,
the, the, the, the r of i, actually, the correlation of w and actually the biotherm is very simple.
Okay. Of course, in practice, actually, and actually, when we use a tree, because the
calculation area, and when we use a different subalvector, we may find a slightly different
b, the bi stuff, okay? So, in practice, quite often, we use each of the subalvector to find a b,
and then we take the average of all the b's, okay? So, use all the subalvector to find a b,
right? So, totally, we have ns subalvectors. Then, we find ns b's, then take the average.
Okay. So, di minus the subalvector, right? And then, yeah, divide by the number of subalvectors.
We take the average. For each subalvector, we find the corresponding, actually,
b. Why we can use subalvector to find the b? Because, actually, subalvectors
satisfy the equality condition. W transpose x plus b equals 1, or equals d, right?
Equal d. Okay. So, in a tree, we can actually use this actually,
you know, this subalvector to find the value for the bi stuff.
Okay. So, in that tree, maybe I should show one example to show some properties, right? Okay. And
so, okay, yeah. Already stated. So, here, we have this example, right? And the data from
two classes. And so, certainly, the data are well separated, right? And, actually, we can use
different ways to find the classifier, right? To find the decision boundary. Okay. So, this is the
decision boundary found using the subalvector machine method. Okay. So, here, we just have a,
here, we have two subalvectors. One subalvector from the positive class, and another subalvector
from negative class. So, now, here, we have a totally 200 tree samples. Actually, 198 samples
have zero alpha values. Only two samples have nonzero alpha values. So, these two samples are
the subalvectors. So, one subalvector is here, another subalvector is here. Okay. And this
W is calculated based on these two subalvectors only. And also, the B, right, the bias term is also
based on these two subalvectors. Okay. So, subalvectors determine the W, determine the B. Okay. So,
these are also the reason why these cost subalvector machines, right? So, only, actually, those samples
are not used. Only these two samples, those two subalvectors are used in the determination of
this decision boundary, including the B, the bias term, and the projection W.
Okay. So, next, actually, we can see that's the case. Okay. So, this case is that, actually, we
have samples, right? And actually, the red sample, actually, one red sample is here. Very close to
these black samples, that's some way in other class. Okay. So, here, we have two decision
boundaries. One decision boundary is this. Well, this is a one decision boundary, right? So,
these decision boundaries set up by the condition that all train of sample are classified correctly.
So, we have zero train of error, train of error, for train of data, we have zero error. So, then,
we have this decision boundary. Okay. And then, another scenario, we have this decision boundary.
We have an error. Now, this is probably located here. And then, this sample will be classified
wrongly. This sample. We have one error for train of data. Do you think which one, which one you
prefer? Well, the two classified. We prefer this one, right? Although one sample is misclassified.
And, but actually, we have a tree, actually, for our other samples, we have higher confidence.
Okay. And we have a larger margin of separation. Okay. So, but if this is for this one, actually,
then we cannot use the condition, right? All train of sample are classified correctly.
Some of the train of sample, we are not satisfied with this condition. Okay. So, this is just the
part that tree is an optimal hyperplane for nonseparable samples. So, when we illustrate, you
know, the principle of the support-widen machine, we assume all the sample can be classified correctly,
100% accuracy. But in practice, almost no such a scenario. Okay. In practice, sometimes,
70% is the best performance. Sometimes, of course, maybe the problem could be 99, right? 98,
97. This is a different application. But in no scenario, we can have 100% accuracy.
No such application. Okay. Then, actually, in most of the scenarios, the so-called nonseparable
samples, actually, for the two classes or multiple classes, they had a region where the samples
overlap. Okay. And, actually, we know the data could be known, the following normal distribution,
for example, right? Normal. The model samples are close to the mean vector. But some samples
could be far away from the mean vector, right? So, if the two classes are very similar, then,
certainly, there is a region where the samples are mixed. So, this is the nonseparable scenario.
Nonseparable. This is a more practical scenario. Okay. In this practical scenario,
if the data are mixed, we cannot 100% actually classify them correctly. Then, actually,
actually, then such a scenario, we cannot use that condition, right? Classify that correctly.
All of them certify the condition, right? Greater than or equals one, right? We cannot actually
use this condition. Okay. And so, in order to address this scenario, the nonseparable
samples and, actually, they introduce, actually, the so-called, actually, select variable. Okay.
The select variable. Okay. They want to, actually, so we introduce a select variable because they
cannot certify greater than or equals one, right? And so, we actually subtract a positive value.
And then, this value, after we introduce such a value, then the condition could be satisfied.
If this sample is classified wrongly, right? So, it should be greater than or equals one. Then,
actually, we show that minus, actually, very negative, very big value. This become, actually,
very negative. Okay. So, if we introduce a variable, we can still introduce such a constant.
We can still actually follow the previous scenario. We formulate the small animation
into a constant or a decision problem. But we need to change the constant. Change the constant.
Okay. By introducing a so-called, actually, select variable. Okay. And for this select variable,
we have two, you know, cases. Okay. The first case is that we can look at the data points, right?
So, for some of the points, so this is the W transpose X plus B equals one, equals minus one.
And for this sample, this sample, actually, should be in another side, right? But now, actually,
it's in this side. So, this sample will be classified wrongly, wrongly, right? For some of the samples,
like this sample, right? It does not satisfy the condition. It does not satisfy the condition.
Greater than equals one, right? Actually, it is greater than zero, but less than one. It is in the
region of separation. But it will be classified correctly. So, there are two scenarios. One
scenario with that, actually, they don't satisfy the condition, right? You know, they,
greater than or equals one, or less than, or equals minus one. They don't satisfy this condition.
But under this, for this scenario, we have two cases. Why is that the sample could be
classified correctly? They are on the correct side of the decision boundary,
but just they don't satisfy that condition. Okay. Another, they are located on the wrong side,
wrong side. Okay. Wrong side, right? So, actually, we can actually, we should introduce, actually,
to solve this problem, we can introduce, actually, select variable, the zeta i. For each training
sample, we introduce zeta i. Of course, for some of the samples, if they satisfy the original
condition, then this zeta i is just zero. But for those who cannot satisfy the original condition,
right? Then, you know, the zeta i will not be zero. Okay. And actually, just now, we have analyzed,
there are two cases. One is that the samples do not satisfy the condition, but they are on the
correct side of the decision boundary. They will be classified correctly. Another case is that
the sample is on the wrong side of the decision boundary. They will be classified wrongly.
Okay. So, actually, these are two scenarios, okay. One case is that the zeta i, actually,
if they are on the correct side, then the zeta i is between zero and one. Between zero and one.
Okay. But if the data is on the wrong side, right, on the wrong side, then this zeta i,
the select variable, would be greater than one. Orally, it should be greater than one, right?
So, now, at least, it should be greater than zero. But they are not greater than zero, right? Because
we subtract a value that is greater than one. So, certainly, they will satisfy. Okay. And this zeta i,
the value, actually, is sample dependent. For each sample, we have corresponding zeta i.
So, for each of the training samples, we introduce a zeta i. Of course, for some of them,
the zeta i could be zero. For some of them, the zeta i is a ring from zero to one. For some of the i
and the samples, the zeta i is greater than one. Okay. So, necessarily, we look at the new formulation,
right, of the primal problem, the sub-animation, for not separate cases. So, here, again, we introduce
a tree. We need to minimize the square norm, right, of the value. So, this is because of the
model separation. Okay. Then we introduce a y-axis term. Y-axis term, this is the summation
of the zeta, the slack variable. Totally, we have n-slack variable, the summation. And the c here is
is a weight. It's a hyper parameter. In practice, you need to assign the values. Okay. This is a
hyper parameter, right? Before you run the program, you give a value. Okay. So, this is a c. Okay.
And then we minimize this code function, j, subject to this condition.
d i times this is greater than one, right? Now, not no longer than one. Minus zeta i.
zeta i could be zero, right? Could be zero, if the sample is set by the condition. Okay. And then
the zeta i here also should be greater than or equal to zero. Okay. So, now, again, for this now,
So in several cases, after the introduction of the select
variable, so the problem is still a constant optimization
problem.
So now the objective function have two parts.
One is the normal of w, right?
The square normal of w.
Another is the summation of the same variables.
So here, again, we can use the Lagrange multiplier
method to solve this constant optimization problem.
So here, and we introduce extra, right?
For this first condition, we introduce,
for this condition, right, we introduce a select multiplier.
For this i equals 1, r, for sample i,
we introduce a multiplier of r.
For this zeta i, we also introduce a multiplier,
because there's also a condition.
So we can use a multiplier like beta i.
So now we have the new, actually the two
that we have to multiply.
When the r of i, right, Christmastime
do the first condition.
And the second condition, the zeta i should be greater than
or equal to 0, right?
Then we have the new multiplier that is beta i.
So now we look at the function, right?
So there are two.
Actually now there are three parts, right?
The original part, these are four parts.
The original part, right now, a part that
relates to the zeta i's layer variable.
And these are, read to the second condition, right?
Constraint.
And read to the first constraint.
OK.
So we have r of i, we have beta i.
And we have a w, and we have a b.
So these are the four, actually,
the two parts of parameters in this function l.
And actually, we can actually solve this problem.
And so this is a KKT condition, or a machine condition.
So certainly the multiplier should be positive or 0, right?
Should be non-negative.
And so this is the beta i, and zeta i should be the condition.
The multiplier times the condition should be 0.
So this is the KKT optimization theory.
And so the dual problem, actually,
based on the same no matter, do some mathematical manipulation.
Finally, actually, we can also have this dual problem
for not separate cases.
And we only have this r of i.
And we have alpha i.
And actually, even beta is no longer here.
But we may actually do a c in the cost function c.
Actually, the c is here.
The alpha should be in the range from 0 to c.
So this is the condition.
Alpha i, d i, 0.
So this is a partial, l partial b, the same condition.
Normally, we have this.
So we can use a QP software to solve this dual problem
to find alpha values.
So once we find alpha values, then we can find this w.
So that's the same, right?
Just a linear summation of all the support vectors,
weight summation.
The weight, just alpha i, d i.
So we can really use the support vectors to determine the w.
I think this is actually the same as the separate case.
Then what is the b?
Previously, we use the w transpose plus b equals 1,
equals 1 to determine the b, to determine b.
But now, because the support vectors
are in the same condition, right?
Actually, in this method, the support vectors
include those in the certified equality condition, right?
Also include those in the region of separation.
Maybe I'll show you first.
So these are all the support vectors.
Alpha i, zeta i, alpha i is actually non-zero.
Not just those in the very few samples,
the certified equality condition is zero.
But now, with the condition changes, right?
Because the changes are y minus zeta i.
So we cannot use this method to determine the b.
We need to use a different way to determine the b.
Now we have so many support vectors.
No support vectors in the certified condition.
W transpose x plus b equals 1, or di.
Then how to determine?
Now we look at this.
So to find the b, right?
And we look at beta.
Part of the region of l, with respect to the zeta i,
the select variable, equal to c minus,
this should be zero.
Should be zero, right?
And because the loss function with respect to any coefficient
should be zero, right?
This is a condition for optimal solution.
So based on this zero, we can find that bi
equal to c minus alpha i.
So this is beta i equal to c equals alpha i, c minus alpha i.
So then according to the KKT condition,
we just elicit that, right?
The beta i times the condition, the zeta i equals zero.
So this is a condition, KKT, right?
So normally the multiplier times the condition should be zero.
So this is another KKT of addition
to the area with this condition, right?
OK, so the beta i, just found here, right?
C minus alpha i times, actually, the zeta i equals zero.
So now we analyze these results.
C minus alpha i times zeta i should be zero.
So here, if zeta i is greater than zero,
then the beta i must be zero.
Otherwise, the multiplication, the product of these two parts
cannot be zero.
So if zeta i is greater than zero, then c minus alpha i
must be zero, because the product of the zeta i
and this beta i should be zero.
Then actually, in such a scenario, the alpha i equals zero.
So zeta i greater than zero, right?
Those greater than zero are not those on this half, two,
no half plane, right?
Two half plane.
Only two half plane should be those double transpose plus b
equals 1 or minus 1.
In such a scenario, the zeta i equals zero.
OK, so here, if zeta i is greater than zero, right?
And then, in such a scenario, the alpha i equals c.
And just now we have analyzed that problem.
We solved the dual problem.
We can find the alpha i, right?
Then we look at alpha i.
Where the alpha i equals c?
If alpha i equals c, then the boundary, right?
Then the non-equality condition is not satisfied.
Then we need to introduce a non-zero slag variable.
So from this condition, we get a first case, right?
So this alpha i equals zero.
So how about for others?
If you see alpha i not zero, if this part not zero,
then the zeta i is zero.
So this part, zeta i is zero, those just
put on a set of other conditions, right?
I'm trying to put x plus b equals 1 or minus 1.
So these are those, I treat the zeta i equals zero.
So for those support vectors, the alpha is less than c.
The alpha is less than c.
So those alpha are less than c.
So in order to find the b, we can use those support vectors
whose alpha values are less than c.
We cannot use those samples whose alpha equals c.
Should be less than c.
And for those part of alpha, for those part of support vectors
on the margin whose alpha value is in this range, less than c.
Alpha must be positive, right?
Otherwise, not support vector, right?
So actually, less than c.
Then we can use those part of the support
vector to determine the b value.
Because those part of the support vector are on the margin.
You remember the two parallel three lines,
parallel to the decision boundary.
So only use those parts of support vector
to determine the b.
So how we can find those part of support vectors?
Those part of the support vectors correspond to the alpha values less
than c.
And then we can use those part of the b.
Again, we can use all those kind of support vectors,
because the calculation area we take,
for each of those support vectors,
this kind of support, we find the 1b, right?
Then we take the average.
So that is just the b.
And then we have a look of this example.
So this is an example, not several case.
I just actually used this in my lab as one example.
But you are not actually required to use it in my lab.
You can use any package.
You should use the Python, which is more popular.
But for me, it's not easy to find a new language.
So I just use these as demonstration.
So I just see what we can get from the function.
And actually, if we have the data in my lab,
actually, we can just fit SVM.
This c means classified classification.
Actually, we can use SVM for regression.
So this is fit c classification.
This is SVM classified.
And then we have a tool on the output of the model.
The model has many parameters here.
And like the bias term, the b, or the given value.
Or whether it's a sub-vector or not.
So for each of the training samples,
they will tell you yes or no.
One, yes, it is sub-vector.
If zero is no sub-vector, right?
Zero.
So easy.
And also, give the alpha values.
For each of the samples, give alpha values.
OK.
No, no.
Just for sub-vectors, give the alpha values.
So that's actually a plot of alpha.
So these actually are first and not plot alpha values.
So these are the alpha values.
Actually, we see alpha of code, actually,
for a natural vector, no, the alpha is zero.
For sub-vectors, some of the alpha
will be equal to the value of c.
In this example, I said c equals 1.
If you set to c, then this should be another value.
The default value is c1.
Then we find that most of the sub-vectors
have alpha value of c or 1.
So those part of the sample sub-vector
could not be used to calculate the b.
But only a few examples whose alpha values are less than c.
Less than 1 here.
Only this 1, 2, 3.
So we use the three samples to calculate the values of b.
These three samples are on these margins, right?
On these margins, the two parallel lines, right?
The two lines parallel to the dissonant boundary.
Setify the equality condition.
W transpose x plus b equals 1 or minus 1.
OK, you can see this, right?
The c less than c, the alpha less than c.
And most of them actually are alpha, actually, equal c.
And yeah.
So is the support vector or not?
Is the support?
So whether or not tell us, this training sample
is a sub-vector or not sub-vector, right?
So like give a 1.
So totally we have 200 samples, right?
For each sample, they give a value.
If not a sub-vector, then alpha 0, OK?
And then only for those sub-vectors,
they give a value of 1.
So it is a sub-vector.
OK.
And then another thing I want to point out is this, actually.
Yeah, so the oldest, this is known part.
All those actually are sub-vectors.
Most of them have an alpha value of c, 1.
Only three have an alpha value less than 1,
of course, greater than 0.
And then, actually, it's on the margins.
Then, actually, we use them to determine the value of b.
So I think this is a very interesting result, right?
The alpha value could just equal to the c, OK?
And only those less than c are those on the margin
should be used to determine the value of b.
So actually, from this study, actually,
we see the sub-vector machine is really
a kind of interesting result, right?
But a lot of interesting results.
First, actually, the width is just
a linear summation of the train samples,
which is summation, right?
And also, we just need to use the full samples
to determine this w and then the b, OK?
And for the non-sebral case, when we calculate the alpha,
right?
We calculate alpha.
And most of the alpha, actually,
is just equal to the value of c.
Only a few actually is less than c.
And those are on the margins, which
should be used to determine the value of b, OK?
OK.
So these are the descent boundary, OK?
So based on the two, three samples, right?
We calculate that.
Actually, the b determination of the w
based on all the samples, based on all the sub-vectors.
Just the b determination, it based on the very few sub-vectors,
part of the sub-vectors.
The w is based on all the sub-vectors.
OK.
And actually, that's what we look at in one scenario, right?
So this is also a typical class opinion problem, right?
We have one sample here.
We have one sample in another class here.
So certainly, we cannot use one string
line to separate the sample in the two classes, right?
So the sample is linearly inseparable.
We cannot use the linear classifier to separate the sample
in the two classes.
We need to use a nonlinear classifier, right?
A nonlinear classifier like this.
A nonlinear classifier is a curl, right?
It's a curl, not string line.
It's a Harper surface like this.
And so for sub-vectors, we can also
extend this idea to the nonlinear classifier.
And so that is kernel support-wide dimensions.
So in this course, actually, we don't
cover the kernel support-wide dimensions.
And actually, in this course, in the next semester,
a neural network and a deep learning
will cover the kernel support-wide dimensions.
A kernel support-wide dimensions is
very similar to one kind of neural network,
which is called radio-based function neural network.
Very similar.
So we will actually cover the kernel support-wide dimensions
in this course in semester two.
So in this machine learning course,
we just cover the linear support-wide dimensions.
OK.
Yeah, I think that's all for today.
Yeah.
Thank you.
So our quiz actually is a face on the week 12
on Saturday morning.
Actually, I think for this course, we have a 680 student,
84, 84 students.
And I need to find three big lecture theaters.
And actually, at the evening time, actually,
I hope we can find the lecture theater
on Tuesday night, right?
But all the lecture theaters are reserved by others.
I used maybe for courses.
So I can only reserve the classroom on Saturday morning.
It's on the, yeah, not the last week,
I think one week before the last, right?
So week 12, I think Saturday morning.
OK.
So I will announce this in our course website.
And also, I tell you the location,
and assign each of you to one lecture theater
to take the assignment.
So I will let you know the detail later.
OK?
Yeah.
Thank you.