Okay.
So in the last two weeks, actually, we started to actually a very important panel classified,
including the Fischer's linear digital analysis and then the linear spot-widen machines.
And of course, actually, the two linear classified actually adopt different ideas.
And in the linear spot-widen machine, we try to find the decision boundary so that the
marginal separation is maximized.
So the maximization of the marginal separation.
So actually, the marginal separation here, actually, we use a distant concept.
So the distance from the nearest sample to the decision boundary.
So that is the marginal separation.
And in the Fischer's linear digital analysis, and we try to project the data into one dimension
so that actually the difference between the classes, right, that is, you know, between
class scatter and is maximized.
And also, the within class scatter is minimized.
And this scatter actually is based on the concept of the distance, right, the distance
from each data point to the center to the mean, to the mean, or within the same class,
right?
And between class scatter is based on the distance between the two mean values after
projection of the data onto the dimension of the value.
So we, in both matters, we use the concept of distance and in particular, the Euclidean
distance.
And actually, this Euclidean distance metric actually is valid, is meaningful, only for
the real value, actually, in Fischer vectors.
But we know actually, in the first, second week, actually, when we study the different
types of features, right, we know there are, can you know the features, discrete features?
For discrete, and we have two types of categoricals.
One is the ordinal, another is nominal.
Nominal quite often is the label, the name of the attribute, right?
For example, for a man, for a gender, right, or sex, you know, we have male or we have
female, okay?
And in such a scenario, actually, and the metric, like a distance, is not actually very meaningful.
And actually, so actually, we know how to calculate the distance, right?
For any arbitrary two vectors, actually, now we use the difference, right?
You use the difference between the two.
Actually, so for the two samples, X, Y, X, O, the feature values, feature number one,
number two, right?
And then for the two samples, we have different values, okay?
The different values, of course, should be different, okay?
And also, the size of the difference, the size of difference, the difference, okay?
Or the difference between the two values also show how different they are, okay?
But for some, actually, like nominal features, although we give them different values.
For example, and in the such data, like a transportation mode, and we can have,
like a train, we can have a car, we can have a bus, we can have actually the air,
and actually, we can have a sea, we can have different modes, right?
And normally, we need to give a numerical value to each of these, actually, values, okay?
For example, one to train, and two to car, and three to air, and four to sea, okay?
Of course, actually, the different values, we use different values, right?
We assign them different values.
The difference only show they are different, but the size of the difference
don't show how different they are.
For example, actually, we see the train car, right?
Just one, actually, one is one, one is one, another value is two, okay?
So the values are different, okay?
We show they are different, okay?
And for value train one, and the sea is four, okay?
So of course, the two values are different.
But these differences don't show how different they are.
They don't mean, okay, the distance between train and car is less than the distance
from train to sea.
And then we see all the train and car are more similar than the train to, actually, the sea.
We cannot see that, okay?
Only, actually, the difference show, you know, really give an evaluation for
the difference, right, of the two, actually, you know, values.
And then, actually, the distance metric is meaningful, okay?
And like, yeah, I think this is quite, I think that's natural, right?
Like if you have a body weight, okay?
Why is 60 kg, another 70 kg, another, you know, like a 65 kg, right?
So the values are different.
And also this, this, this is actually, the value also show how different they are, okay?
So in such a scenario, these are real value that we, you know, make us, I think,
the distance metric is a good evaluation, is a good measure, and to evaluate the similarity
between the data samples.
And, but if the data is a mix, a mix, that means the data contains real value,
no features, contain, actually, the, like, a nominal features.
And then we should not use, actually, the distance metric based on the classifier.
Of course, we can still use that, but then the result may not be, actually,
the optimal result, okay?
I think you can still use that, okay?
And this is because the reason here, right?
And actually, the similarity, actually, can only be measured based on the difference
between the two values, okay?
So this is for the nominal features, and another example for the color, right?
So it's also nominal.
And actually, for such a mixed data, and certainly, we should use, actually,
the non-metric, non-metric based method, non-metric.
That means that we don't try to, actually, design a classifier based on the distance
between the, actually, the feature vectors, between the samples.
Okay, we can use a non-metric method, okay?
Of course, you can still use a metric based method, like linear
spoil animation, or use a linear, linear,
these monies, you can still use them, okay?
But actually, the performance may not be optimal, okay?
And today, actually, we are going to introduce, actually, one method that is,
actually, is a kind of non-metric method, okay?
We don't, based on the specific distance metric, okay?
And this method is, actually, just the classification tree, classification tree, okay?
And so, so this diagram shows a classification tree.
So, certainly, classification tree is a graph model, right?
It's a graph.
You can see these are graph, right?
So, this is different from other models, like, in the linear spoil
animation, the classifier tree, just a linear, actually, no function, right?
A linear equation, okay?
So here, actually, we use a graph, okay?
And actually, this graph can be considered as a implementation.
It's a certain way of implementation of the rules, okay?
So, later, actually, through one example, we can see, actually, correspond to rules, okay?
So, this is actually the graph representation of the rules, okay?
So, it's based on, and actually, so, from this graph, actually, or
this classification tree, and we can see many, like, circles, right?
This could be quite often, this could, no, not a circle, okay?
So, here, this is actually, this is kind of a node.
This is kind of a node, okay?
And there are many nodes here, right?
And each node, actually, we ask a question based on one particular attribute or feature, okay?
For example, here, we are going to classify a fruit, okay?
And each fruit, actually, represented by a few features.
For example, the size of the feature, the size of the fruit.
Another, this is the color of the fruit.
And then, another is the taste of the fruit.
The color, the size, the shape, and also the taste, okay?
So, each fruit is represented by these four features, okay?
We can see, actually, at a different node, we ask different questions, okay?
And regarding a different attribute, okay?
So, this is just a classification tree.
And actually, on the top, the top level here, the node here is called rule node, rule node.
And also, we have many nodes, actually, which are the terminal nodes, also called leaf node.
So, you see, these are leaf nodes.
And actually, the leaf node, I gave a class label, right?
Each leaf node has a label.
For this node, it is a watermelon, okay?
And this node is apple, and grape, and cherry, or different tree, class labels, okay?
So, these are the leaf nodes, which are also called terminal nodes.
So, we have the rule node, and we have the leaf node, okay?
And also, we have many nodes in between, okay?
And for one node, a testing sample, you have one sample, right?
And we have certain features regarding the size, the shape, the taste, or the color, okay?
And then, we can just go through this graph, okay?
Based on the question asked, okay?
Color is all green?
Yes, we go to the left branch, no, we go to the right branch.
And then, we ask another question, like, based on the color.
And then, later, we based on the shape, or based on the taste.
And we ask a series of questions, or a test sample, answer a series of questions.
Finally, it will come to one of the terminal nodes, okay?
Once you come to a terminal node, and then the label is determined, right?
If you come to this node, then it is apple, okay?
So, there are many terminal nodes.
So, this is a class label.
So, for data, with the nominal feature, and also, other continuous features, right?
And we can recommend to use this kind of model classification tree to perform the classifications.
Okay. And some of you, actually, may not be very familiar with classification tree,
but some of you probably know the random forest, right?
So, later, we will also talk about the random forest.
So, random forest consists of many trees.
Of course, the trees actually are trained on different, actually, data set.
Random is selected from the training data set.
Okay. So, it's called random forest.
Okay. So, later, today, class, we will talk about that.
Okay. So, you are familiar with that.
Actually, the foundation, actually, is a classification tree.
Okay.
So, actually, from the node, these trees are called branch, okay?
Branch, actually. So, after I ask this question, the data is the full data.
At the beginning, actually, the data is a full training data set, right?
Full training data set. Okay.
And then, the data will be divided into two paths.
Okay. Or we will split into two data subset.
Okay. One subset to the left side, another to the left side.
Okay. So, this is called branch, okay?
Or split, or division of the data.
Actually, each node, after I answer this question,
the data will be divided into two subsets.
Okay. So, this is a classification tree.
Okay. So, it's a flowchart.
Okay. So, with a tree structure.
And, okay. So, the question asked at each node is regarding a particular
property, right? Property just, you know, the feature or attribute.
Okay. And one of the reasons we use this classification tree,
I already answered this question, right?
And because the tree for mixed data, which contains the nominal features.
And then, the distance metric is not very meaningful.
Not very meaningful. Okay.
Of course, this metric is meaningful for those part of the feature,
continuous features, real value features.
For part of the feature who are nominal,
then the distance metric is not very meaningful.
Okay. Then there's a reason why we use this class feature tree,
which is a non-metric method, not based on the distance metric.
It's a non-metric method. Okay.
Of course, besides this, actually, we have other tree, you know,
advantage. So, that is interpretability.
In AI, in machine learning, right?
Actually, we know sometimes, actually, we just need to,
we just need a prediction based on the model.
Okay. We don't need to understand, actually, the inside of the model.
We don't care, you know. Okay.
But in some scenarios, actually, not only we want to know, actually,
the prediction, right, the prediction result, but we also know,
actually, why we get these results.
Okay. So, we want to explain, right?
So, that is the explainable AI.
We're not going to explain the model.
We want to know the result, but we also know how these results are obtained.
So, that is the interpretability of the model. Okay.
And actually, the class feature tree is a kind of interpretable model.
Because, actually, at each, you know, we get these results.
Actually, we get a reason, right?
When we go through the graph, actually, when we go through this class tree,
actually, we answer the question.
So, why we get these results?
Why is the watermelon okay?
Or because the size is big and because, you know, green color.
And because, actually, you know, the taste is sweet, right?
Based on all these features.
And then we finally get these results.
So, I think, through answer this question, and at each question,
you know, we, at each node, we answer questions about this specific feature, right?
So, this process, it just, it's just this plan.
Okay.
The explanation of why we get these results.
Okay. So, class tree is interpretable.
So, this is a very, actually, an important feature.
And of course, these depend on applications, right?
So, in my past research, you know, many of my work related to very important areas, right?
So, like, security or defense.
So, actually, the explainability is very important.
Okay. And because we need to make, you know, critical decision-making.
Okay. We need to, actually, the model could actually, you know, make decision, right?
But the decision is very critical.
Okay. And not like, say, you know, it's a web page, right?
Whether you receive an advertisement, this is a tree, maybe you are not interested in that.
You will receive such a message.
But that don't matter, right?
That don't create a very, you know, severe consequences.
Okay. But some scenarios, okay, like if you use AI or machine learning to perform diagnosis
of a certain disease, right?
If the model tells you, oh, the patient has a cancer, for example, right?
These are very critical and decision-making problems, right?
So, we must know why, actually, this patient is diagnosed with, actually, the cancer.
We want to know the reasons.
So, the explainability of the model is very important.
So, this class of clinical tree is just this kind of model.
Okay. And, okay.
Another tree, very important feature is that, actually, we can actually put the prior knowledge
into the class of the clinical tree.
And the machine learning, of course, is data-driven, right?
Data-driven.
And we try to build the models based on the data.
But some, in some scenarios, actually, we need to incorporate the knowledge.
Okay. And in particular, if the data, actually, available is in small size.
Okay. And, you know, nowadays, the model becomes, actually, more and more complex.
That means we have more and more parameters in the model.
And then we need to have more and more, actually, training samples in order to estimate, actually,
the value for the parameters in the model.
Okay.
But if we use, actually, the knowledge, the, I mean, the explain knowledge, actually,
now we can reduce the reliance on the data size.
Okay.
And based on the knowledge, okay, even with a small size of training data, we can still,
you know, build a model with, actually, reasonable performance.
Okay.
So, this is very reasonable, right?
And we already know, actually, oh, water management is big, right?
So, naturally, I think you can design a rule, right?
You can design a rule.
Actually, we recall the development of the artificial intelligence.
The first generation is just, you know, the rule-based, the rule-based model, right?
Based on the, I mean, as per knowledge, and we write many rules.
Okay.
Actually, in the class-fusion tree, actually, each, actually, node, actually, is equivalent
to a rule.
Okay.
So, in rule, naturally, I think we can actually incorporate, I mean, as per knowledge, right?
So, we can easily incorporate the expert knowledge into this, this, no, classification tree.
Okay.
So, I think this is the advantage of the pen and classification, the classification tree.
If you think about a different network, they're very deep, right?
And you probably don't know how to incorporate, actually, the knowledge, the human knowledge
into the model, but this kind of model can.
Okay.
Of course, now we come to the key issue, right?
The most key issue, how to build a tree?
How to build a tree?
We see we have these advantages, right?
And they can handle the mixed data with nominal features, and the model is interpretable,
and we can easily incorporate the human knowledge into this classification tree.
So, these are the advantages, right?
Then the key is how to build, actually, a classification tree.
Okay.
And so, given a training dataset, of course, this dataset needs to be labeled, right?
So, given a label training dataset, how we could actually build such a model.
Okay.
And actually, if you go back to this model, and you can see, actually, at the top, we
ask questions about the color.
So, why you ask the question about color in the root node?
Why you ask this?
Why you don't use the tree the size?
Why you don't use the shape or taste to add the question in the root node?
Okay.
And then the data branch to two, then followed, why you ask the question based on the size?
In the left-hand side here, why you ask the question based on the color in the right branch?
Okay.
And then why actually you stop further branching, and you stop further branching, and you declare
this node as a leaf node?
How do we know that?
Okay.
And actually, this is the question that we need to answer in order to build, actually,
a classification tree from the training data.
Okay.
So, then, okay.
Then to build a separate tree, we need to answer this question.
Okay.
Here, first, how many sableit?
This is not a show you, right?
Actually, at each node, we ask a question about a particular feature or attribute.
Okay.
And then the data is divided into two branches.
One goes to the left and another to the right.
Okay.
And in other words, actually, the data is split in the two subsets at each node.
So, the split is two.
Okay.
And actually, the classification tree, I just show you, is called a binary classification
tree because at each node, we divide the data into two.
The split is two.
Okay.
Of course, actually, the number of sableit could be two for some features.
For example, if you ask the question based on the gender, right, is a male or female.
If you ask the question, is the person male?
And then, of course, actually, it will come to the two branch, right?
Male or female.
Okay.
So, I think there will be no issue, right?
So, certainly, the sableit should be two.
Okay.
But if for some features, for example, just in the previous, right, for the size of the
fruits, the example, the size could be big, could be small, could be medium.
Okay.
Three values.
And then, how many sableit?
If we ask a question about the, based on the size of the fruits, okay, and then how many
subset, which should be obtained?
Okay.
After sableit.
Or in other words, what should be the number of sableit we should use for this particular
feature?
This is a question, right?
We need to answer this question.
Okay.
Otherwise, actually, you don't know, right?
You don't know.
Okay.
So, you want to build a class-quenching tree, actually, we need to answer this question.
How many questions, right?
How many questions to ask?
That means, actually, sableit.
If I just ask one question, the data will sableit into two.
Right?
If I have two questions, the data will sableit into three.
Okay.
So, this is the question to ask.
And then, which probably should be used as a node?
We have each node that we ask a question about the particular feature.
And what feature we should use?
This feature is just a property, right?
Or what attribute we should use to ask a question?
In particular, at the top level, and for the rule node.
So, why you ask the question based on the color, rather than based on the size, or based
on the shape, or based on the taste?
Okay.
So, we must actually develop some metrics based on which, and we can actually decide
which feature to use.
And then, after we select the particular feature, for that node, we also need to determine the
first question, how many questions to ask based on this particular feature, based on
the size, how many questions to ask, based on ask one question, right?
The size is big.
Then, just one question, right?
The data becomes big, and then small and medium, first we'll be put into another group.
Okay.
The big we'll put in one group.
All we ask three questions.
The size is big, this is one question.
The size is the medium, the size is small.
Okay.
Then, we ask three questions, then we have three subsets.
So, we see the, I think, after the feature selection, after the determination of the feature,
particular feature to use a certain node, and then we need to actually determine the number
of questions.
Okay.
And later, we will say, you know, even after the feature, we determine the feature, and
in particular, for those continuous features, we need to decide a split point, split point
for continuous features, there are so many values.
Okay.
So, based on which value, we should split the data into two parts or more parts.
There's also a question, right?
They need to answer in order to construct a class feature tree.
Okay.
When should we be a node, be declared as a leaf node?
We have so many leaf nodes, right?
And all these leaf nodes actually are at different levels.
So, for example, this is a level, no, top level, level zero, level one, the level two.
And these nodes in the level two, it is declared as a leaf node.
But for this one, a level three, and then the level four.
So, they are at different levels.
Okay.
And when we should actually declare a node as a leaf node, and then further branching,
we're not conducted.
The data no longer need to be split into more parts.
We can just stop the split of the data.
Okay.
So, this is the, I think the question.
The fourth question is that if the tree becomes too large, how can there be a smaller and
simpler?
So, that is called a prong.
Okay.
And the tree, the construction of a tree, a tree, a classification tree, normally involves
two phases.
The first phase is the phase of gruel.
We start from nothing, right, from empty.
Okay.
And then we grew the tree.
So, this is the first phase.
Okay.
And the tree could be very big.
Very big.
That means we have many nodes, right, many nodes.
And then one is extremely case that actually each node in the terminal node or leaf node
just cover one training sample.
So, in such a scenario, actually the model actually extremely overfit the training data.
Of course, we know when a model overfit the training data, then the performance on the
testing data, that is the generalization capability, could be very bad.
Okay.
So, we prefer a small and simpler model.
So, you already grew a very big model.
Then how the model can become small.
Okay.
So, that is the second stage, the pronging of the tree.
The pronging is just the cut.
Some of the branches merge or join some of the terminal nodes of the leaf node so that
the tree could become smaller.
A smaller model is less likely to overfit the training data.
Okay.
So, given a classification problem, so all ways that we, if we can use a small or simpler
model to solve the problem, then we should use the small and simple model to solve.
Okay.
Rather than using a more complex model.
So, now actually machine learning, deep learning become very popular.
So, everyone want to know, like you know, use a deep learning to solve every problem.
They're not right.
Okay.
You don't need to use a GPU to calculate 1 plus 1 equals 2.
Right.
Actually, you can just calculate it right easily.
You don't need to use a calculator to calculate these values.
Right.
Okay.
If you can solve a problem using a simpler solution, right, then we prefer the simpler
solution.
We prefer the smaller or simpler models.
Okay.
So, that is the second stage, right.
The pronging of the tree, the cut, some of the branches in particular, starting from the
merging of the leaf node.
So, later we will talk about this issue again.
Okay.
So, this is the fourth question, actually, to large pronging.
And so, if a node is in pure, actually now, actually the leaf node declare, right, declare
and then this node, any sample finally come to this node and then this cut label will
be assigned to that sample, right.
So, this is a leaf node.
Of course, actually, you know, if we, you know, each, you know, if a model overfit the
tree data and then, actually, the data is very pure in each, actually, you know, the
leaf node because the leaf node maybe can recover one or two, actually, you know, samples,
right.
That's an extreme case, of course.
And then, actually, the leaf node also contains a sample from class two, for example.
Then, of course, actually, we can assign class two to this leaf node.
Any sample come to this node will be class two sample.
Okay.
But in some scenarios, actually, in particular, if we prong some of the branches, right, some
of the nodes will merge, some of the leaf nodes will merge, right.
And then, in this, actually, node, we could have some, you know, a sample from a project
class.
Or like, you know, we can have some sample from another class, like a negative class.
Or we can have some sample from a fruit.
We can have some sample that we from, like, orange.
Okay.
They all come to the same node.
So the node, actually, is a mist.
Mist.
Mist, here, actually, that means contain the sample from different classes.
And then, how should the category label be assigned to this leaf node?
If the node is not pure, can see the samples from different classes.
Okay.
So these are all the questions that we need to answer.
You know, to construct a classification tree.
Right.
So let's look at the first one, the first question, right.
The number at split, number of split at each node.
And actually, let's first look at this.
Okay.
And we have one example.
And then, this is the example, it's just attribute.
The name is CP.
And for this attribute, we have four values.
One, two, three, four.
Okay.
And actually, if we, the feature has just two values, right, it's a binary, and then
there's not a problem.
Okay.
We can just actually use the node, use this feature to divide the data, right, into two
branches.
One, each branch corresponds to one of the, no, two values.
Okay.
But if a feature actually has more than two values, like this, have four values.
And so how many actually split we should use?
Of course, we can still use actually binary split.
Actually, the classification tree, I show you, it is a binary classification tree.
Okay.
And in other words, the number of splits, as you should know, is two.
So for all nodes, the number of splits is two, no matter how many values for that particular
feature.
We just have two.
Okay.
So for this feature, although we have no four values, we can still use actually the binary
split.
Okay.
Of course, the tree, based on these four values, and then the question is, so how to split
the data?
How to split the data into two parts?
Okay.
So what is the split, the splitting, you know, point we should use to split the data?
And one example here is that a CP is greater than two.
Because then two, that means the value is three or four, right?
Then go to the left-hand side.
And then if no, that means the CP value is one or two, then we come to this right-hand
side.
So this could be a question, right, to divide the data into two parts.
Okay.
And although the next case is still actually the two splits, the binary split, but the
question is very different, right?
So if we divide the CP equals one, if you, yes, then left, then no.
No, that means the tree, the CP equals two or three or four.
And then we go to the right branch.
So this is actually the question, right?
I think this is also a challenge.
Given a feature, if I'm more than two values, even if we adopt a binary split, then what
is the splitting at the point?
So what question we should ask to split the data into two branches, into two subset?
And later we will see we need to follow some criteria in order to split the data.
And the principle is that we should actually build a small classification tree.
Based on this principle, we split the data.
Okay.
But how to do that, actually, this is the key issue we need to address today.
And how to split the data.
Okay.
The binary split.
So there's a look at the multiple split.
So for this feature, we can also adopt the multiple split.
And in the left-hand side, actually, the data is split or divided into three parts, right?
If CP equals one, if CP equals two, if CP is greater than two.
Okay.
So we have three parts.
And then in the right-hand side, actually, the data is split into four parts.
We ask four questions, actually.
CP equals one, yes, then here, right?
CP equals two, yes, yes.
Okay.
So the data divided into four subset.
So, and actually, in the sum of the famous classification tree, like a cart, so later we will talk about
that classification and regression tree cart.
And it adopt, actually, the binary split.
In all nodes, actually, we split the data into two parts.
So the binary split.
Okay.
But in another very famous classification tree, which is called CE4.5, and it adopts, actually,
the multiple split.
Okay.
So different models, actually, actually, different, you know, classification trees adopt different,
you know, splits, number of splits.
Could be binary, that could be multiple splits.
Okay.
So this is a typical, when the binary split, binary tree.
Binary tree, that means it splits into two.
One, two, right?
Left-hand side, right, left branch, right, right, right, right, right, right.
For every node, we divide the data into two subset.
Every node.
Okay.
You can see that, two, right?
Then for this node, further divided into two.
Okay.
So this is a binary tree, a cut, classification tree, cut, and then belongs to this kind of
binary tree.
Okay.
And the next tree is a query selection.
Query selection is just a question to ask.
Okay.
And the node impurity.
We talk about this concept.
Okay.
And so, given a tree of data set, when to start, where to start, right?
So which node should be used as a rule node?
Okay.
And even if we have determined which value, which feature, or which attribute to use,
then we also need to determine what the question to ask, right?
So, different questions can have different splits, right?
It can have different numbers of splits.
Okay.
And so by the principle here is that the simplicity, simplicity is the principle.
And we should try our best to select the questions, to select the attribute or features, and
so that the tree we construct is a simple tree.
Okay.
So if you ask one question, for example, you have two class question problems, right?
You have two class question problems.
If you ask a question, then this question can actually classify the sample correctly into
two branch.
Okay.
And one branch corresponds to class one.
And then another branch corresponds to class two.
Okay.
In other words, actually by actually asking one question based on one feature, one attribute,
and then the data actually, you know, is divided into two branch, right?
And each branch, the data is very pure.
So pure, that means that all the sample belong to the same class.
These are very good questions, right?
You just use one question.
And just one step, you are completely constructed on the tree.
Actually, then, to the class question tree, just as you know, the two levels, right?
The level zero, the rule node.
Okay.
Then into the leaf node.
We just have three nodes.
These are very simple tree, right?
Very simple tree.
Okay.
But then we look at the characteristic of the simple tree.
And then the tree, or the node, or the tree of data in the left node, the hand side branch,
or the right hand side branch are very pure.
Very pure.
Okay.
So the purity will be used as a metric to decide which feature to select to ask questions.
And also, we need to decide which question to ask for this particular feature.
Okay.
So based on the purity measure.
All purity, all the impurity.
Okay.
So we based on the purity measure.
So we seek a property test.
Property test, I mean, we seek a test on a particular feature.
And also a particular question.
Okay.
And at each node, and that makes the data reaching the immediate descendant nodes as pure as
possible.
Okay.
So for this, just now we talk about the rule node, right?
Even for other nodes, we ask the same question.
Okay.
These are rule nodes.
And then the root below this level is called descendant nodes.
Okay.
So like parent node and children node, right?
Actually, this is like a descendant node.
Okay.
So this is the rule node descend node.
Of course, actually, for each descendant node in the next level, we can further divide
the data into two branches.
Then we also get the descendant node, right?
Okay.
So for every node, after split of the data, actually, the data should be as pure as possible.
At every level, at the first level, the rule node, okay, and after division, after split
by a selected feature or attribute, and also as a particular question about this feature,
okay, after split, the data should be as pure as possible.
As pure as possible, that doesn't mean it's really 100% pure.
Just as pure as possible.
And actually, for a practical problem, we need to have many levels, right?
Many levels.
And of course, actually, we see as pure as possible, but no 100% could be very low even
at the beginning.
Okay.
You cannot be on just one feature, right, to classify the samples correctly, right?
Just one feature, you can separate some of the samples.
You can classify some of the samples correctly.
But most of them will be misclassified, just based on one feature, right?
Yeah.
So that, actually, you know, the classification tree, actually, ask questions just based on
one feature at each node.
So certainly, you cannot actually classify the sample correctly based on one, just one
feature.
So after feature, the data split, okay, they are still very impure, very impure, not very
pure.
And it contains the data from different classes, okay?
But we should actually make this as pure as possible, okay?
So this is the principle we follow, okay?
And to select the features and those two to ask the question regarding this feature,
based on this problem.
After split of the data, the data should be as pure as possible.
Okay, of course, actually, a very natural question is that, so how to measure the purity?
How to measure impurity, right?
Okay.
And, okay, actually, you know, here, actually, we are interested in the concept of impurity.
Purity, right?
Impurity, just the inverse of that, right?
If purity is 100%, then the impurity is zero, right?
If the purity is zero, then the impurity is one, okay?
So this is actually, we use impurity as a measure, okay, to select features and also decide which
question to ask regarding this selected feature, okay?
So now, actually, we can see that node.
I mean, actually, the impurity.
I, see, I mean the impurity.
N, see, I mean node.
And for a particular node, N, actually, the impurity, okay?
The impurity, you know, the impurity, okay?
And the impurity, we want the impurity.
This is a measure, right?
The impurity measure could, we want this to be zero.
If all the samples that reach to the node be at the same category level, okay?
All the sample categories of the nodes are from the same class.
Because the purity is very high, right?
And then the impurity is zero, okay?
So we want to have such a metric.
This metric, actually, should be, this impurity measure should be zero.
If all the samples in this node are from the same class, okay?
So this impurity measure should certify this condition, right?
This is one condition, okay?
And then, actually, another condition, that, and this impurity measure should be very big.
If the data is mixed, and that the, the reach or the proportion is the same for all classes.
Okay, so we see, and, actually, the, if the, you know, categories are equally represented.
50-50, yeah, two class confirm problem.
Okay, so in this node, we have some samples.
50% from class one, 50% from class two, okay?
So this is a very impure, right?
So the impurity measure should be big.
We need to have such a metric, right?
When the data is all from the same category, the impurity measure should be zero.
So this metric should have a zero value if the data from the same class, okay?
And also this impurity metric should be big.
Should be big, okay?
If the data, actually, you know, actually have equal proportion, right?
From different classes, okay?
So this value should be big.
So we hope to have such a metric, okay?
Then what metric set for this, you know, conditions?
Here, actually, we will introduce a few.
And the first one is called entropy impurity, entropy.
It's a very important concept in machine learning, right?
And also in information theory, entropy, okay?
So what is entropy?
Actually, entropy is defined as the product of the probability under the logarithm, right?
Of the probability, okay?
So here, actually, we assume the data in the mix, right?
In the mix.
Then we have samples from different classes, okay?
And of course, actually, you know, a special scenario that the data is pure, right?
And then, actually, you know, of course, actually, then the probability for that particular class is zero, okay?
So p omega j is a fraction of probability of samples belonging to omega j.
This is something like a prior probability, right?
Given a data set, and we count how many samples are from, actually, you know, class omega one or class one.
Then we calculate the proportion, the fraction, the percentage.
So that is just the, you know, prior probability, right?
The prior probability, okay?
So that is here, the pure omega j is a fraction of samples, okay?
So based on the cost, right?
How many samples belong to class one, class two?
Then we can calculate this fraction.
Just a probability, right?
Percentage, okay?
And then, based on this, we can calculate the entropy.
And because, actually, the probability is less than one, right?
Normally, less than one.
And then, the log will have a negative value, right?
So, like, then we put a negative sign here, negative sign here, okay?
So this is actually the impurity measure.
The entropy, actually, impurity measure, actually, is a positive number, positive.
It could be zero, could be zero, okay?
Actually, it's non-negative, non-negative.
So this is the entropy impurity.
And actually, the entropy impurity, you can see, even though one, there are two classes.
One, from class one, the opium omega j is one.
That means that this, this, this, you know, they are very pure, right?
Very pure.
And that omega j equals one, right?
And then, omega p omega j omega 2 is zero, okay?
So we just use, actually, you know, omega one to calculate the entropy, right?
Then, one times log one, this is value zero.
So this is a set of other conditions here, right?
If the data is pure, all the samples are from the same class in this data set.
And then, the impurity measure is zero.
So, indeed, actually, this is the entropy impurity measure could set this condition.
Okay.
So this is the first measure, actually, we can use the entropy impurity measure.
And then, we'll have a look of one example.
And in this example, and we have, totally, we have 100 samples.
And one from, 10 from class one, and then 90 from class two.
Class two.
And actually, 90% of the samples belong to class two, right?
So this is actually, I think the data set is relatively pure, right?
90% from one class, okay?
Of course, no 100%.
So now, we can use entropy impurity measure to evaluate the impurity.
Okay.
So based on the distribution of the data in the two classes, we can kind of pure omega
to 10 over 100, right?
So it's 0.1.
And people may have to, the perfection of the sample from class two is 90% 0.9.
Then, we can substitute formula to calculate, right?
So this is the cross entropy impurity measure, the entropy impurity measure.
Okay.
Probability times the logarithm of the probability, right?
So the base of the logarithm here is two.
Okay.
Then minus 0.9 pure omega two, right?
Times logarithm of pure omega two.
Okay.
So this value is 0.6, 4.6 null.
So this is the entropy impurity.
Okay.
And the full data set with 50-50% distribution, 50-50, right?
Just now, we see all the classes are equally represented.
That means the fraction for each class is the same, the same.
Okay.
For two class, currently we're probably on 50-50.
So these are 50-50, actually.
Then the entropy impurity should be very big.
Okay.
Then we can evaluate this.
So it's minus 0.5, the probability times log 0.5, right?
Then minus another 0.5, omega two, pure omega two, and the logarithm pure omega two.
Actually, this value equals one.
So the impurity measure.
Okay.
Actually, now we know, actually, if the data is pure, you know, that all the samples from
the same class, then the impurity measure is 0.
Even all the classes are equally represented in this data set.
That means the fraction of the sample from each of the classes are the same.
And then the entropy impurity measure is one.
This is a big value.
Impurity measure is big, right?
So it means one.
That means the impurity.
Okay.
And so this one is pure because 90% from the same class, right?
So this value is relatively small.
0.469.
Okay.
Even 100% from the same class.
Then you can imagine, right?
Pure omega one, zero.
Pure omega two, one.
Okay.
Then you can substitute.
Of course, actually, we don't need to care about class one, right?
Because we cannot have a log of zero.
We cannot have that.
But then we have one times the logarithm one.
So zero.
Okay.
So this is the entropy impurity measure.
So this is the...
So that's actually...
We look at another measure, which is called a few virus.
Okay.
Yeah.
I think we should have a break, right?
Okay.
Maybe ten in a break.
So after a break, we look at another metric for the evaluation of the impurity.
Okay.
So,
so,
look,
look.
Okay.
Yes.
And the
What do you think?
Okay.
And the gene impurity.
So what is the wiring impurity?
And this wiring impurity definition here is very simple.
Actually, the wiring impurity is just
the product of the two, omega 1 times p omega 2.
And actually, from this here, we can also
see if the data is pure, it's 100%.
And all the samples from the same class,
then one of the p omega 1 or omega 2,
p omega 2 will be 0.
Then the product is also 0.
So again, if we use this wiring impurity,
and it is satisfied the condition,
when one of the data from the same class,
and then the impurity matter should be 0.
It is 0 if the data is pure.
Because one of the probability or fraction, p omega 1 or p omega
2, actually is 0.
Then the product is 0.
So this is a matter called actually a wiring impurity.
Actually, a more commonly used impurity
is the so-called gene impurity.
And the gene impurity actually is
the tension of the wiring impurity to more than two classes.
So the gene impurity is different.
It's the summation of a pair-wise product.
For example, we have three classes.
We have p omega 1.
We have p omega 2.
We have p omega 3, right?
Three classes.
And then actually, the gene impurity,
which is the summation of p omega 1 times p omega 2.
And p omega 1 times p omega 3.
And then p omega 2 times p omega 3.
So this is actually the gene impurity.
We need to calculate this actually,
pair-wise actually, the product of the probabilities.
Then get the summation.
Of course, if the number of the classes is big,
and then there's no pairs, the number of pairs
could be a very big value, a very big number.
And then that means you need to do a lot of calculations.
So actually, this actually is equivalent to this measurement.
So one subtract and p omega j squared.
p omega j squared.
And the j from 1 until the total number of classes.
So for each of the classes, and we have a probability,
or we have the fraction, then we just get the square.
Then one subtract, p omega 1 squared, p omega 2 squared,
then your p omega c squared.
Then divide it by 2.
So this is a method called gene impurity.
And this gene impurity is frequently used.
So later in the demonstration, I will use this gene impurity
to calculate the impurity measure after the data
split by a particular feature or a particular question.
OK.
So this is a gene impurity.
And in that sense, we look at this calculation.
I think this is very straightforward calculation.
And based on the distribution of the sample
in the two classes, we can easily calculate
omega 1 and the fraction for class 1, class 2.
This fraction is just a probability law.
Probability is just a fraction.
This is one of the methods to estimate the probability.
It's the fraction.
So class 1, 10%, 7.1, class 2, 90%, 7.9.
Then actually, the varying impurity
is just the product of the two.
The gene impurity is the same.
1 minus omega 1 squared minus actually
pi omega 2 squared divided by 2.
So this is gene impurity.
And another impurity metric that we can use
is called miscarcification impurity.
Miscarcification.
And actually, this miscarcification,
and we know actually in the leaf node,
we need to declare the class label of that leaf node.
And normally, even the leaf node is not 100% pure.
If we have 100% pure, most likely,
the classification tree overfills the training data.
So in the leaf node, the data could be mixed,
continue, sample from different classes.
And then when we actually declare the class label
for that particular leaf node, and then we identify the class
with the largest probabilities.
For example, we have two classes, just another sample.
And in this node, if this is a leaf node,
10% of the data from class 1, 90% of the data from class 2.
And if this is a leaf node, then the label of this leaf node
actually is class 2, class 90%, class 2,
because 90% is greater than 10%.
So we declare the class label of this leaf node class 2.
But actually, all the samples here
will be classified to class 2.
So certainly, 10% of the data will be misclassified.
And actually, we can, based on this,
this is actually the classification area
as an impurity measure.
So here, the misclassification emc,
and misclassification impurity measure
is 1 subtract the maximum p omega j.
Just now, we see p omega j, the maximum,
actually is 90% 0.9.
1 minus 0.9, just 1, 10%, 0.1.
So this, of course, is for a two-class classroom problem.
For a three-class classroom problem, for example,
we have an example.
And p omega 1 is 60%.
p omega 2 is 25%.
And then p omega 3 will be 15%, right?
15%.
So if this is a leaf node, then, of course,
the class label of this leaf node will be class 1.
This is because the p omega 1 is the largest, is the 60%.
Others are actually 15% or 25%.
And then, actually, if we declare this leaf node as the label
of leaf node is class 1, then 40% of the data
will be misclassified, right?
40%.
All the data will be classified, actually, as the class 1.
Then the area is also the 1 subtract the maximum value.
The maximum here is 60%, 0.6.
Then the 1 minus 0.6 is 0.4.
So that is 40% of the data will be misclassified.
So this could be used as an impurity measure,
classification area.
So this is the impurity.
And for the example, right, for example, it's 10%.
This is a misclassification impurity measure.
So we have introduced three, right?
First, actually, the entropy, right?
The entropy impurity measure.
Second, actually, we have the variance.
And then we send to a more class,
that is the gene impurity, right?
Vibrant gene impurity.
And then we have the misclassification impurity,
so the three impurities.
And actually, the entropy impurity
is frequently used.
And because, actually, it is a very important concept
in the information theory.
Information theory, entropy, right?
Entropy is a very important concept.
Now in deep learning, we use the loss function
as a cross entropy.
So this is an important, actually, measure.
So entropy.
But actually, the gene impurity receive more and more
considerations.
So that's the reason why in the later demonstrations,
I use the gene impurity, right?
We don't need to calculate a logarithm.
Just one subtract, a square of the probabilities.
Then we can get the divide by two.
We can get the gene impurities.
OK, so this is the impurity measures.
So naturally, we will use these impurity measures.
In particular, we will use the gene impurity measure
to select attributes at each node,
including the level zero, the root node,
and then the descendant node.
Actually, each descendant node, you
need to perform a split of the data.
And then we need to select one feature, one attribute.
After we have selected attributes,
we also need to decide actually a question.
And we need to decide actually the splitting point.
OK.
But actually, both.
That means that the selection of the attribute
and also the determination of the splitting point,
the two are all selected, are determined
based on the impurity measure.
OK.
So naturally, we apply this impurity measure
through one example to see how we can construct
actually a classification tree.
OK.
So naturally, we will look at that actually a measure.
We have a node.
After data split, we all call it after data split.
Actually, we can have an entropy measure.
Before data split, we can have an entropy measure.
It's very easy.
We just based on the proportion of the data in each class.
OK.
We can see the entropy.
We can measure, impurity measure.
We can have the gene impurity measure.
We can have the misclassification actually
in entropy, misclassification in impurity measure.
And maybe we can have an impurity measure.
Before split, we can have an impurity measure
for this data set.
After split, we can also have an impurity measure.
OK.
And actually, as I already explained,
we hope actually we can have a maximum reduction
after split.
We can have a maximum reduction.
The ideal scenario is that actually after split,
actually the impurity measure is 0.
The data is a pure.
All the data that need a same node,
left node or right node after split.
And the impurity measure is 0.
OK.
So we can actually, we hope we can have a maximum reduction
of the impurity after split by a feature.
And also a question based on that feature.
We can have a maximum reduction.
So let's say we look at the impurity reduction or drop.
So before split in the node n, and we have an entropy measure,
i, i, n.
So this is the before split of the data.
So naturally, after split by a paid feature,
and also one question based on the feature.
And then for the data in the left branch,
because the data divide in the two parts,
two subset, one subset in the left-hand side branch,
then in the left side branch or in the left side node.
And then another data set in the right-hand side branch
or in the right-hand side node.
For each of these data subset, we
can have a measure of the impurity.
We can have a impurity measure impurity.
Assumably, in the left branch, we have a node l.
l here means the left.
In the left branch, the left node,
descendant node after split.
This is called descendant node.
And we have the impurity of measure of i.
And then for the another node, the node here also
corresponds to another subset of the data.
We can have an impurity measure.
And actually, the total impurity after split
is a weighted summation of the two impurity measures.
For the data in the left-hand side,
we have impurity measure.
For the data in the right-hand side,
we have the impurity measure.
So i, l, i, and r.
We need to combine these two impurity measures
to get a total impurity after data split.
So this total impurity actually is a linear combination.
Weight is a summation of these two impurity measures.
What is the weight?
The weight here is pl.
pl.
What is pl?
I read pl.
pl here actually is just the proportion of the data
going to the left.
pl is the proportion of the data going to the right.
So for example, you, based on one feature and one question,
the data is divided into two parts.
Initially, we have 1,000.
700 go to the left.
300 go to the right.
Then this pl, pl, the proportion of the data
going to the left.
The left node, right?
It's a 700 divided by 1,000.
So it's 0.7.
Then the data to the right, the pl, 300,
is divided by 1,000.
It's 30% or 0.3.
Then the two impurity measures need
to be combined, one multiplied by 0.7,
another multiplied by 0.3.
So the total impurity after data split
is a weighted summation of the two impurities.
The left-hand side impurity, right-hand side impurity,
weighted summation.
The weight is just the proportion of the data
in the left node and in the right node.
So we hope actually we can have a maximum reduction.
Maximum reduction.
And actually from this formula, data, data, data,
ion, that ion is a drop or reduction of the impurity measure.
And actually you could ion.
So this drop.
Actually before split, of course,
this ion is already the data that is fixed value.
How we can have a maximum data ion, the maximum drop.
That means this part is the minimum.
If this part is the smallest, after data split,
the entropy measure, the impurity measure, is a minimum.
Then this is the best selection, the best split of the data.
Because this will achieve the maximum drop
or maximum reduction in the impurities.
So if the after data split, all the in the left-hand side,
the sample belongs to the same class.
All the sample in the right-hand side,
node belongs to the same class.
The impurity is zero.
Then we have a very maximum reduction of the impurity.
So that means the E. So later we
don't look at the reduction.
We just look at the impurity measure after data split.
PL, R and L, PR, R and R. We just look at the two parts.
We should select the one that has the minimum value of this.
OK.
So this is the principle we should follow.
You have to determine at this node which feature we should use
and what question we should ask.
Actually, what question we should ask basically
is to determine the splitting point, which value we
should use to split the data.
So with the maximum drop, actually, so later we look at,
we try to minimize this.
We find a split so that the impurity measure
is minimized.
So then the tree, there is another tree.
So now if we are actually assuming
there will be multiple split.
And then we just talk about the two.
Then the natural split is this.
If we have more than two, we have multiple split.
And then, of course, I think that then not just left or right.
Now we have a branch one.
We have branch two.
We have branch three.
And if we totally, we have B branched.
We have the data split.
Data is split into B part.
Then what is total impurity measure after data split?
So that is the same.
For each of the parts, for each of the parts,
not just two parts, left, right, right, part, right.
That's not just two nodes.
Left node, right node.
We have multiple nodes after data split.
If we adopt multiple split scheme,
then we have a multiple subset.
For each of the subset, we can have a measure of the impurity.
And then we combine all the impurity measures
based on the proportion of the data in that sub-data subset.
So these are very natural extension of this case.
They are very natural.
Now there are two split, binary split.
So now we have multiple split.
Then we have this data.
So here, actually, we need to decide
whether we should use a binary split
or we should use a multiple split.
Of course, actually, I think it's very natural, right?
For a data with multiple values, like the one CP,
we have used the example.
We have 1234.
Or transportation mode, we have 1234, even more values.
So actually, we can divide them into many split.
We can divide them into many subset.
Or we can also just divide them into two subset.
Whether we should use a binary split
or we should use a multiple split.
I think a very natural thinking is that we should evaluate.
We should evaluate if the B is 2.
Then we look at the impurity measure.
And then we look at the B equal to 3 or 4.
We look at the impurity measure.
And then we see which one will achieve the maximum drop,
maximum drop, or which impurity is the minimum after split,
by binary or by multiple split.
Then we can decide which split a number we should use,
binary or multiple split.
But here, there is one question, one issue with that.
This measure actually will fewer this actually.
This measure fewer as a larger B. That
means actually, if you the data derive more split,
and then or more subset, and then actually this
actually drop will be more.
OK, so this measure will actually fewer
the multiple split.
The more split we use, then we have a more significant reduction
in the impurity measure.
OK, actually, this is not a good thing.
This is because actually, then based on this question,
there are every time that you will use a multiple split.
Multiple split normally makes the tree more complex.
OK, because the fewer multiple split, right?
So every node for every feature, as long
as the tree has more than two values,
it will use multiple split.
But this may not be necessary.
OK, so then we need to change this, modify this actually,
drop, right?
We need to modify this actually, drop of the impurity measure.
So this is a modified one.
So it's kind of scaled actually impurity measure.
So data, I, and I, and then divided by this.
So this is actually is a modified, or scaled impurity drop.
Scaled impurity drop, OK?
And then this is actually, even the measure,
will not actually fewer the multiple split.
And actually in the C4.5, right?
So it adopt the multiple split.
But not necessarily, at every node,
it adopts actually multiple split.
So it will adopt multiple split if necessary.
And then what a measure to use to determine whether we
should use or not, they based on this.
They based on this actually scaled actually impurity
measure in the nowhere frame by the C4.5 classification tree.
OK.
So next tree, I show you step by step,
OK, and how to construct tree.
So here, we have one example.
This is, I think the data set is also,
until you learn the core site, you can also
download this data to play, right?
To try to practice.
So here, in this data set, the tree, the data set
is about the heart attack, heart disease data set.
The tree in the left column is just
index of the samples.
Each sample is one rule.
It's a one rule, right?
And the first feature, H, the second feature is sex.
Then that feature, CP.
And then actually we have the rest of BPS.
So in the written state, what is the pulse?
I think all the values.
So totally, we have 13 features.
So these are 13 features.
Are the properties of the characteristics of the patient?
OK, so for each patient, for each subject,
we have one measurement for all the 13 attributes or properties.
OK?
And some of the features are actually binary.
You can see, even from the example, right, for sex,
of course, we know we only have two possible values, right?
And male or female.
And then, of course, here, we use the numerical value
to denote male or female.
So one, maybe denote male and zero different female.
OK, so we can see this sex count is a binary feature, right?
Only two values.
So for this feature, sex, I think it's easy to determine,
right?
We should use the two split, right?
So binary split, OK?
And then, also, for the CP, right?
For the CP, actually, here, we have
seen that we have multiple values, right?
Not just two.
One, two, three, four.
All the four values.
If you can have four possible values.
And therefore, for the age, age, actually,
is a continuous variable.
It has multiple values.
So this data is a myth, right?
It has many other features, right?
Like, it's a myth data.
We have a binary feature.
We have discrete features, like one, two, three, four, right?
And also, we have continuous features.
And then, we look at other features,
like FBS is a one-zero, right?
It's a binary feature.
And then, it's changed.
It is a zero-one, all the binary features.
For this, actually, it's continuous.
For this, actually, it's a multiply, right?
OK.
Now, it's a zero.
Two can be three.
It can be one.
It's four values.
So, actually, and then, as I said, we look at it.
For all these features, which feature
we should use as the root node, as the first node in the zero
level, level zero.
Which node we should use?
Which feature we should use?
OK.
So, actually, we don't have ID, right?
But we have the method to determine which feature we
should use as the root node.
In other words, actually, we need to evaluate the impurity
measure.
And when each of them attributes is used in the root node,
then we evaluate each of them.
OK.
Then we identify the one that has the smallest impurity
measure, so after split by the feature and also the question
based on the feature.
And OK.
So, in that tree, we look at that.
So now, we just have a summarization of the data set.
And this data set, actually, contains samples
from two classes.
One class is the patient with a heart attack,
and a heart problem, right?
And then the class two contains samples without heart attack.
And the number of samples in class one is 139.
The number of samples in class two is 164.
So these are the distribution in the two classes, right?
And also, we know each of the samples
is represented by 13 features, 13 attributes, 13 properties.
So age, sex, we have seen that, right?
So for each of the attributes, we have these plots on them,
right?
We know they are binary, or they take multiple values,
or they are continuous.
OK.
And so now, actually, based on this understanding
of the data set and also the features,
so, naturally, we first decide the first node, the root node.
So which feature we should use?
We should use age, or we should use sex,
or we should use a CPU or others.
It's the first feature in the root node.
So, OK, so, naturally, we assume sex is used.
Sex is used, right?
And if sex is used, for this feature,
we just have, actually, two values.
So, naturally, we can just divide the data into two branches,
right?
Two branches, OK?
And so here, in this course, actually, I just follow two.
We just assume two.
Even the feature, actually, adopts,
actually, the multiple split.
Have multiple values, we can still use the binary split.
So here, I just use the binary split.
And so here, in the sex, of course,
this question about sex, we can really
ask whether sex equals 0 or sex equals 1, right?
Then, because it's just two values,
so naturally, we can divide the data into two parts.
OK.
So then, actually, the data come to the left node.
Data come to the right node.
In the left node, left branch.
And, totally, we have 97 samples.
And 25 from class 1, 72 from class 2.
So these are the samples in the left side, in the left branch.
And then, in the right branch, we have most data set,
and the data.
We have 206 data samples.
OK.
And 119 from class 1.
Actually, from class 2, we have 92 samples.
OK.
So certainly, actually, the data is very impure, right?
Because, actually, here, we see 25, 30.
This is like 25% or 70% from one class.
25 or 30% from another class, right?
So impure.
Not like 100 versus 0, right?
Not like that.
Or 95 versus 5%.
So here is like 70, 30%.
OK.
Very impure.
And then, we call the tree.
We can measure the impurity measure.
If sex is used as a rule node, and then, based on this question,
sex is 0 and the data divided into two parts,
then we will look the impurity measure
for each of the two parts, for each of the two data subset.
OK.
And for the data in the left branch, 25, 79, right?
So based on this, we can calculate the probability, right?
The probability belonging to class 1, p omega 1,
is just a p omega class 1, right?
25 divided by 97.
Then, p omega 2 is 72 divided by 97.
So we know p omega 1.
We know p omega 2, right?
So naturally, we can easily calculate the impurity measure.
Any of the three measures we can use,
assume the gene impurity measure is used,
and then we can calculate the samples of the data set
in the left side gene impurity.
1 subtract p omega 1, right?
Square minus p omega 2 square, then divided by 2.
OK.
So omega 1, 25 divided by 97.
p omega 2, 72 divided by 97.
Then, divided by 2, we have this value, 0.19, 1, 3.
So this is the impurity measure for the data subset,
actually, in the left node.
For the data in the right node, similarly,
then we can evaluate the impurity measure, right?
The impurity measure in the right side.
OK.
So here, omega 1 is 1, 1, 4, right?
Divided by the total number of samples in the left node.
In the right node, 2, 6.
OK.
Then, for class 2, it's 92 divided by 2, 6.
Then we can measure, 0.2471.
So these are the impurity measures for the left node,
left descendant node, right descendant node.
So next, we need to combine the two nodes, right?
The two nodes impurity measure into one single impurity
measure, combined the two.
The combination of the overall impurity measure,
just weight the summation of these two, weight the summation.
That means each of these impurity measures
should have a weight, right?
What is the weight?
The weight is just the proportion of the data
going to the left, going to the right.
OK.
So it's the proportion, 97 going to the left, right?
Total sample is the 303.
OK.
So the weight goes to the right, 2, 6,
goes to the left, right?
And then, 303 is the total number of samples.
So this is the PL, this is the PR.
So linearly combine them, or weight the summation
of the two impurity measures.
Then we get the overall impurity measure, 0.2276.
So this is the impurity measure if the impurity measure,
if the sex is used.
OK.
So whether this sex is the best selection,
we're not very sure, because we have no try others, right?
So the necessary we should try others, one by one.
So necessary we try FBS, for example.
FBS, again, if you look at the values,
is a binary feature.
And we have two values, 0 or 1.
So then, again, we can ask questions like, FBS equals 0.
You can also ask, FBS equals 1.
Then you can divide the data into two subsets.
So for the FBS, then we have this split of the data.
In the left-hand side, then we have two 5-8 samples.
And in the right-hand side, we have 45 samples.
And then based on the distribution of the data
in the two classes, then we can find the proportion.
Pumir 1, Pumir 2, then we can find the gene impurity measure.
For the data in the left-hand side,
for the data in the right-hand side.
So I think this measure is quite straightforward, right?
Pumir 1, 1 by 7 divided by the total number in the left.
Minus Pumir 2, 1 for 1, divided by all of these.
So this is the left-side impurity measure.
And then this is the right-side impurity measure.
And then that's a treatment to combine these two measures,
two values to produce one overall impurity measure.
Based on the proportion of data going to the left,
going to the right.
So the overall impurity measure, if FBS is used in the rule
of the descendant node, right?
And then this is 0.2481.
So the first one, if sex is 0.2276, right?
So here is 0.222481.
So certainly the sex is better than this FBS, right?
Because the sex is used, the impurity measure,
in the descendant node is less than the descendant node
because FBS is used, right?
Because 1 is 0.22 something, and not 0.24 something, OK?
So the sex is better than FBS.
But whether sex is the best among all the 13, we don't know.
We have no try others, right?
So necessarily we should try others one by one, OK?
So necessarily we try the age.
Why age is selected?
Because age is different.
Age is a continuous variable.
Just now we have FBS, we have sex,
which are binary features, right?
Binary features are easy to determine.
Just the splitting point is easy to determine.
Because you just have two values, right?
You use other value to ask questions.
If you have 0 or equal 1, you can ask the question easy, right?
And before age is continuous, we have so many values, right?
So which value should be used to divide the data into two
subsets?
So that's the issue, OK?
Because it's continuous, OK?
And actually for other discrete features like CP,
we have 1, 2, 3, 4, right?
Actually, we can follow a similar method like age.
So because you have multiple values.
For age, OK?
So it's continuous.
So how to find the splitting point?
Which age we should use to divide the data?
Age should be greater than 65 years old,
based on this question, to divide the data into two subsets,
from very young to 66, right?
65, 66, and then from over 66, right?
Until we're at old age, two data subsets, OK?
So we need to decide the data points.
So how to decide?
First, we need to sort the data in ascending order,
increasing order, from a smallest to biggest.
We need to arrange the data, look at all the data, the values.
Actually, the 29 is smallest, then 23, OK?
So from this example, this is 29, OK?
34, 35, 37, and all, very big values, right?
And then for each of the two adjacent values,
neighboring values, we find the middle point.
Middle point, actually, just the mean value,
every value of the two, right?
For each adjacent point, for example, 29, 34, we get average.
OK?
Then 34, 35, we get average.
35, 37, we get average.
So we get the middle point of the adjacent values.
Then we can have this.
31.5 is the value between 29, 34, right?
The middle point.
And then 34.5 is the between 34, 35.
36 is between 35, 37, right?
So you can actually all get all the middle point values.
Then we need to use each of these points
as a possible splitting point to divide the data
into two types, into two subsets.
OK?
And for example, if we use 31.5 to divide the data
into two subsets.
So each of the middle points is one candidate splitting
some point.
And then we divide the data into two subsets.
Then we evaluate the impurity measures of the two parts.
And then we combine the impurity measure of the two parts
into one overall impurity, right?
Based on the proportion of the data going to the right,
going to the left, going to the right, combined.
OK?
So this is an impurity measure.
If age is selected as the feature to ask a question.
And if 31.5 is the splitting point to divide the data,
then we can get this value.
OK?
Then we try 34.5 to get the corresponding impurity
measure.
OK?
So for example, as we use 31.5 to split the data.
And then we can find that age greater than 31.5.
You can also ask age smaller, no less than 31.5.
The same, no problem.
Just the tree, the left, come to the right,
right come to the left.
It's not no matter.
So if we use age greater than 31.5,
this question to split the data, right?
And then actually we have a majority of the data
coming to the left node.
And only one sample going to the right.
OK?
And then that's actually we can calculate the impurity
measure for all the data in the left node.
OK?
So for class 1, POML 1139, right?
Divided by two to the number of samples.
That tree is 302.
The minus 163 divided by the total number of samples
in the left.
So this is POML2, that's square.
OK?
I divided by these two.
We get this value.
This is the impurity measure for the subset in the left.
And then the impurity in the right.
I treat the data in the right-hand side only one, right?
It's a pu.
It's pu, right?
Only sample from one class.
I treat the impurity measure should be zero, right?
Should be zero.
Indeed, it is zero.
For class 1, only zero sample, right?
So it's probably zero.
For class 1, for class 2, one sample, one.
This is class 2.
So it's POML2 equals 1.
Then the total impurity measure for the data in the right
side is zero.
Then we need to combine this i left, i right,
based on the proportion.
Going to the left, going to the right, right?
So this is the overall impurity measure.
And if 31.5 is used as a splitting point for the edge,
we can get this.
3.2476.
And this is 31.5.
Whether this 31.5 is a good one, we have no idea.
We should try another one, right?
So that is 34.5.
And actually, for each of the possible splitting points,
and we can find the corresponding impurity
measure after data splitting by this splitting point.
Then we can have this.
We can have this.
And this is actually the horizontal here.
Just shows a splitting point.
The vertical here shows the corresponding impurity measure.
Certainly, actually, when this value, this is actually
34.5.
When this value is used as a splitting point,
then we have the minimum impurity, impurity measure.
So that is around the impurity measure,
it is 0.228.
So for each, for this feature, the best splitting point
is actually 54.5.
Of course, actually, here, for illustration,
actually, you can write a program to do just a loop,
to evaluate one by one.
You can write very easily.
So although it seems tedious, actually, it's quite easy
in practice.
You just write a loop to execute this process.
Then you can get the best splitting point for H.
And then we can also get the best impurity measure,
so that is just 0.228.
If H is used, and the splitting, we use other question,
and if H greater than 54.5, so this feature
and this particular question, then
impurity measure in the descending node is 0.228.
So this is H. And then similarly, we
can measure all of them, assume actually that sex is selected.
The sex is the minimum.
Assume.
So until so far, sex is the minimum value.
So sex is selected.
Then this is the first node.
The rule node is determined.
And then the question here is easy,
because sex is a binary feature.
So yes or no.
As a splitting point, it's just 0, 1.
It doesn't matter.
It's just too value.
So this is the first node, the rule node.
And then we have the descending node, left,
descending node, right, descending node.
And then from each of the data now,
in the left side, in the right side,
we should repeat this process.
So for this data set in the left,
then we should try the features.
Which feature we should use to divide the data in the left?
Based on the same procedure.
We check if a trigger.
Maybe sex cannot be used, because sex is just
in the parent node, in the rule node.
Then maybe here we should not use sex.
We should use others.
We should try others one by one.
You can also try sex.
You still try sex.
And because sex comes to here, all have the same value, right?
Same value to the left.
They all have one.
You cannot use this, actually.
One single value.
You cannot use it to divide the data, right?
So you cannot use sex.
But if a feature, for example, the feature, actually,
already known like a CP.
Assume CP is the user first.
And then you divide the data into two split.
For example, in the left-hand side,
actually, the data, the CP value equals 1 or 2.
In the right-hand side, the CP value equals 2 or 3.
And then in the next node, we can still ask questions about CP.
Because the CP still have two values, right?
1, 2 in the left side.
And in the right-hand side, 3 or 4.
We can still split.
But not for sex, because there are only two values.
All the data in the left side, only one value.
That is sex equal to zero.
You cannot use sex to divide the data.
But we can use other features.
We can try remaining 12 features one by one,
following the same procedure.
But just based on this data, not the full data,
based on the data in the left, we ask the same question.
We follow the same procedures.
Then finally, we decide the best one.
Because that's actually, we have a break.
So timing is broke.
OK.
So just now, we have learned how to select the rule node.
And actually, the selection of the descending node
in the next level follows exactly the same procedure.
We need to test or we need to evaluate each of the remaining
features, right?
And all the 12 features, one by one.
And for some of the features with multiple values,
like continuous features or features with multiple values,
like even discrete.
And we also decide the optimal splitting point.
And then we get the optimal, actually, the smallest
impurity measure, if that feature is used.
So then finally, we need to compare the impurity measures.
Resulted from each of the 12 features, right?
Including the best splitting point.
Then we decide which one to use.
And for example, here, for this, right?
After data, we can test the ABS.
If the ABS is used, so previously,
we evaluated the ABS based on the full data set.
But now, actually, the ABS is used based on the data set
going to the left only.
I think the data going to the left is only 97 samples.
So based on these 97 samples, we decide, actually,
the impurity measure in the descending nodes
if the ABS is used.
And similarly, so this is actually very straightforward,
right?
Your BS is used.
And then we look at the sample here, right?
And if yes, you have the use.
And this is very easy, right?
Because the ABS is a binary sample, right?
We can only ask this question.
Oh, the ABS equals 1, right?
That's true.
I try identical.
And then going to the left, 97, right?
We look at 97.
Sorry, it's 85, right?
85 sample going to the left.
Because totally we have 97.
I go to the right 12 samples.
So for these 85 samples, then we look at the impurity measure.
For these 12 samples, we look at the impurity measure.
That is the right, right?
So then finally, we combine the two.
We follow the exact same procedure.
Based on the percentage of the sample going to the left
or going to the right.
So that is the impurity measure.
If ABS is used, if ABS is used, right?
But whether this is the best, we cannot see at this step.
We need to try remaining 11 attributes.
We will try one by one.
Necessarily, if we use this one, we try this one.
It's changed.
It's changed to use.
Then the 97 sample will be split into two parts.
Then the derivative here is different from the previous case.
Previous, if you add this, so one set have 12 samples.
Another set have 85 samples.
But if we use actually the exchange as a feature,
it's a binary.
And then we have this kind of split.
And then we can again calculate the impurity
measure in the left node, in the right node.
Left, I mean this immediate descendant.
Immediate descendant.
Then we can have the two impurity measures.
Then we can combine them.
So this is 0.1493.
Previously, if actually the ABS is used,
then it's 0.18 something.
So here, obviously, this 0.14 is smaller.
In other words, the exchange actually
is a better feature to be selected as a node.
But actually, we are not aware of other.
We already know exchange is better than ABS.
We also need to check others.
Finally, we calculate each of the impurity measure.
When each of the features is used, then finally,
we decide which one to use.
We assume this impurity measure exchange,
the exchange is the best.
Then we can have this model.
This is the one.
So after we try 12 times, repeat 12 times.
And then we identify exchange is the best, assume.
Then we can have this tree.
So now we grew the tree from one node.
So now we have a tree, a tree more node.
We have the next level, right?
It's changed.
Then we have one, we have zero, right?
Then we have a root node, and then two descendant nodes.
Then now for the left descendant node,
we further have a tree, and this is a tree, the two nodes.
So now we have one, two, three, four, five nodes.
We have this node.
So we grew the tree.
And then we grew the tree.
So when we should stop?
When we should stop?
So that is the issue, right?
So here, I've got a dream for those data
set in the right branch.
You can follow the same procedure, right?
Evaluate each of the top features.
And then you decide which feature
to use in this level for the data in the right hand side.
When to stop splitting?
So this is the problem issue.
I want to detail.
And in the extremely case, normally,
this will not happen.
And each leaf node just corresponds to one training
on data.
So if there is a tree, the data is extremely overfitted.
So one leaf node corresponds to one training data.
Of course, the purity is very high, right?
And also, from the number, you just have one sample.
You cannot perform further splitting of the data.
You certainly should stop.
So that is the terminal or the leaf node.
But whether we should grow the tree until this step,
certainly we should not.
Because this is a tree, we are overfitting the training data.
And also, the tree will be very big.
You want to identify the classifier one testing sample,
then it will go to many branches, right?
Many and the path is very long.
You want to determine actually the class label
of that testing sample.
Because the tree grows to a very big tree with many layers,
many levels.
OK.
Conversely, if splitting will stop too early,
so these are stopped too late, right?
Too late, then we have overfitting.
OK.
Conversely, if splitting will stop too early,
an extremely case is that we just have one root node.
And then the next level terminal node or leaf node,
these are extremely case, right?
Early stopping.
And then a tree, such a scenario tree,
we see the tree will underfit the data, underfitting.
We have overfitting, we have underfitting.
And underfitting we can imagine, right?
Just based on the sex.
For example, just not sex, the best, right?
After this, we can see the data is very impure, right?
If we just have a leaf node, just like this, just one level.
You can see, that is the 25, 32 right here.
This means that left side, if you see the leaf node,
then the class label of this leaf node will be class 2.
Then almost 25 divided by 97% of the data
will be misclassified.
So the error rate is too high.
For the right-hand side, 92 samples
among the 206 sample will be misclassified.
OK.
This is the tree growing is stopped too early.
This is an extremely case.
Of course, not just this level, we will stop later.
But it's early stopping.
So the data will underfit it.
Underfitted.
Underfitted, of course, the performance on the tree data
will be bad.
And on the text data also will be bad.
So we should try to, of course, actually
award these two scenarios, right?
To extreme cases.
One is actually overfitting, and the other is underfitting.
And how we could overcome or could award these two scenarios?
And actually, so how we decide when to stop?
And quite often, we can use the so-called validation,
like cross-validation, right?
And actually, we are talking about the cross-validation
in the part of classification evaluation.
And we were talking about different evaluation procedures
and also different evaluation metrics.
So here, actually, one of them is called cross-validation.
And actually, normally, the data is
divided into two parts, like training data, testing data.
And also, quite often, we divide the data into three parts.
Or we divide the training data into two parts.
One part is used to fit the model.
Another part is used to determine the hyperparameters.
So the highest parameter here is just the size of the model.
When we should stop?
So this is a hyperparameter.
How to determine the hyperparameter?
Actually, we should be some validation data.
OK, so that means that for the training data,
we can divide them into two parts.
One part is used to group the tree.
And one part of the data will be used as a validation data
to determine whether we should stop.
OK, if the addition of the more node
will result in a degradation in the performance
on the validation data, then we should stop.
We should stop.
So this is, often, the criterion we should follow.
For almost all the models, we use the cross-validation.
In the neural networks, they train
actually we train many iterations.
The deep neural networks are also.
And then the data will be overfitted.
So when we should stop, we're based on the validation data
performance.
So these are frequent use criterion
to determine when to stop, to determine
actually the size of the suitable model size.
Suitable model size determined based on the cross-validation.
So this propagation or the validation data
is to determine the high-performance.
OK, the size of the model here.
And so actually another method is that we can set a threshold
value.
And actually, every time we see we
have a reduction of the impurity measure
by adding one extra actually level
or by performing a further splitting of the data.
We can reduce the impurity measure.
We can have a reduction.
If this reduction, of course, at the beginning of the introduction
of the reduction of the impurity measure,
is very significant.
But with the growing of the tree,
and then the further splitting of the data
may result in a very small reduction in the impurity
measure.
Actually, you can set a threshold value.
If the reduction of the impurity measure
is less than a certain value, then we stop.
This is also a frequent use criteria in the model training.
And particularly for models, the training procedure
is based on the black propagation.
And if the model is the right size,
we normally, based on this threshold value,
if the error is less than something, we stop.
Here is if the reduction of the impurity measure
is less than something, we stop.
So these are criteria we can use.
There are some other errors.
So I like a cross-validation.
I treat the train directly using all the train data.
So here we don't divide the train data into two parts.
Sometimes the train data is small.
It's very precious to get the train data, very costly.
A very small train data set it has.
But you further divide them into two parts, validation
and training.
So you are always part of the data.
So if we set the threshold value,
then we can still use all the train data to grow the tree.
So this is the advantage of you setting a threshold value
for the reduction of the impurity measure.
And also, if you use the threshold value,
and then the leaf node can lie in different levels
of the tree.
If you go back to our model, to this example,
you can see this is a tree that the leaf node
at different levels.
We don't grow the tree until we're low level.
We're not this low, zero level, many levels.
You go to many levels, then we have a big tree.
So we can have a tree like the terminal node
at different levels.
Different level to make sure we can have a smaller model,
smaller tree.
So this is the meaning.
So this is the advantage of using the threshold
as a solving criteria.
So this is the advantage.
And oh, sorry.
We have a figure here.
OK.
You can look at this.
And actually, another method that we can stop,
if actually the number of samples in a node
is less than a certain value.
For example, we can see for the train data,
if the data points after splitting,
come to the node, the left node or right node,
come to the descendant node, if the number of samples
is less than 10 or less than 5, this
can be a value, a threshold value,
then we should not perform further splitting of the data.
We just stop.
So this can also be used as criteria.
So certainly, actually, we should
use the solving criteria to stop the growing of the tree.
And here, we can have a few methods, validation, results,
the result of the value in data.
And then we can look at the reduction of the impurity
measure.
And also, we can look at the number of samples
in the descendant node.
If it's small, there will be no need
to perform further splitting of the data.
We can stop for that node.
For other nodes, if they still have more than 10,
we should continue until the number of samples in that node
is less than the threshold value, like 10 or 5,
we said that.
So here, normally, we can use a trade-off.
One trade-off is the size.
Another is the leaf node entropy.
Even though the entropy.
So we should have a balance, right?
Balance.
Normally, the impurity in the leaf node is small.
It's small, right?
There is no.
So even the size of the model is big.
So one is small and another big.
So we should have a true, actually,
now balance is the tool.
The size of the model is not too big.
And also, the leaf node, the impurity in the matter,
is not too low.
No need to be too low.
So we have a trade-off between the two.
So this is actually the grouillon, right?
Grouillon, the tree, then actually
we determine when to stop the grouillon process.
This is the first phase in the construction of the tree.
And in the second phase is the pruning.
Pruning to cut some of the branches.
How to cut?
Actually, we start from merging of the leaf node.
So cutting by the trees, actually, called pruning.
And this actually tries to reduce the size of the model
to avoid or to elevate the overfitting problem.
OK.
So here, actually, how to perform this pruning?
Actually, normally, we look at the leaf node.
We start from the leaf node.
Of course, from the leaf node.
We start from the neighboring leaf node.
The leaf node should come to the same, actually, no parent
node.
And then if we combine these two, then we look at the performance.
Look at the performance for mobile.
Even on the train data, right?
If we combine them, right?
And then what should be the degradation of the performance?
What should be the degradation of the performance?
And if the degradation of performance is tolerable,
and then we can combine the two.
If we combine the two, we are resulting in a very big drop
in the performance.
And then we should not combine these two.
OK.
So actually, now we start from the neighboring leaf node.
Then we combine them, right?
For example, for this diagram.
OK.
And then we can look at this, for example, right?
And then the cherry and the grape.
If the two combine them, that means, actually,
we don't do this splitting, right?
Then we just, based on this tree, in this node,
based on this part of the sample,
how many belong to class one?
How many belong to class two, right?
And then we just decide to determine the class label
of that particular branch or node.
And then we look at what is the degradation of the performance.
If the degradation of the performance is not much,
then we can combine.
OK.
So this tree, cherry and the grape, will be cut.
It will be cut.
We will cut.
Then we have this node.
Then, actually, this node will become a leaf node again.
And then this leaf node is a leaf node.
Then we are still looking at whether this new leaf node,
this leaf node, and the apple should be combined.
Because leaf node, the apple and this combined leaf node,
come from the same node, size small.
So we also need to look at others, right?
But we combine the leaf node from the same parent node.
Come back.
Then what is the degradation of performance?
If it's small, then we come back.
Then this node become a leaf node, right?
Then at another level, we also look
at whether this leaf node, new leaf node,
could be combined with other leaf nodes.
OK.
So we should continue until the degradation will
be significant after the merging of these two leaf nodes.
If there is significant degradation of the performance,
that means we should not merge these leaf nodes.
OK.
So this is the pruning process.
So we have the grueling to make the tree big.
Then we cut some branches, right?
We merge the leaf node to make this small.
So this is called pruning.
Grueling and pruning are the two processes,
two phases of the construction of the class-fission tree.
So this is the pruning, right?
The assignment of the leaf node labels.
I already talked about this point.
I think for the leaf node, normally we
don't expect 80% percent pu.
And it contains samples from multiple classes.
Then how we could determine the label of this leaf node?
We look at the majority.
We identify which class has the largest probability.
Then we just assign that class label for that leaf node.
We look at the majority, right?
We look at the majority.
So this is the assignment of the leaf node.
So each tree leaf node corresponds
to the pattern in a single category.
And all that has the largest number of samples.
So each leaf node should be labeled
by the category that has the most samples.
Of course, actually, this will result in some misclassifications.
We will result in some class-final areas.
But as long as the area is in the tolerant range,
then actually, this is OK.
If not tolerant range, then you should continue to grow, right?
You should divide the data into split data into,
two nodes.
And then the data will become pure.
And then we can have less misclassifications.
So this is the assignment of the leaf node.
And that's actually we look at one example.
So this example has been used before for linear class-file
design in the linear sub-blog-1 machine
or in the Fisher-Linux human analysis.
So you can both.
And then, actually, we have a design
on the decision boundary linear line, right?
To separate the sample in the two classes.
So now, use the same data set.
We design another class-file.
That is the class-filling tree.
And so here in the data set, we have two features.
X1, X2, horizontal X1, vertical X2.
So we need to determine which feature we should use
in the root node, X1 or X2.
When we determine, then, of course, we
should evaluate actually if X1 is used as a root node,
so what is actually the impurity measure
after data splitting?
If X1, 2 is used, so what is the impurity measure
Then we compare to determine which one is the best one.
But actually, for each of the features,
when we evaluate the impurity measure after data splitting,
we need to determine another factor, right?
Another thing.
That is the splitting point.
Because actually, the two features
are both continuous features.
They have more than two values, much more than two values,
much more values than two.
So we need to design a suitable value of a splitting point.
Just like H in the example, H is continuous.
So we should sort in the data.
We sort the data from a small to a large for X1,
then, as a decision value, we determine a middle point.
Then each of the middle point will
be used as a candidate to divide the data into two parts.
Then we evaluate the corresponding impurity measures.
Then we identify the best splitting point for this feature,
X1, and then similarly for X2.
Then we compare another best splitting point.
What is the best feature to be used for the root node?
So actually, this is X1, the same process.
This is for X1.
Different nodes, actually, the splitting point
have different impurity measures.
So this is the one.
Around 1.0 something, then the impurity measure is 0.14.
This is the best one for X1.
Similarly for X2, this is the best one, 0.08, very small.
Even the best is 0.14 something.
This one, the best is 0.02 for X2.
Certainly, X2 is a better feature
to be used as a root node.
Then you can just actually, or X2 is the best splitting point
divided data.
Going to the lab, 100 data.
Going to write 100 data.
Then you can do, for the 100 data in the lab,
you can look at X1.
Because we can only use X1.
You can also use X2.
It's possible to use X2.
And then you can divide the data.
You value the best splitting point for X1.
Then you can group.
Similarly for this part, you can also
determine the best splitting point.
So you can group the tree.
So actually, this is a procedure.
You can group the tree.
And actually, of course, in many tour bosses,
like in my lab or others, actually,
we can have some function to use for classification
tree construction.
In the my lab, for example, they have a fit classification
tree, fit C tree, C mean classification.
Then actually, if we use this, we can fit C tree.
We can get these out.
So this is the tree.
And a very big tree, right?
Very big trees.
Although two features, the tree, we
can see there are many splits, right?
There are many nodes.
And actually, this is a node.
Actually, in my lab, a tree, they also output a root.
Actually, you can see the tree, right?
And each tree, for a tree, each node of a tree is a root.
X1 greater than something, or X2 greater than something,
or less than something, right?
This is a root.
And actually, these are the roots.
So in the center tree, they also create these roots.
So tree is just a graph representation of these roots.
So tree is a root base classification, a root base.
This root, of course, is the length from the data,
rather than from the demysperia knowledge.
And so this is the root base classification, right?
So this is the descent boundary.
And actually, we can see this descent boundary
is no longer a straight line.
So class of tree is no longer a linear classifier.
This is a, the boundary is a nonlinear.
Actually, this is a nonlinear, consists of three straight lines,
linear boundary, right?
Actually, we have a linear boundary here.
We have a linear boundary here.
We have a linear boundary.
We have three lines.
So this is a nonlinear boundary, consists of three lines.
So this classifier is a nonlinear classifier.
Classifier tree is a nonlinear.
This boundary is not a hyperplane or a straight line.
It is nonlinear.
So this is the descent tree.
And so from here, we can see six training samples.
Actually, I'm misclassified.
And so here, actually, if we set, so the tree,
you can see the tree is very big, right?
We just have two features.
Then we have a few layers, right?
We have so many nodes.
And so if we set some threshold value
for the number of samples in each node,
we use these criteria to stop, criteria
to stop the growing of the tree, right?
OK, then this is the result.
If we request at least 10 samples at leaf node,
then we have this result.
Just a tree, a small tree, a much smaller tree, right?
Much smaller tree.
If we set, actually, the threshold value
for the number of samples in a node, then it says 10.
But if you set to five, then this is not the tree
will be bigger, right?
So if you set to five, then these are not the tree.
This tree certainly is a bigger tree, right?
Bigger tree.
OK.
And so if you set the number of samples in a leaf node,
a threshold value to 10, then we can have this tree,
and then this is the decision boundary.
This is the decision boundary.
And this decision boundary, we have 10 training areas.
Previously, we have six training areas.
But now a tree is much smaller, right?
Then it has 10 areas.
From here, you can see the smaller the model,
the more areas in the training data.
The bigger the tree, the smaller the training areas.
So we should have a trade-off.
The model size, the area.
So as long as the area is in the telearrange, it's acceptable.
And then, for example, 10 training areas acceptable,
we have 200 samples, right?
10%, 5% area is acceptable.
And then we can use just this tree.
Tree is smaller, right?
Then the reason for this is inference process is faster.
Inference process, I mean, for testing data,
the process will determine the class label.
Actually, this process is faster.
The area is acceptable.
But what area is acceptable?
It depends on application, right?
For example, I think in classification,
if you have some web page, you are looking for something.
And then, the system will recommend some web page to you.
Even if there is an area, they recommend you 10.
Maybe only 9 is relevant, 10% is not relevant.
And not a big issue, right?
It's acceptable.
But we require a fast result.
We search.
Immediately, we can get the list of the relevant website.
We want this process to be fast.
Even there is a 10% error.
No problem.
So we should use this kind of model.
But in other scenarios, for example,
if we use a tree, a decision tree
to decide whether you can access your bank account, right?
If the error rate is 10%, that means
you have a high chance, right?
Actually, the money will transfer to others, right?
From your account.
Because actually, that's an error rate of 10%,
or 5%, 10%, right?
That's a no rate.
It's too high.
Then you need to grow a very big tree
to ensure the accuracy is as high as possible.
So this all depends on application.
You decide the size and also the acceptable error rate.
OK.
So by then, you treat all of them, right?
You kind of see, I want to get a small model.
Then the best performance is the best.
No such thing.
OK.
So that's a tree.
Maybe I show some typical cloud-future trees.
And some like a cart.
Cart is actually a cloud-future regression tree.
And then we have AD3.
This is for, actually, the cart is a binary tree.
So here, it's used a tree, multiple split.
A more famous one is the C4.5.
So the name is a bit strange, right?
C4.5.
This is very famous, a cart-future tree.
So here, they use a multiple split.
The split is greater than 2, no longer binary.
And then, actually, they use a gain ratio.
What is gain ratio?
The no-scale that tree, you remember the scale that
tree, the impurity reduction, right?
That is the gain ratio.
It's used for the selection of the features
and also the determination of the significant point.
So these are the commonly used.
And then another very famous is the random forest.
So now, these random forests become
a very popular decision tree.
Based on decision tree, the forest, right?
Forest, that means more than one tree.
So it's a forest.
And by random, while random, actually, later, we
will see that random mechanism, actually,
underlying two paths.
And so here, this diagram shows, actually, random forest.
So we have multiple trees.
So these are called the forest.
We have multiple trees.
And each of the tree, actually, is based on random
selected samples, training samples, a subset of the
training samples, random selected.
Also, based on random selected features, not all features
are used in each of the trees.
All the trees use different features.
So random selected samples, random selected features, are
used to create each of the trees.
So these are called random, multiple trees.
So it's a random forest.
And then, for each of the sample, we can have one result
from each of the trees in the forest.
Then finally, we can combine the results into one single
result.
So how do we determine that?
We take the majority.
So majority voting is used to determine the final level of
the training sample.
So this is actually random forest.
So that's the tree we have a look of this random forest.
And actually, random forest here, and so it's a use
multiple trees, or multiple classified.
So this is also called a tree ensemble method.
Ensemble.
We use multiples.
And in the construction of each of the trees, they use
random selected samples.
So here, they use the ensemble training backing.
Begging is a combination of the two parts.
One is called bootstrapping.
Bootstrapping is a kind of sampling technique.
And aggregating would mean combining the result from
multiple trees.
So it's an ensemble technique, or begging.
So begging is a bootstrapping for the creation of the data
set.
Aggregating means the combination of the result of
different trees.
So bootstrapping is kind of a tree sampling technique.
And this sampling technique is called a tree, often when
it's not stated, we call sampling with replacement.
For example, I want to select one student, 10 students.
I select one student, and then put it back.
So this is called a tree.
This is a bootstraping.
So this is actually an idea.
Bootstraping is called random sampling with replacement.
You sample the data.
When you collect the second data, you still have the
chance to get this data.
So these are known as sampling with replacement.
You have some repeated samples, sample number 10.
So in another sample, you get repeated samples.
Because after sampling, you put it back, then get another one.
Then this is the same one.
Also have the chance to be picked in the second time,
the third time.
So this is a bootstrapping.
And then actually, we have the random sampling without
replacement.
After this sample is selected, the next time only other
samples could be selected.
So with all the replacements.
So instead today, it's quite often we have this name,
right, concept term.
Sampling with replacement, sampling without replacement.
Then you can get another set.
So here, with the bootstraping, sampling with replacement.
Sampling with replacement is a bootstraping.
To create the data set, a useful data set will be used to
create one tree.
So this is the, and then finally the tree results are
aggregated, combined.
So this is called a sample attending or backing, right,
a backing.
Bootstraping for data generation.
Aggregating for the results from multiple trees.
OK, so some properties.
And then these are the steps.
I just show you, I think this step.
So we create an end data set through bootstraping.
You randomly select 100 samples.
Randomly select replacement 100.
This is got a one data set.
Then you randomly select another 100 samples.
Get another one, put back, get another one, put back.
Repeat 100 times.
You get 100 samples.
So you repeat this many times.
You create end data subset.
End data subset are randomly selected using the so-called
sampling with replacement technique.
And then based on each of the data set, we randomly select
end features.
Not all features are used.
So these are not the randomness, right?
So random features, random data.
So then after a random selection of the features,
and also based on this random selection on the data set,
the data, then we create a tree.
How to create a tree?
Just follow the method we introduced today.
You can create binary trees.
You can create the multiple split trees.
So for each of the data, we create a tree.
But each of the tree uses different data set,
uses different features.
Of course, some of the features could be different.
Some of the features would be different.
So they use different features subset.
And then we repeat this process until all the data set I use,
until all end trees are created.
So this is just the illustration of this, right?
We have to subset one, create one tree, subset two, create
another tree, right?
So we totally end subset.
We create end trees.
And during the classification of a testing sample,
and normally we go through each of the trees.
I get one result, calculate the voting.
Then we get the voting, take the majority.
Then we just say, this is called aggregating, right?
Bootstrap aggregating the backing.
Then we can look at the majority.
This is a tree, the combination, the aggregating.
Then we just output this majority, the voting result,
as the final result of this testing sample.
So here also list some of the features of the diversity
and the crest of the minority.
Because we just use a subset of each tree, right?
And also parallelization and some of the things that's lit.
So this diagram just shows the comparison, right?
Cloud-fine tree and also the random forest, right?
And the bottom, cloud-fine tree is a foundation, right?
And then we use this foundation to build multiple trees.
Based on different randomly selected data set,
and different randomly selected features subset.
Finally, we combine the result from different trees.
So this shows the comparison, right?
This is the comparison of the features of random forest
and the cloud-fine trees.
For big data set in particular, right?
So now data is very big.
For high-dominant data and the tree.
So we normally use the random forest.
So that is the reason why random forest is very popular
nowadays.
Because nowadays the data is big, right?
Domino is high.
The number of samples is high.
But the big data.
So we prefer to use the random forest and matter.
Of course, the tree, in terms of the interpretability,
I think the traditional cloud-fine tree
is more interpretable.
I think that's all for the cloud-fine tree.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.