Okay, I made it. So can you hear me from the back? I understand that sometimes the voice
is still a little bit too soft. Can I just do a check? Is this volume alright? Is it okay?
You can hear right? But if at any time you find that the volume somehow gets softer and you can't hear,
you just raise your hand, you know, and then as a signal to me, okay, then we'll adjust the microphone
accordingly. Let me just mix it out a little bit. Okay, hopefully that is better. Okay, that should do.
Okay, see a blank screen because I would like to do a recap of what we have done last week.
Right? So this is the second week of our lecture. So next week we have one more week. So next week we will do the quiz at 8.30.
Alright? So the quiz will be somewhere in the north spine. I have specially reserved three big LT to handle the quiz all at one go.
Alright? So by next week, halfway through, you know, we will stop and then you go for the quiz because it will take some time to walk.
So I'll remind you again, we've met to give you an indication roughly where it is. Alright? So next week, 8.30 quiz.
Alright? By 8 o'clock we should be done. Alright? So the question as to what is covered in the quiz, mainly on what we have done on lecture one and lecture two.
Alright? Hooray, right? Okay? One and two only. Okay? So we will still carry on lecture three because it has some substantial material where you'll be responsible also for the exam.
Alright? The final exam. Remember the final exam you say 25 marks there. Okay? But for the quiz, let's not get too complicated.
We'll just do one and two. Alright? Whatever we covered on one and two. Also another note I want to make is that you can see that I gave you quite a bit of materials.
Alright? In terms of the lecture slides. And I think you get the idea or you get the drift that, you know, is quite impossible for me to complete all the slides.
But nevertheless the slides are there. So if you are interested enough in the subjects you want to know a little bit more, you can use the slides and look through it.
Right? Because I would like to think that at least I've got you started in the topic. So you know on a broad picture in a bigger framework what the method is all about.
Alright? I think a lot of time is like that. You know, once you get, you understand at the top level what the general idea is all about.
Then I think the rest of it is just to enhance your understanding in the deeper manner and then to get a little bit more details.
Alright? So whatever I covered in lecture you'll be tested. If you ask me what is testable in the exam, whatever we stop, if I stop at slide 95, that is all there is to it. Up to slide 95.
That I'm quite certain. Is that clear? Okay. So that's for your exam. But for your quiz is what we've done on lecture one and lecture two.
Alright? Fifty minutes could be multiple choice or short question, short answer.
So let's go back to our agenda of what we want to do today. So today let's take a quick recap on what we covered last week.
Alright? I think in the beginning we kind of espal on the fact that you know what we want to learn is about GA genetic algorithm.
And as I said earlier it is all about problem solving. Isn't it? You want to solve a problem.
Now when you want to solve a problem, okay one method available is method heuristic.
And today I hope to show you that you know, don't think that this is the best method for optimization. There's no such thing.
So today hopefully by the end of it you will see on a very top level perspective, right?
Where you must look at algorithms in a very broad sense, right? In order to decide whether it's good, it's bad and so on.
Alright? So it's a method heuristic, right? Heuristic you know what it is. Heuristic is precise.
Now what we are dealing with GA is like some kind of heuristic, right? But it's not the heuristic per se as what the human perceive as heuristic.
It's a heuristic that is based on nature, right? Nature has a certain rules of how the process for example in this case evolution, you know, adaptation and so on.
So that's what we talked about, method heuristic and GA is one of the method heuristic.
So we want to solve a problem. So it kind of makes sense that we understand the nature of the problems.
So last week we categorized or characterized the problems. So this is by no means the absolute way of categorizing.
But certainly this is one way to look at the kind of problems that we are dealing with.
So kind of brought you to the understanding of what is black box, right?
From the perspective of black box, how you see problems, right? Basically there are three entities input, output and model.
So from there you can do a categorization of the kind of problems that you're trying to solve.
And we look at search space, understand the search space, you know, the size, it will give you an idea of the complexity.
So from the perspective of the solution landscape, for example, and optimization and constraint satisfaction.
We did a bit of practice and I hope you have a clear understanding of what it means by constraint satisfaction and optimization.
And I think basically we talk about so-called constraints and then objective function.
So from that little table there, that should give you a clear indication on how to categorize or classify them.
So what is also important from the perspective of problem is the hardness of the complexity.
So the idea is, you know, it's no point telling somebody, oh, it's very complex.
Oh, how is this problem? It's always very complex. That doesn't mean anything.
What is more meaningful is for you to be able to so-called characterize it in such a way that there is indication in terms of problem solving.
That is MP hardness. So understand what is P, NP, NP-hard, NP-complete.
And motivation and inspiration. GA is inspired.
It's an inspired methodology based on evolution and genetics.
So I've come across many students or PhD students. They say, oh, they use GA.
I say, oh, can you explain? This is especially in the qualifying exam.
I say, can you explain the inspiration or motivation of GA?
After a bit of questioning, they kind of admit or they didn't think about it.
They just know how to use it, which is all right, I suppose.
You know, you use it to solve a problem. I think it will be more meaningful and engaging if you know where it came from or how it came about.
All right? So that's what we're trying to do.
And I showed you that there are actually two aspects in the natural metaphor.
One is evolution, Darwinian evolution, survival of the fittest, adaptation.
Why? Because of limited resources. So therefore there is this competition.
All right? There's natural evolution.
So there is somewhat so-called inspire the process of our problem solving.
Now, then we're going to think, OK, how do we put together this information?
How do we transfer and encode the information?
Remember, we're talking about problem solving.
So how do we actually encapsulate or capture the so-called the problem?
And that's where we go to genetics.
Chromosomes. All the information about us is in our DNA, the 23 pairs.
It's a signature of who we are.
The expression, the phenotype, whether we look at phenotype.
So the inspiration, evolution, and genetics.
And of course, at the end of it, we want to know, OK, how? What?
How do you put together a GA?
That's what we aim to do.
So to do that, of course, I think first of all, let's take a look at...
So that's kind of where we left off.
So let's pick it up from there for last week.
So first, we'll look at the scheme of a GA.
It's good to have a big picture or a blueprint of what the GA or EA is all about.
So we look at the scheme of the EA.
And the main components of it, the three things that are listed there.
How do we represent it? How do we evaluate it?
You know, the population and so on.
So that's the second thing we'll look at.
And then we will delve into the Aqueen's problem.
Let's think a little bit more details.
So that should illustrate how we do the capturing or the encoding of the information or the problem.
Typical EA behavior.
Understand where EA stands in terms of optimization.
And I think it's going to change our perspective.
If you understand, say the behavior.
So today we'll look at that.
And EA is in global optimization and neighborhood.
Global neighborhood.
The name implied global means a complete search space.
Neighborhood means, you know what's neighbor, search nearby.
So let's have some understanding on this.
So we follow along this outline and then develop our understanding on what a GA is.
So we look at this slide here.
Always remember these slides.
Not difficult. It's intentionally simple.
Here are three entities. Population, parents, and offspring.
From population, you go to parents.
So remember all the processes that are in nature on evolution as a process of selection.
And also survival of the fittest.
So all this here must be captured or should be captured in our problem solving methodology.
So three entities, population, parents, and offspring.
So parent selection.
So from population to parents, we select according to fitness.
When there's a selection, there must be a basis for selection.
That means that you must have a fitness.
When you have a fitness, there must be a way for you to measure or evaluate.
So there must be an evaluation function.
And then from parents to offspring, there are operators in your GA.
Just like in arithmetic, you have 3 plus 4 and the plus is your operator.
In GA, you have your operators.
We have what we call the recombination operators.
The word recombine means that it involves two or more.
So you recombine.
One famous or most commonly used recombination is crossover.
So you hear the usage of the term crossover quite often.
To cross over means you have two parents and then you just swap information between the so-called,
you take part of the information from parent one and parent two to produce another variation of it.
So you have recombination, random.
So from, this is where the power of GA is.
So in many problems, many algorithms get stuck in local optimum.
So when you get stuck, sometimes basically it is a stalemate.
You cannot get any better.
So usually you need a mechanism to shake it.
A mutation is something like that.
So from parents, you have your offspring and then you have your, from offspring,
survivor selection, create a new gen, so-called a new population.
So that becomes one generation.
So you see the so-called, the mechanisms or the forces at work.
There's some kind of bias towards the, the solution that are good is going to survive over the generations.
So you do these many iterations and in time, all right, the overall fitness should improve.
And then if any luck, you may hit the best solution, what we call the global optimum.
So just a general picture I want you to be very clear about.
If you remember this picture, I think you pretty much have a reasonable high level understanding of GA.
So you understand that, not difficult to put it in quotes.
Okay, even if you don't have background in computer science, I'm sure you can see.
If I put the picture below, this figure below, right, of what is GA, you can quite quickly, quite quickly, right,
see how you can transform this block diagram into pseudo code.
So the whole process entails initialization.
So you, you initialize according to this year, initialize the first set of populations.
So at the beginning, you don't know any better.
So you do a random initialization.
That's quite common.
Now, because there's a selection process involved, so you need to evaluate to determine the fitness.
So once you have that, you have this loop here that will each loop constitute one generation.
So you repeat this loop.
You have selection, recombine, mutate.
So after you select, you have the parents, and then you recombine, and then you mutate.
And then you have your offspring.
From your offspring, you decide who is going to survive to the new generation.
That's called survival selection.
And of course that involves fitness measures as well.
So that's it.
That's the whole process.
See how easy it is, you know, how elegant the whole GA process is.
So what you've seen is that evolutionary processes involves populations of individuals.
These individuals, we understand by individual.
Individuals are sampling, sampling of the solution space.
Many sequential methods, conventional optimization methods, they are sequential.
They work on one sampling or one solution.
GA is different.
Works on a population.
For example, you have a population of 100.
Then essentially what you are doing is that you are sampling 100 different spaces in parallel, simultaneously.
But of course your simulation is still sequential.
But the whole idea is that the population represents like a sampling of different regions of your solution space.
And that is the power of GA.
And each, this population of individuals, each of them have a fitness, right?
Measure the fitness.
How do you measure the fitness?
That's according to the problem that you're trying to solve.
For example, you're traveling salesman problem is the minimum distance.
So your fitness is a connection to the real world, the problem that you are trying to solve.
And then you have a variation operators, which is crossover and mutation.
And selection, survival of the fitness and mating of the fitness.
So that's what you see in the whole evolutionary process that we're going to transcribe into an algorithm.
So you have essentially, right?
All these backgrounds, what you have essentially done is that you have a new form of Darwinism.
A new Darwinism.
So what you've done is that going from the real world metaphor, evolutionary progress towards higher life forms in nature, evolution is the evolution process.
Okay?
Brings a species, so living things to a higher life form.
Well, in your optimization role, you are optimizing according to some fitness criteria.
That is the parallel.
You see, in your Darwinism, so your evolution drives the species.
The evolution drives the species to make it more competitive.
And then the reward is that of course survival of the species.
What's the manifestation of a survival to be able to reproduce?
Okay, that is Darwinism.
But what we do in optimization is that our so-called, instead of reward in terms of reproduction, we have transformed it into or transcribed it into a fitness-based kind of evolution.
So that is quite clearly what is happening.
So let's take a look at the process involved in terms of diversity.
Now what do you understand by diversity?
When you say diverse, what does it mean?
It's different.
So you all come from diverse background.
Diversity.
Do you prefer diversity?
I think in general the answer tends to be yes.
But let's take a look from the optimization point of view, see what is more desirable.
So actually, in the process of optimization through evolution, there are two opposing or competing forces.
One of the fours tends to increase the diversity.
The other decreases the diversity.
Now think about the variation operators like your mutation and recombination.
Well, from a diversity point of view, what you're doing is that you're increasing the diversity.
You want to increase the diversity.
Remember we said in general diversity is good.
But on the other end of it, we want to look for that special thing.
This is optimization, that special thing.
So therefore we must somehow narrow down to so-called what we want.
To narrow down, that means that decreasing diversity.
Where's the process that happens in evolution that brings it to decreasing diversity?
There you go.
It's a selection process.
When you select, you're very biased.
You select according to the fitness.
So you can see quite clearly these two, they are opposing.
In GA or EA, there are processes that increase the diversity and there are processes that decrease the diversity.
So what it means is that push towards novelty, increasing diversity means that,
wow, there are many noble or different solutions.
The other end of it is the quality, specialization.
So here's a question.
In your GA, which one is better?
If you have to pick which one is better?
Equal?
Both.
Quality is better.
That's your objective.
But to get to your objective, you have to increase diversity.
Both are important?
Increase diversity.
Cut.
Then converge.
Increase diversity and then converge.
Okay, which one is more important?
Clearly you describe both, which is more important?
Both important?
You are right, both are important.
Both are necessary.
Both are absolutely necessary.
Therefore, the key idea behind optimization is to have a good balance between increasing and decreasing.
That is what optimization is all about.
To have a good balance in Chinese, the yin and yang, they must be balanced.
So same thing here in our algorithm, they must be that balance.
So it kind of makes sense also when you think about it, because problems are very difficult.
Don't think about simple problems.
We are thinking of problems that are intractable, not solvable.
In order to solve it to the extent where we are able to achieve good solutions,
we must have a process that has a good balance between increasing and decreasing diversity.
And later on, I'm going to throw you a couple of terms as well.
What we call the exploration and then the exploitation.
You must be able to explore and then you must be able to exploit.
Again, the same idea persists.
Which is more important?
Both.
Both are important.
So you see that.
Once you see this, I think you come to a realization, wow, this is indeed a high level understanding
where you can understand the process of what optimization is all about.
So the first thing, to be able to solve a problem, we need to understand that there need to be a representation of the problem.
So quite often we have a problem that comes in different requirements of complexity.
That's the real world.
The real world presents you with a problem to solve.
Here you are, you are a system marketer, algorithm designer.
Your job is to solve it.
I'll come up with methods to solve it.
So in order to come up with the methods to solve it, you must be able to represent it.
You must capture the requirements, specifications, and then to represent it.
Go back and think of the so-called many problem solving that you have done.
It's all the same idea.
You must be able to represent and then formulate it.
So GA is no different.
So representation means that provides code, like a binary code, integer code, or symbolic code.
Provides code for candidate solutions that can be manipulated by the variation operators.
It means the coding.
So two levels of existence.
One is the phenotype.
Phenotype is the physical part.
It's the object in original problem context.
That's the outside.
That's the phenotype.
And then the genotype.
Code to denote that object, the inside.
There's a chromosome.
There's a genotype.
So which means to say that there must be some kind of mapping process going on.
So there are two types of mapping.
One is to encode.
Encode means to go from the real world to the genotype.
And then there's the phenotype to the genotype.
And the other type is the decoding.
After you solve the problem or you want to evaluate it, you need to do decoding.
So for example, your code means a certain specification of a design.
Because maybe it's similar design to know.
Meaning you've got to go to the phenotype space in order to know how good your solution is.
I'm wanting to know this.
Phenotype to genotype.
Not necessarily one-to-one.
So this means you have a problem.
You need to code it.
There's no such thing as only one way to code it.
You can use binary coding.
You can use integer coding, floating point.
Or you may even code it differently.
So it's not a one-to-one.
But your decoding must be one-to-one.
Any code should only be converted.
Or there's only one unique phenotypic expression.
So the coding of it is your chromosome.
To bring the physical world to our programming or computing world.
We need to code it.
So in GA, we call them the chromosomes.
Chromosomes are made up of genes.
Genes, which are usually fixed positions called the low side.
Singular is locus.
L-O-C-U-S.
And have a value of a lew.
A-L-L-E-L-E.
That's a value.
For example, you have a string.
10 characters.
So 10 characters.
That's your chromosome of length 10.
You want to say the gene.
Then you say, OK, the third gene.
Then that's the third character.
Let me write this down.
OK.
This is your chromosome.
So what's the length of this chromosome?
9.
Where are the genes?
OK.
Gene number 1.
Gene number 2.
Gene number 3.
Gene number 4.
And so on.
What's the value of gene number 4?
The value of gene number 4 is 1.
The gene is the position, the locus.
So that is how we're going to do our coding in terms of representation as chromosomes.
So to evolve a population, you're actually evolving a population of strings or chromosomes.
So to put it in picture.
So for example, in this case here, you can see in our phenotype space, that's the value 18, 2, 9, and so on.
If you do binary GA, then you will represent each of so-called the value as a binary in your genotype space.
So 18 will be 1, 0, 0, 1, 0.
2 will be 1, 0, and so on.
So this is going from the phenotype space to the genotype space.
So in order to find a global optimum, every possible solution must be represented in the genotype space.
I think this is quite logical.
Your representation must be sufficient to cover the entire space.
Quite intuitively logical.
Alright, fitness functions.
So fitness function is also what we call our objective function.
We have said quite often the word objective function.
Basically in GA, we transcribe it as a fitness function.
So we use the word fitness, this is in accordance to so-called natural evolution metaphor, where we say the fittest survive.
So in next period in our genetic algorithm, we also have user term fitness function.
But essentially it is the objective function of the problem or the cost function.
So basically in your fitness function, basically you just want to assign a single value to the phenotype.
So that will give you an indication of how good it is.
It's like a fitness of goodness measure.
Now what you need to know or understand is that GA is powerful.
This is another reason why GA is powerful.
Or a good method, maybe I shouldn't say powerful.
GA is a good method because it's easy.
Why is it easy?
Well, your problems are complex.
The problems that you are trying to solve comes in all shapes, different requirements and so on.
So it can be very complex, be it a design problem or traveling salesman problem or whatever problem it may be.
Now in your GA realm, all you need to do is you must have a way to find a fitness.
It's like the GA saying, I don't really care how complex your problem is.
As long as you give me a metric to know how fit each solution is.
So in that sense, GA doesn't really care about your problem, the complexity of the problem.
You can have thousand and one requirements and so on.
But as long as the GA is concerned, all it wants is that to be able to measure the fitness.
And that is through the fitness function.
And that is another reason why because the GA has a very flexible, easy to use.
And it is indeed very easy.
It's robust enough to solve many different types of problems.
Because it's easy, so it becomes very popular.
That's why people, when it was first introduced, it was perceived as very elegant and easy to use.
And it's easy to apply.
So typically when we talk about fitness, we want it to be maximized.
Because to be fit, it means that it's a maximum fitness.
But many problems are minimization problems.
But there's no issue.
You can always convert it.
For example, a plus can be converted to a minus.
Or you can use a big constant just to modify the effect and so on.
So not an issue, whether it be maximization or minimization.
All right.
So we look at population.
So population basically candidate solutions of the problem as individuals, which are the genotype.
So we work with our population.
So out of the model that I showed you, you have population, parents, and then the offspring.
So normally in RGA, we are a fixed population.
Let's say 50, population of 50.
Then you have a 50 of each.
So it's a multi-set of individuals.
Repetitions are also possible.
So when we evolve, we are evolving the population.
But from the population, we select individuals.
So the selective process is on the individuals.
So and then the variation operators.
The selection is from the population set.
But the variation operators are on the individuals.
So the variation like your recombination and the mutation they are on the individuals.
So population are usually constant.
There are some sophisticated EAs that exert a spatial structure on the population.
You understand the word spatial?
Space.
So for example, on a grid, there are some GA's that is based on so-called the grid spatial distribution of the population on a grid structure.
So selection usually takes the whole population into account.
So reproductive probabilities are relative to the current generation.
So let's go back to diversity.
I think in general you understand what diversity means.
Different.
But from a GA perspective, what could it mean?
Diversity could mean fitness.
Fitness meaning like for example, fitness 0.7, 0.6, 0.1 and so on.
So if it's diverse, then the population is different fitness.
Diversity could also be in the context of the phenotype, the expression of it.
The chromosomes may be a little bit different, but then the expression of it could be very different.
Although the chromosome is different or fitness is very small, but then the phenotype expression of it is very different.
For example, maybe one gene different, instead of black, you have white and so on.
So the point is very simple.
When you think in terms of diversity, it's just not in the context of the fitness value.
So fitness is a way for us to tell which chromosome is better or fitter and so on.
So keep that in mind.
So another mechanism is your selection.
You can see earlier on there are two areas where selections happen.
One is selection of the parents and the other is a selection for survival to make up the new generation.
So both are driven mainly by fitness.
As long as they are selection, basically there's a fitness mechanism that is used.
So selection pushes population towards higher fitness.
So generally in the selection, good quality should be rewarded.
Higher fitness should be rewarded either in terms of survival or reproduction.
So how do you make this selection?
It's called probabilistic.
So it is probabilistic.
Now what does it mean in terms of problem solving?
Well, it means that because it's probabilistic, so it's all based on probability.
If two individuals, one has a fitness of 0.9, the other has a fitness of 0.2.
So obviously the 0.9 has a higher probability of selection.
But what is important to note is that even if the fitness is very low, it still has that chance to be selected.
It's just that the chances of selection is lower.
So in an optimization context, this stochastic nature is not deterministic for sure.
So this stochastic nature is what gives it the ability to get out on local optimum.
So what is the so-called the power or the advantage?
So on selection.
So how do you do the selection?
There are many, many different ways to do the selection.
Now when we do selection, we want selection that favors the fitter ones.
So one very common way is to some kind of what we call the roulette view selection.
So if you have three individuals, A, B, and C, so the fitness of A is three, fitness of B is one, fitness of C is two.
So if you put it as a roulette view according to the fitness, then what results is that you have unequal slots for the roulette view.
So what we call this a bias roulette view.
It's bias according to the fitness, the fitter, the individual, the higher the slot it is.
The higher the slot it has, the higher the chance it is selected, either as parents or survival.
So this is one of the most common ways to do selection.
But as I said, this is one of the many, many different ways to do selection.
If you go deeper into GAA, you will realize that there are many selection methods that has been used in many different applications.
But I hope you see the principle of what constitutes an effective solution is one that implements some form of selective treasure according to the so-called fitness.
So there's another type of selection.
Your three modules, remember, you have your population, you have your parents, and then you have your offspring.
Selection for the parents we know, according to the fitness, we want to select potential parents.
So the parents are selected based on fitness, which means to say that individuals that are fit will have a higher chance to be selected as parents.
The other entity is your offspring.
Now you need to select the new generation.
So basically what you have, this is your survival selection.
So what's the purpose of survival?
Survival selection to select individuals to make up the new population, replacement of the old population for the new generation.
So after one generation, you have a new population.
So most EAs use fixed population size.
So we can assume population is fixed.
If it is 50, it shall be 50.
Although they are GA that use populations that changes or variable population size.
So most EAs use fixed population size.
So basically what we need is a way to get the new population from the parents and the offspring.
So in saying that, what this means is that we have to have a mechanism to decide who survives and go into the population, new population.
Earlier on I didn't include the parents, but the real GA has this option to select from the pool of parents and then from the offspring.
For example, if I have a population size of 100, so in the survival selection, I have 200 candidates to select from.
100 from the parents and then 100 from the offspring.
So how do we do this selection?
So in general, there are two ways to do this selection.
That is the fitness base that is according to the rank of the parents plus the offspring.
Pick the best.
Or it could be age based.
Make as many offspring as parents and delete all parents.
Total renewal.
So both can be used.
Sometimes a combination of stochastic and deterministic is used, which is quite common.
When we incorporate the deterministic part, we call it elitism.
Elites, you know the meaning of elites.
It's special treatment.
It will survive regardless.
So sometimes we use both stochastic selection for survival or we could use deterministic which is elitism.
For example, I make the top tree.
I give it special treatment, it will survive regardless because they are the best tree.
So I will fix it such that they will survive.
What's the benefit of it?
You keep the best solution, you don't lose it.
Isn't it? It's an elite, it's the best one, so it's survive.
Is there any potential danger or disadvantage?
What could be the potential disadvantage?
Just imagine this. You understand what is elite.
It's a good one, so it survives regardless.
And so on, it will survive.
What happens with time?
Let's say there's elitism, so after 5,000 generations, what happens?
All the same.
Because the fittest one will dominate, suddenly everybody looks the same.
Not very good.
So that's a danger.
Because does that mean you don't use elitism?
Well, you could still use. There are different methods to actually force the diversity.
For example, people use fitness sharing or scaling.
Or other mechanisms just to forcefully inject diversity.
What is done in a true experimentation?
So variation operators from this diagram here, these are your variation operators.
So the word variation means to cause variations.
To cause variations to the populations or the individuals.
So let's ask ourselves from the viewpoint of diversity.
When you go from population to parents, does your diversity go up, down?
From population to parents, diversity up, down, down.
Because of the selection.
From parents to offspring, up.
That's what the variation does. It causes that kind of variation in the individuals.
So from parents to offspring, the diversity increases again.
So how do we increase this diversity through two different processes?
One is recombination and then the other is mutation.
So your mutation is what we call an arity one kind of operations.
Where it takes only one individual and then produce another individual.
It takes only one input, one individual. So it's arity of one.
So recombination usually is a process that has an arity of two, greater than one.
Can be two or more.
For example, your crossover is an operation that is an arity of two.
Equal to two.
So crossover is a type of recombination or reproduction process.
So arity greater than two is also possible.
It's also possible. It's not used often.
But it is definitely possible.
For example, when you have chromosomes on very long strings.
So sometimes it makes sense to use operations that has arity of greater than two.
So there has been much debate about relative importance of recombination and mutation.
So again, are both necessary?
Well, we found out from experience that it is good to have both.
But however, if you only have a choice of one.
Then between recombination assuming you have only a choice of using either recombination or mutation.
What would be your choice?
You would use mutation as shown by the earlier evolutionary algorithm approaches.
Many of the earlier versions of it are based on mutation type of operation.
Or intuitively you can think of it.
Mutation is a bit random.
But if you do it often enough, there's a good chance or reasonable chance it will hit the solution.
Mutation.
So the main thing about mutation is you must remember it is a random mechanism.
The idea behind mutation is just a small random disturbance or variation.
That is what mutation.
It must be random.
As compared to your recombination, it is based on the fitness of parents that are selected.
Hopefully the offspring will inherit properties from both the parents.
For example, mutation.
We say, for example, before mutation.
This is a binary coding.
The valuation set is only 0 or 1.
So it's either 0 or 1.
So when you mutate the fourth gene, which has a little 1, when you mutate it flips to 0.
So notice when I say gene, it's a fourth gene.
I don't say gene with value 1.
Everyone has a value 1.
So we say gene, the fourth gene, the position of it.
And it mutates to 0.
It flips to 0.
So recombination merges information from parents into offspring.
Choice of what information to merge is stochastic.
All this is a stochastic process, meaning that it's driven probabilistically.
So later on I'll use an example to illustrate the process.
Through some form of simple hand simulation of a problem.
Modes of spring may be worse or the same as parents.
So in recombination, essentially what you are doing is that you are causing the transmission of information from parents to the offspring.
Let's use a simple illustration to see how it works.
So in this example of two chromosomes, one with value of 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, and the other with a value of 0, 0, 0, 0.
So in recombination or crossover, normally we specify a crossover side opposition.
How do we decide the crossover side?
Random.
So in this case, crossover could happen anywhere within the chromosome.
So the result of the crossover is that, for example, the two offspring generated, what you will see is that it inherits properties from parent 1 and parent 2.
Now that's very important to note.
The purpose of this is the inheritance of the problem.
So meaning that because your selection is ready, you select according to the fitness.
So chances are the parents are fit.
So when you do recombination, what is likely is that some of the good features from the parents will be passed on to the offspring.
So that's the purpose.
So there's a form of inheritance.
Now in the context of machine learning, that's learning.
Learning from whatever was before and then from there to improve on it.
So that is the learning part of your GA.
So initialization and termination.
So your algorithm will run.
Initially, you generate a population.
So your population, one good way is just to randomly generate it.
So basically in our population, usually it's done at random to ensure even spread and make sure of possible allele values.
Not necessarily you must do it randomly.
In some problems, we use some kind of problem specific heuristics to seed the population to start the initial population.
For example, you may know you may have some kind of existing heuristics that produce a reasonably good solution.
Not the best, but a good solution.
So the hope is that if you seed the populations using heuristics, the hope is that you don't have to run so long because the starting point is really quite good.
And then you run it, hopefully not too long, you get even better solutions.
That is the whole motivation of seeding it using heuristics.
So termination, condition, check every generation.
So when you reach some hope, some fitness, you quit or reach some maximum allowed number of generations, then you quit or some minimum level of diversity, meaning convergence.
So when you converge up to a certain level, you terminate.
Reaching some specified number of generations without fitness improvement is basically a technique.
Now, what is the best termination to use?
In practice, it really depends on your problem or your requirements.
So if you are solving a control problem where you know it's a feedback, you probably only have like within 1 millisecond.
You got to adjust, make adjustment.
Then probably you got to, your algorithm got to reach a point where within 1 millisecond, it gives you so-called the solution to make the adjustment.
As compared to, for example, you are solving a logistic problem.
For example, every day you plan the logistic, maybe the last mile logistic of your deliveryman.
So you probably have solving it in 5 minutes, that is not an issue.
So you can let it run for 5 minutes and then determine the solutions.
Alright, so you've seen the different flavors of EA.
So the one that has been popular is what we call the genetic algorithms.
In 1975, now you know evolutionary algorithms has been around for many number of years.
It was not until 1975 when genetic algorithm was first proposed or came up.
What was the main innovation of your genetic algorithm?
It's the crossover.
So in the 60s and all, they are evolutionary algorithms.
It has been in existence but not used often enough.
Until in 1975, genetic algorithm came about and it turns out that the main innovation was the crossing over operation.
And some day we are in a situation where even representation as binary strings, just with evolution and crossing over process,
we have a reasonably robust problem solving method.
And then from then on, 1980s and so on, GA has become very, very popular.
So suddenly everything is about GA.
So although there are different types of evolutionary algorithms,
your genetic algorithms, evolutionary strategies, evolutionary programming or genetic programming,
let's not get too preoccupied with it.
So these differences are not so relevant.
So basically, when you talk about GA, you are talking about approach,
the evolutionary process, a population-based algorithm to solve your problems.
So I also mentioned about the selection, selection operators, selection and fitness.
Selection relies on fitness and are independent of your representation.
So the fitness is the connection to your real world.
It's not about the representation, it's the connection, it's the what your real world problem is all about.
Let's take a look at this Aqueen's problem before we take a break.
So specification for the Aqueen's is very simple.
We saw this earlier on.
Basically it's to place Aqueen's on an 8x8 chessboard such that no two queens are attacking each other.
That's the specifications of the Aqueen's.
So we first propose to demonstrate what we call the backtracking algorithm.
So it's quite a well-known computer science problem.
So when we talk about representation,
the phenotype of it will be the board configuration and the placement of the queens.
So it is an 8 queen.
So it will be the phenotype.
When you decode it, the phenotype expression of it will be the actual configuration.
What about the genotype?
Permedation of the numbers 1 to 8, that's one way to do it.
For example, here, I have a chromosome of a string of 8.
And the way it encodes is this.
The first queen is in row number 1.
So I put here 1.
The second queen is on row number 3.
So it is 3.
And then the third queen is row number 5.
Row number 5, so the value is 5.
So the allele is 5.
Gen number 3, the allele is 5.
Is this the only way to represent?
Absolutely not.
I'm sure you can think of different ways to represent.
Notice about these numbers.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, they are all different.
They are all different.
These numbers are all different.
We call them the permutation string.
It's a permutation string.
They are all different.
But more importantly, I would like you to know.
When you have permutation string, what are you actually doing in terms of the constraints?
They are all different.
So you guarantee when you have different values in the strings,
what are you guaranteeing?
Or what part of the constraints are you satisfying?
Same row or column.
So how do you satisfy the same so-called, in this representation here?
Let's get a little bit deeper.
How do you satisfy and make sure that each one is only one row?
How do you make sure that each one is only one column?
So the row part is one.
Do you see it's a permutation?
Because they are different rows.
So the values are all different.
So they are all different rows.
What about column?
They only eight positions.
So you have satisfied two sets of constraints.
Then diagonal.
That's what you solve for.
So when you solve, you'll be looking for a permutation string that satisfies the so-called diagonal attacking requirements or constraints.
So again, the node is this is one way or coding it.
I can also use binary string.
Can I know?
You think about it.
My representation could also be binary string.
So if that's the case, we got to think about the fitness function.
How do we measure the fitness?
Again, there are different ways to do it.
Early on in our first lecture, we talked about so-called the number of queens that are not attacking.
That's one way to do it.
Another way to do it is based on penalty.
Penalty of one queen, the number of queens she can check.
So if there's an attacking, you give it a penalty.
So the penalty of a configuration will be the sum of the penalties of all the queens.
So to measure the fitness of the whole configuration, you take the sum of the penalties of all the queens.
Now we talk about fitness.
Fitness means the bigger the value, the better.
You say, oh, this is more fit than this.
So meaning the fitness value is higher.
The context of the meaning of the word fitness, usually that's what it means.
But penalty is to be minimized.
So we want to minimize penalty, but fitness we want to maximize.
Based on the meaning of what fitness means.
Therefore the fitness of a configuration could be the inverse penalty to be maximized.
So you can actually change.
That's definitely not an issue.
You can convert.
If something is maximum, you can convert to minimum.
So how would our mutation look like?
Again, one way to do it is only one way.
You can, you mutate a gene, right?
So you pick a gene to mutate.
For example, I pick gene number three to mutate.
Randomly.
Randomly it occurs like gene number three.
Then what will be the new value?
Again, random.
Let's say seven comes out.
Out of the possibility of one to eight, seven comes out.
So meaning that seven takes the place of five.
So you have seven.
But because when you replace five with seven, it conflicts or you violate that requirement of seven.
So you got to look for the corresponding seven and then flip it back to five.
That's the idea of the thoughts so-called flipping, the values during mutation.
But essentially you can see that the result is basically the exchanging of these two values.
Okay, what about recombination?
Recombination involves two parents.
So you choose two parents, choose two permutation strings.
So some kind of probabilistic random process.
And then we choose a random crossover point.
So what would we mean by random crossover point?
Well, let's say for example we choose crossover point number three.
Or crossover position or site number three.
So this is one, two, three.
So this is a crossover position.
So in crossing over, which involves two parents, we take part of parent one and then part of parent two to generate the offspring.
So here's how it works.
So for example to generate the first offspring, I take part of parent one, one, three, five.
One, three, five.
Let me change this to point.
So this is one, three, five.
So it gets copied here.
So that's one parent one.
And then I generate the other half from parent two.
So from parent two, one, three, five already there.
So I can knock it off.
I knock off one, three, five.
Because it's already here, one, three, five.
And then the remaining of it, I construct it based on parent two.
So from parent two, you can see four, the first one is four.
So four goes to the first position.
And then after that, two goes to the second position.
And then the remaining, then you go back to the beginning, round, one round, and then eight, seven, six.
Quite easy to see.
But the philosophy is what you should, or behind this is what you should recognize.
So this is a recombination.
It involves two parents.
So what you have seen is a simple process of just exchanging strings.
But what is important for you to note is that the offspring inherits property from both the parent one and parent two.
And that's the kind of mechanisms in your GA.
And also to note that whatever operators that you implement has to conform or adhere to the constraints requirement of the permutation strings.
So go back and try to implement these days.
It's very easy.
You can implement all this in Python.
So let's talk about the selection.
As always, we said there are two areas of selection.
One is the parent selection.
So to select the parents to form the parent pool.
So one way to select is randomly pick five parents.
Just random.
And take the best two to undergo crossover.
Out of the five, you do some kind of competition.
Z out of the five, which is the best two.
Now there's the parent selection.
So let's say in this eight-quins problem, this is one way you can do the parent selection.
And then the other one, the survivor selection.
How do we do the replacement?
Well, in this example here, we can do something like that.
Use these rules.
It says when inserting a new child into a population, choose an existing member to replace by it.
So first of all, you decide which member to replace.
Sort the whole population according to fitness.
And then enumerate this list from high to low.
And then choose the first one with fitness lower than the given child.
So you just do replacement until your whole population is replaced.
So all in all, typically in your GA, you have all these parameters or mechanisms.
So I can create a tableau to show you what is in this so-called eight-quins problem solver.
So the representation is a permutation string as what is shown.
And then the recombination, which involves two parents, we call it a cut and cross-fill crossover.
Choose a cutting point and then cross-fill across with both parents.
Recombination probability.
Usually you have a probability like crossover is 60%, crossover or 50%.
Here, let's say we implement 100%.
Meaning so-called crossover recombination will always occur.
Mutation, we do a simple swap.
Mutation probability, 80%.
In the earlier GA, typically the mutation probability about 0.01, very small.
So that doesn't mean that we must conform to that.
It all depends on problems.
So here, our mutation probability, 80%.
And then the parent selection, two out of random five.
Selection, survival selection, replace worst.
Population size, 100.
Number of offspring, two.
Initialization random.
And then termination condition, 10,000 fitness evaluations.
One of the possible way.
So what I'm trying to tell you is in a GA, this is typically the kind of parameters you will set or you will tune.
This is an example to illustrate.
And so typically in a EGA.
So what you will see is that in the early stage, because the fitness of the population tend to be poor.
So on the fitness landscape, you will see that the points are all over the place.
Overall, the fitness is still relatively low.
Then as you evolve, the population, the fitness tends to improve.
From a fitness landscape point of view, the points seems to move towards, converge towards the peak or the optimum.
And then towards the later part, it converges to the close to the optimum.
May not be the optimum, but close to the optimum.
That is typically what the evolutionary process causes the fitness to change.
So I think this is a good example to think about all this process here.
So later on, we do a hand simulation on another problem just to illustrate further.
Let's take a break and then we meet again in 8.25.
Thank you.
Okay, we are back.
So, we have looked at the Aqueen's problem quite clearly.
I think this is a kind of discrete problem.
Okay, discrete problem.
So, I showed you, typically in a GA, these are the kind of parameters that are involved in a GA.
For example, in the Aqueen's problem, we talked about this template of all the parameters, the different methods.
So, the GA you implement may be different.
They have a different set of parameters.
Now, you must remember these are all stochastic algorithms.
So, some of these parameters, there's no hard and fast or absolute rule to say what the values should be.
But that doesn't mean that you totally have no knowledge on what should be the appropriate value.
They are usually what we call the rule of thumb that we follow.
Okay.
For example, if you know in your Aqueen's, say somebody could decide maybe I use binary coding.
Not to say it won't work, but then the question to ask would be, you know, is it the most effective way or efficient way to code the problem?
So, that's the kind of thing that one would have to consider and so on.
So, all these parameters here, if you have implemented your GA, or if you look at so-called some codes that some implementations of GA,
you find all these parameters of the evolutionary algorithm that has been implemented.
So, the representation, how it's represented, depending on the problem and so on, the recombination method, mutation rate and so on.
So, this is quite typical.
So, not to worry if you don't have very solid graphs on this, but after you see a couple of examples, you will develop that intuitive view for what GA is all about.
So, I want to go through another example which is quite different from the Aqueen's.
So, quite often we implement, we optimize a function.
So, henceforth, it's called a function optimization.
So, in typical mathematical optimization, we optimize a function to find the maximum or the minimum.
So, in many real world applications, the model of the behavior, the dynamics, the physics of it, usually can be modeled.
And usually, that model would involve certain kind of complex functions that needs to be optimized.
So, I'm just going to use a simple example.
So, this example is more for illustration on the mechanisms at work in GA.
Now, say for example, you have a function fx equal to x square.
So, this is a function with one variable.
So, needless to say, it is an extremely simple problem.
Now, a typical problem that you will want to solve in your GA, it could involve hundreds or even thousands of variables with many constraints.
Definitely not doable by hand.
But of course, for the sake of illustration, let's just look at this simple problem on optimizing a function.
So, you are trying to maximize fx equal to x square.
And subject to a limit of, let's say, x from certain minimum up to a maximum.
So, therefore, you are trying to find x, you are trying to solve for x.
So, x is the phenotype, the expression of the value.
To bring it to GA, you've got to code it.
So, you have to code it, then you have to think about a representation.
So, you have different options for representation.
One option will be binary.
The other option will be real value, for example.
But let's say we choose binary representation.
So, let's say we choose our chromosome to be 5 bits.
So, 5 bits meaning 2 to the power of 5, so 32.
So, the range of value in your phenotypic space is from 0 to 31.
So, there are different steps involved in the genetic algorithm.
So, for example, you generate the initial population.
So, since it is 5 bits chromosome, you randomly generate a population of 5-bit individuals.
Randomly.
How you generate?
So, each bit you flip a coin, 0 or 1, and then for each chromosome, you do it 5 times and so on.
And then, there are...
Then after that, you go, you compute the fitness.
How do you compute the fitness?
According to the function you're trying to optimize.
So, you're trying to maximize.
So, how do you know how fit the individuals are?
You use the function to evaluate.
And then after that, you decide on reproduction.
So, reproduction means you got to select according to the fitness.
So, we're going to create a mating pool.
And then, crossover.
So, there are some written details here, but later on, we go straight to the table,
and then it's easier to illustrate from the table.
And mutation.
Let's assume there's no mutation.
Or theoretically, there's a mutation, but let's assume mutation is very, very small.
Such that in our small sample size, it doesn't happen.
Just assume.
So, mutation, let's assume mutation probability is 0.001.
For each bit, there's a mutation probability of 0.001.
Now, if we have 20 bits in our population, then the chances of mutation occurring is only 0.02.
So, that means that it is very, very small.
So, in our example, we just assume there's zero mutation or it didn't happen.
So, we do the calculation and go to the table and see how the evolution process progress.
So, assume we have a population of four individuals.
So, we create four strings.
Remember, our coding is five bits, five binary bits.
So, string number one, we randomly generate.
So, we generate our first string, 0.1.1.0.1, number two, 1.1.0.0, and so forth.
So, we have four individuals.
So, now you go back to the figure I showed you earlier on.
After you have the initial population, what must happen?
You're going to do the selection, remember, to get the parents.
In order to do the selection, you must know the fitness.
So, how do you evaluate the fitness?
Well, according to your function.
The function is x squared.
So, the expression of 0.1.1.0.1 is 13.
This is the coding.
The coding is 0.1.1.0.1, the chromosome.
But in the phenotypic space, it is actually 13.
Then, to evaluate the fitness, you use your fitness function, x squared.
So, you have 13 squared, you have 169.
So, same thing for 1.1.0.0.0, which is 24.
So, 24 squared is 576.
So, the whole column four is calculated according to the fitness function.
So, you sum up the total fitness.
You have 1170.
The sum of all this, the column four is 1170.
You take 1170 divided by four, the average fitness is 293.
So, keep in mind we want to maximize.
To optimize in this case means to maximize the function value.
Find x such that fx is maximum.
So, let's take a look at the percentage.
So, in terms of percentage, the relative fitness of the individual.
169 over 1170, 14.4.
576 over 1170, 49.2.
Alright, 64 is 55, 5.5.
361 over 1170 is 30.9.
Alright, so we're going to use the roulette view.
But of course sample size is a bit small.
So, I will guide your thoughts in another way on how the selection works.
So, naturally because of the different fitness, you will see that two is going to be selected.
Most favored, right, because of higher fitness.
So, the first step you do out of this four, right, if it is equal slot,
what is the percentage for each individual?
25%.
If it is equal size slot, 25%.
So, according to here, 49.2 is the highest.
So, string number two get one copy.
Here, 11000.
49.2 is the highest.
So, I minus 25 from 49.2.
I am left with 24.2.
Because I have already given 1, 11000.
So, I am left with 24.2.
So, there is one individual, 11000.
Alright, string number two in the mating pool.
Now, string number two, I compare again.
14.4, 24.2, 5.5, 30.9.
Which is the highest?
30.9.
So, I put 100, string number four, 10011 into the mating pool.
Which is 10011.
So, I have two copies.
So, this 30.9, I already given one.
So, I minus 25 is 5.9.
Alright, now I have two strings, 1100 and 1001.
Now, the third string, I am left with 14.4, 24.2, 5.5, 5.9.
Alright, 24.2 wins.
So, I give string number two another copy.
11000.
Alright.
So, because of its fitness, string number two gets two times in the mating pool.
So, now I have three strings.
Alright, this, this and this.
So, now the fourth string, 14.4, this one is zero because it's two times.
Alright, then this is 5.5 and then this is 5.9.
14.4 wins.
So, I put 011, 01.
That's the first string.
So, as a result of the selection, my mating pool is this.
Alright, so the second string seems to fit us almost two times relative to the other.
So, it gets two copies in the mating pool.
Alright, it has two copies, chances of it chosen for recombination is higher.
So, now we decide on the mating.
So, for example, string one, we decide, okay, random, random, okay.
Randomly, generally, it's like two comes up.
The first string, alright, the parent two will come from 1100.
Okay, so you take these two strings, less.
Alright, so this is number two.
So, meaning, I will take this and this, number two.
Alright, cross over side the position, randomly, randomly generate a number.
So, you generate four.
So, which means to say, you go to the cross over side, let's say, gene number four.
So, one, two, three, four.
So, this is the cross over side.
Here.
Alright, so recombination of these two parents.
So, the new offspring comes from first one, first part comes from here.
Alright, the first four bits come from here.
And then the second part, zero, comes from parent two, which is here.
So, that is your first offspring.
And then you repeat for offspring number two, which involves, right, the second one, two, right,
and then you make with one, so parent one.
So, from this, you generate the new so-called the offspring.
So, from this offspring, according to our diagram, right, so the offspring we also need to evaluate the fitness.
Okay, in order to evaluate the fitness, we take zero, one, one, zero, zero, the phenotypic equivalent of it is 12.
So, 12 squared is 144.
And then, one, one, zero, one is 25.
So, 25 squared is 625.
And then the third one, one, one, zero, one, one, 27.
27 squared is 729.
Alright, and finally, 16 is 256.
So, there you have it.
We just done one generation.
Alright, of course, you need not stop.
You carry on.
So, we sum, sum up all.
So, it's one, seven, five, four, and then compared to the earlier generation, it is one, one, seven, zero.
So, what is clear is that through that one generation, through the selective pressure, and then the recombination, you have seen the overall population improve, right, significantly.
Okay, so of course, in the beginning, it's going to improve quite significantly.
But towards the end, the tail end of it, you're going to see that the improvement is going to be very marginal or gradual.
So, that's how simple GA, so you hear the term simple GA.
Simple GA is like a plain vanilla kind of GA.
It's a very, the basic mechanism is just crossover and then mutation.
And of course, these days GA can be a little bit more complicated or more complex with different mechanisms to enhance the search.
So, this is what, right, so I hope you see the process of simulation through that example of a hand simulation.
So, typically, this is your GA behavior.
So, if I do a plot of the, with time, the value, right, the best value in a population.
So, I think it's not difficult to see, right, how this performance curve come about.
With time, as time goes on, the performance or the goodness, the overall fitness of it will increase.
Initially, the increment will be quite good or quite significant.
Then towards the tail end of it, it's going to stagnate.
So, then the next question is this, you know, of course, you like to run it until you find the best solution.
But, I also like to think that sometimes the best solution is not known or you have no knowledge of what the best solution is.
So, therefore, what you do is that you run it until you cannot improve any better.
So, you run it until you cannot improve any better.
Meaning, you just let it run, carry on, right?
But does that mean that if you leave it theoretically, it should find the answer?
Well, not necessary, right?
Okay?
So, quite often you don't.
Because basically, many of the algorithm will get stuck at a certain point.
It just cannot improve, simply because of the complexity.
So, our long runs are beneficial, well, not necessary.
Well, it all depends on how much time you can afford or the problem that you have.
Or it all depends on your requirement also.
So, sometimes it may be better just to restart it and run again.
Because this is a stochastic algorithm.
Stochastic means that every time you run it, you may get a different answer.
So, theoretically or in principle, basically, whenever you restart it, you are sampling.
Your sampling is quite different.
And the solution that you evolve into may also turn out to be different.
So, the other question would be, you generate the initial population randomly.
Correct?
Random.
No a priori knowledge.
It's just a random.
So, if it's random, chances are that the fitness is going to be very, very low.
No good.
So, you can assume that most of your GA would start at...
So, most of your GA would start at this point here.
Because it's random.
Very low fitness.
So, therefore, it begs the question, okay, would it help if I start off with better population?
Would it help?
Well, again, the answer is maybe.
Not necessary.
See, logic will tell you that if I start off with good ones, I should get better ones.
Right?
Well, the answer is not necessary.
So, which means to say, sometimes you have heuristics.
For example, in your travelling salesman problem, you have the greedy approach on the dystra.
So, that's very quick.
You can find a good solution quite quick.
So, if you have that approach, you could use that to start off the initial population.
Right?
So, the logic is that you start off on good ones.
So, therefore, you take a shorter time to find the best solution.
Sounds very logical, right?
Okay?
Perhaps there's a lot of truth.
It's possible.
Right?
But also, sometimes we don't really know.
Sometimes it depends on the problem.
Right?
So, when you think about it conceptually, right?
Your whole algorithm is a global search algorithm.
Okay?
So, in other words, your population is a sampling.
So, if you use heuristic, chances are you're confining your algorithm to a certain region.
Right?
So, if you confine it to a certain region, the global reach of it may not be as what you
expect it to be.
Right?
So, index sense from a conceptual or theoretical point may not necessarily be better.
Okay?
So, but many problems are solved using smart initialization.
Right?
In many of the design problems, quite often it's in order to circumvent the time that
it takes to solve the problem.
Right?
Many times, quite often we use method to create favorable or advantageous solutions to begin
with and then from there we evolve.
Okay?
So, your whole machine learning paradigm is also can be viewed in that sense.
So, nowadays you do a lot of incremental or transfer learning.
Correct?
So, for example, if you have a neural network, you train from scratch.
Of course, you can train from scratch.
Just start everything from ground zero.
Right?
What surprise you may have, you may take a long time especially if the training set is
very large.
Right?
So, instead of doing that, why don't you adopt an existing model?
And then take it from that strain, because that will be like your initial point.
Right?
So, in a way you have transferred a model to this and then you train it.
So, the concept is also quite similar in this sense.
Okay?
So, the general conclusion is that possibly good.
Right?
So, there are good heuristic or solution methods exist, but we need to be careful and that's
why in many sophisticated GA, there's a concept of hybridization or using different methods
to work together.
Okay?
So, my area of research on genetic algorithm is more on the hybridization aspect of it.
Let's take a look at how we can perceive EA in the context of optimization.
Okay?
So, there are actually many views on GA and over time it has changed.
Over the years, the research on GA.
So, what we want is basically our goal is very simple.
We want a good robust method.
Right?
So, what does it mean good robust method?
It means you can work well over a big, huge set of problem.
Right?
The problem set.
Over a range of problems and instances.
Okay?
So, to put it another way, we want an algorithm that's good for all.
Right?
One size fits all.
Sounds logical, sounds reasonable.
Right?
That's all we want.
Okay?
So, let's see what, let's explore a little bit and see whether we can rethink this ideology
of looking for the blue sky or best algorithm.
So, the book by Goldberg is very commonly referred to text.
Right?
So, according to Goldberg, the typical behavior of your algorithms.
You can look at it this way.
This is your random search.
Right?
Your random search.
Compared to a special custom method.
Right?
So, what this means is your random search is generally weak.
It can work, but performance is generally weak.
So, when you customize your algorithm, it's going to work well, but because it's customized,
it's going to work very well for a class of problems.
So, notice in my plot here, you see the scale of all the problems.
And then on the vertical scale, there's a performance.
Right?
So, your random search compared to your custom or tailor-made method.
Generally, the tailor-made method performs well on a small set of class of problems.
What about GA?
Right?
GA is known to be robust.
So, robust means that it works reasonably well across all the problems.
So, it works reasonably well.
So, without saying, you know, it's quite obvious that it is much better than your random search.
Right?
So, that is how your EA is perceived.
So, that is back in 1989, you know, in the book by Goldberg.
Okay.
Let's take a, explore a different path towards EA.
Right?
What about if you know something about the problem?
If you know something about the problem, meaning you have domain knowledge about the problem.
Right?
Or you have special a priori knowledge about the problem.
Okay?
So, we look into EA's and domain knowledge.
So, the recent trend in the 90s, we have begun to, as GA advanced on more and more people
find that GA is useful in solving many different types of problems.
So, we begin to explore a class of evolutionary algorithm or approaches that incorporate knowledge
into it.
So, another term for it is to incorporate what we call the mimatic.
Right?
If you do a search on mimatic, then you will find the explanation of it has to do with
knowledge.
Okay?
So, we add problem specific knowledge to EA's like the special variation operators
or repair and so on.
Okay?
Now, because we add this information, so the GA is enhanced the performance of it.
So, therefore, we have, if you look in terms of the curve, we have what we call the curve
deformation.
So, the curve is going to be different from our typical EA.
Remember, I showed you the previous, right?
So, your EA like that.
Okay?
So, remember, our EA is going to incorporate domain.
Right?
It's going to be customized, you know?
There's going to be domain knowledge.
So, it should be able to solve problems in a more efficient way.
Right?
So, it's going to deform the curve.
Okay?
So, quite obviously, when you have this kind of knowledge incorporated, it's going to
solve that class of problems better.
Right?
So, this is what we designed it for.
Okay?
So, this curve deformation here, right?
What it's going to suggest is that you're going to come to the realization that if you're
looking for the all-purpose algorithm, right, you'll be very disappointed, right, according
to theory.
Okay?
So, let me explain what I mean by that.
So, in our typical GA, right, a simple GA, we've seen the performance quite good.
Well, EA2, as we incorporate a little bit of information or knowledge to it, well, the
curve deform, right?
It seems to be like it's better than for a small class of problems.
Right?
I wonder, that's a laser.
Okay.
So, EA2.
So, you can see the hum there.
It means that it does well for a certain smaller class of problems or certain class of problems.
Right?
Now, as you go more, right, let's say EA3, you incorporate even more domain knowledge,
so you're going to deform it even more, right?
It does better for that class of problems.
And you can go on and then EA4, right?
Now, I want you to take a look at this set of curves in a very visually intuitive way,
right?
If I say, imagine, this is a set of all problems, all.
Can you take note of the word, all?
All problems, right?
All.
Okay?
So, if you take the area and the curve, right, do you think that it looks like they could
be the same?
All problems, okay?
So, for all the problems, according to the curve, the way we draw it, you know, it looks
like if you look at the area, you know, visually intuitive way, it seems to be everything is
the same, you know, the area, you know, if you plot it big enough, right?
So, that means that, does that mean that all algorithms are the same?
The answer is yes, all right?
In 1997, Wolberg and McCreedy published a paper, what they called the No Free Lunch
Theorem.
No Free Lunch.
I don't have to explain what No Free Lunch means, right?
It's true in our real world, okay?
So, No Free Lunch, right?
What it simply means is that if you take the average across all the problems, all the algorithms
are the same.
Again, I know all the problems, all the algorithms are the same, okay?
Which goes back to my earlier assertion of what I said.
If you want to search, or you're looking for all purpose algorithm, doesn't exist, all
algorithms exist, all algorithms are the same, right?
And another enlightenment that comes out of this is that you want to solve a particular
class of problems, right?
So, it means that you must give that special advantage to it, right?
So, in other words, you understand the problem, right?
Incorporate, give it a special boost in terms of the knowledge about the problem.
So, that's what the theory tells us, right?
So, we call that the No Free Lunch in optimization, right?
It's a well-known theory, okay?
If you talk to people who do optimization, they know what it means, okay?
Or another way, you say, ah, your boss said, give me the algorithm that works for all, right?
Then you can take out this, show him the No Free Lunch, right?
No Free Lunch, all right?
Okay.
So, you understand what is global optimization, right?
So, there are many methods that are not doing global search.
Many heuristic approach are what we call local search, right?
You know, you understand?
Global search means to search, right?
So, some problems are so complex, you know, just the thought of global search may not be practical, okay?
So, global optimization search for finding the best solution, X out of some finite set,
S in your solution set, landscape is finite, right?
For example, the combinatorial optimization problem, right?
In your 1000-city traveling sales room problem, it is finite, but it's very huge, right?
The possible solutions.
So, you have two requests.
One is deterministic approach or your classical optimization approach.
And the one you guarantee to find a solution is mainly a sequential search, right?
So, you search, you follow, you guarantee the solution, okay?
Now, the other is more like a heuristic approach, right?
Heuristic, and these days, of course, we have our method heuristics like a genetic algorithm, okay?
So, heuristic approach belongs to what we call the generate and test, right?
You generate, you test it, see how good it is, and then based on that, you decide your next move and so on, right?
Heuristic approach, okay?
No guarantee.
No guarantee that best solutions found are globally optimal, right?
Okay?
In your deterministic, right?
In theory, you can, but practically, you will never, it can never happen,
especially the problem is complex enough, right?
So, what does that mean?
You will take the view of comparison between the deterministic approach and the heuristic approach.
Basically, your attitude towards problem solving goes like this, right?
The deterministic approach, basically, what you're saying is that, okay, I don't really care if it works.
As long as it converges, right?
It's guaranteed, right?
You follow the exercent path, sequential search, put, it's guaranteed, right?
As compared to like your heuristic, like your GA, right?
So, you must understand, basically, your attitude is like this, I don't care if it converges, right?
As long as it works, that's the attitude you're adopting, right?
That is what GA means, okay?
So, I used to do consulting for some defense organizations, right?
So, quite often when I talk to them, they would ask me, can I guarantee, you know,
because I do work in this area, right?
So, a lot of time, my methods will be more of an evolutionary kind of methods or algorithm.
So, the question always, because it's defense-related, so they say, can you guarantee, right?
Can you guarantee the run time and also, like, within certain level of performance?
And the answer is, no, I cannot 100% guarantee, right?
But maybe, 99.9%.
Now, because there are defense people, they say, wow, in your mind, right?
There's still that possibility of not being able to find a solution, right?
So, what I want to say is that, you know, that is when you do GA, right?
This is basically what it means, okay?
So, you know that it works, right?
You've done it time and time again, you know it works.
But in theory, you know that you cannot prove, absolutely, like, you know, it will converge, right?
Okay, that is a whole so-called scenario or situation.
Okay, let's try and see what it means by neighborhood.
So, many heuristics impose a neighborhood structure on S, okay?
So, there are many heuristics that you know about.
Many of it are hill climbing type of heuristics.
So, basically, when you do hill climbing, you're looking for your neighbor, right?
That has better, something that's close to you.
And as compared to your other methods, EAs are used population.
So, you use multiple stochastic search, right?
And then variation operators with RIT greater than one and stochastic selection.
So, what you can see is that the ideology between EA and heuristics is quite different, right?
In heuristics, it is very sequential, local search methodology, okay?
Now, when you say neighborhood, right?
What do you understand by neighbor?
So, it's close to each other, correct?
Neighborhood, right?
Now, if you think in the context of GA, what are the possibilities of your definition of what neighbor means?
Now, here's what I'm leading to, you know?
Is that concept of neighborhood, does it mean the fitness?
I think you see it not necessary, right?
There's just one possibility or one dimension of what you mean by neighbor.
For example, fitness of 0.71 and 0.711, you can say there's a neighbor based on the fitness, right?
But is it always the case, you know?
It could be that when you convert it to the phenotypic space, it shows a very drastic difference, right?
It could be in terms of the performance of the system that you are trying to design, okay?
So, what I want to say is this, you know?
The concept of neighborhood, right?
In GA, you should not take it in a very narrow perspective, right?
Another example, if you look at two strings, all right?
So, two strings, does that mean that one bit is different?
They are neighbor or based on some hamming distance?
I think quite logically, you will see that, of course, not necessarily the case, right?
It all depends on the so-called problem, okay?
So, when you incorporate neighborhood search in your GA, you must do it with an understanding of what constituted neighborhood search.
In the context of the problem that you are trying to solve, okay?
All right?
So, the next thing we want to cover is on the representation, right?
So, this part, I think probably will be quite straightforward, most parts of it.
We won't go too very deep into it.
But let's just start on the first one.
And then after that, you can go back and rest, okay?
So, go back to the so-called general scheme of EA again, all right?
So, we are talking about representation, so, mutation and recombination.
So, let's talk about representation, all right?
So, the role of representation and variation operators.
So, the common type of representation, your binary, I have quite often used binary as example.
Integer, real value of loading point, and then permutation.
We also talk about permutation.
And finally, the tree, all right?
So, representation is the first step of your GA.
You have a problem to solve.
The first thing you need to talk about is how to represent or code the solution.
All right?
So, this is the first stage of building an EA, and can be the most difficult one, all right?
So, therefore, we have to choose the right representation for the problem.
And also, we need to think about the variation operators.
Depending on the representation, we also have to choose or incorporate suitable variation operators.
Okay?
So, it all depends on the type of representation.
So, you can just think about the TSP problem.
So, if the TSP problem, if you understand what a TSP problem is, there's a traveling salesman problem.
What would make a good representation for the TSP?
I think most of you would have in your mind, oh, the permutation string seems like a good choice, all right?
Because the requirement says that it is to visit each and every city once and only once.
So, you have 10 cities, right?
Each of the cities should occur only once.
So, that could be like a permutation string, all right?
But does that mean that that is the only way?
Obviously not, all right?
But let's think about it the other ways.
Well, first the question is, which is better, all right?
Okay?
And binary representation, all right?
To go from phenotype space to your genotype space, all right?
So, from phenotype space to genotype, it is your, it is the encoding, all right?
And then from the genotype to your phenotype space, there's the decoding.
So, in the encoding part, because it's binary, basically the value set of the allele, the value set, all right, is either 0 or 1, is binary, all right?
The value set of it is from 0 to 1.
So, this L corresponds to the length, all right?
It's a value set over, you could say, like the L dimension.
Okay?
And then mutation, we alter each gene independently with a probability Pm, all right?
Pm is the mutation rate.
So, a good guideline is the probability of mutation rate is between 1 over your population size and 1, the range of 1 over your population size and 1 over the chromosome length, all right?
So, the way you apply mutation goes like this, all right?
So, this is your parent.
So, I go to each gene, I flip the mutation coin.
Mutation coin say, yes, mutate, then I change.
Mutation coin say, no, I don't change, all right?
So, this probability, of course, is specified here depending on the mutation rate.
So, I go according to each gene, all right?
So, if they are 20 here, 20 times I flip the mutation gene, mutation coin to decide whether to mutate or not.
So, mutation can cause wearable effect, all right?
So, we can consider using gray coding, all right?
So, maybe let's go back here.
So, when you have a binary string like that, right?
Let's say your binary string, your binary string.
So, this is one string.
So, let's say your binary string converts to, in your phenotype, is an integer value.
You understand?
Now, my question to you is, if I flip the first bit as compared to the last bit, this is a mutation, right?
Mutation means to flip the bit.
So, if I flip the first bit, the first bit here, compared to the last bit, which one do you think has more effect?
Obviously, the first one, all right?
Because it converts to integer, all right?
So, the first one has more effect.
So, what does that go in terms of what our philosophy of what mutation is?
Small variable change, all right?
Small variable change.
So, in that sense, it has that bias, all right?
This mutation has a bias, you understand?
So, again, this binary string converts to integer, right?
Converts to integer.
So, the first bit is the most significant bit.
Now, in my mutation, I say, each bit, you flip the mutation coin, right?
So, if mutation coin say yes, you flip from 1 to 0.
So, if I take the first bit and the last bit here,
then there's more effect, the first one, all right?
So, the point is that in your mutation also, sometimes, I know if some of you have implemented GA, it works.
But you may not realize that your mutation may not be the so-called mutation, the ideal mutation that you want.
But your algorithm still works, all right?
But perhaps it is better if your mutation does take into account that possibility of so-called causing too much variation.
All right?
Cross-over can be very simple, all right?
So, in the earlier versions of GA, it usually occurred with probability in the old days, it's quite common.
Or in the earlier versions of GA, seems quite common.
It is 60% or 90%, you know?
Okay?
So, you can see how it works through this illustration here, all right?
Very simple process.
Okay?
So, cross-over also, there are many possibilities of cross-over, okay?
Also, take note, the design of a cross-over operation is a possibility of what we call the positional bias or so, all right?
Depending on positional bias, for example, your whole string.
Because your cross-over is such that you decide on the side where you cut, all right?
So, you cut at a certain point.
So, what happens is that no matter how you cut, the first and the last one, those tending towards the end, all right?
Will never be affected.
So, there's no way to actually alter, all right?
So, in your crossing over, because you're trying to create variation, you understand?
So, remember your cross-over recombination, you're trying to create a variation.
But yet, because of positional bias, certain variations cannot be affected or cannot happen, okay?
All right?
You can also explore endpoint crossover, okay?
I think this figure should illustrate what it means, okay?
So, uniform crossover.
And so, let's do one more slide here.
So, you have cross-over and mutation.
There's a long debate which one is better, all right?
Is it necessary?
So, go back to the GA when it was introduced, all right?
The main innovation was the crossing over, all right?
So, obviously, it has done a lot of good, all right?
Because I think from then on, GA became very popular, all right?
So, which one is more important?
Well, it really depends, all right?
It really depends, see?
In my view, all right?
In my view, the end-quins problem, all right?
This is from experience because I do a lot of end-quins problem, up to a thousand queens and so on.
Mutation kind of variation seems to give good results, right?
High mutation.
So, in that sense, I would say mutation seems to be a little bit more important, or seems to be more important than crossover, okay?
But the general consensus is that it really depends, all right?
We should not put ourselves in a position, oh, definitely crossover is better or mutation is better, all right?
So, both has its role, okay?
But having said that, I think if you only have one, all right?
If you only have one mutation, would be the one, okay?
Recombination alone will not work.
You can prove to yourself just with mutationary kind of operation in your end-quins, it should work, all right?
But with recombination, just selection and then recombination, it won't work, all right?
Okay?
So, I'm dragging a little bit, but anyway, let's call this, let's make it a night, and then we can go back and rest, all right?
See you next week.
Thank you.