.
Because everyone begins to look for 10.
OK.
So today, actually, we are first thing is a lecture,
actually, about the evaluation of the clustering.
And then, actually, we have a reviewer.
We will review what we have learned in the main content
running this machine learning part.
And finally, I think in the last one hour,
actually, we have a Q&A session.
OK.
We use Zoom to type your question.
I think when we started the super hard learning,
we have started different kind of classifier.
And then, of course, actually, this classification,
classifier are learned from the label training data.
Right?
So after we have learned the model,
and, of course, actually, we need to evaluate the performance
of the model.
OK.
So normally, we just need to use, actually,
the testing data.
Right?
We can use the learning model to predict
the class label for testing data.
OK.
And then we compare the prediction with the ground truth
of the testing data.
And then, based on this, actually,
we can have a different matrix to evaluate
the performance of the classifier, such as error rate, accuracy,
recall, precision, or the combination recall, precision,
that is the F score.
OK.
So we can, I think, in general, the evolution
of the super hard learning is simple.
Right?
Because we have a ground truth.
And we can compare the prediction model with a ground truth.
OK.
So for unsupervised learning, we know
classroom or unsupervised learning is based on un-labeled data.
We don't have a ground truth.
OK.
Then how to evaluate the performance of unsupervised learning,
in particular, that class.
And I read the evaluation for unsupervised learning.
I think it's much more challenging than the evaluation
of super hard learning, simply because we
don't have the ground truth.
OK.
You can imagine, right?
And the data is a high domino space in the high domino.
You cannot visualize the data distribution.
And you don't have a ground truth.
So I think it's really challenging to evaluate the performance.
OK.
But basically, the evaluation of the classroom
is based on the principle of the classroom.
And you remember what is called a classroom.
A classroom is just a group of data, right?
Group of data.
We want to find the natural groups underlying the data.
So classroom is a natural grouping.
And when we talk about this natural group concept,
we have two aspects, you remember, right?
One is that within the cluster, actually,
the samples show strong similarities.
So this is one aspect of the natural grouping.
Another aspect is that between clusters,
there should be strong dissimilarities or separations
between clusters.
OK.
So these are the two aspects of the natural grouping.
And actually, in the evaluation of the classroom,
actually, we will follow these two.
We will actually, necessarily, we
will have different metrics or index
to evaluate the performance of the classroom.
But the basic idea, I think, still
follows these two aspects about the natural grouping
of the classroom.
Within cluster similarity, between cluster dissimilarities.
But just knowing the issue last thing,
how to measure the within cluster similarity,
how to measure the between cluster dissimilarity.
And we can have different methods to evaluate.
And based on these different ideas,
then we can have different metrics or index
for the classroom evaluation.
OK.
So here, we assume, actually, totally, we have n samples.
Now, in super learning, we have the training data, validation
data, or testing data, right?
But for unsupervised learning, we don't have this concept.
We just have a data.
You can call it the training data or what?
OK.
We just have the data.
We don't have testing.
We don't have any validations.
OK.
We just have the data.
As you may see, there are n samples, x1, x2, and xn.
And so these samples have been partitioned into,
or assigned to n, actually, or to k sub, this is the subset.
d1, d2, dk.
And each of these subsets correspond to one cluster.
One cluster is just a group, right?
It corresponds to one group or one cluster.
And here, actually, we see they are disjoint, right?
Disjoint, that means, actually, between clusters,
there are no relapses.
OK.
Of course, they're not the all-fourth classroom, actually.
In some classroom methods, one method is called C-means,
fuzzy C-means classroom, actually.
And in that method, actually, each sample has a certain probability
belonging to one of the clusters.
OK.
So, but actually, we did not talk about that, actually,
and introduce that method.
So in all the methods introduced in this course, actually,
in that, actually, the older known clusters, actually,
are disjoint.
OK.
So we have k1, d1, d2, dk, right?
And each of these d correspond to one cluster.
So totally, we have k clusters or k groups.
OK.
And also, actually, we know for each of the groups,
we have the number of samples, n1, n2, and nk.
OK.
So these are the following, actually,
the metrics or the index we are going to use for the evaluation,
actually.
So I think these have different meanings, like different tree.
But actually, the older tree tried to actually measure the two
aspects of the cluster, actually, that natural group,
but within cluster similarity and between cluster,
actually, no, disimilarities, between cluster, right?
We don't have the cluster cluster,
but within cluster, between clusters.
OK.
Actually, yesterday, actually, I sent you an email, right,
about the teaching material of this part, actually.
I probably, I think, I made this a change, actually.
Last semester, probably, they copied the material from a
very old, actually, like last, I think last year, not last
semester, last year, actually, photo.
OK.
And that's why, actually, I emailed you about the change,
right?
We need to update of the lecture notes.
OK.
And so you need to use a new lecture notes.
And the first method we are going to introduce is called,
actually, silhouette coefficient.
OK.
And in this method, so basically, actually,
it measures these two things, actually,
one is called a coherent.
A coherent, here, actually, just how close a sample is
to other samples in own cluster.
So this, basically, this coherent is kind of metric
for the within cluster similarity.
How close, right?
How close?
Actually, because, actually, we know each sample is
represented by a vector.
And in the official space, we know each vector is just a
point, right, a data point.
OK.
So the distance, actually, between, actually,
the samples show how, actually, similar to samples are,
right?
So if they are close, how close it is to other samples
within the same cluster.
That means how similar, actually, the sample is,
how simple is similar to other samples within the same cluster.
So here, this, actually, silhouette coefficient,
they call this a coherent.
But the coherent, here, basically,
is about the within cluster similarity.
OK.
So this is one, actually, aspect.
Then another aspect, actually, is the separation.
So how far away, how far a sample is from sample
in other clusters.
OK.
So one sample to sample in other clusters.
So this, actually, is called a separation.
Separation.
How far, right?
How far is, how about the feature space?
OK.
And then the geometric view, right?
Actually, the distance, how far away they are,
how close, how similar the samples are.
OK.
So these, actually, the two know in the silhouette
coefficient, and they try to evaluate these two aspects,
coherent and separation.
Basically, they are trying to evaluate the within cluster
similarity and the between cluster dissimilarities.
OK.
And so how the tree is here in the silhouette coefficient
method.
Each sample, for each sample, now we can calculate
the so-called silhouette coefficient.
OK.
So this is the definition of the silhouette coefficient.
So actually, here, actually, it is a ratio, right?
Bi minus ai divided by maximum ai bi.
OK.
So what is ai?
What is bi?
And actually, if I see, if I just say, for the silhouette
coefficient, the larger the better.
The larger the better.
OK.
So do we think, what is bi?
If we can get, what is bi?
What is ai?
The larger the better.
Normally, we see, for the separation, right, the larger
the better.
And so for the coherent, for that one, the smaller the better.
I mean, if you look at the distance, right, the distance,
the larger the better.
So that means, actually, the bi here, basically, is about
the distance from one sample to other sample in other
clusters.
OK.
And ai basically should be the distance from the sample to
the other samples within the cluster.
So this difference, the larger the better.
So this is the definition of ai and bi.
OK.
So ai, we look at ai.
So for the sample, for sample ai, sample xi, and we can
take the distance to all other samples within the same cluster.
So the cluster here is p, right, cluster p, because actually
the sample j xi, it's a, both belong to the cluster p, right,
dp.
OK.
dp is the sample in cluster p.
So this actually, for each of the sample, for sample xi,
we calculate the distance to all other samples within the same
cluster, within the same cluster, right.
Then we take the average, the take the average.
OK.
Totally, and then we have an MP sample, right, we have an MP
sample for this cluster p.
OK.
So totally, here we calculate MP minus one distance.
So this is the average distance from sample xi to other
samples within the same cluster.
So this is the ai, the ai.
OK.
Ai is the, you know, average of the distance, OK, from one
sample xi to all other samples within the same cluster.
So this is the ai.
OK.
So we assume all the samples, right, other samples within the
same cluster.
OK.
And dij is just the distance between xi and the xj.
And then we look at what is bi?
Bi, look at this bi, right.
OK.
And actually, you know, so this is the sample, right.
So bi actually, just now we talked about, you know, bi should
reflect actually the separation, right, the separation.
The sample, distance from the sample xi to other samples, to
sample in other clusters.
OK.
So here, now we have our favorite sample, actually xj,
xi, right, xj, and the, q, p not equal to q.
And then we have to all samples not belonging to, you know,
to the cluster p.
OK.
Then we calculate the distance.
Then here is a minimum distance, minimum distance.
OK.
So how to, you know, understand this distance.
If you remember, we recall actually the hierarchical
cluster, and you remember, you know, we know in the
agglomerative algorithm, we start from the bottom, right,
the bottom arm method.
We gradually merge the clusters.
OK.
So normally, when we calculate the similarity between two
clusters, for example, right, between two clusters.
OK.
And how to evaluate?
For each of the clusters, we have some sample, right,
some sample.
For example, for one sample, you know, we have so many
distance, so many samples in other clusters, right.
So which distance should be used as a separation between
one sample to others?
Actually, you remember, we have a different linkage, right.
Complete linkage, fetids, you know, actually, you know,
the single linkage, every linkage.
OK.
Every linkage, you remember, just, you know, like,
every distance, right, and then complete linkage,
like the fetids samples, and then single linkage,
the, you know, the nearest samples, right.
So actually, we have different linkage.
So all the known are reasonable, right, just different ways
to evaluate the distance, similarity or distance between
two clusters, and each cluster has a multiple sample.
So here, now, this is a specific idea, right here,
similar idea.
So for a sample XI, we calculate distance for all other
samples in other clusters.
So which distance should be used as the separation,
should be used as distance between this sample to other
clusters?
So here, they use the minimum distance.
This bi is the minimum distance.
Actually, this minimum distance could be,
could be something like, you know, this is a worst-case
estimation for the similarity between one sample and
sample, and the other sample in other cluster,
worst-case estimation.
Because these are minimum value, right, minimum value.
Some of the samples are very far away from this,
very far away from this sample, right.
But some of the samples, actually, they use a
closest sample distance as the, you know,
the value, actually, for the separation.
So this is the minimum, right, makes minimum
difference between the sample and the sample.
So this is the worst-case, worst-case,
actually, estimation.
So this is the best idea for the bi.
Okay.
So we use the minimum distance.
Worst-case.
Okay.
I think this is actually, you know, like,
very reasonable, right.
Even in the super-linear, if you remember,
actually, you know, we have like, you know,
we try to maximize actually the margin of separation.
So what is defined as a margin of separation?
Actually, it is defined as distance between
two closest samples in the two classes, right.
So this distance is used as distance, you know,
between the two classes, right.
But some, actually, in others, like,
like in the, in the Fisher-Linian distance,
Fisher-Linian distance analysis,
when we try to, you know, evaluate the distance
between two classes, we use the distance
between the two mean vectors, two mean vectors, right.
So that's in between the mean vectors.
Normally, the distance is greater than the distance
between two nearest samples.
Okay.
So here are just the different ways
to evaluate the distance.
Okay.
So different considerations.
All are actually, are, are, are right, right.
All are correct in the method to evaluate the performance.
Okay.
So here to evaluate the separation.
But here they use a worst case to represent,
actually, the distance between one sample
with a sample in other classes,
actually, as a measure of the separation.
Okay.
For coherent, they use the, actually, the,
they use the, you know, the average.
And for the separation, they use a worst case.
Okay.
That's nearest, actually.
The distance between the nearest sample
in other classes.
Okay.
So we get a Bi.
And then we combine this Bi and Ai,
actually, you know, to form the so-called
S-celloid coefficient.
So Bi minus Ai.
Okay.
Then divided by the maximum of the two.
So again, this is a very conservative estimation
of the celloid coefficient, right.
Actually, Bi minus Ai, then divided by the maximum value.
Very conservative estimation, right.
Very conservative.
They don't use Bi, they don't use Ai,
they use the maximum of these two.
Then you murdered the maximum.
That means that the value should be,
tend to become smaller, right.
So again, this is kind of conservative estimation.
Actually, for the, actually, for the two, right,
combined two.
Okay.
So Bi minus Ai, divided by the maximum Ai and Bi.
So later we will see, actually,
in other total method for the evaluation of the classroom,
then they adopt different thinking,
different logic, okay, to, to measure similarities
within cluster or dissimilarity between clusters.
But here in the celloid coefficient,
they use this.
And actually, I think in the research, right,
you never, actually, I talk about the celloid coefficient.
We always, we can find some variants.
I know from this.
Some actually, even though they, the distance from one cluster
to another, some to other cluster,
they can also use the every distance.
There are some variants, right, they can use distance, right.
But here we introduce this method.
Okay.
Some they use the average.
They don't use the worst case.
Okay.
So, okay.
So this is the celloid coefficient.
For every training sample, for, not training,
for every sample, for every sample,
actually we can calculate celloid coefficient.
Okay.
So finally, actually we can take the average
of the celloid coefficient.
Take the average.
Submission for, actually all samples,
because each sample we can calculate celloid coefficient, right.
And then we, after we calculate celloid coefficient
for every sample, then we take the average.
So these are, you know, we'll be used actually, you know,
to indicate actually the goodness of the cluster result.
And the value of actually celloid coefficient
is in the range from minus one to one.
Could be negative.
Could be negative, right.
For very bad actually cluster result,
maybe the BI is less than AI, right.
BI is less than AI, that's possible, right.
So the NBI money could be, you know,
could be, you know, negative value, right.
So it is actually the celloid coefficient.
And so normally the higher celloid coefficient
and the indicate that the samples are well-clustered.
So the higher, the better, right.
The higher the better.
Okay.
So this is the celloid coefficient.
You need to understand, right, this is the meaning, right.
For each training sample, we can calculate celloid coefficient.
And this celloid coefficient evaluates the cluster performance
based on two aspects, co-coherent and the separation.
Coherent is, you know, for a sample,
is just every distance to all samples within the cluster, right.
So that is AI.
And then BI, actually we use the worst case, right.
So the distance to the nearest samples in other clusters.
Okay.
So finally we combine the two, right.
So BI minus AI, okay.
Because we hope that the known BI, the larger the better.
AI, the smaller the better, right.
So BI minus AI, you know, AI minus BI, right.
So BI minus AI, okay.
Sometimes we hope when one is the larger the better,
another smaller the better, right.
Then we use the ratio, sometimes we use the ratio, right.
In the, for example, in the future linear distance analysis,
we hope that within class similarity, right.
To the distance represent the smaller the better.
And between class distance, the larger the better.
Then we use the ratio, right.
So we have to finish at the ratio, okay.
But here they use the difference between the two.
BI, the larger the better.
AI, the smaller the better, right.
BI minus AI.
Sometimes we use the division, we use the ratio.
Okay, so different ways, okay.
So different ways.
All right, okay.
Okay, so here actually we have a little one example.
And certainly, you know, from the distribution of the data,
we can see that there are three clusters, right.
We can assign the sample to three clusters.
Actually, indeed, actually, when I create the data,
actually I use the three Gaussian functions.
And actually to create the data points.
And so certainly there are three clusters, okay.
So that's actually, of course, in practice,
normally we don't know, right, how many classes
are underlying the data, right.
Even if, for example, you use the k-means clustering,
and we don't know the k-value, right.
And previously we have now used this,
now able method, able method to decide the cluster, right.
Now suitable number of clusters.
And so here actually, now we can also use
the silhouette coefficient to determine
the suitable number of clusters.
Okay, for example, if we don't know, right.
Okay, then you can set the number of clusters to two.
To two, then you can perform a clustering,
you know, k-means clustering, for example.
And then you can finally use the silhouette coefficient
to evaluate the performance.
Then you can calculate the h-e-value.
Corresponding to the scenario when k equals two, right.
Then you can set the k to three.
Then you again perform k-means clustering.
You can get the result.
And then again you can use the silhouette coefficient
to evaluate the performance.
Okay, then you set it in the k to four to five.
Okay, so this is the result.
This is the result.
And the first actually, the horizontal axis
actually are the number of clusters.
And the vertical axis actually shows the silhouette coefficient.
So you see actually when the number of clusters
is set to three, set to three, right.
And then this h-e-value,
silhouette coefficient value is the maximum.
So that is the peak value here, right.
The peak value.
Okay, so the three is the better.
And you can use the WCSS, right.
Within cluster sum of squares.
Okay, and actually the more cluster we use, right.
The more cluster we use.
And then the rule of the WCSS, right.
It's always monotonically decreasing.
And so we use the, actually, you know,
the Able method to determine the suitable number of clusters.
But if we use the silhouette coefficient
to determine the suitable number of clusters,
and then actually we can use this peak value, right.
We can use the peak value.
The peak value is a trip when the number of clusters is three.
Okay, then, or probably you can just actually
three is the suitable number of clusters.
Okay, so this is the silhouette coefficient.
Okay, I hope actually you understand
actually the meaning of the silhouette coefficient.
You interpret.
Not just a formula, right.
I never ask you to remember the formula.
But actually you need to, actually, you understand this, right.
You understand.
Okay.
Okay, so next I just call that down index,
down index, and down index actually
quantifies the compactness and the variance of cluster.
Compactness, compact, right.
It's still actually then talked about
the within cluster similarity, compactness.
But it's just a different word, right.
The wording different.
But actually what they want to actually evaluate the same thing.
Okay, compactness is just within cluster, right.
Within cluster similarities.
And then they use the, you know,
and the variance of the cluster.
Variance, here they mean between clusters.
Okay, then let's look at how they evaluate these actually
compactness.
How they evaluate these actually, you know,
variance.
Okay.
So here they define, you know,
data P.
Okay.
And so actually a cluster is considered compact.
Compact normally the spread, the dispersion is small, right.
It's small, compact.
If spread very big, actually they're not actually compact.
Small, right.
Very tight.
Okay.
Compact.
And a cluster can see the compact.
If there is small variance between sample of the cluster.
Small variance, right.
Small variance.
Within the cluster.
Remember within the cluster.
Okay.
So how to define this, okay.
So here actually, you know, we have two samples,
after two samples, right.
Actually, you know, for all the samples,
and within actually the same cluster P,
we can have many pairs, right.
Every sample to other samples, right.
We can form many pairs.
Okay.
So here, you know, there are one pair of the data.
The sample within the same cluster.
Okay.
So X, R, X, J.
And of course actually we can calculate the distance,
pair-wise distance.
Okay.
And then actually, so what distance could be used,
actually, you know, to represent the companions of the cluster.
Okay.
I think very naturally, I think before,
we see probably for each cluster,
you know, we can have a centroid, right.
And then we can calculate the distance to the centroid
to determine the companions.
Yes, actually some of the matter later,
we will see you adopt these ideas.
But here, they use the distance between two fuzzies,
the fuzzies, you know, samples.
This distance, actually, as a measure
for the compactness of the cluster.
So again, this is the worst case, right.
Worst case estimation for the companions.
Because actually some of the samples could be very close, right.
Some samples could be very far.
Actually, they use the fuzzies distance.
The fuzzies, the distance between two fuzzies samples
actually represent the compactness of the cluster.
This is a delta P.
So this is also a worst case, right.
Worst case estimation about the compactness of the cluster.
They don't use the Irish.
They don't use the smooth, the best one, right.
So these are no pessimistic, pessimistic estimation.
No optimal, optimistic, right.
Pessimistic estimation.
Very conservative estimation.
Worst case estimation about the compactness of the cluster.
Maximum, right, maximum.
Okay.
And so these are delta P, right.
So these are actually delta P is used,
is a measure for the compactness of the cluster.
So for every cluster, we can have this,
this measure, right.
We can carry the pair of distance
for all sample within cluster.
Then we find the maximum weight.
Actually, that is just a distance between
two fuzzies samples within the cluster.
Okay.
So then, next up, we look at the separation, right.
Actually, the separation.
And the two clusters can be considered as well separated
if the cluster are far apart, right.
Of course, we already have this concept, right.
In super high learning, we see,
well, under the concept of class, right.
If the sample in two classes are far away, right.
They are well separated.
Then the classification is easy.
So well separated, they are far away from each other.
So here, actually, we can also calculate the distance, right.
So here, actually, we have two clusters,
P and Q, right, P and Q.
P and Q.
And of course, actually, for all samples
from one cluster to all sample in another cluster,
we can calculate the pairwise distance, right.
Pairwise distance.
So there are so many pairs, right.
So there are so many values.
So which value is used to represent, actually,
the separation between the two clusters.
We use the minimum.
Worst case.
If you compare this with the hierarchical cluster, right.
We compare, we calculate the distance between two clusters.
Each cluster has multiple samples.
How to calculate the distance between two clusters.
So these correspond to the single linkage.
Single linkage, right.
The sample, the closed samples in the two clusters, right.
Closed.
That is single linkage, right.
Now we are talking about separation, the larger the better.
But now they take the, with the smallest value, right.
So we see this is a worst case.
Worst case.
When we talk about the compactness, right.
The smaller the better.
But they take the maximum value.
So I see this is a worst case.
Right.
So for the, you know, within cluster compactness,
they use the worst case.
And for the separation between cluster,
they again, they use the worst case.
Right.
Worst case, right.
Because the larger the better.
But they use the smaller, the smallest value,
the minimum value.
Okay.
So these are not correspond to the, like, a single linkage, right.
They are not distant between two clusters.
There are so many samples in the two clusters.
So actually, so here are closed samples.
These are correspond to a single linkage.
Right.
Single linkage.
Okay.
And so these are DEPQ.
And these are the separation, the distance between two clusters.
Okay.
So now we have these two values, right.
Two values.
Okay.
We need to combine, right.
Combine all these, actually.
DEP, actually, you know, we assume,
we have multiple clusters, right.
You know, normally, you know, many, right.
So pairwise, as you know, we can calculate the D,
the separation, DEPQ, right.
And the larger the better.
Right.
But now we use, actually, you know, single linkage.
We take the minimum value.
These are worst estimation between two clusters.
But finally, when we combine all of them together, right,
we again, we use a minimum value.
Again, this is another round of, you know,
worst case estimation.
Worst case.
Okay.
Some of the clusters maybe are well separated, right.
But some of the clusters are not well separated.
But they use the worst case.
So it's a minimum, minimum.
And when we talk about, you know, for each cluster,
you know, actually, you know, based on the distance, right,
we use the worst case estimation to estimate, you know,
the company of each cluster.
But finally, when we combine all of them, right,
we use the worst case.
Maximum.
Maximum data P, right, among all data P.
Because these values should be, you know, smaller the better, right.
They use the largest value.
I mean, these are worst case.
Okay.
So finally, combine these between class separation
and also the within class, actually,
cluster, no compactness, right.
They finally calculate one single, actually, you know,
value, right, that the, the, the dine index, D i.
Okay.
So all worst case estimation, right, worst case.
So a few rounder.
Within, for each cluster, they use the worst case.
Okay.
Between class and worst case.
So they combine together, right,
for the between class separation, you use the worst case.
For the no, within class, within class compactness, right,
because each one has their own, right.
Some of them may be very compact, but some are not.
But they use the worst case.
Okay.
So finally, actually, they calculate the d i.
Actually, the higher the dine index, the better, right,
because the separation, separation over, you know,
the compactness.
So sometimes, you can see, we use the ratio, right,
we use the ratio.
Sometimes we use one value minus another value, right.
Actually, in the, in the, in the,
I see it as a coefficient with a separation minus,
actually, the cohesion, right.
So the larger the better.
But now they use, you know, the separation over the,
over them, the ratio of over the cohesion,
something like that, compactness, right.
So, so, so they know the larger the better.
Okay.
Sometimes we use the ratio, sometimes we want to subtract
another bit.
Okay.
So I think in research, sometimes we all use these two,
two different ways, right.
If we want to emphasize, we want to look something,
one variable, the larger the better,
another smaller the better.
Sometimes we combine them, right.
Actually, using the ratio.
Okay.
And sometimes we use one, subtract another one.
So this is the dine index,
the larger the better.
Okay.
And so this actually, actually shows, actually,
you know, the example, right, the example,
and we have three clusters, and we use the K-means
cluster to, to cluster, to group the data.
And we set the K to different value,
to two, to three, to four, to five.
And finally, actually, you know,
get the corresponding dine index, right.
Finally, actually, we plot this.
And you can see, actually, when the cluster is number,
set to three, right, then the, the,
the dine index is the maximum, the p value.
Okay.
So again, from here, actually, we can use this dine index
to determine a suitable number of care, right,
if we use the K-means cluster.
Okay.
And not just for K-means cluster,
but even for, for others, right, actually, like,
I remember, I think we have the, like,
another one, it's a distribution-based method, right,
distribution-based method.
We also need to determine a number, right.
I showed you a number of, you know,
in a Gaussian-Misterial model.
We need to determine how many Gaussian components
need to be included in this Gaussian-Misterial model.
So this is also a hyper parameter.
So from here, this is not,
this is not, the number is also not the same
as the number of clusters, right.
So we can also use this, actually,
on the dine index to determine
the suitable number of clusters.
Okay.
So that would be the peak value.
Next, that's why it's called Davis-Boulding,
actually, index, actually, the dB index.
Okay.
So again, here, you can just see different ideas, right.
Here again, there are things they need to know,
emphasize the natural group in the 2S-A, okay.
Within class similarity, between class difference
or separation.
But just, you know, there are different ways
to evaluate the within class similarity
and also different ways to measure the
between class, actually, you know, separations, okay.
Okay.
So here, they have the idea,
actually, this is a dB-Dine index.
Evaluate the goodness of a cluster
result based on the within class dispersion.
Spread.
Like compactness, right, this is the same.
Okay.
See, actually, then and also the between class separation.
So that, again, the two parts,
the two aspects of the natural group here,
within class similarity, between class difference
or separation, okay.
But how to measure the within class dispersion, right.
Actually, previously, we can use the average distance.
Oh, actually, now we can use the worst case, right.
Here, in this method, how the method is.
And actually, for this, in this method,
within class similarity, right,
actually, they use the distance to the centroid.
For all the samples, you know,
within the class DI, actually,
they can calculate the centroid, right.
These are just the mean vector, the average,
the mean vector.
This is also called the centroid or class centers.
And then from, for each of the samples,
we calculate the distance.
We calculate the distance, right,
to the centroid, okay.
So finally, we take the, you know,
this is the square distance, right.
And then, summation for all the samples,
each of the samples, we have one distance to the centroid.
For all the samples, and I, okay,
then we have, you know, the average square distance.
Then we get square roots.
So this is the dispersion, okay.
So within class, actually, you know, the dispersion.
So this is used, you know, as a evaluation, right,
for the compactness, actually,
all the within class similarity.
So they have a centroid,
and then they take, look at the distance to the centroid.
Okay, so this is one aspect
for the within class similarity.
So for this data, right,
actually, the smaller the better, right.
You can imagine that there is centroid.
If all the samples are very close to the centroid,
then the distance is very small, right.
Then the tree, this is data R, right.
Here they call dispersion also, very small.
Okay, if the spread of the cluster, right, is big,
then the distance is big.
Okay.
Okay, so this is actually within cluster.
So next, we should look at the between cluster, right.
So this is between cluster, this similarity,
this similarity or separation, okay.
And so then the similarity between two clusters, okay,
is defined as this, the similarity between two.
Actually, before that, we see the separation
between two clusters, the R, D, J,
are defined as the distance between two centroid.
Okay, these are very natural, right.
We look at the, in the official linear dish analysis,
we look at the distance between two clusters, right.
Actually, we, between two clusters,
we use the distance between two centroid.
Here they use this concept, right.
That is the between cluster,
between cluster separation actually is measured
by the distance between the two centroid
of the two clusters.
So this is using the D, I, J to denote actually
the distance between the two centroid, M, I and M, J.
Okay, so now, this is a separation.
Next, we need to combine the separation and dispersion, right,
into one single metric.
So that is data I, data J, D, I, D, J.
If you look at this, just like in the inverse of the
facial ratio, right.
Facial ratio, we look at the distance between two cluster,
these are the classes, right.
So that's D, I, J, divided by the sigma I or sigma J.
All we use is the distance squared,
divided by the sigma I squared, sigma J squared, right.
So this is similar.
This case, but for the, for the, for the,
for the facial ratio, right.
So now they use this kind of similarity.
That I, that J, D, I, D, J.
But you can use it in inverse, right.
They just use it in this.
But for us, if we want to evaluate,
actually we can use it in inverse of this, right.
Like D, I, J, divided by data I,
that J, just like facial ratio, the larger the better.
But here for this S, I, J, here the smaller the better, right.
Because the compactness, right,
the D, I, that J should be small.
And the big, you know, between cluster separation,
the D, I, J should be the larger the better, right.
So the ratio should be the smaller the better.
So this is defined as a similarity
between between two, between two clusters.
Okay.
Similarity between two clusters.
So these are clusters, S, I, S, J, right.
So now actually we, of course we have many clusters, cluster, right.
Actually we need to calculate a pair-wise,
you know, similarities,
based on this.
Okay.
And finally, we take the maximum.
S, I, I, J, right.
The smaller the better.
But they take the maximum.
So it's also a worst case estimation.
S, I, J, right.
Pair-wise, some could be big, some could be small, right.
And the smaller the better.
But they use the biggest value.
The worst case, maximum.
Okay.
So the similarity of the most similar cluster to cluster D, I, right.
So cluster D, I, for you to know,
kind of have a know, calculate the S, I, one S, I,
not all other cluster for class S, I, right.
But the, some could be known, actually this value could be, you know,
big, some are small, but they use the big, maximum value.
So this maximum value indicates actually the similarity of class S, I,
to other clusters.
So this S, I.
Worst case.
Okay.
So this is just for S, I.
Then for each of the cluster, we can calculate one, right.
We can calculate one similarity to other clusters.
Okay.
So finally, we need to actually take the average.
So finally the last step to take the average.
S, I, J is a class I to class J, right, to all other clusters.
So finally we need to have one value, right, as a measure of the similarity
of one cluster with others.
So this is S, I, the maximum, the worst case.
Okay.
So finally, we take the average.
This is the DB, actually index.
And from here, we know that DB, for the DB index,
actually the smaller the better, smaller the better.
Actually, you know, for S, actually, you can also modify this, right.
You can modify this.
For example, for S, I, J, I can use the inverse.
D, I, J divided by sigma, I, M plus sigma, J, right.
Just like fish and fish, the larger the better, right.
And then later, actually, I also take the worst case.
S, I, J, here I take the minimum S, I, J.
And finally, take the average, right.
You can also choose the inverse.
But in the original index, they use this.
Okay, the smaller the better.
Okay.
Then we have this, actually, the DB index underline,
as you correspond to different key, key values.
Okay.
So a number of clusters.
Set to two, to two, three, to four, to five, actually,
you can see when this set to three, the value is a minimum.
It's a minimum.
Okay.
Again, this DB index can be used, actually, you know,
to determine the suitable number of care, right.
Okay.
So this is the DB index.
So let's look at another index,
Kalinsky-Harabas index, okay, the C-H-H index.
Again, the two concepts.
Okay.
You just look at how they evaluate these two.
Then, cohesion, right, separation, the two, right.
Okay.
So next we look at how they measure the cohesion.
Actually, for each of the clusters, we have a same choice, right.
We have a same choice.
And then, actually, the summation for all samples, right,
the distance.
This is the same choice.
So this is, similarly to the, you know,
the dispersion measurement, right, dispersion.
Okay.
And the dispersion just actually is,
here is a square distance.
And also, you know, dispersion, you know,
is, you know, the average distance, right, average.
But here, they just, the summation of all the distance
to the same choice, square distance.
And this is the CI.
And this CI indicates the cohesion of sample within the cluster.
This value, the smaller the better, right.
Because, you know, the similarity in versatility
proportion to the distance, right.
So the smaller the distance, the more similar, right.
So here, actually, for the CI, coherent,
it's smaller the better.
Okay.
So these are, for the coherent, right,
the within cluster, they use this metric to evaluate,
to measure.
Okay.
We have seen others, right.
So this is also one way.
And then, how about the between cluster?
Between cluster.
Between cluster, here, they don't do the pairwise.
They don't do the pairwise similarities or distance.
They don't use this.
Okay.
Here, they define a global, global, you know,
centroid.
For all samples, right, for all samples,
we, we, we carry a global centroid.
And then, from, from each of the cluster center
and to the global centroid,
we can have a square distance.
So this is different SI.
SI.
And then, you should remember,
to either multiple, you know,
feature linear disk analysis,
when we calculate the, you know,
between class, between class distance, right.
And then, we don't use the pairwise.
Actually, we also calculate the same global centroid,
global mean vector.
And then, from each of the class,
mean or centroid or mean vector,
we can calculate the distance to this global centroid.
So here, the base, the, the similar idea.
Here, just, we don't have the concept of a cluster.
We have the concept of a cluster.
Okay.
So this is the, for each of the cluster,
from the centroid to the global centroid,
we can calculate a square distance, SI.
Of course, for this SI,
the larger the better, the larger the better.
And for this SI, the smaller the better, right.
Finally, we need to combine the two, right,
combine the two.
Okay.
So this is a global centroid.
This is M.
And finally, we need to combine the two.
And combine the two here, actually,
in the LSI calculation, right,
we just have a few values, few values, right.
But here, we have many values, right.
So we have a number of the sample to the,
to the, to the, to the centroid, we have one value, right.
So, you know, to balance the size of the numerator and denominator, right.
So here, they multiply the number of samples.
And I, SI, then divided by the summation of CI.
So this is a CAH index.
Okay.
So SI is a between class separation, the larger the better.
And CI, the cohesion within class similarity, right.
The smaller the better, the larger the better,
the distance smaller the better, right.
So this will show the larger the better CAH.
Okay.
So for this CAH, and the, and the high value of CAH index
means that class are dense and well separated.
So here, that means the larger the better.
Okay.
And so, again, we use this index to evaluate the performance
of K-means classroom for the previous example, right.
When the K is set to different values, to two, to three, to four, to five,
then we can see the corresponding value, right.
So here, you can see a tree, for this tree, you know, a CI index,
the value is very big, right.
Not like others in the range from zero to one or from minus one to one, right.
But here, very big.
This depends on the data, how many data you have, right.
The larger the number of data, because you times the N i, right,
in the numerator part, this value could be very big.
If you have more samples, then this value could be even bigger.
But no matter the scale of the data, right, the values,
we can always find the peak value, right, the peak value.
Okay.
So we just use it based on the peak value to determine the suit of the number of K.
So this is the CI index.
So so far, we have introduced four, right, four methods, right.
Four methods, four metrics or index, actually,
to evaluate the performance of the cluster, okay.
And all of these four shows the peak values, right, peak values.
Okay.
And so this is different from WCSS, right.
WCSS actually, with the increase, actually, of the class numbers,
actually, the WCSS decreases.
Okay.
So we don't have peak values.
But for these four metrics, actually, or index, we have peak values.
And then I think it's easier to determine the suit of the number of, you know,
class and underlying the data.
If we use these four metrics, right, okay.
The last one, actually, is to, the last one is called the run index.
Actually, this method is to compare the, you know, results of the data.
You know, result of two class and algorithm, compared to two class and algorithm.
Okay.
And so they're not for evaluation of one class and algorithm.
This is different.
They just compare, right.
How close the result of two class and algorithms.
Okay.
How close the two class and class, class and result, right.
And so here, this is the formula for run index.
And as, indeed, as the number of pairs of sample assigned to the same cluster.
Okay.
So the, there are many pairs of the data, right.
Numerous pairs.
Not numerous.
There are so many pairs, the number of pairs of data is this.
This is not common at all.
From n, we select two.
Okay.
So these are numbers, huge, right.
So, so actually, these are total number pairs.
And these are number of pairs, the data assigned to the same cluster, across the same, the
two algorithm.
Okay.
For all, how many pairs?
There are so many pairs, right.
How many pairs, the two algorithms, send them to the same cluster.
Send them to the same cluster.
So these, the number of pairs is n, n.
So, indeed, here, the number of pairs of sample assigned to two different clusters.
How many pairs, right.
So these pairs for one algorithm, for this data, one assigned this, no data to one cluster.
Then another set to a different cluster, right.
So these are number of pairs.
Then divided by total number of pairs here.
Select n from two, common factorial, right.
So this will be n factorial divided by n factorial, two factorial, m factorial, two factorial.
Okay.
So these are used to compare to actually, you know, a class on an algorithm.
Whether that results in a similar or a very different.
Okay.
So I think this is not commonly used.
But actually, the first format are commonly used in the evaluation for a classroom.
Okay.
This is just like, you know, previously we have, you know, error rate, we have, you know, accuracy,
we have a precision, we have different metrics to evaluate the performance.
Okay.
Okay, I think, yeah, okay, that's all.
Yeah.
So this is the evaluation of the classroom.
I think this part is very important, right.
We learn, but what is the learning result?
The learning result is good or not, right.
So you study this course.
So what is your learning outcome?
So finally, when you, you will be tested, right, through the quizzes, through the exams.
Okay.
So this quiz exam, just like this kind of metrics, right, to evaluate the performance of the linear.
So linear is one aspect, but the evaluation of the linear result is also a very important aspect.
Right.
So, okay.
So that's actually, we have a ten-minute break.
So after a break, we have a revision, right.
And to summarize the main points in this course.
Okay.
In the first part of the course, actually, we talked about data preparation for machine learning, right.
And in this part, the first thing we know, we have studied different types of data.
And basically, the data can be categorized into two categories, right.
One is continuous data.
Another is discrete data.
And the discrete also called categorical data.
And under this category, categorical data, we have two types.
One is the, you know, the ordinal data.
Okay.
So we just have a few values, right.
And actually, the distance between the ordinal data can show the difference.
How big the difference is.
And then another type of nominal data.
Nominal data, actually, then the difference between the two values cannot represent how different the two values are, right.
They're just, they're different.
Just show they are different.
Okay.
And so the challenge of, you know, mixed data that contains both continuous and discrete, in particular the nominal data.
That, you know, the distance metric normally cannot be used.
I cannot say it cannot be used.
Actually, distance, there are some limitations if we use the distance metric.
Okay.
And actually, many classified use the distance metric, right.
And even in the, you know, just now when we talk about the evaluation of a classroom, we'll also use a distance concept.
Okay.
But if the data contains nominal features, then the distance is not very meaningful.
But we still can use, but just actually, when you will use the distance metric and maybe the performance is not the best.
Not optimal performance.
But we can still use that.
Okay.
And in particular, if there are not a number of features, but only a few number of features that are nominal.
In that tree, and this scenario, and then the influence of the nominal feature is not very big.
Okay.
So we can still use that.
But maybe just the performance is not optimal.
Okay.
So these are the data types.
So discrete, continuous.
Okay.
Or categorical, discrete.
And we have nominal, we have an ordinal, right.
Okay.
Another note is that, in the tree, quite often we can have mission values, right.
In the sample, we can, some of the values, some of the features for some of the samples, we don't have a value there.
So it's called mission value problem.
Okay.
So before we apply machine learning algorithm to the data, right.
So we must actually handle this mission value problem.
Okay.
We must feel a value.
And actually, of course, the tree to handle the mission value problem.
And first of all, the simply method, I need to remove the sample that have mission values.
Okay.
This is a simplest way, right.
But actually, only if the number of samples is small, the number of samples with mission values is small.
And then the elimination of these samples, we are not having a significant influence on the final learning result.
And then we can just eliminate these samples from the training data, right.
Training data set.
Okay.
If the initial, you know, the training sample is just small, right.
For example, we just have hundreds of samples.
But actually, like 10, 20 samples are with the mission values.
So in such a scenario, we cannot actually just discard these, you know, mission samples with mission values.
We should use other methods to handle this mission value problem, right.
And for example, we can use the so-called impute method, right.
And actually, we can use other samples to estimate the mission values, such as the mean values, the median values, right.
To replace the mission values.
And if the data is discrete, we don't have median, we don't have a mean value.
And then problem, like nominal data, we don't have a mean, median value, we don't have mean value.
Okay.
Of course, you can carry mean or median value, but this value is a meaningless.
But then we can use the mode.
The mode actually, the value that moves frequently occur.
Actually, that is called mode.
We can use the mode to replace actually the mission values.
So these are the ways to handle the mission value problem.
And then this problem, you know, auto-lias.
Auto-lias, that means samples have some, you know, extreme small or extreme large values, right.
So these are called, these samples with this kind of data is called actually auto-lias.
Of course, if the auto-lias number is small, right, very few samples are auto-lias.
Then, of course, you can remove them from the trinium data set.
Okay.
And if the initial trinium data set is small, right, and we should not actually, you know, just eliminate these auto-lias.
And for the very few extreme values, right, we should try to replace this using the median values or mean values, right.
Or even the mode to replace.
And you can also use other methods to estimate actually like a camping, right.
And most of the data is in the range, for example, from zero to one, right, I assume.
And then for some of the value in our feature, it could be like 10, 20, right.
A dream, you know, camping method.
Okay, we see.
If greater than one, then we will let the value just set one to that value, right.
Okay.
So, we have different ways to handle this mission value and the auto-lias problem.
Then another issue is the standardization and normalization.
Sometimes the features actually have different scales, right.
For example, if you measure the body weight, normally it's KG, right.
50, 60, 70, 80 KG, right.
And if you measure the height, right, maybe 1.7, 1.8, 1.6, something like that, right.
The scale are very different, right.
So, you put all the features in the same metric, like this metric.
As in some of the features with very big scale, we are dominant, right.
So, in such a scenario, we need to standardize the normal data, okay.
So, all the features are in the similar range.
Okay.
Standardization is to convert the data X to X prime.
And so that the X prime could have a zero mean.
Every value is zero.
Some could be positive, could be negative, right.
But the value is the mean zero.
We shift the data, right.
And then we also scale the data by dividing the data by actually the sigma, the standardization.
So, after this standardization, the data is zero mean and standardization of one.
The sigma will become one, okay.
It becomes one and the mean will be zero for the X prime.
So, this is called standardization.
So, another is normalization to normalize the data to a certain range.
For example, from zero to one, from minus one to one, so you can decide the range.
Okay.
So, this is the so-called treat normalization.
But sometimes they don't know the difference in the two concepts.
They all call it normalization or standardization.
But we know that they are just trying to actually make all the data to a similar range, right.
Similar range.
Okay.
So, this is the first part of the data preparation for machine learning.
And then we have a link over this.
Okay.
And then after that, actually, we started the, you know, the business classifier, right,
which is the statistical approach for decision making.
Decision making here is just to decide the class of the sample, right, class one, class two, class three.
This is the decision making in classification.
Okay.
So, decision making is based on the probabilities.
Actually, it is based on the posterior probabilities.
Okay.
So, the probability of omega j given x.
So, this is actually the posterior probability.
Pursuant probability, right, given x.
Okay.
So, this is actually, you know, equal to the, you know, the new px omega j times p omega j.
p omega j is called actually the prior probabilities.
So, we can easily estimate the prior probability from the percentage or proportion of the, you
know, sample of each class.
Okay.
So, this is 20% beyond class one, 20%, 30% beyond class two, 30% beyond class three.
Or then we can have the prior probability, right.
Zero point two, zero point three, zero point five.
This is called prior probability.
Can be easily estimated from the percentage of the sample in each class, right.
And so, from the training data.
Okay.
So, the key issue actually here is the px given omega j.
This is called actually class-candinal probability density function, px omega j.
Okay.
So, actually normally, you know, we assume the data for normal distribution, right.
Then we can specifically form for this px omega j, the class-candinal probability density
function.
Okay.
And in this code, we assume, you know, it's this px, the data for normal distribution,
multivariate normal distribution.
Okay.
Our focus is just to estimate the parameters in this Gaussian function, right.
In the Gaussian function, multivariate Gaussian distribution function, we have two parameters.
One is the current matrix and that is the mean vector.
Okay.
So, this is the, okay.
So, this is the, yeah.
So, we see there are two parameters, one mean vector and the current matrix.
Current matrix.
Okay.
And also, actually, we know the decision rule, right.
And actually, we're based on the probability, right.
Actually, after we calculate the posterior probability, then we look at which probability
has the maximum value, right, is the maximum.
And then we will start to assemble to the corresponding class.
Okay.
So, and the, often we can use a variant of this.
We don't need to calculate the posterior probability.
Instead, we can use a joint probability of the omega, the class, and the x joint probability,
which is just the product of these two, right.
The probability and the class-candinal probability density function.
Because the Px is a common factor, right, for all classes.
We don't need to calculate that part.
Okay.
So, and so I think, one, one extension here is the NIO base, right.
NIO base actually assume the features or attributes are independent in between.
Then we can simplify.
We can simplify.
Okay.
So, this is a multivariate, multivariate, actually, in the normal distribution.
Actually, this multivariate normal distribution can be actually decomposed into the multiplication
of multiple, multiple, right, and just, multiple, actually, you know, it's a univariate question,
the normal distribution function, univariate, right.
So, for each of the univariate function, and we have this, right, this is mean, right.
Subtract the mean divided by the, you know, the C squared, right.
Yeah.
The two C squared.
So, this is the, actually, the univariate normal distribution function.
So, we assume the independence between the features.
Then we simplify, actually, the multivariate normal, normal distribution, right, to the
multiple, actually, univariate normal distributions.
So, this simplified this process.
Okay.
And so, this is actually the, the mu ij, so j here means, you know, class of omega j, right,
class of omega j.
So, this i, i here means which feature, okay, feature number one, feature, along feature
number two, along feature number three, right.
So, this is actually, this is for sample in class j, and along the feature i, this is
the mean value.
This is along the feature j, i for  in class rj.
So, this is the standard.
Standard.
Okay.
So, this is the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the.
Okay.
So, here, I, I, I gave an example to further, I chose, actually, if you have, you know,
like a mean vector, right.
If you have no, this is actually a quaring metric and actually, the estimation of the
quaring metric and the, the mean vector is based on the so called the maximum likelihood
measure, right, with the, maximum likelihood, to estimate the parameters of the multivariate
normal functions, okay.
function.
So we estimate the mean value and the current matrix.
So current matrix is estimated based on this.
And so first, we have the mean value.
Mean value here is just average.
So we, based on the mean value, then
we can calculate current matrix.
If a current matrix is given, so this
is the diagonal elements on the main diagonal.
So this is the four class.
Because here is the sigma 1.
This is four class 1.
Four class 1.
So this is the sigma along the feature 1.
So this is the standard region along the feature 2.
So both are actually for a sample in class 1.
So if a given such a current matrix,
and this is for class 2, sigma 2.
And so this is along feature 2, actually the standard region.
So this is along the feature 1, the standard region, 1.188.
So given the current matrix, you need to know the mean.
What do you mean by know the mean?
But this is on the main diagonal.
So this is class 1 along feature 1.
Sigma 1, 1.
Sigma 2, 1.
OK.
This is the mean.
The mean is just all the samples in the same class.
We take the average, the mean vector, the centroid.
So this is actually for class 1.
For class 1, then this mu, the first element,
is along the feature number 1.
And this is the second value along the feature number 2.
So this is mu 1, 1, mu 2, 1.
So similar for class 2 samples.
So this is along feature number 1, along feature number 2.
We have the mean values.
So given current matrix and also the mean vector,
which will be able to design the basic design rule.
And we assume the multi-variable normal distribution
function.
And also we can assume the dependence between the features.
Then we can use the naive base method
to classify the samples.
OK.
So this is the statistical approach
for pattern classification.
Then the next part, there's the feature
of linear dismal analysis.
So the objective for feature linear dismal analysis,
and later we see the linear support-widen machine,
are both linear classifies.
Linear classifies.
Actually, the feature linear, the base design rule,
is not a linear classifier.
And then we see the design boundary is not a line.
It's a curve.
But for the feature linear dismal analysis
and the linear support-widen machines,
the dismal boundary is a straight line or hyper plane.
So they are linear classifier.
For all linear classifiers, they have the same form.
Js equal to w transpose x plus w is 0.
So w determines the projection direction.
And also we determine the dismal boundary direction.
And w is 0 determines the bias term.
W determines the position of these dismal boundaries.
So in the feature linear dismal analysis,
we try to find such a w.
And so that after projection of all sum on this w,
and we could have the maximum between class difference,
between class separation.
We could have the minimum within class similarity.
And within class minimum similarity,
within class dissimilarity.
So this is a big idea.
We want to have the maximum between class separation
and the minimum within class separate difference.
Then in the feature linear dismal analysis,
they try to find such a w so that this ratio makes more.
So one is a lot better, another is smaller the better.
So here they use the ratio.
The ratio, the numerator, the larger the better.
The denominator, the smaller the better.
The ratio of course, the larger the better.
So they find that this is a big idea of the feature linear
dismal analysis.
I think previously when we talk about each method,
I think probably you cannot connect them, cannot link them.
But now you have learned all the methods.
You have learned linear class.
You have learned the class, super linear.
You have learned unsupertional.
You have learned unsupertional class.
You can also compare the similarities.
And in particular, when we talk about the between class
or between class separation, and within class,
or within class difference or variance,
you can link them.
So here we have two very important metrics.
One is called between class scatter.
So this is the between class.
We have two main vectors, two main vectors.
And then, so what is how to calculate the scatter,
the sb, b means between class scatter, right?
Between class scatter metrics.
You know how to calculate, right?
And also for each class, we can have a within class scatter
metrics.
For all samples, look at it based on the centroid, right?
And then we can calculate the within class scatter.
For each of the two classes, we have a within class scatter.
So the summation, so we have sw, w here,
I mean within class, right?
So within class scatter metrics, b is between class scatter metrics.
OK.
Of course, the way to find w, and we can use a few ways.
In the class, we talk about the general value problem, right?
By solving general value problem,
or solving the normal value problem, we can find w.
And also we have a finder, they introduce another way, right?
Another way.
That is, sw inverse m1 and m2.
Actually, these are easy to understand, right?
Because we want to know m1 and m2, right?
Something represented between class, right?
m1 minus m2, OK, between class.
Sw is within class.
So again, for calculation of the w, we use a two-part of information.
Between class.
So here between class, we use m1 minus m2.
Within class, we use sw to represent.
So in the calculation of the w, we still use a two-part of information.
Between class, within class, OK?
And within class, sw should be smaller than better, right?
Within normally compact, right?
So we use an inverse.
Inverse, something like a divider, right?
But just because it's a metric, we cannot divide the metric.
We still use an inverse.
So I think so m1 and the larger the better.
Sw inverse is smaller the better, right?
So we use this part.
OK, the compactness, right?
Sw, the compactness, OK?
So I think for this formula, I think it's easy to understand, right?
m1 minus m1, no, it's not SB, right?
If you use SB, inverse, that's wrong.
m1, m2 represent between class.
Then you should not use another metric just for between class, right?
So here we should use a metric representing within class.
OK, so that is sw.
OK, and then of course this is for the determination of w.
The next part is determined the w0, the bias term.
So the basic idea is that we hope that the middle point of the two centroid is on the dissonant boundary.
On the dissonant boundary means that the gx should be 0, right?
So that means that w transpose x plus w0 equals x equal to the middle of the two.
That is m1 plus m2 divided by 2, right?
Then plus w0 should be equal to 0, should be 0, right?
Then based on that, actually we can calculate this w0 value.
So this is the way to determine the bias term.
Of course, here we have one assumption.
So that is the spread of the two classes are the same or very similar, the spread.
But if one class spreads very big, another class spreads small,
and then this value, w0, actually is not the best value.
If you only give a rough value, then along this value, we can plus, we can minus, right?
We can do, you know, try a few values to find the best ones.
Because this is a formula, this way is assumed the two classes have the same spread.
If another variable, another small, right?
If you think of the middle point, right?
So actually the middle point, actually is not on the dissonant boundary.
If you're on the dissonant boundary, then you will have a lot of class-fying areas.
So usually this will give us a very rough guide.
Then based on this value, we can increase or we can decrease, right?
Then we can find the optimal value.
We can try a few w0, based on this w0, right?
We can try a few values to find the best one.
Okay, so this is the, I know, the Fisher linear gymnastics.
So I think why I introduce this matter?
I think this concept is really good, really good, right?
And for example, sometimes, for example, the whole fair neural network,
when I talk about neural networks, I mean another cost.
This whole fair neural network is very old, some don't think, but I think the idea is very good.
So for years, I always talk about that.
But indeed, this year, they won the Nobel Prize, right?
I think, because this idea is really good.
So here, I also think for the Fisher linear gymnastics analysis,
I think the idea is very good.
So we should know, right, the between class, within class,
between class, within class, okay?
In many different methods, even super, unsupervised, we all use this concept.
Okay, so here I think this idea is really good.
And then another thing we, okay, so here I want to also
talk about relationship with the career metric and the scatter metric.
Okay, so we have scatter metric, right?
We also have a career metric.
Actually, there are a relationship between the two.
Okay, and actually, we see the career metric, actually,
we know we divided by a number of samples.
In the scatter metric, we don't divide by the number of samples, right?
So this is a relationship between, this SI is a scatter metric,
within class scatter metric for class one, right?
So this sigma one is a career metric for class one.
Okay, here n one over n one, right?
Actually, this is actually estimated, it's called,
actually, maximum likelihood estimation,
maximum likelihood estimation, n one, n one, right?
But some, actually, you know, both actually this,
u is a one over n one minus one.
n one minus one is called the third degree of freedom.
So that estimate is called unbiased estimate of the career metric, unbiased.
So this is called the maximum likelihood estimate.
But if n is big, right, one over n minus one or one over n,
that doesn't make much difference, right?
In particular, I think for a large value of n.
And in most of the, in all the tourbos, like in my lab,
when we talk about career metric,
what they gave actually is unbiased estimate.
So they divided by n minus one, n one minus one.
Okay, so this is just the relationship between the career metric and the scatter metric, right?
And actually in the official linear determinacy,
we use the scatter metric.
And in the previous tree, we used actually,
we used in the Gaussian, which is more,
in the Gaussian basis tree, you know, the basic decision rule, right?
So in the previous tree, for the multi-weather Gaussian function,
we use the career metric.
So this shows the relationship.
So don't confuse that too, okay?
Okay, so the next method actually,
we have started to call linear support wind machines, okay?
And so the basic idea is for,
again, this is a standard form for linear classifier, right?
So they just use different ones.
No w, b, b represented bias, okay?
And so the basic idea here, they try to find a w
so that the margin of separation makes mine, right?
So this is the basic idea of the support wind machine,
is to maximize the margin of separation.
So what is the margin of the two classes?
Actually, the distance between the two closed samples, right?
No, no, actually the boundary,
no, no, no, you direct the distance, right?
So they use another hyperplane by part of the snare sample,
then they use this distance, right?
So this is called a distance, right?
And between, so this is the distance,
this is the margin of separation.
So we want to find w so that the margin of separation is maximized.
Under the condition that all samples could be classified correctly, right?
So linear support wind machine can be summarized
as a constant or a musician problem.
So we first actually did a constant,
and this linear constant, every sample should be classified correctly.
And this condition, we minimize actually the square norm of the w,
which is inversely proportional to the, you know, the margin of separation, right?
The margin of separation maximized.
So here is a, actually, minimize the square norm of the w.
So this is a, you know, for the separable case.
And for the non-separable case, actually,
we introduce a select variable, right?
Select variable.
And so in such a scenario, we call the margin soft, margin soft.
Okay.
And so here in the loss function, we introduce one extra term.
So this is a seed, a hyperparameter, right?
So we have this, actually, here is a quasi-i, the select variable.
So this is a non-separable case.
So in all cases, actually, you know, we can find the w, right?
And actually, the very important, you know,
carrier 6 of these smaller machines, then the w, this is no present w, actually,
is a linear summation of the support vectors.
It's a w-summiner support vector.
Because here we have support vector xi, right?
Summation of the extra.
By each of the support vectors, we have a corresponding w.
And this w contains two parts.
One is the class label of this class support vector.
Another is the Lagrange multiplied alpha, alpha, right?
So alpha, corresponding alpha times the class label.
So this is a weightage for this support vector.
And then each support vector has a corresponding weight, right?
So finally, we get a summation of all the support vectors.
So we get this w.
So this w is a linear summation of the support vectors.
We know most of the samples will have a corresponding alpha with a zero value.
So normally, a small number of samples will have a non-zero alpha.
So this sample are called support vectors.
We just use this part of sample to determine this w.
To determine this w, right?
OK.
So w is determined by the linear summation of the support vectors.
Summation.
Get a sum of them, right?
So this is not the real summation.
Each support vector has a corresponding weight.
This weight is just a product of the class label with a greater alpha, the corresponding alpha value.
OK.
So this is the calculation of this w.
For the bias term, I think bias term calculation is easy, right?
Because if we substitute the support vector into the non-discipline function,
the value should be equal to 1 or minus 5, equal to class label, right?
So for each of the support vectors, we can calculate a bias term, right?
So because of some calculation, rounding areas or whatever,
so you may use a different support vector.
Maybe we can get a slightly different trade bias term, but b.
OK.
So normally, we can use each of the samples to calculate b, right?
And then finally, we take the average.
So we substitute this w, and not any support vector, into the discriminant function.
W transpose x plus b equals 1 or minus 1.
Equal to di, right? di.
So you can get.
So this is the way to calculate b, the bias term.
OK.
So this is for the separable case.
In the non-separable case, when we introduce the quasi-i, right?
So this is the zeta i, which is the slight variable.
And therefore, some of the, I think for the calculation of the w, the same.
We still use all the support vectors, right?
But for the calculation of the b, we don't use all support vectors.
We only use some of the support vectors, right?
We support vectors.
That is the alpha.
Of course, the alpha should be greater than 0.
Otherwise, this should not be a support vector, right?
And we use only those part of support vectors with the corresponding alpha, less than the
c, which is the c, not in the loss function, right?
And we, for the slight variable zeta i, and we have a weight c.
So this is the c value.
OK.
So in this range, I think only for those part of the support vector, and we can use to calculate
the bias term.
So this is the support vector.
So for support vector, I think first you need to understand the basic idea, right?
So what's the basic idea?
The maximization of the model separation, and then they summarize the support vector machine
into a constant omission problem, right?
For linear separable case, for nonlinear separable case, OK?
So this is called a primal problem, right?
And also, we have the concept of the dual problem, right?
And we just have to solve a quadratic programming problem to find alpha values.
OK.
The loss function is only a function of the alpha.
So this is a dual problem.
OK.
So we find alpha values.
Once we know the alpha values, and then actually we know the corresponding support vector,
then we can calculate this w and this b.
OK.
So we need to know this, OK?
The next part, I think, is a classification tree.
And so here, I think the answer to this question, right?
You know, to build a tree, right?
So these are some key points.
And actually, normally to determine actually which variable to use and to ask what question
in a node, right?
Actually, we're based on the drop of the impurity.
OK.
So we have two methods for impurity measures.
One is the entropy impurity, another is the gene impurity.
So the total impurity, right?
So after we divide the data using this attribute, and ask this question about this attribute,
we can have the maximum reduction of the impurity.
And then we can select that variable and ask that question to divide the data.
OK.
And also in this part of the tree, we have studied the random forest, right?
And this also, I think, now is very popular, very popular.
So actually, in the random forest, actually, now we have multiple trees, right?
And each of the trees is built on part of the data, a random selection from the original data, right?
So this random data tree is the so-called, based on the boost-raping technique.
It is kind of a sampling technique, sample with replacement.
You collect this sample, then you put it back, right?
Then you have another chance to get this sample be selected.
OK.
Then another is aggregating.
Aggregating is the final stage.
When you, from each of the trees, we have a decision, decision, right?
We have a classification result.
So finally, we need to combine all the results.
So this aggregating, we normally use a majority of voting.
OK.
So boost-raping means, actually, the kind of sampling technique.
And we sample the data, then we build a tree.
OK.
Like this.
Training data, we sample the data, right?
Randomly select a certain number of data to get subset number one, randomly select another set, right?
So total, we have n set.
Then based on each of the set, we can build a classification tree.
And how to build classification tree?
Just the one we have, the method we have studied, right?
And actually, for the classification tree, we have introduced how to build a tree, right?
So here, based on each of the subset, we should build a tree.
But of course, in the random forest, each of the trees use different features or attributes.
OK.
So after you get these samples, actually, not all features are used.
You randomly select some of the features to build a tree.
OK.
So here, you can see all the data are different.
The features used are different from one tree to another tree.
OK.
So finally, we combine the result, right, from all trees.
And then there's regression.
I think we also talk about regression, and read regression, and also the multi-regression.
The only release square estimate for the parameter estimation.
OK.
So classifier performance evaluation.
And for the method that we talked about, for you, right, hold out method, repeat hold out.
And care food cross validation, repeat the care food cross validation.
And also the leave out.
It should be clear about each of these methods, right?
Hold out, randomly select, right?
And then we have repeated hold out.
Care food cross validation.
Divide the data into care food.
Care food is used, actually, once as a testing data, right?
You repeat these current care times.
So that is a care food cross validation.
Leave out.
All of them for the metrics, right?
Accuracy, error rate, selectivity, specificity, precision recall, and F score.
OK.
So, yeah.
This is one example.
And the test is playing.
I think to enhance your understanding about this, actually, like precision recall and F score.
I didn't even notice you can have a look at that.
OK.
So that's actually about feature subsets selection, right?
And actually, in this part, actually, we have some very important concept, like cursor of the minority.
Cursor of the minority have two issues.
Actually, there are two issues related to the cursor of the minority.
One is actually in the hard terminal space, there is a concentration, different concentration.
So another actually is, I think, the sparsity of the data, right?
You can imagine in a hard terminal space, the data could be very spars.
So this is actually, and also actually, the picking phenomena, right?
Just not in the quiz, we have the picking phenomena, right?
So this picking phenomena can guide us on the data collection, right?
And also on feature selection.
So we should try to collect as much as possible of the data.
And if the data is limited, then we should not select a limited number of features, right?
So this will give us some guidance on the features, on the selection and the data collection.
And also in the video feature evaluation selection, and also the feature subsets selection.
We need to have an answer on all these concepts, OK?
And also in a feature subsets selection algorithm, we have two components.
One is a set algorithm, another is a evaluation criteria, OK?
And actually the set algorithm is to generate a candidate feature subset, OK?
And then the evaluation criteria is to evaluate the goodness of each of the generated candidate features subset.
And then finally, we'll find the best performing subset, OK?
So this is the two components.
And so based on the evaluation criteria, actually all the matter can be classified into two categories.
One is called field of matter.
So we don't use actually the pent-clustering result.
We use other metrics like the Mahanobhi distance or other separability measures, like based on the within class,
keta matrix, between class, keta matrix, we can have some separability measures.
So based on separability measure or based on Mahanobhi distance, right?
We can actually evaluate the performance, the goodness of feature subset.
We can also actually, based on the classification result to evaluate the performance of the subset.
So that is called wrapper method.
OK, so it depends on actually the evaluation criteria that are classified.
All the matter can be classified into wrapper or field of matter.
You're based on the set algorithm, then all the matter can be classified into optimal, suboptimal.
For suboptimal, then we have forward search selection by one nation.
Forward selection, that means that we start from empty set.
Every iteration, we select one feature.
Then we gradually build up the features of set until actually the solving criteria is satisfied.
The solving criteria could be a certain number of features or could be the improvement of the criteria.
The trivial after the addition of one extra feature.
Then the back-rolling nation is to remove the features one by one.
So we start from the full feature set, then we remove one at each step until the solving criteria is satisfied.
Then the classroom, the four types of classroom algorithm, right?
Central-based method, distribution-based method, hierarchical classroom, and also the denser-based classroom.
For each of the methods, we introduce one.
K-means, agglomerative, hierarchical classroom, DB scan, Gaussian-Mister model.
I think for the evaluation, I don't give the formula, but this part we just talked about in the last session.
I don't list all the equations here, but you need to understand each of these evaluation metrics.
Silhouette coefficient.
If you use the old nodes, you need to use the updated nodes.
Because in the updated nodes, I introduced the updated silhouette coefficient part.
But the one in the old feature, actually, old nodes are not wrong.
But actually, they are just a variant, right?
But most commonly, we use this one, you introduce this today.
Silhouette coefficient.
Dine index, a DB index, series chartry index, this different index, right?
And the advantage of this index is that we have a peak value, right?
We have peak values.
And then we can easily determine the number of clusters underlying the data.
Peak value.
We look at the peak, right?
Okay.
Okay, I think that's revision.
The main, the key point, the main content of the machine learning part.
Okay.
So that's actually, we have a 10-minute break.
So after break, actually, we do zoom.
If you bring laptop, then probably you can log into the zoom.
Using the link I sent to you in the announcement, right?
And then you can use the chat function to type your questions.
Okay, then I shoot a question on the board and then I'll answer your questions.
Okay.
I think the, I just reviewed the machine learning part, right?
I treated general rhythm.
One question, exam question.
One question from the genetic algorithm part.
Three questions from the machine learning part in the final exam.
Okay.
I think I ask a question.
Right?
Can I ask for another question from the preparation group?
Any more questions?
I think you are in the Monday morning class.
Actually, a lot of questions actually answer the whole hour,
actually, for the questions.
I think you can also ask questions, right?
Yeah, I think you better bring the calculator.
In the exam, you cannot use the handphone, right?
You cannot bring the handphone to the class room,
to the examination hall, but you need to bring the calculator.
Yeah.
So, more questions.
Are there any more questions?
Any kind of questions that you can ask?
Yeah.
I think, yeah, if you understand these,
actually, then you can write it out, right?
Yeah, I think like, which way?
Like, covariance matrix, or like, I think the, you know,
the within class can measure between class, right?
If you understand the meaning,
I think it's easy to write out them.
So, I don't know.
Classroom method, right?
Actually, normally in the exam,
we should expect a standard answer, right?
So, we know the question will be very specific.
If you ask you to use what method, like,
what distance, or whatever, which is specific.
Yeah.
Come on, questions, right?
You can ask questions.
No questions?
So, you ask.
Don't ask others to ask, right?
You ask questions.
In the past years, actually, I think a lot of questions.
This year, actually, the morning, morning class,
lot of questions.
So, you ask questions, then clarify.
Then everyone should benefit.
So, that means you make a contribution, right?
So, if you don't actually, you know, have a computer,
I think you ask questions directly, right?
So, anyway, any form, right?
Anyway, you can ask questions.
Any questions?
I think NTU, NTU, I think the 40 marks is past 40.
But the result here is different from in China.
Now, you can see all 80 marks, 90 marks, right?
So, here, almost impossible.
So, I think this year is like 75, the A minus, Gp is 4.5.
80 is 8, 8 is 5 upon 5.
So, you can imagine, right?
So, actually, you get 80 marks, it's very hard.
75 is also hard.
So, 40 marks is a past.
40, 40, yeah.
But if you just pass, you cannot have a degree, right?
Actually, if you get a degree, you need to be about 2.5, right?
2.5, maybe, I think you need to get 50 something, right?
Yeah, basically, I think it's a learning part, I think.
Should be, let's go.
So, which part I miss, or I think that's a little bit of a moment.
I think that's an important point, right?
We need to master in this course.
But maybe some part, I don't know where I miss or not.
Yeah, yeah, that's right, that's right, yeah.
So, if you get familiar with all the countertits today,
at least you can pass a lot, right?
Not a problem to pass, yeah.
Questions? No questions?
Any questions?
Yeah, maybe I think you recorded it, right?
Because on the web, so maybe you can look at that.
Yeah, normally that is lecture recording, right?
I'm not very sure, actually.
Sure, I think.
I have no idea, actually.
Can you see the yesterday recording?
You cannot see.
Maybe a check whether I can share this part.
You ask questions, right?
You ask questions, then you, Benny, I think,
or other benefits.
You ask questions, benefits just from those groups, right?
If you ask questions, then I've uploaded today's video,
then other groups also benefit from your question, right?
Then you ask questions, try to think about which you don't understand,
or you want me to clarify.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think then, yeah, I think,
I think today, I did a revision at least some main point, right?
So at least I think this part needs to understand a lot, yeah.
Yeah.
So today's revision, at least the important point,
this, that's, yeah.
Yeah.
Okay, no questions?
Sorry.
Yeah, I think we need to have calculated,
calculate, calculate, right?
And to calculate, like,
what kind of instruction?
Normally in the exam, you can bring nothing.
You cannot bring anything to the,
to the, yeah, to the examination hall.
Yeah, they have found an announcement.
Normally, you know, actually normally, you know,
in the very big examination hall, you can bring the bag,
but you can, you need to put a bag in one side,
in one corner of the examination hall.
You cannot bring anything, any paper.
I think last year, I think in the examination hall,
two students, I think, yeah, I think,
what I called about the, in the major data,
you bring, I just remember a paper,
and you write some formula on the paper, so, yeah.
So you cannot bring anything.
Here, the examination is very, very straight.
Now, if you, you know, do that,
they can see that it's cheating, actually.
Why see a research, yeah.
So, yeah, you can already bring the computer.
Maybe then, no, no, bring, bring the calculator.
Calculator, you also need to be certified by, you know,
NTU, then, set the office, yeah.
And so, you cannot bring the handphone.
You cannot use the handphone,
or kind of bring any book, reference book,
or notes, anything, anything, yeah.
In the exam, they will provide the so-called answer book,
actually, just like a notebook, actually,
many pages, actually, everyone have this.
You cannot write your name on the, on the, on the,
on the answer book.
You can only write your metric calculation number, okay.
And also, you need to bring your metric calculation card, okay.
You, you, during the examination, actually,
no, I really don't know, the emulator,
I will also be there as an emulator.
I will check, actually, based on the sequence, you know,
compare the name, your metric calculation card, actually,
to make sure you sit on the right seat,
and the seat number, right, you try the right seat,
and also, you know, you check, actually,
if you actually miss your metric calculation card,
probably you need to bring your passport to prove,
you know, you, you, yourself, right.
Yeah, so, I think in the, in the,
in the, during the exam, actually,
because this is the first time we've been come to NTU, right.
So, probably, you know, you can come to the,
you can enter the examination hall,
10 minutes before the start of the exam, okay.
Then you cannot write down anything,
you can just, actually, then they will give instructions,
I went to start, I went to stop,
after they say stop writing, you cannot write.
Here, it's very strict, okay, very strict.
You cannot, you cannot actually,
because during the quiz, I see some,
soon I come in, they write, they write down something, right,
they start to write, and then they emulator the student,
actually, you know, get the papers,
and then give them a new one, don't let them write,
but to start writing, until we are not, we start, okay.
Yeah.
And we don't have,
don't have a, we don't have a,
kind of a solution, but roughly, you know the answer, right.
You know the answer, right, yeah.
But actually, something like, if you,
if sometimes, if you don't actually, like,
I see, or train a neural network,
or talk about something, right, just something like,
so can you introduce yourself, if I ask a question, right.
Of course you can see, my name, you can just see,
I'm called actually, like, David, for example, right.
This is also an introduction,
but you can also give a more complete introduction,
or I call David, I'm David, I'm from, you know,
scrub, shubo, NTU, and I'm involved in, you know,
in which program, you know, it's a more complete introduction,
right. So if you, you know, what kind of answer you expect,
right, so you ask me, right, how to answer that question,
so, I mean, what kind of answer you expect,
that should be the answer I expect from you,
right, it should be as complete as possible, yeah.
Okay, that's my question, good.
Okay, let me ask the question.
Okay, I think the problem, I think, actually, you know,
we know, you know, the basic idea of the support machine
is to, you know, to find that W, right, to find the projection
and the boundary, and so that, actually,
the margin of separation makes a mark.
Actually, we know margin of separation is two over the norm of W,
right, norm of W, actually.
Then, actually, the optimization problem, actually,
is that we try to optimize, actually, the minimized.
Now, maximize the norm, the margin of separation,
but in practice, we minimize the square of the norm, right, of W, okay.
Subject to a certain constant, that means all samples are, you know,
classified correctly.
So, support machine is summarizing to,
or converting to a constant optimization problem, okay.
So, to solve this constant optimization problem,
actually, we need to use the Lagrange Multiply method.
If you recall in your year one calculus, right,
actually, we learn how to solve a constant optimization problem.
You learn Lagrange method.
But just, actually, in our previous work, actually,
we just tried one variable, two variables,
but here, the number of variables, you know, the dimension are very high.
Okay, so, no, no, the constant,
in previous, we maybe just had one constant,
but here, we have a lot number of constant,
because each sample needs to be correctly classified.
So, this should be a constant, okay.
So, this, actually, we have lost function,
and then combine the two parts, right.
Why is Lagrange multiplier, okay, Lagrange multiplier, okay.
Another part, actually, is the, you know, the original, you know,
lost function, the square of the norm of the W, okay.
So, this is a parameter problem.
And the dual problem, actually, through the relationship, right,
and also the KTT, you know, like, you know, the optimization theory.
And finally, this is no lost function,
is converting to another, you know, lost function
that contains the Lagrange multiplier only.
Previously, we have a few, you know, parameters, right.
Why is W zero or B?
We have a W parameter.
We have multipliers, the alphas, okay.
So, this is the parameter problem, right.
But after, actually, the conversion in the dual problem,
we just have one top of parameters.
So, that is just Lagrange multiplier.
So, that's the dual problem.
So, we solve this, you know, the dual problem to get alphas.
And then from alphas, actually, we can get the W, right.
The W is just the weight summation of the, of the, the, the support vectors.
And the support vectors are those with the non-zero alphas, right.
So, with the weight summation of the W, the support vectors,
the weight of the support vector is just the class label
multiplied, Lagrange multiplied alpha i.
So, this is the weight summation of W.
So, this is a dual problem.
It's just a lost function that contains, actually, the alpha i
as a coefficient only.
Okay.
So, these are the difference between the two, right.
Yeah.
So, this is the difference between the two, right.
Because actually, the dual problem is equivalent to the, the primal problem.
Equivalent.
Okay.
Because we, we discovered the relationship between the W's and the alphas, right.
So, all the W's are replaced by alphas.
And finally, we get one, actually, the lost function contains,
contains alpha only.
So, that is a dual problem.
Okay.
Please.
Any kind of question, right.
This is probably the last chance, right.
We, we made, actually, after that, I will see you in the examination hall, right.
On the 29th of November, right.
So, you have a question, actually, you can ask in the class.
Any question?
Yeah.
No, no need, no need.
Actually, I'm, I'm a book, right, into, right, actually, but you kind of calculate in the back of the paper.
We just, when we mark, we just look at that.
Yeah.
Not in the back, yeah.
If you kind of bring any paper, you can bring a few pens, right.
A few pens, the calculators, the water bottles, maybe, you know, maybe a coat, actually,
because in the examination hall, it could be a coat.
Okay.
Yeah.
For that part, I don't know, actually, yeah.
But actually, I don't know.
I'm going to bring one question from the general argument part, three questions from the machine learning part.
The answer, actually, I don't know if it's wrong, maybe it's just not complete.
I think I don't know what is your mark.
But when you calculate the mark, you cannot compare the mindset, you know, I need to be 1890 something, that's not China, right.
The mark normally in that range.
So here, you know, like, 18 marks is a, you know, GPA is a full file, right.
You can see that the standard here, right, is different.
You don't see, oh, I just get 75, right.
75, like, you know, those like in China, 90 marks like that, because the GPA is full with five, right.
75 is already, you know, 4.8, right, 4.5, very good.
If 18 marks, the GPA is five, a full mark.
A plus 85, A plus is also five GPA.
So you need to consider that, actually, not just actually.
So I see if you get a mark, actually, you see like 70, 80, and this is because normally, you know, the standard here, you know, we don't give that kind of mark like about 90,
unless your, your really answer is perfect, right, because open answer questions, you know, we don't have this kind of perfect answers.
Okay, but when you answer the question, I think if you, the mark is not satisfactory, I don't see your answer is wrong.
Normally, in most cases, actually, your answer is not complete.
Okay, and for example, if you like, you know, the nine, the, you know, multi-variable normal distribution, and then we use the nine bits, right, when you compare the two, actually, you can compare from different aspects, right, like, you know, the computational efficiency,
and also for the, for the, you know, primary estimation point of view, right.
Actually, if you use the multi-variable normal distribution, how many parameters you can estimate in the current matrix?
Then if you use the Gaussian, you know, the nine bits, right, and then how many parameters you can estimate?
Even a small number of samples, so how, you know, which should be more accurate, right, you can't expect all these, many aspects.
So if you don't get a very high mark, most likely your answer is not complete, not wrong, actually.
Yeah, so this kind of question normally is a open answer.
Okay, so sometimes you, or train a classifier, train that, you, you need to give a classifier.
For example, in the linear distribution analysis, right, in the assignment, I think it's a feature, in the, you know, in the, in the, in the basic decision rule.
Some just give, actually, the, you know, the, the mean vectors give the, the current matrix, but you don't give the form of the, the decision, you know, the, the decision rules, right.
So that's actually, you know, I mean, actually, you are not wrong, but your answer is not complete.
You just give part of the question, right.
You are not actually really trained at a, at a discrimination, kind of, you know, decision rule, right.
Because actually you just give the mean vector, you don't know, actually you need to put this into a, into a function function.
I will assume you don't know.
Okay, so this kind of answer is not complete.
So we will get some marks.
So I think the example, whatever, when I ask a question, you should elaborate, try to give as complete as possible.
Just like I asked you, you know, please introduce yourself.
Oh, I'm joined. This is a very simple answer, right? It's wrong? No wrong.
But even the other way, I'm joined from China with my degree from which university and they are now in NTU, I mean, we're all in which program, right.
Then this answer is more complete. Which answer you prefer when you ask a student to introduce yourself?
You prefer the complete answer, right. Yeah.
So that's the way when you answer a question in the exam, in the assignment, you quit.
You should, you, more complete, that means you answer them more about this problem.
Okay.
And maybe I don't know how to answer your question.
And I think in the, in the use of geometry, every year, you know, we need to show some difference, right, on the question.
Because the school always check whether this year's different question, the same as last year's or whatever.
We cannot have the same question.
So last year, we did not test, but I don't know me in this year, we were not test.
But sometimes actually, indeed, actually, maybe not easy to, if something you need to know, to use a computer, right, then we cannot test you, right, in the exam.
Okay. So, yeah, I think you don't, I think at least the last year, you know, the past year exam papers can give you a basic idea on the format of the exam questions, right.
But don't say, in the past, we have this question, this year, we have the same question, no.
Actually, we will try to set different questions for different years.
But just for some of the questions you can imagine, right, it's easy for us to set an assignment because we can use a computer.
But in the exam, maybe not easy, right, yeah.
Questions?
Sorry.
This course is related to the learning model.
What?
Can you?
This course is related to learning model.
Do you think it's in the sense?
During the market, we give the marks.
But finally, based on the mark, they give you ABCD.
You just get ABCD that is like the letter graded.
You just get this result, letter graded.
I think for all the courses, you finally get A or B or C.
Yes, actually, we, yeah, then, yeah, of course, actually,
initially you get a mark.
And you know, 1929 or 1885, this kind of mark.
But finally, based on the mark, we get a grade.
Question?
Any questions?
Optimal.
Optimal and suboptimal, right?
In the, okay, her question is about, for the future sub-sacrination,
the optimal method is all the carbonatorals.
We have no features, and the current features are X1, X2, Xn, right?
So how to find the optimal features?
I think based on the set, set of algorithm, right?
Based on the set of algorithm, we have the resultive search.
That means all the combination, all the possible combinations.
So that is an optimal method.
And the sequential based method, sequential forward search,
or sequential by-willing nation are the suboptimal method.
Because actually, we select one first.
Then once this one is selected, right?
Normally, we don't remove that.
Then we select the second one based on the first one.
And we select that one based on the first two.
So this kind of a suboptimal method.
This is called stepwise, stepwise optimal.
It's not global optimal.
Global optimal, we need to use the resultive search.
All the possible combinations.
Normally, this is all possible combinations.
This number is huge, right?
Then you need to evaluate a huge number of features subset.
So this normally is a computational variable.
It's passive.
So this method is possible only the initial feature subset.
The feature set, the full set, only have a small number of features
that we can use.
Yesterday, actually, something asked us, actually,
when we should use a back-willing nation,
when we should use a forward selection, right?
And actually, these depend on application.
For example, initially, you have a huge number of features, right?
But normally, in the final,
we just use a small number of features, right?
So that means that we best use a forward search.
Because forward search, for example, initially,
we have 1,000 features.
Maybe finally, we just need to use 20.
Even if we use a forward search, right?
We just need to repeat all the first one, the second one,
the other one with 20.
So 20 steps, 20 iterations.
We can find the feature set.
But if you use a back-willing nation,
you need to go through 980 steps, right?
From the full search, you remove one.
Then you remove the second one.
You remove the 98 features.
Then you get 20 features remaining.
So this is a different application.
So how many features will be finally set in the feature subset?
But even the number of features,
the initial feature set is small, not very big, right?
So then you can use other methods.
Forward search or back-willing nation.
And sometimes, actually, we combine the two.
So we select the few, and then we remove some of them.
And then, again, for example, we select five,
and then we remove two.
We get three, right?
When we select another five, then we remove two.
It's kind of a combination.
The forward search and the back-willing nation are combined.
So there are different kinds of ways.
At least, yeah, search, or go in there.
Question, yes, D?
No more questions?
Sorry.
So, I think that's the difference.
So I know that there are many
teachers that teach the science.
I think that's the case.
So maybe there's a standard.
I think I gave the same standard.
But, of course, in the marketing process,
actually, they could have their own judgment law.
Now, they could be exactly the same law.
So I think for a class with 700 students,
it's hardly actually for one person to mark.
Oh, actually, it's very hard.
But in the exam, actually, each marker will mark
one single question.
So for example, actually, maybe one marker
will mark one question.
So for all, yeah.
But different questions, maybe slightly different standard.
Then there's reasonable.
And even today, you mark that.
Tomorrow, maybe after a few days.
I think the standard may be a bit different.
But actually, basically, you cannot have a profile of that.
Even in China, I go, actually, today, tomorrow,
different days, the marketing standard, maybe
will change a bit.
But actually, the variance should be smaller.
The TE, actually, I normally, we have this.
I tell them the marketing standard.
But of course, actually, even for me, right, actually,
you know, from day to day, right, could be changed a bit.
I think therefore, TE is the same.
But they all have a reason, like, no, no, normally, yeah.
Tomorrow, you get that mark.
Okay.
Any more questions?
Okay, even no questions.
I think that's all, yeah.
So thank you very much.
I think this year, I think I'm very happy to teach you.
I think that attendance anomaly, I think this class is good.
So of course, some of you, I think it's all your choice, right?
Someone to attend a physical lecture,
and then have some interaction with the professors
or with fellow students.
I think it's good.
But some prefer, because of the career,
some are used to kind of online lecture.
They prefer to watch a tree.
Maybe they prefer to, like, when you are studying here,
listen to a lecture, they prefer to watch more way
or whatever, right?
Then they prefer to use other time to study this course.
So that's the, you have your own freedom, right, to do that.
So, but actually, I see the attendance of this class is good.
So I feel very happy to teach.
And of course, actually, for this year,
this is quite a big challenge for you, right?
Also for the lectures, actually, for the professors,
because we have a very big class.
And we have more questions, actually.
Also, we have all three other prayers,
in particular for the Monday class, actually.
Actually, I'm informed, I'm well-informed
to have the Monday class, actually.
Let's see.
Because in Singapore, I remember Friday, the public holiday,
Saturday, Sunday, right?
So we're informed the Monday-Monday class from 8.30 only on Saturday.
So it's quite a big challenge.
For me, actually, now on Monday-Monday, 8.30, right?
I need to be here by 8.00 or 9.00.
I need to get up at 6.20.
Then breakfast, and then I leave my home at 10.00
before 7.20 to make sure I will be in class room by 8.30.
It's a big challenge.
I think for you, the same, right?
I need to come to the classroom for the Monday class
very early.
But anyway, I think we have gone through this process
from your quiz and also the assignment,
I think, I've done very well.
And today we have the revision, right?
You can prepare your exam based on the main points.
Actually, you cannot see, based on this,
you can get 100 marks, or you cannot never get that, right?
But at least the main points are reviewed,
actually, in the revision slides.
So we can hope that the revision slides can help you
to prepare the final exam.
Just now, actually, some of you asked questions about the exam, right?
Actually, I think that's good.
Actually, because this is the first time, right,
you take the exam in NTU and you need to know the rules
and regulations in NTU.
And it's very strict.
You cannot bring anything, right?
The computer, the handphone, the papers,
other material, like reference material,
to the examination hall, okay?
So, and you can start writing.
Only when you are allowed to start writing,
you need to stop writing when the announcement, okay?
You cannot continue writing.
Sometimes I do see some students,
but maybe that's okay in your university,
and I know where you started your university, right?
But now in NTU, I think this is very strict.
I should stop writing. You need to stop writing.
Okay, so these are the points you need to note in the exam.
Okay, so I really appreciate it.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
Thank you.