.
The first part is the data, right, the data collection.
And the second part is the abstraction.
So the objective of abstraction is to build a model, right,
build a model from the given data, okay.
And then the last component, that component is the
generalization.
The generalization is just to apply the model in the
abstraction step.
The model lands in the abstraction step and to the
future data, okay.
So application of the learning algorithm, application of
the model is also considered as a part of the machine
learning, okay.
So today I will look at the data preparation for
machine learning.
Data is very important, okay.
In machine learning there is one thing that is garbage
in, garbage out.
We, the data is garbage, the rubbish, very bad data,
right, very noisy data.
And then the model obtained or learned from this data
could be very bad, okay.
Of course actually the prediction based on the learned
model could be bad.
Bad, that means the performance is bad, right.
Then there is low accuracy, okay.
So this actually seeing is pressed the importance of
data and data quality in machine learning, okay.
So we first look at the machine learning activities,
right, okay.
I just mentioned machine learning actually start from
a data collection, right, because this is the first
component in the three actually component of the
machine learning system.
So machine learning actually activity start from data,
okay.
And actually in the last week actually when we talk
about learning and also we see there are three basic
types of learning.
The first type is called supervised learning,
supervised learning, right.
So in supervised learning when we collect the data
and then we also need to label the data, okay.
So labeling on the data actually of course depends
on the problem, right.
So for example we want to recognize the objects in
this classroom and then of course we kind of take
pictures of all objects in this classroom and then we
give a name to each picture, give a tag.
This tag is also called class label, right.
You take picture of this screen and then you just
know this is a screen, okay.
You take picture of this computer then you give a
tag or label of a computer, okay.
So this is called labeling.
So in supervised learning we should provide the label
training data, okay.
And another type of learning is called unsupervised
learning, right.
So in unsupervised learning we just collect the data
and we don't label the data so the data in unsupervised
learning is unlabeled, okay.
And then what objective of unsupervised learning,
actually we want to discover the patterns underlying
the data, okay.
Actually one important learning task in unsupervised
learning is the grouping of the data called classroom,
okay.
We try to put actually samples with a great
similarity into one group and samples with different
similarities.
Actually in another group, okay.
So this is a classroom or pattern discovery, okay.
Of course actually we have, we know actually there is
that type of learning that is a reinforcement learning
but that is not covered in this course.
So this course we only cover the supervised learning
and the unsupervised learning.
For supervised learning we collect the data and also
we label the data, okay.
And in unsupervised learning we just collect the data
with every new need to do the labeling of the data.
Okay.
So after we have collected data and also label the data
for supervised learning and then actually we should
perform the following activities.
The first, we need to understand the type of the
data in a given input data set.
Okay, later we will see actually the data can be
categorized into different types.
Okay, some data like a categorical variable data,
like gender, right.
So every student in the classroom can have a value
of male or female, right.
So this value, for this gender only two values, right,
two possible values.
So this kind of variable is called categorical variables.
Okay.
And for some variables, and this actually variable
could be continuous, this feature or attribute could
be continuous.
For example, and your height, okay, and you could be
like 175 cm, 162 cm.
Actually, so this actually number actually can be any
number in a certain range.
Okay, so this kind of feature is called continuous feature.
So we are looking at this type of feature later.
And actually the data type directly determines what
model or what actually learning algorithm we should
actually adopt.
Okay, so at the beginning we should actually look at the
nature of the data, look at the time of the data.
Okay.
And then we went to explore the quality and understand
the nature and also understand the quality of the data.
I just mentioned, right, and there is the same
garbage in, garbage out.
So this actually the data quality certainly is
very important.
Okay.
And if the data is noisy, and then we should take
measures actually to address these issues.
Later we will see actually some quality issues include
like outliers and some values are extremely high or
extremely low, and these probably are noise.
Okay.
And some data have missing values even.
We don't have a value.
Okay.
So actually, so this kind of data actually, you know,
these are issues in the data.
We should now take some measures actually to address
these issues before we can use the data or can input
the data to a machine learning algorithm and to
obtain or to learn a model.
Okay.
So these are also the activities, right.
And also the explore relationship actually among
the data elements.
So this data element normally means actually the
attributes.
So later we will look at this issue, attributes or
features or variables.
Okay.
And actually some, when you collect the data, you
probably not very sure which data or which attribute,
which variable is important.
For example, we want to predict actually a person's
salary, right, a person's salary after your first job
salary, right, after the graduation of your MSE.
So of course actually at the beginning we have no
ideas what are related to the salary.
Maybe we will actually collect a large amount of
data, right, your height, your gender, your weight,
right, your GPA, and your undergraduate GPA or
postgraduate GPA.
You collect a lot of data, right.
So but actually some of the data may be actually
irrelevant, right.
So your height, your body weight, your gender is not
relevant to your salary, but actually your CTP may be
relevant.
Okay.
So during this data collection stage actually we
have no idea about this.
Okay.
So we can look at the later tree.
We can look at the correlation, the relationship
between the class label and also each of the attributes
you have collected.
Okay.
If some of them are irrelevant, that means that
the correlation between the class label and the, for
example, the body weight, your height, actually
correlation is very low, right, close to zero.
This means that this feature is irrelevant and then
we should remove this.
Okay.
And sometimes the tree, the data you collected, right,
are quite correlated.
Okay.
In other words, the tree, when you collect one
feature and then another feature will provide very
little extra information.
So this kind of feature is redundant.
Okay.
So we should also try our best to remove the
redundancy underlying the data.
Okay.
And also we should remove the significant features
from the data.
Okay.
So these are the, through the exploration of the data
relationship.
So later we will see, so what actually and the
data we can use to explore the relationship between
variables.
Okay.
Then actually now we can try our best actually to
eliminate these variables.
Okay.
And so actually find the potential issues in the
data.
I actually already just mentioned the issue, right,
these are related to the quality.
Like actually some data could have missing values.
Okay.
And some of the missing values, that means that
for this data and for a specific feature or attribute
there will be no value.
Okay.
So missing value.
And some actually could be outliers.
Okay.
Maybe during the recording of this data, right,
and you, there's some errors, right,
you record down the data wrongly, right.
And the percentage, you use a CM, a 175 CM.
And later you write down wrongly, right,
like a 75.5, right.
So this could be an error, right.
So actually, so we can also try our best to actually
address these issues and before we can, you know,
input the data to the learning algorithm.
And then of course after we have identified the issues,
the noise, right, the noise in the data,
the correlations, and also actually the redundancies
and also the insignificant features, for example, right.
And then we can actually take some measures
to address these issues.
Okay.
And then after that we will perform a pre-processing.
So this pre-processing means actually the scaling,
the scaling.
So later we will see this.
We should perform normalization or a standardization of the data
and so that the data could be in the same range.
Okay.
So here, for example, you record your GPA of 4.4.
NTU is actually known as the system five, right,
five in most actually, not four, okay.
So your GPA is 4.5.
Then you record down your height.
It's 170 something, right, your body weight is 60 something,
70 something kg.
Actually the data is in very different range, right.
So actually we could have some issues actually
with the data in very different range.
So we should perform some pre-processing.
Okay.
So later we will talk about this again,
looking at the details, how to actually perform this scaling
so that the features could be in a similar range.
Okay.
And then after the data is obtained,
then we can start the linear, right.
So the linear normally, you know, the data.
If you have the data, you collect the data, right,
and you also perform labeling of the data, right.
And you know, this data will be divided into two main parts.
One part is used as a training data.
Another part is used as testing data.
So in the last week we have already talked about this concept, right,
like training data, testing data.
The training data actually aims to,
or training data are used to estimate the values,
the parameter values in the model, right.
Normally in a model we could have many parameters,
in particular in deep neural networks.
We should have a large number of parameters.
In some models the parameters could be 100 billion,
you know, so big models.
Okay.
So we should actually estimate the parameters.
But actually normally the data should be divided into two parts,
training and testing.
And testing is just actually used actually to evaluate the quality
of the model length.
Okay.
So these are actually divided into two parts.
And quite often we have one extra part,
which is called a validation data.
And the validation data normally is used to determine the hyperparameters.
Normally the hyperparameters actually is not learned directly from the data.
Okay.
And so we have some parameters that we need to determine.
So these actually, validation data will be used to determine the hyperparameters.
Okay.
So in such a scenario the data will be divided into three parts,
training data and the validation data and the testing data.
Okay.
And normally 70 percent of the data will be used as training data,
15 percent for validation,
and the remaining 15 percent of the data will be used for testing.
Or sometimes it's 60 percent for training,
20 percent for validation,
and then the remaining 20 percent for actually testing.
Okay.
So this is the, of course, this is for super-ideal learning.
And for anti-parade learning actually we don't have,
we don't have label, right, and also we don't divide them into two parts.
Okay.
And then we should consider different models or learning algorithms for selection.
And so for each learning task,
either super-ideal learning or anti-parade learning,
there are many methods.
Okay.
And so actually in the organization there is one theorem,
which is called No Free Launch Theorem.
No Free Launch.
Okay.
So what does it mean?
It means that there are no single algorithms that perform the best for all scenarios.
So these are actually the organization.
Of course, we knew machine learning also is a kind of organization problem.
So this No Free Launch Theorem also applicable to machine learning problem.
In other words, there are no single algorithm,
there are no single model that perform the best for all applications.
Okay.
So in real application we always need to try different learning algorithms
and then look to find the best performing one.
Okay.
Of course, when you do the data selection
and we need to have a good understanding about the data,
the type of the data and normally the data is mixed.
It contains continuous features and then the categorical features,
okay, or discrete features.
Okay.
And so we need to think about in this learning algorithm,
so in this model, what are the other assumptions?
Okay.
Whether the data is setting by this assumption.
Right.
If the assumptions are not satisfied in the data set,
then of course probably this model or this learning algorithm
could produce a performance.
Sometimes the problem is good, but it could not be the optimal results.
Okay.
And then we should understand the nature of the data.
We should also understand the details of the learning algorithm
and understand the assumptions that we have made
actually when we develop this model or this learning algorithm.
Okay.
So there is a need to consider actually different learning algorithms or models.
And finally, you know, after we have learned the model, right,
and we should actually evaluate the performance.
This is just like, you know, you learn this code, right.
Finally, you will actually, you know, sit for the exam.
You will see the exam, right, in the Latin.
So this actually the exam will test your learning outcome.
Okay.
So this is the evaluation.
And actually in this course, of course,
we will cover actually different learning evaluation procedures,
and also we will introduce actually different metrics
for the performance evaluation.
Okay.
So this diagram is just a summary of the process, right.
So we have the input data.
And then in step one, actually we prepare the preparation well, right,
for the modeling.
So this is just today's focus, preparation for the data.
And then after that actually we will perform a linear,
the objective of linear is to find the mathematical model, right,
and to find the model.
And then we can apply the model and to the technical data
and to evaluate the performance of this model.
And sometimes actually the performance is not satisfactory.
For example, in applications actually we hope actually,
you know, the accuracy should be greater than 99 percent.
Of course, this is a very ideal scenario, right.
Indeed, in some applications actually this accuracy should be very high.
Right.
For example, if you use your fingerprint, you use iris,
you know, you use actually many biometrics, right,
as a password for example to your bank account.
So this accuracy must be very high.
Okay.
So in some applications actually maybe the accuracy is low, right.
So the model produces actually anti-satisfactory performance.
Okay.
Then we need to think about, okay, so maybe, you know,
the issues could arise from the data and could also arise from the model.
Okay.
If it's from the data and then suddenly actually we should actually take some
measures to address these issues.
For example, there are outliers.
Okay.
So outliers, that means some of the data has extreme high values or low values.
So how we should handle this?
Okay.
And then we should actually take some measures to address all of these issues
and then to get the so-called data, the refined data, right,
then use the refined data to analyze another model with the improved performance.
Okay.
And really it's not actually just actually these are four steps.
Normally these four steps are going to, you know,
you know, iterations.
So we need to go through a few rounds, you know, to produce a model,
a good model.
Okay.
And sometimes you probably think, you know,
we just introduced in the last week, you know,
there are some platforms like computer language,
Python, MATLAB, R or even other, you know, computer languages or platforms,
and where the machine learning algorithms actually are built in the platform.
We can simply call the function and then learn.
Maybe you already have some experience on machine learning, right?
You get the data, put the data, call the function, and then get a result.
Okay.
Your learning task is complete in one second, right?
So fast.
Machine learning is not so simple.
A project could last one year, right?
Could last one year.
Actually one day, one week, one month, even a few months time.
I think you have so many long time actually to produce a good model.
Okay.
So it's not a task of just actually put the data in the function.
Not so simple, right?
You need to actually explore the data,
and you need to explore different learning algorithms.
And finally, actually you will find actually one that actually suits your application the most.
If all the existing machine learning algorithms actually do not suit your application very well,
then you should actually develop your own learning algorithm or learn your own model
in order to produce the best performance or optimal performance for these specific applications.
Okay.
So these are actually learning the three steps that normally go through a few rounds.
In order to produce actually ideal performance for a given task.
Okay.
So let's look at the basic types of data in machine learning.
And so a dataset is a collection of related information or records.
So this is a dataset, right?
And the information may be on some entity or some subject.
So here maybe we look at one example.
So this is a student dataset.
Okay.
So it's a collection of records.
So a dataset is a collection of records which contain related or relevant information.
Okay.
So these are student dataset.
So these are the dataset records actually on the information of many students on different entity or subject, right?
So like we call the rule number, matriculation number, and the name, and the agenda, and also the age.
So we call all this information.
This is a student dataset.
Okay.
So a dataset is a collection, right?
Not just one sample.
Not just one, right?
We have a lot of records.
So this is a dataset.
And this is another dataset, the student performance dataset.
So we have the rule number, the matriculation number, and then the result, the score for math, the score for science, and the percentile or percentage.
Okay.
So this is another dataset.
And in this table, we have a lot of rules, right?
So normally the rule normally is that each rule is one sample.
Okay.
So each rule of a dataset is called a sample.
A sample, right?
So a sample.
So actually the rule one, actually the matriculation number, and also the math, and the science result, and also percentage.
So one rule will correspond to one sample.
Okay.
So that means a dataset normally contains a large number of samples, right?
Not just one sample.
One sample is not called a dataset.
It's a collection.
Okay.
So we must have multiple samples.
And also each data actually has multiple attributes.
So in this dataset, so the rule number actually, so then each attribute corresponds to one column in the table in the dataset.
Okay.
So we have the record number, rule number, and we have the math, and then we have the science, and then we have the percentage.
So these are the four attributes.
So each rule is one sample, and each column is one attribute.
And this attribute is also called feature, or actually variables.
Okay.
In statistics, actually, you know, model fitting, normally they call actually like variables.
In machine learning, these are quite often called actually attributes or feature.
Okay.
So in this example, actually, you know, we have, you know, four features, right?
Rule number, the science result, the math result, and also the percentage.
There are four actually features.
Okay.
So how many features in a dataset?
This depends on application.
Okay.
So in the past, actually, you know, I used to actually handle some, like, GMAC query data.
Actually, the terminology could be 40,000, but the sample could be just a few, like a few hundred.
But the columns could be 40,000.
Okay.
So these are really dependent application, how many features, right?
And to use, in particular, at the beginning, initially, how many features you use in the data collection stage, right?
Okay.
So these are now the sample and attribute of features.
So these are about the data, right?
And let's look at the data type.
So data can be broadly divided into two types.
One is qualitative data, qualitative data.
Another is quantitative data.
Okay.
So what is qualitative data?
It's about quality.
Qualitative data is about the information quality, quality.
And so this quality normally cannot be measured, cannot be measured.
Okay.
So this is qualitative data.
And here are some examples.
Okay.
For example, about the performance, right?
And we can use actually, like, you know, good average or per or very good, excellent.
All these actually can be used.
So normally, actually, the qualitative data, the values are named values, named values.
Not numerical value, right?
Not a number.
But given actually, you know, this is called named value.
Named value.
Okay.
So good, very good.
About gender, right?
Male or female, right?
So these are named values.
Okay.
And talk about the university, right?
So NTU, NUS, SMU, SUTD in Singapore.
So these are the named values.
Okay.
So these named values are qualitative.
So qualitative data is also called categorical.
Categorical.
Okay.
And actually even qualitative data, just now I mentioned, right?
Actually, we give some example.
Actually, it can be further divided into two types.
Okay.
One type is called nominal data.
Another type is called ordinal.
Okay.
So the difference is between the two.
So what is nominal data?
So nominal data is one which have no numerical value, but a named value.
Named value, right?
Just now, that's very good.
Actually, these are all named value, right?
Certainly, it's named value.
This is one.
Okay.
Named value.
So for example, for black group A, black type, right?
Black type A, type B, type O, type AB, right?
So these are actually the named value, nominal.
And also called by the nationality, Chinese, Singaporean, Indian, American.
So all these actually are named values.
So they're nominal data.
Okay.
And another example, yeah, these are gender, right?
Male, female.
Okay.
So these are important, actually, characteristic for the nominal data.
So nominal data, for nominal data, we cannot perform these mathematical operations like
addition, subtraction, multiplication.
Okay.
And of course, actually, then we cannot have the mean value.
For example, in this class, actually, many students have no black type of A. Some have
black type B. Some have type C. No, C, sorry.
Some have AB, right?
Then we talk about, is there a value?
What is the average black type of this class, of the student class group?
We don't have these, right?
We don't have average black type.
So this is because actually we cannot perform the summations, actually the addition.
Okay.
So then we cannot have the mean value.
Of course, we cannot have the standard variance.
We cannot have the average.
Okay.
So these are characteristic of the, actually, the nominal data.
We cannot perform these kind of operations, right, mathematical operations.
Okay.
So the nationality, some are Chinese, some are Indian in this classroom, some Singaporeans.
So what is the average nationality?
There are no such thing, right?
No nationality.
You can see the average result, right?
Average GPA, but we don't have average nationality, right?
We don't have this number.
Okay.
But we can use others.
Later we will see that we can use the so-called mode actually for this kind of data.
Okay.
But we cannot have the average.
We cannot have the mean, right?
Okay.
So these are the nominal data.
See the nominal.
And then another type is called ordinal.
Ordinal.
And ordinal is also kind of similar to the nominal data, but actually the data can be
ordered.
The data can be ordered.
So ordinal data actually also assign name the value to attribute name the value, but
actually this name the value can be actually arranged in a sequence.
In ascending order or descending order.
Increasing or decreasing.
Okay.
So we can also see one value is greater or better than another value.
So this kind of data actually are called ordinal.
Okay.
So here are some examples.
And we talk about the result.
Happy, unhappy, or very happy.
Happy, very happy, happy, unhappy.
Okay.
Or when we talk about the, like, you know, the grid.
We talk about get A, you get B or get C, right?
And we know A is better than B than C. Better B is better than C.
There is a sequence.
Although they are named the value, but there could be a sequence.
Right?
One value could be better or greater than another value.
So this is called ordinal.
Okay.
And actually this is probably similar to numerical values.
To the actually quantitative data.
And that could be an order.
Okay.
When we talk about the height of a person, right?
So later we will see 175, 160, 60.
And we can have actually arranged in a sequence of increasing or decreasing order.
Okay.
And this is actually quantitative data.
Quantitative data.
Okay.
So this ordinal in this aspect is very similar to the quantitative data.
So the hardness of metal are very hard, hard to solve.
Right?
So we can put them into a sequence.
Okay.
And for this ordinal data, okay, and we cannot find the mean.
But we can find the median because we can put them into sequence.
Right?
Into a sequence.
And then actually we can put the median.
We can get a median value.
So what is the median value in the middle?
Okay.
So these are ordinals.
So we can look at these properties.
Right?
So these probably are the, you have seen these kind of variables, but probably have never
thought about whether we can perform operations on them.
Okay.
So this also, this property determines the linear algorithm or the model we should use.
Actually, in some model, we assume that it's all continuous.
Okay.
And the quantitative data.
And then we assume the following normal distribution, for example.
Okay.
And so if the data is mixed, contains something like this.
Right?
Then we should not actually assume the following normal distribution.
Because we cannot use actually the distance calculations.
Okay.
So this is the, yeah, ordinal.
And then the first timer, qualitative data.
Then the next one is quantitative data.
Quantitative data, we know the information about quantity.
Quantity.
And it can be measured.
It can be measured.
Okay.
And the quantitative data is also termed numerical data.
So categorical and not the numerical.
Okay.
Categorical, that means actually the data values are the categories.
Good, very good.
Actually, no.
Average.
Right?
Or per.
So these are category.
Okay.
And the black type.
Right?
Category A, category B, categories O, category AB.
So these are categorical.
Okay.
And then for the quantitative data, they are also called the numerical.
Numerical, numbers, right?
Numbers.
Okay.
So for this quantitative data, and we can further divide them into two types.
One type is called interval data.
Another type is called ratio data.
Interval.
Okay.
A Buddha tree, of course, data tree and numerical data.
And interval data, numerical data, not only the order is known, but the difference between
them is also known.
The difference.
Okay.
For example, we talk about the temperature, right?
Now it's 25 degree.
And then if there is a 10 degree, there's a difference of 15 degree, right?
So this 15 degree, you can understand that this is exactly the meaning of this 15 degrees
difference.
Okay.
So this is interval data.
So for interval data, I did not quantitative data.
Normally this operation like addition, subtraction possible could be conducted or performed.
And also a tree, the central tendency, the mean.
Later we will look at this further.
Central tendency or the mean of the data could be calculated.
Okay.
Because we can use the summation, right?
This is the numerical data tree.
We can look at the mean, which is the central tendency.
And also a tree, we can look at the standard deviations.
Okay.
The variance.
So this is a tree, the interval data, ratio data.
And ratio data actually represent the numerical data for which the exact value can be measured.
So this similar to the interval data.
And the tree in the interval data, no absolute zero.
But in the ratio data, there is absolute zero.
Okay.
So this is the definition of the ratio data.
And also the data can perform addition, subtraction, the multiplication operation.
Okay.
So central tendency can be calculated.
And the tree in practice, the tree, although this data can be put into different categories.
So quite often we don't try to differentiate the two types of the quantitative data.
The numerical data.
Okay.
There's a big difference between the two, but actually not much.
So in practice, we normally don't actually try to differentiate whether this data is
an interval data or whether this data is a ratio data.
We just consider them numerical data.
But for the two categorical type of data, nominal and ordinal, actually sometimes need
to be differentiated.
Okay.
And for example, actually even a tree in the literature, I think in some way we all study
a decision tree.
Sometimes the tree, one, the data decision tree, the tree structure and the classifier.
And in one node, we need to put the data into two categories, right, into two parts normally
based on a certain rule.
And if the data is an ordinal, and then we can use something like if this feature is
greater than some value.
Okay.
If the result is greater than good, that means even very good, right?
And then we can divide them.
Because ordinal.
Okay.
We can see which value is bigger than or greater than another value, right?
If this is nominal, we cannot see, you know, use greater than something, right, or less
than something.
But we can use actually if a value equals something, and then we divide them in, then
equal, and then equal, right, divide the data into two sets.
Okay.
So we should differentiate the nominal and ordinal.
When you sum classifies, we should differentiate the two types of data.
But for the numerical data, whether the quality is interval or ratio, normally we don't try
to differentiate the two types of data.
So this diagram just shows the categorization of the data.
So attributes, then we have quality or categorical data, then we have quantitative data or numerical
data.
So for each of them, we can divide them into two types, nominal, ordinal, interval, or
ratio.
Okay.
So we need to understand the nature of the data, the type of the data.
And this actually, you know, I just mentioned, right, if you know the type, whether it's
ordinal, and then if ordinal, we can use greater than something, right, in a value.
Okay.
And what is greater, actually, in the computer part of this actually, very good or good or
bad, actually, powerful is denoted by numerical value law.
Okay.
For example, good, okay, good, you know, we started from bad, very good.
For example, it's four, okay.
And then good is three, and then actually, you know, the average is two, and then per
is one.
Okay.
So something that we can use greater than something, right.
If this actually is like a performance, it's greater than two.
Okay.
Because this is not ordinal, we can use this, right.
So if this is nominal, then we can reuse whether this value is equal to this blood type.
We cannot see our blood type is greater than something.
We cannot see that.
Okay.
So this is another kind of categorization for the data.
So in this data, they seem to consider that discrete or continuous.
Okay.
The data, whether this feature or this data is discrete or this data is continuous.
So we use this actually, the data is simply putting these two groups or two categories.
Okay.
For the discrete, that means that this feature or this attribute, we have limited possible
values.
Just now, we use a gender, right, the gender.
Male, female, just two possible values, right.
The blood types.
Okay.
A, B, A, B, O.
Only has four types.
So these possible values, they were limited.
Two and four, right.
And just now in the result, okay, good average per three categories, three possible results.
Okay.
So this is the kind of data actually is a discrete.
So we still have a finite.
Okay.
So actually our count of countably infinite.
They mean this number could be very large, huge.
Okay.
But there is a correspondence shape with a natural number.
Although the number is bigger, right, then this one, actually this number could correspond
to a one.
This number could correspond to, this number could correspond to one billion.
Right.
Actually there is a one to one correspondence shape with the natural number.
Although the number is huge.
So this, it is still considered as a discrete.
Okay.
So quite often we think about a discrete.
We think about the only limited value, right, limited.
But this value could be huge, countable, infinite.
Okay.
So that means actually as long as there is a one to one correspondence shape with actually
a natural number.
Natural number could be a very big number, right.
So as long as there is such a correspondence shape.
And then actually, you know, it will be considered as a discrete data.
And so nominal data certainly not, only not, right, nominal, all actually the, you know,
it's a, okay.
If this actually discrete, only two values are male or female, right.
So, or female or past.
So this kind of value they call binary attributes.
Okay.
So these are special kind of discrete attribute.
Only two possible values.
Okay.
So the next actually is a continuous, continuous attributes can take many values, right.
Can take actually any possible values in a range.
Okay.
And actually, so we're just actually, your body weight, right.
These are all temperature of the room.
They compare the temperature, right.
And the 25 or .5, maybe at the beginning, later change to 26.5, and later, you know,
change to 26.3.
So any possible values.
Okay.
Yeah, I said the range, right.
So these are just continuous, continuous.
Okay.
So sometimes actually you differentiate actually, you know, ordinal, nominal, interval, ratio.
But sometimes you simply put this into two categories, discrete and continuous.
Okay.
So in general, nominal and ordinal attributes are discrete, right, because they just have
a limiting value.
They are called categorical, right.
Categorical.
Okay.
And interval ratio tree, they are quantitative data, so they are continuous.
Or they are also numeric data.
Okay.
So these are just the data types, right, the data types.
So next actually we look at the exploration of the structure of the data.
Okay.
So when you give a data, right, when I give a data, so or when you collect the data, actually
quite often, actually, you know, get the data, for example, from the website, right, and
actually quite often actually the data is also attached with the so-called data dictionary,
dictionary.
Okay.
And actually this data dictionary actually presents the information of this dataset,
the information.
Okay.
In particular, the information about the features, the attributes, the types of attributes.
So these are the data dictionary.
But if you collect data, right, you collect data, and you also want to keep the data for
us to use in the future.
Okay.
So probably you also need to actually now make such a data dictionary attached to a
certain dataset.
Okay.
So data dictionary actually introduce all its present information about the dataset,
in particular, about the property or natures of the features.
Okay.
Including the name of the feature, the time of the feature.
The detail information of each of the attributes.
Okay.
So this is the data dictionary and the data type.
Some random details.
Actually, sometimes you just give a feature, right?
You must give the, sometimes actually you need to introduce how this feature is obtained.
Okay.
And remember there is some dataset.
So the dataset actually, it is not very raw data.
This data actually is derived from the image.
Okay.
This feature is the top on which property is extracted from the image feature.
Image.
Okay.
And this feature, second feature, is what feature, which property of the image.
We introduce this.
Also give the name.
This feature is about the blood pressure of the patient.
And this is a feature about the temperature, body temperature of this patient.
Okay.
They talk about, they give, not only just give the value, right?
In this dictionary, they also talk about on this feature is the name of the feature.
How this feature actually obtained.
Okay.
Extra information about the feature.
So of course the tree, sometimes maybe actually the detail, the dictionary is not actually
available.
And then tree, we should use some like functions in the toolbox to discover the type of the
features, the nature of the features.
Okay.
So these are the dictionary.
So here actually I just show one data dictionary.
Actually just actually the, if you send the machine learning, I think basically we should
know machine learning or data repository.
Okay.
This is the UCI, University of California at Evering.
Actually UCI, machine learning or data repository.
Okay.
And there are a lot of data set.
For each data set, for example, tree for the author in the car, right?
Author, the MPG data set.
And they give this information, right?
The number of samples, the feature types, right?
And whether there are missing values, right?
So here then for the wearables, as we are talking about, the wearable name, like a displacement.
And then, so the type of the data are continuous.
Okay.
And the cylinder and all the integer types, okay, whether there are missing values or
not, they all give this kind of information.
So these are data dictionary.
I think it's very useful for us, right, to understand the nature of the data, the data
types.
Okay.
At the beginning, I see the data type is important.
And when we actually look for or select or choose a suitable learning algorithm or suitable
models, actually, we need to have a good understanding about the data type and also
have a good understanding about the model.
So this model, whether it can be applied to nominal data or ordinal data, right?
So we should have this understanding.
Okay.
So where to get the information about the type of the feature?
Actually, we can get it from the data dictionary.
Okay.
I just imagine you're not available, and then we maybe need to use some software, right,
to discover that we can use my plot, the data, right, to decide whether this data is continuous
or discrete.
Okay.
If we know the nature, right, the nature, this should perform good or very good.
And then, oh, we know this is ordinal, right?
So through this exploration, we can understand the data.
Okay.
So, okay.
So now, actually, we have a 10-minute break.
Okay.
After break, then we will look further into the exploration of the data structure.
Thank you.
Okay.
So here, actually, I copy, you know, part of the outer MPG dataset, okay, to show this.
And this dataset, I have a few features, right?
MPG, cylinder, displacement, horsepower, weight, and all the acceleration, model year, origin.
Okay.
So these actually all actually do the features, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
Okay.
And then the last one is the car name.
Car name.
Okay.
And actually here, some of the variables are already given all the numerical, right?
Origin.
And actually these origins, normally, these are actually categorical variables.
Although they are numerical here, they are not named by any, right?
But they are categorical.
Okay.
So because for the origin, which is the origin of the car, like one is USA, two is Japan,
and number three, maybe Germany.
Okay.
So this origin of the cars.
So just a limited value, right?
And also the car name, also limited.
These are the actually nominal values, right?
Nominal.
You cannot see one country is bigger than another, right?
The value is bigger than another one, right?
So the origin and also the car name.
So these are the nominal data, right?
So the categorical are nominal.
Okay.
But for some of the variables, actually, you can see, like, cylinder, right?
Cylinder actually is in here, they just show like four, six, eight.
Okay.
And actually this shows one is bigger than another one.
Actually cylinder actually is categorical, but it is ordinal.
Okay.
It's ordinal.
And then we have some other like horsepower and also the displacement.
So these are the continuous.
These are the quantitative data or numerical data.
Okay.
Or continuous.
So some of them are discrete.
Some of them actually are continuous, right?
So for the discrete, some of them actually are nominal and some of them are ordinal.
Okay.
So these are just already analyzed, right?
Origin means the country.
So although each country here is denoted by one numerical value, it is still numerical.
So these are categorical.
Actually, this actually is nominal.
The car name here, they are given the name and name the value, right?
But actually it's nominal, right?
We cannot see one name is bigger than another name.
Normally we don't see this.
Okay.
So this data normally is called mixed.
Mixed.
Okay.
If a data set contains actually more than one type of data, then this data actually
set is called mixed data.
And the data is mixed.
Okay.
We have different types of data.
And for the nominal data, actually, I think the ordinal is denoted by the number here,
right?
And actually I think this point, I want to emphasize, right?
I talked about this a few times actually.
I want to emphasize this.
Although here they are given numerical values, but normally we cannot see one value is greater
than another value.
We cannot see that.
They are denoted by different numbers.
These different numbers only show they are different.
This country, two, is different from another country, one, is different from country three.
So this value only shows the difference.
We don't have a sense that one value is greater than another value.
Okay.
So I think these are very important properties.
So when we build a model, sometimes we need to analyze this nature and then we decide
actually what kind of model we should use actually in the learning.
Okay.
So these are some analysis, right?
Real numbers.
Okay.
And actually the cylinder here and the origin, they are given numerical values actually.
Although they are numerical, they are denoted by numerical value.
But actually in practicality, we should consider them actually like as categorical.
Categorical.
Okay.
So next actually we explore the numerical data.
Now we know that data can be categorized into categorical or numerical, right?
So next actually we first look at how to explore the numerical data.
And the first exploration is to understand the central tendency.
The central tendency.
Okay.
The central tendency, how to measure the central tendency.
I think the most commonly used measure is just the mean.
Okay.
Mean actually the most frequently used metric and for the measure of the central tendency.
So the mean value.
The mean.
Okay.
Mean just average, right?
Instead it takes.
So this is called expectation.
Expectation.
Given a random variable, so what is expectation?
Okay.
So it depends how to calculate expectation, right?
And we have formula to calculate.
Okay.
But actually, you know, this actually, I think the mean, expectation or mean is just average.
Average.
Right?
So here we can put the summation first and then divide it by the total number of numbers.
Then actually it's just got average.
Okay.
So from here for the mean we first get a summation addition, right?
So addition.
So certainly, you know, this addition should not be performed actually on the categorical
data, right?
Categorical data.
We cannot actually get the average.
Okay.
Because we cannot get the summation, right?
So we don't have the mean for categorical variables.
Okay.
So this is for continuous, right?
For numerical values, number four continuous.
For quantitative data.
Quantitative, the continuous is in numerical, right?
So for numerical data we can calculate the mean.
So mean is the most frequently used measure for the central tendency of the data.
Okay.
And then another measure is called median.
Median value, right?
So no median.
Normally we need to actually arrange the data in a sequence.
Yeah.
Increasing order or decreasing order.
And then the median is just the value in the middle, right?
In the middle.
So here we have five numbers and then we arrange the data in an increasing order, right?
Then the 67 actually is in the middle number, right?
So this is just the median.
Okay.
So these are the median.
So mean is impacted if too many data elements are having values close to the far end of
the range.
Okay.
In other words, even in a data set there are many extreme values.
Many extreme values.
Okay.
And not just one.
So there are a few extreme values.
Extremely high values or extreme low values.
Okay.
So this extreme low or extreme high value could be caused by error.
Error, right?
So if we use, you know, we take the average to find the mean, right?
So certainly these are not small number.
Not many number of big value, small value.
Certainly will have a big impact on this mean value, right?
So mean value is easier to be affected by noisy data.
The mean value.
Okay.
In particular, if the data has some outliers, right?
We want to cover the average wealth of the people in this classroom together with the
and Bill Gates.
Right?
So there are increase.
Actually, certainly this is not actually a good measure for the central tendency of
the wealth of the people in this classroom.
Right?
Because there's outliers.
Okay.
So in such a scenario, actually, we should use actually the median value, right?
You arrange them, right?
Arrange all the wealth of average people in this classroom together with the Bill Gates.
We still find that this median value is less affected by those extreme values of outliers.
Okay.
So this is actually the median, right?
Median.
And actually in practice, actually we compare actually the difference between the median
value and the mean values.
So normally, you know, the median values and the mean values should be close to each other.
Although they are not the same value, right?
Actually, but normally there should be no big difference between the two.
Okay.
So we should use plot deviation between the two.
If the deviation between the two, the difference between the two is big.
And then actually we can look further into the data.
Okay.
For example, right?
And if there is a big difference between the mean and the median.
So most likely there are some outliers in the data.
There are some extreme high values or extreme low values.
So both types of values, right, will affect the mean value.
Okay.
So you can observe the difference between the median and the mean, right?
From here we can, you know, deduce probably the data contains some outliers.
Okay.
Then we should try to find these outliers and then take some measures to impute these
outliers.
Okay.
So this is, I think, the use of plot deviation, right?
Look at the tendency, the tendency.
Look at the mean.
Look at that.
And then we can look at the median.
Then we can discover some potential issues underlying the data.
Okay.
Another common use of a tree measure is called mood.
Mood actually is more frequently used actually for others, right?
We see for the nominal or for the ordinal.
And so we cannot get the summation, right?
We cannot get a summation.
And we cannot get the average.
Certainly we cannot take the mean, right?
We cannot take the mean.
Okay.
But actually we can take the median.
And also actually we can take the so-called mood.
Mood.
Okay.
Mood actually is the most frequent value in the data.
And for example, in the class, right, actually we can test the blood type of each student.
Okay.
And we have blood type A, we have blood type B, A, B, and O, right?
Actually, of course, actually we know and probably the result is that actually we cannot
take the average.
I see every blood type of the student in this classroom.
We cannot have these value.
But we can see the most frequent, right?
Probably the blood B has the largest number, largest proportion.
Okay.
So the mood, the mood, right, actually is the most frequent number, most frequent number
here.
Okay.
We can take this as a central tendency for actually the categorical, right, for the categorical
values.
Okay.
Of course, for continuous we can still look at that, right?
But for continuous and probably mean and median actually are better measures for the central
tendencies.
Okay.
So these are the three measures, mean, median, mean, and mood for the central tendency.
And this diagram shows us, you know, the mean value and also the median value for all the
features, right?
And as you can see also we can find the deviation, the difference, the difference.
And for the MPG, the difference is only 2.17 percent.
So this actually is a low number, right, the low, this actually difference is low.
But for some values, right, for some features or attributes like displacement, the median
is 148.5 and the mean value is 193.4.
So there is a very big difference, actually the difference is 23.22 percent.
So this is very high.
Okay.
So by looking at this summary of the mean and the median, then we check the difference
and then we can know actually which feature has a high difference between the mean and
the median, right?
And then we can look further into the data to see whether there are some issues in the
data, okay, for that particular attribute.
And also in this table we show the horsepower, there is no value for the median, there is
no value for the mean.
Okay.
Certainly, actually, we have a RAM program, the program cannot calculate, is unable to
calculate the mean value and the median value.
Okay.
Then we should look further, right, look into the data to check.
So what are the issues?
And then we should try our best and to address these issues, right?
Okay.
So for this actually we can look at the tree like why we have these actually, you know,
question mark there, right?
So this is because actually we look further into the data and we find actually for the
horsepower, there are six samples whose horsepower have no values, so six samples have no value
for the horsepower for this attribute.
So if no value, actually this is the so-called mission value problem, mission value.
So later we will actually talk about this further actually.
So if there are mission values in the feature, so how we should address this issue?
Mission values, right?
If there are mission values, don't believe, you know, the question mark, right, or just
empty, right, for that cell, for that element in a matrix, then the program has no problem
to calculate the mean.
That's the reason why we see the question mark there.
Okay.
So by just now do a bit of exploration, right, actually we have a very good understanding
about the data, right?
Look at the data dictionary and then we can understand the data types, right?
Nominal, ordinal, you know, all actually we see the numerical, right, or we see the continuous.
We can look at this, right?
And by looking at the mean, the central tendency, look at the difference between the mean and
the median, right, and we can have further understanding, you know, about the data.
So potentially, about potential issues, right, like, you know, autolies in the data, okay?
And also in this example shows that we probably, you know, the data could have the mission
value problem.
Okay.
For some features, we don't have actually the mean, we don't have the median, right?
And this because the program, the code cannot actually, you know, calculate this value because
of the mission values in this feature.
Okay.
So this is collaboration, right?
Just give a data set, just at the beginning, just give this, right, give it to you, right?
I think this data, right?
We just knew the value there, right?
And after, you know, through many steps, right, look at the feature, the natures, and
then by looking at the median and mean values, certainly now we have better understanding
about the data set, right, better understanding, okay?
So that is actually, you know, before actually, you know, certainly we should, you know, understand
our data, right?
We cannot just call a function and then put the data in and then get a model based on
the model to make prediction.
Our task is to get a good model to make accurate prediction and not just, okay, get a model,
get a prediction.
Your work, job here is not just to learn this code.
Your job is to get a good result, to graduate with a high GPA, right?
So that's the same thing, right?
So we show that we use the data in order to actually produce the best model and the best
prediction from the model.
Okay.
So through, and here now actually we look into the central tendency, check the difference
between mean and the median value, and then we can have better understanding, right?
And also we have discovered one issue in the data, so the mission values.
Potential issue outliers.
Okay.
So next issue we answer the data spread, the dispersion or the spread, actually the variation
of the data, the range of the data.
So that is the data spread.
So beside the central tendency, we also need to look at the range of the data, look at
the dispersion of the data, and also the position of the different data values.
So this is actually another aspect, another characteristic of the data, the spread, okay?
So for the dispersion, actually the measure, so normally we use the standard vision.
So here actually we can see why we need to have this measure, or have this understanding
of the data spread.
So here we have given five values, right, five values, and for feature one or attribute
two, and actually both values, both attributes actually have a mean value of 46.
Actually the two have the same mean value, right?
But if we look at attribute one, the value is 44, 46, 48, 45, 47, the mean is 46.
That means all the values are around the mean value, right?
Spread is small.
Okay.
And actually the range of the data is close to actually the mean value.
But if we look at the second attribute, so 34 is very far from the mean value 46, right?
And also the 52, or 59, very far away from 66.
That means the spread, dispersion is very high, variation of the data is very high,
variation for this attribute, attribute number two, okay?
And so to measure this spread, and quite often we use the so-called variance, okay?
So in practice how to calculate the variance?
So assume a tree for the variable X, or feature X, and so we have N values, N values, right?
So this is the average of X squared, average of X squared, right?
For every value for this feature, right?
So we take the square, get summation, then get the average.
So this is the mean of X squared.
And then the second part of the tree, so you look at the tree, the one in the bracket,
inside the bracket, so this is simply the mean of XK, the mean of X, okay?
So this is the part of the tree, the square of the mean, right?
So these are two of the variance equals the mean of X squared, right?
A minus the square of the mean of X, okay?
So this is the variance, okay?
And actually certainly we can have actually almost an equivalent measure, which is just
the square roots of the variance.
So this actually is defined as the standard deviation, standard deviation of sigma actually
equals the square roots of the variance of X, okay?
So for spread, for data dispersion, we use these two measures, okay?
These two actually are identical, right?
So one is standard deviation, another is the variance.
So why this is very important, why this measure, right?
So the general tendency and also the spread, the variance of the standard deviation measures
are important.
So later, I think not today, I think week five, week six, week seven probably, I think
we will study one type of pattern classification, which is called the linear discriminant analysis.
And actually you understand actually independent classification, so what features normally
we prefer.
So normally we hope the data in classification, so what could be considered is an easy task
if, okay, the two classes are very different.
And for all the samples within the same class, they are similar.
Then it's easy to differentiate, right, easy to differentiate, okay?
So within class, within class difference is small.
Within the same class, the samples should be very similar.
Between class, the samples could be very different, okay?
So how to measure actually within class similarity, how to measure this, oh, within class, all
the samples are similar.
Actually this is the spread of the data around the mean vector, normally it's not just a
mean value, right?
So normally we use multiple features, so it's a mean vector.
So around the mean vector, the spread is small.
Then that means within class, similarity is high or the difference is small.
Then the classifier, the classification task is easier, okay?
Then between class, the difference is big, that means it's easy to differentiate the
two types, right?
Because the difference is big, but how to measure the difference between the two?
Actually we use the distance between the two mean vectors of the sample in the two classes.
Okay, so from here you can see the importance of the mean, right, the mean of sampling within
the same class and the spread of the sample within the same class, right?
We try to find the tree, even though the features or projections, so that sample within the
same class could have a small spread, okay?
Between class, we could have a very big difference, okay?
So that is the reason why we need to look at the central tendency, the mean vectors
and also the variance, okay, and covariate metrics, okay, if we had high domino space.
Okay, so these are the two measures, right?
So through this plot, this data tree, we can understand that tree, oh, this problem probably
is an easy task.
This problem could be very challenging, right?
Even in a feature, right, all the data are mixed, right?
If we use the CGPA to differentiate the male and female student, are you able to do that?
All the CGPA on male and female also moves overlap, right?
You cannot differentiate, you cannot differentiate, right?
So that's the reason why we don't see the tree, because the tree, the mean of the two
tree, the difference between the classes, actually, it's small, right?
The difference is small, okay, so it's very hard, actually, it's a very hard task, okay?
So through exploration of the spread and also the central tendency of the data tree, certainly
we can understand whether this is a task or this is a very challenging task, okay?
So you can also see the reason why we need to do this exploration, right?
Even before we perform learning, right, we need to perform such exploration of the data
to understand the challenges of the given task, okay?
Okay, so next tree is called the data value position, and just now we see for the spread
of the data, look at the dispersion, look at the various or standard measures, right?
Here we also look at the position of the data, so the position of some values, so here the
mean of five values, the position of five values, okay?
So this position of five values also describe the characteristic of the data.
By analyzing these five values, we can also have a better understanding about the data
distribution, okay?
So which of the five values, right, actually just now we talk about the median, right?
If you put the data in a sequence, sending all the, or descending all the, we can find
the middle, right, the middle point, so that middle value is just the median, okay?
Then actually the median value divide the whole data in the data sequence actually into
two half, right, the first half, the second half, okay?
So for the first half, we can also find the middle value, right, the middle value, median
value, okay?
And actually the first half, the median value of the first half of the data is called the
first quantile, or Q1.
So we define this way, these are value, right?
These are actually first quantile, these are 25 percent, you rank the data, right?
So these are 25 percent, what is this mean, this is Q1, the first quantile.
Okay, and then for the second half, certainly you can find the middle value, right?
So this middle value actually is 75 percent.
So this is called the third quantile, Q3.
I think Q2 is just the median, the overall median of the data, so the 50 percent.
So Q1 is 25 percent, right, Q2 is 50 percent, the one in the middle, right?
Q3 actually is 75 percent, okay?
So normally this is called percent tau, right, 25 percent tau, actually 50 percent tau, and
75 percent tau, okay?
So these are Q1, Q2, Q3, okay?
And besides these three values, and we also have another two values, that is called minimum
value and the maximum value.
So remember, this minimum value is not the smallest value in the sequence, it's not the
maximum value in the sequence.
So later we will see how to find this minimum value and maximum value, okay?
So these are the five values, okay?
So for example, actually, you know, either auto MPG data set, right?
And we have actually this data, and also we have found actually the Q1, Q2, Q2 is just
the median, overall median is just the Q2 and Q3, and also the minimum and the maximum,
okay?
And actually for displacement, you can also find the value.
For origin, you can also find the values, okay?
So these are the, yeah.
So these are just to summarize, actually, these five values, Q1, Q2, Q3, 25 percent
tau, 50 percent tau, 75 percent tau, okay, minimum, maximum, these five values, okay?
And actually through it, we analyze this Q1, Q2, Q3, and we can also discover some issues
of the data, okay?
And for example, actually, we look at the difference between Q1 for the displacement,
right, the displacement, which continues, and actually the Q1, so here actually the
calculated actually the Q1, 38, 68, right?
And then actually the, sorry, 104, 104, these are Q1, right?
And then actually we see the minimum distance between the minimum and the Q1 is 36.2, right?
And the difference between Q1 and the median is 44.3, okay?
And okay, but actually this is for the first half, right?
Then we look at the second half, and the Q3 is 11.5, and okay, so I think Q3 is, okay,
is 262, right, it's 262, and the difference between actually the median and Q3 is 113.5,
and the Q3, our maximum value difference is 193, okay?
You can see actually in the first half, actually the difference between the minimum and the
Q1, the difference between Q1 and Q2, this value is small, right?
But actually for the second half of data, that means actually from Q2, Q3, and the maximum,
right, then the difference is 100 something, much bigger than the previous part, right?
So actually from this difference, we can actually see some problems, okay?
So that means that the data, the larger values are more spread out in the, okay, in the larger
values spread out, okay, than actually the small values, okay?
So actually through this, you can also imagine the data, right?
Even previously, you had this experience of handling data, right?
So you can imagine, oh, in the low data, in the low part, they are concentrating in that
part, but for the high values, they spread out, so you can have some imagination, right?
You can imagine the data distribution.
This kind of data normally is called skewed, skewed, okay?
Skewness of the data also present challenges to machine learning, to modeling, okay?
So through this analysis, you know, we can discover issues with the data, right?
And then we can actually, you know, adopt necessary actions or measures to address all
these issues.
But if you don't do this kind of exploration, you cannot find the issue, okay?
You just, oh, this is a number, right?
So you cannot just look at the number to discover the issues.
You need to do exploration, right?
Look at the central mean, the central tendency.
Look at the spread of the data.
Look at, you know, the farm numbers, okay?
And the next tree, I think, is for illustration of the farm numbers, and a tree, we can use
a so-called a tree, a box plot, give the numbers, right?
But maybe, you know, if we can visualize the distribution, probably we can understand this
problem even better, right?
Okay, so this is the box plot.
And this diagram, actually, box plot is just a visualization of the farm numbers, right?
The position of the farm numbers, okay?
The mean, the M1, Q1, Q2, Q3, right?
A tree in the box plot, so in the middle, there is a box.
So this is one of the reasons why I call box plot, right?
There is a box.
And this, actually, this is a boundary, the edge here is a Q3.
And the low boundary edge here is Q1.
And in the middle, there is a big tree line, right, a big line, and this is just the median,
Q2.
Okay, so we have Q1, Q2, Q3, Q1, Q2, Q3.
So these are three numbers, right?
And then we also need to find the tree, the minimum and maximum.
And treating minimum and maximum are not necessarily the minimum and maximum of the data, okay?
So in this tree, we look at the tree, how these minimum and maximum values are found.
So here we define a so-called inter quantile range, which is the difference between Q3
and Q1.
We have Q1, Q2, Q3, right?
So the difference between Q3 and Q1 is called inter quantile range, AQR.
So based on AQR, we can find the minimum value and the maximum value.
So from the diagram here, we can extend this tree further to Q1 minus 1.5 AQR to get the
minimum.
From the bottom of both, Q1.
Then we can get that tree.
So this gets a minimum.
So get a 1.5 times of the AQR.
So in this question, Q1 is 73, just so we see that.
And then Q3 is 79.
Then the AQR inter quantile range is Q3 minus Q1, right?
In the example, so it's 79 minus 73 is 6.
And then we should from the bottom, the bottom Q1, Q3, and then from here we minus 1.5 times
6.
1.5 times AQR, right?
So we should actually from 73 minus AQR minus actually 1.5 times of the AQR, then get 64.
But this 64 is not really the minimum.
The minimum should be found from the data.
So we show that we look at all the data that is around 64.
We should find a one that is above 64.
For example, in the real data there, actually the data around 64 is 63, 70, and 60.
We should use the value that is above 64 as the minimum value.
So here, this actually is 70, right?
So we can use the minimum value, the 70 and the minimum value.
And then if our value is below this 70, it will be considered as outliers, extreme values.
So this is the minimum value.
And for the maximum value, we should start from Q3, Q3 plus 1.5 AQR.
So for the upper whisker, it's 10 to 1.5 in this question, right?
So like Q3 plus 1.5 AQR.
Q3, we already found the node value, right?
Q3 is 70 now, and then times, then plus actually now.
So this should be like 88, right?
So 88, 88, okay.
But whether this 88 should be used as actually the maximum value, no, actually we need to
look at the data, right?
We should find one that is slightly below this 88 from the data sequence given.
So from the data sequence, from the data we find actually 82, 84, 89, close to 88, right?
So the one that is below this, immediately below this 88 should be the one as the maximum value.
Okay, so we use actually 84 as the maximum value.
Then the value above 84 will be considered as extreme values, outliers.
So if you look back to this diagram, this box plot, I know this plot has some values
like, you know, the box plot like Q1, Q2, Q3, the minimum value, maximum value, then
above here, you can see there's the outliers, extreme low or extreme high values, okay?
And these extreme low or extreme high values could be called by many reasons, right?
Some could be called by errors, okay?
And sometimes these actually outliers are natural, right?
Just actually example, look at the data, original wealth, right?
The wealth of every person here you have, and also the wealth by the, you know, Bill
Gates.
So these, they are the value outliers, but certainly these outliers are natural, right?
And not noise, okay?
By some scenario, this actually could be, you know, an error when you record on a number,
called by error.
Okay, so, you know, if we're different, we have different reasons, then probably we need
to use a different actually, you know, actions or measures to address these outliers issue.
Okay.
So these are the data, right, the box plot, actually all the function on my lab, they
provide this function, give the data, then automatically, you know, help us to plot this
box plot, okay?
Just use the box plot, this function, then I plot this, okay?
This actually in diagram shows the box plot of a different, you know, attributes.
The box plot, you know, for cylinder, you can see the shape is quite different, right?
So these show the data, you know, characteristics, you know, are very different from one feature
to another feature, okay, because if the box plot, you know, looks similar, right, and
then actually maybe the data distribution will be similar, but here then you look at
that, they are very different, right, they are very different, okay?
So this box plot is a good visualization tool, which can give us, you know, a good
understanding about the data distribution, right, okay?
Just now we see, you know, for the displacement, actually we find that there are big difference,
right, between the median and the mean value, right, and in the, between Q3, the difference
between Q3 and the median, right, and also between the difference between Q2, right,
and also the difference between maximum value and the Q3.
So we have looked at that value, and also we have looked into the, this value normally
not big, right, like 100, but for the first half of the data, the difference between the
mean value and the Q1, actually, you know, is small, the difference between Q2 and Q1
is small, 30 something, right?
So we see all the data is probably, you know, is spread out for larger values, okay?
So this diagram just shows the, you know, the box plot of the displacement, actually
you can see the data, right, in data, this is the median, right, so then for the larger
range, right, this is actually indeed spread out for the larger values, right, for the
larger values.
For small values, they're more concentrated.
For this part, a big difference, right, between the maximum value and the median and the Q3,
and also the difference between Q3 and the mean.
So this is actually the very effective visualization tool, right, box plot is very efficient visualization
tool, which can help us to have a good understanding about the data distributions, okay?
The understanding of the good, the distribution of the data could help us decide, you know,
what measures we should use to address these issues, okay?
For example, you know, if the data, big value data, right, probably for the data you can
take some measurement operation, like you can take a logarithm operation, right, then
to actually reduce, actually to make the data less skewed.
Now it's all in the high part, right, if you take a logarithm operation, right, and then
the data will be actually more evenly or uniformly distributed, okay?
So through this exploration, you can find the issues, and then you can take measures
to address the issues, okay?
And then finally you can get a better model, which can produce a more accurate predictions.
Okay, so from here, today until now, and I hope that you understand, fitting a model
is not just a core function, put the data in, right, actually it's very necessary to
do this kind of exploration, to answer the data, and to find the issues also, and take
some measures to address the issues, and before we apply, input the data to the learning algorithm
to fit a model, okay?
The next visualization tool is called a histogram, histogram, because now we just see the five
value position, right, Q1, Q2, Q3, minimum, maximum, right, then we have both plots, they
give us an understanding, right, and actually a histogram is another effective visualization
tool, right, to analyze the data distribution, okay?
In this histogram, normally we divide the data into many bins, for example the data
is from the values from 1 to 10, for example, right, you can divide the whole range into
10 bins, okay, from 0, from 1 to 10, right, from 11 to 20, okay, from 21 to 30, okay,
you have different range, and this is called bins, and then you are checked, so how many
data points actually fall into this range?
Then you count the number, okay, then you can explore this, so this is called actually
the histogram, so the horizontal shows the values, okay, so here you can see this, right,
so this is a bin, from here to this value, right, from here to here, actually the whole
range is divided into many bins, of course in the functions, part of it, the default
value is set to 10, but you can decide the bin number, you can also decide the tree,
the bin size, the range of the bin, from which, you know, from which, starting from which
value to what value, right, decide the range of the bin, you can define normally, okay,
then actually we count the number, count the number, so this diagram shows the distribution
of the data, right, so here the first one, symmetric, uniform, you can see, you know,
all the bins, right, the number, actually the horizontal shows the number, the cost,
how many data points, how many values, okay, how many values are in this range, okay, so
here they are all similar, right, similar, doesn't mean the data distribution is quite
even, right, uniform, uniform, uniform, they're quite uniform, the first one, right, then
the second one, as you can see, this is symmetric, like, you know, this is symmetric, right,
a uni model, uni model, uni means no single, right, uni model, just the one peak, so this
is quite like, you know, Gaussian distribution, right, Gaussian distribution, so from here,
oh, this sample, this data point, this is no feature, and probably the data follow normal
distribution.
You can look at this, this shape is quite similar to a normal distribution, right, and
then look at another data, this actually skewed, skewed, this is called a left skewed, okay,
and then this is quite, actually these are right skewed, skewed, okay, and then from
here these are treated like a bimodal, because here we can see like two peaks, right, from
here to here, then from here to here, so probably actually the feature shows two normal
distributions.
If you want to build a model for this kind of distribution, and then we can use a so-called
Gaussian mixture model, so in the next week, when we study actually one approach which
is the statistical approach for finite classification, and actually one important part of this algorithm
is to estimate the probability distribution function, probability density function, okay,
plus conditional probability density function, and the part of that we assume actually the
following normal distribution, and then we need to find the parameter of model distribution
to fit the data, right, but sometimes the data maybe cannot be modeled by one single
actually normal distribution function, it will be modeled by multiple normal distribution
functions, so that is a Gaussian mixture model, right, so through this analysis, this histogram
actually we can discover the data, right, or there are two peaks, something like that,
probably there are two, we can use the two normal Gaussian functions to actually model
this data distribution, right, so if you don't actually plot this histogram, actually we
cannot have this outstanding, right, then probably you just use one, then you fit the
model, it's fine, oh the performance, no satisfactory, you don't know the reason why, right, but
actually through this analysis of the data, through this histogram, we can understand
actually indeed actually the data from normal distribution, but we need to use more than
one normal distribution function, more than one Gaussian functions to fit the data, right,
so we can discover the root cause of the problem, right, then you can take measures, right,
use two Gaussian functions actually to model the distribution, okay, so here probably there
are multiple, right, so there is one Gaussian function here, another Gaussian function,
so here we need to use more than two in the multiple Gaussian function, Gaussian mixture
model actually to fit the data, okay, you can see now, right, sometimes you fit the
data, get a color function, performance, no satisfactory, you don't know the reason,
right, but through exploration of the data, we can find actually the issues, right, so
these issues, these phenomena, this distribution information can guide us to design the super
models actually for these specific tasks, okay, and then actually you can get a better
model to make more accurate predictions.
Okay, so we have a ten minute break.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Okay, so both plot and the histogram are provided with effective tools and for visualization
of the data distribution, okay.
And actually here we can have a look of the distribution and all the histogram of the
different features, different attributes in the auto MPG data set, right, and then we
can see actually the distribution, right, are very different, right, for some data set,
right, for MPG and for all other like model years it's quite uniform, right, quite uniform,
but for some of them like for this acceleration, right, it follows like a normal distribution,
normal distribution.
So you can see the different characteristics of the different attributes in the data set,
okay.
Certainly through exploration of the data, right, particular visualization of the data
distribution by the histogram or the both plot, we can have a better understanding about
the data, right.
So certainly these help us to decide on the suitable models and also the learning algorithm
for this data set, okay.
So next we know these are just the information for the numerical data, right, quantitative
data or the continuous data, continuous quantitative of the numerical, right, or sometimes actually
we use them misly, right, exchangeably, okay, so they are basically so we can measure the
mean, we can measure the median, okay, so that's the measure of the central tendency.
We can also look at the dispersion, the spread of the data, okay, and also plot through the
workforce plot and also the histogram to look at the data distributions, okay.
And for categorical features like gender, right, like the gender, right, so like so
we cannot actually use this, actually, you know, we cannot carry the mean value, so what
the average of the gender of this class, right, we don't have the average of gender, right,
so we don't have average, we cannot, we don't have the central tendency, okay.
So then actually how to actually visualize the data and actually we can actually use
a table, use a table, okay, so here actually this table, no, one table is for the car name,
car name, actually we can recount the number of samples that taking each of the values,
right, for acceleration, for this actually, these are for, I think this here is for car
name, right, for car name, so among all the cars, all the samples, so how many cars actually
have this name, how many cars have this name, how many cars have been named, okay, and for
the cylinder, right, so how many cars have actually three, that's four, right, how many
cars have four cylinders, so these are four cars, right, so this table also can give an
understanding about the distribution, the value distributions, okay, so like for this
actually, the second part, right, for the cylinder, we know most of the cars have actually
four cylinders because there are two, four, 200, and the four cars have four cylinders,
right, and actually one or three cars have eight cylinders, okay, so very few cars have
three cylinders or five cylinders, okay, so this table can also give us an understanding
about the data, the value distribution, okay, so we cannot actually have this actually the
histogram and also the box plot and for the categorical data, but we can only have this
kind of table, okay, so next actually is for the relationship between the variables,
between the attributes or features, okay, and at the beginning of this class actually
I told about the relationship between the features, right, and through this actually
relationship actually we can explore the interdependence of the data or sometimes we
call the redundancy between the data, okay, so for this actually the relationship exploration
we can use actually the so-called scatter plot, actually we can use one actually attribute
as x axis, right, horizontal axis, we can use another attribute as the vertical axis,
right, so for each sample actually we have an attribute one value, we have attribute
two value, right, so the x1, x2 as a coordinate we can find a location in this actually in
a plane, right, so this box plot is just actually one actually sample versus another sample,
okay, so this is like a displacement, it's horizontal, okay, and then vertical actually
is the mpg, so each data point, each point here, circle here represent one sample, for
this sample and the value of displacement is this and the value mpg another value, right,
we use this two value as the coordinate and then we can plot this position, no, coordinates
are the position, right, we can actually plot the data on this plane, okay, so this order
and through this actually scatter plot actually we can find the relationship between the data
points, okay, if one extreme case you can imagine, one extreme case, okay, the two attributes
actually are identical, the same, okay, then all the coordinate the same, the coordinate
the same, right, and then actually you can imagine actually then actually all the points
actually are on a straight line, on a straight line, so these are extreme cases, this data
actually has severely correlated because the data with itself, right, the one attribute,
the correlation between one attribute and itself, of course is what, the maximum, right,
so the data point is just on a straight line, on a straight line, so this is the case, when
the samples are, when the two actually variable are severely correlated, that means the redundancy,
there are redundancies, okay, and then the two attributes, and then actually the spread
is quite narrow, along a line, okay, but if the two variable are independent, totally
random, if you actually draw them, right, you can see the data like a ball, this is
really like a ball, x1, x2, or sphere shape, something like that, okay, so this is true,
they are strongly independent, okay, so these are the two extreme cases, right, where actually
all the data points on one straight line, you can imagine, right, so all the data points
on one straight line, because the two attributes are the same, all the points on a straight
line, so very narrow, right, very narrow, another very spread, spread very much like
a ball data point, this is the case when the two features are independent.
Okay, so through these two extreme cases, and also we look at the true scenario, right,
for a specific feature, and another feature, right, against another feature, then we can
understand the correlation between the two, whether they are strong, strong redundancy,
or strong correlation between them, or the two variables are independent, right, so through
actually, this scatter plot, through analyzing this scatter plot, actually, we can have a
basic understanding about the relationship between the variables, okay, sometimes the
one variable, another variable has a proportion relationship, okay, so again, they are on
a straight line, they are not along a straight line, not exactly on the straight line, but
narrowly along the straight line, so this means the two features are actually severely
correlated, okay, so this is a scatter plot, I think it's another visualization tool, okay,
to understand the relationship between two variables, okay, so this, of course, this
plot is for continuous attributes or features or variables, for discrete, or categorical,
or actually the sort of qualitative data, now we can use the so-called two-way cross
tabulation, two-way, okay, so this actually just shows such a table, actually like one
origin, another model here, origin is a vertical, one, you know, USA, two, you know, Japan,
three, you know, like Germany, all the carmaker countries, so actually, so in the middle year,
model year, 1970, 1971, okay, until 1982, right, so this shows the number, okay, so
for example, for the car made in USA, right, so the model years, so for the number of the
cars in 17, 22, okay, so these are, show these values, okay, so these are the cross
table, two-way cross table, actually also give us an understanding about the relationship
between actually the two categorical variables, okay, so next actually we talk about the data
quality, and actually remediation, so at the beginning I already talked about the importance
actually of data quality, right, so actually these are very important, the success of machine
learning depends, largely depends on the quality of the data, okay, and so, but in practice
problem, we could encounter some issues, right, actually the data quality is not perfect,
okay, so we could encounter some issues, and so there are two kind of problem, one is the
mission values problem, mission value, actually at the beginning, when we talk about the mean,
right, the central tendency, they used to illustrate the mission value problem, for
some of the features, for some of the samples, and some features, the value are missing,
okay, so actually the mission value could cause by different reason, right, and for
example, if you ask you to do an interview, right, like an interview of a student in NTU,
and you can ask your opinion on different policies or regulation about NTU, you can
actually share your idea, right, and then of course actually we can record down your
view on each of the regulation, right, you think what is your thinking, what is your
thought on this, right, I also give you a score as an evaluation of this policy, right,
your satisfactory score on this, but sometimes actually you ask this, but you don't want
to comment on that, right, then of course in that scenario, they just don't have a record
of your score about a certain policy, okay, so this could be called, this could cause
a mission value, right, for that particular sample, for that particular attribute, sometimes
maybe you give the answer, but the recorder forgot to record down, write down this value,
okay, so there are many reasons that causes mission value problem, okay, and so the data,
sometimes the data elements, normally the attributes have values surprisingly different
from the other elements, so extremely low values or extremely high values, so these
are the outliers, they are very different from other values, just like an example, talk
about the income, right, talk about the wealth we have, and then suddenly some are being
in there, right, they are outliers, outliers also could be caused by many reasons, right,
and why not, they are naturally outliers, okay, and maybe in such a scenario, maybe
we take the wrong data, right, you just look at the average or the normal, like Singaporean
or Chinese, you know, household income, right, but actually you're just normal, common, right,
people, but you include some billionaires, so this actually could be caused by an incorrect
sample set selection, maybe you use some of the data, right, so you should not use the
data billionaires to calculate the average income of the ordinary people, right, but
actually you use that, so these are the outliers, it could be, it's caused by the incorrect
use of the sample set, okay, and also could be caused by errors, you write down, when
you record down this value, you record it wrongly, okay, so this wrong value could be
an outlier, okay, so these are the two main issues actually, or two frequently encountered
issues in the data, so if we have these issues, then we must actually eliminate these problems,
must address these problems, and before actually we apply this data to the linear algorithm,
okay, so next we look at data remediation, remediation, how to handle these problems,
if we have missing values, if we have outliers, okay, first we look at the handling of the
outliers, okay, so we already understand actually what is an outlier, right, extreme low or
extreme high values, you know, very different from other values, so these values considered
as an outlier, okay, and so one simple way is to remove the outliers, if one sample has
one specific feature, the value is extreme high, extreme low, so I think the easiest
way to handle this outlier problem is just to remove the host, that sample, to remove
that sample, okay, so we can remove the outliers, okay, so for every sample, if there is one
attribute contain outlier value, right, extreme low, extreme high values, we can just remove
this sample, okay, so of course this is the easiest way to do that, right, just remove
that by checking the sample, so this is also a way to improve the data quality and also
the quality of the model, right, so this is the reason why we say we need to explore the
model, we need to look at the quality, right, if there are missing values, there are outliers,
we must address these outliers and the missing value problems, okay, so remove the outliers,
then we can improve the quality of the data, and another is the imputation, okay, so we,
you know, if the outliers, right, extreme high, extreme low, maybe we see, oh, this
could be caused by, you know, the errors, okay, then we should correct this error, correct
this error, correct it, but how to correct this error, so what value we should use to
replace these extreme low or extreme high values, actually we can use the average, we
can use the average, right, actually we can use the mean, media, or mode to replace these
extreme low or extreme high values, we just, if we believe they are caused by errors, but
now we want to use a value to replace that, but what value to use, actually then we can,
then naturally we can think about the media or mean, right, or the mode, we can replace
the outliers, right, using these values, okay, so we don't remove the outliers, actually
instead we keep the sample with the extreme low or high values, but we change the values,
right, replace the extreme low or high values using the mean, media, or mode, okay, another
is keeping, okay, so this is extremely low, extremely high, right, so just now actually
when we have the box plot, we have the five number summary, right, Q1, Q2, Q3, the minimum,
maximum, okay, these minimum, maximum are not necessarily really the minimum value or
maximum value in the data, right, actually we have ways to calculate minimum and maximum,
based on Q1, and then we subtracted to 1.5, actually, you know, accurate into quantile
range, okay, and for Q, for maximum from Q3, we have plus 1.5, you know, accurate, right,
so, so we have this value, right, we have minimum and maximum, right, so if the value
is extremely low, we know this area, right, so we just, you know, replace the value using
the minimum value to replace, if the value is extremely high, we use the maximum value
to, to replace, okay, so this method is called camping, okay, camping, and here actually
you can also treat, now use a different like, you can use the file percentile, file percentile,
95 percentile, Q1 is 25 percentile, right, you can use the file percentile, you don't
use really the minimum, right, we can use the value, that is the file percentile, the
maximum value, we don't use the maximum value, we can use the 95 percentile, okay, so this
is the, okay, this is the, you know, the camping method, okay, so this is another scenario
that if there is extreme significant number of outliers, extreme number of outliers, then
they should be treated differently, separately, okay, we know among the 200 samples, or like,
you know, 50 samples, or 25%, right, have extreme value of outliers, and maybe these
outliers are natural outliers, right, they are not caused by error, okay, so here is
such a scenario, actually we should treat them, you know, the data, normal data, as
one group, and then the data with the stream values, right, outliers into another group,
okay, then we can build a model separately for the two groups, okay, and, okay, then
if we make prediction, right, make prediction, then we can just look at the data, right,
normal data or an outlier, then we can decide, actually, which model to use, okay, this is
another way to handle the outlier problem, okay, so for one single problem, actually
we have multiple solutions, but actually, of course, each of the solution is a purpose
within certain context, okay, so you always need to analyze the given task, analyze the
task specific data, right, to find the issues, and also to take the corresponding measures,
right, the best measure to address the issues, okay, we always need to do the analysis, right,
do the analysis, so here these are just actually one scenario, significant number, okay, so
if the outliers are natural, right, actually, you know, they're natural, okay, so we should
not amend them, so they're not caused by error, they're natural, okay, so in such a
scenario, maybe we just put them into two groups, that's a good solution, okay, so another
tree, we see the mission value problem, right, mission values, there are some mission values,
but then, of course, the tree, we can, the simple way to eliminate the sample with mission
value, right, so this is the simplest way is to eliminate records or sample having a
mission value, because we have a market, right, we cannot decide the value, and we simply
remove this value, remove this sample, and this sample has a mission value, and we can
remove that, and this sample have, you know, extremely low or high value outliers, then
we have to remove that, so at least this is one way to address the problem, but not
necessarily the best way, it is a way to address the entire problem, to address the mission
value problem, but not necessarily the best way, okay, so the eliminate records or sample
having a mission value, okay, so this anomaly is applicable when the number of, you know,
a sample with mission value is limited, a small proportion, okay, you have like, you
know, only 10% or 5% of the data are mission values, right, 5%, and if you have a large
number of samples, then removal of this 5% of the data will not affect our learning result
much, okay, then we can just remove, right, so this anomaly is applicable, can be adopted
under such a scenario, the removal of these samples will not affect actually the learning
result much, okay, so we can remove them, okay, just actually in this example here,
I gave, originally the data has 392 samples, and actually you find the six sample mission
value, right, because now we see the six sample, you know, question mark mission value, you
remove these six samples, we still have 388, 86 samples, right, so just actually, like
you know, six, how many percent, 2%, yeah, less than 2% of data, right, have mission
value, you know, remove all this percentage, right, of the data will not affect the learning
result much, okay, then we can take this simple way to remove them, okay.
So this will not be possible actually if, you know, many data points have mission values,
a tiny percent, you know, 392 sample, right, or 100 sample mission values, if you remove
these 100 samples, then actually this will affect the learning result very much, okay,
so then in such a scenario we should not remove, okay, through this process you can see that
we all need to analyse this problem, right, analyse, we look at the scenario, so under
different scenarios we have different solutions, okay.
And then of course the next actually is the imputing the mission values, okay, we don't
try to remove actually the sample because of just one mission value, right, because
actually in so many scenarios the data collection is not easy, in particular in biomedical research,
right, and actually you, or just now as an example you interviewed a student about a
policy, right, the interview can take maybe like 10 minutes, okay, just because of one
value actually in mission, then you remove the sample, then this 10 minutes effort is
wasted, right, so these are actually some scenarios, many scenarios, the data collection
is very expensive and you will just have a limited number of samples, we should not remove
actually the sample, instead we should take some other measures, right, actually to actually
compensate the mission value, to address the mission value problem.
So here is the imputing the mission values, we should just like outline it, right, we
should replace, we should give a value, right, for this mission value, actually what value
to give, actually we can of course like improve actually for the outline, we can use the median,
we can use the mean and we can use the mode, right, to replace, to assign to this mission
value, okay, so this is the mission value and actually we cannot, another issue, right,
and in particular I think for the sample, right, actually sometimes actually we don't
use the overall mean or overall media, but even in classification problem we know this
sample belongs to class one, okay, and then actually we should not use the overall mean
or median to compensate, actually to assign the overall mean or median to the mission
value, right, we should not use the overall, instead we should now look at this sample
belongs to class one, right, so it's more similar to sample of class one, then we should
use the median or mean value of sample of class one to replace this question mark, right,
this actually certainly will improve the accuracy, right, so this is the one method, okay, another
method is that actually even within the same class, some samples actually are more similar
than to other samples, right, even within the same class, right, because within the
same class they also have dispersion, right, spread, okay, although the spread may be small,
but for some sample actually if we look at other features with no missing value, okay,
then we find actually the most similar samples, so based on other features we find which sample
is most similar to this, to the sample with the mission value, okay, then we look at the
feature, we look at the value of that sample, right, then we just use that value to replace
the question mark, this is probably another way, right, so we analyze the problem, although
we also impute the mission value, but we could have different ways, okay, so this is the,
yeah, okay, and here for another example, right, for the horsepower and so they also
based on the relationship, right, actually previously we see, you know, we can explore
the relationship between the variables, right, between the variables, if you know the horsepower
is probably, is more similar, is correlated with the cylinder, with the cylinder, right,
so actually, oh, then we can look at, you know, if this sample actually have cylinder
like eight, right, like eight, okay, so because these two variables are correlated, and then
we can look at the, you know, all the data with eight, cylinder eight, okay, and then
we can look at this sample, you know, along the horizontal, along the feature now, so
what are the values, okay, then we take the average of this sample with eight cylinders,
okay, then we use this value to replace the mission values, right, we use the most relevant
samples based on the relationship between the features, okay, then we kind of, so this
again, the exploration of the relationship between the features or attributes is important,
right, this can help us to improve actually the solution and for the mission value problem.
So here, you know, it's all we need to analyze, right, not just give a problem, actually just
adopt that, put in the function, not so easy, we all need to analyze, okay, look at the
specific problem, look at the characteristics of the data, okay, then apply or adopt or
develop proposed new solutions, okay, so these are, okay, I think these are the estimating
mission values and actually, you know, this estimation is that actually the features run
a number correlating, just now already see two feature correlating, right, actually the
feature can also, you know, correlate with many variables, we can always use actually
other variables to fit another variable, to fit, okay, so we can use, you know, the mission
value, right, for this feature, we can use actually build a model, another model, okay,
to use other features to predict these features with mission values, okay, so that is estimating
mission values, okay, so there are many, many solutions to the mission value problem, okay,
so, okay, so these are like the solution to the two main problem, right, the mission value
problem and the autolayer problems, okay, so let's actually look at the data preparation,
so you still remember to have this preparation, actually the last step in the preparation,
actually preparation here means the scaling of the features, okay, so here for scaling
actually we talk about two main methods, one is called normalization, another is called
actually standardization of the data, okay, so scaling is, I think, is very important
and therefore in machine learning, so what is feature scaling, you know, the feature
scaling is the data preparation technique to transform the values of features of a different
range, right, to a similar range, so this is called actually the feature scaling, okay,
and so this purpose is to ensure that all features
contribute equally, right, to the model and to award the domination of features with big
values, okay, so later through one example we can see why the big, you know, values,
you know, dominate, okay, we should try to avoid this problem, okay, and this actually
you know, normally in machine learning how often we need to calculate the distance between
the samples, the distance, okay, the distance is used as a similarity measure, distance,
okay, and how to calculate the distance between two features, right, normally we look at the
difference between each attribute, right, you know, between the two samples along each
attribute, then square, then summarize them together, right, so for example, GPA, you
know, and most of 5, right, 4.5 and 5, the difference is only 0.5, then square is 0.25,
but if you look at the body weight, something like 50, something like 100 kg, right, then
the difference, 50 squared, 200, 2500, right, so it's a known thing that the body weight
actually will dominate in the calculation of the similarities between the samples, because
this feature takes big values, okay, we should try to avoid this problem, okay, so this is
because in many machine learning algorithms we need to calculate the distance between
the samples, okay, one of the examples is the, I think the nearest neighbor, distance
based learning algorithm, and then, you know, for actual learning, the K means the classroom,
also based on the distance to determine the similarity of the samples, okay, and that's
the whole way of the machine, the same, they all use the distance, okay, I think most of
the, almost all, not all, most actually, you know, machine learning algorithm use the distance
between the samples, okay, so we should try to avoid the dominance of one feature of others,
right, okay, and so this is just to give one example, I think, so initially, you know,
the salary, you know, in this range, right, all big values, the CGPA, all small values,
okay, so after scaling by a certain method, so later we'll talk about two methods, and
all in a similar range, right, all in a similar range, so none of them will be dominant, okay,
so we should actually, you know, use feature scaling to avoid the dominance of one feature
or others, okay, so just not show the example, we're not good for example, another actually
is that actually many algorithm actually based on the so-called gradient descent method,
like neural network training, back propagation algorithm, okay, or deep neural network, of
course, actually, so many linear algorithm actually, the training of the model is based
on the so-called gradient descent method, okay, so here actually the gradient descent
is a kind of incremental linear or sequential linear, so every time we give one sample,
then we update the weight, okay, so these are the weight in the step K, and these are
the weight in the next step, so the second term here is update, the weight update contains
three parts, one is the eta, the linear rate, another part is the gradient, the gradient
of the first order derivative of the loss function with respect to the parameter, then
another is the feature, X feature, right, the feature is very different, and then the
weight update will be very different, right, because the X I, one is only four point something,
right, you input data, then you can have update, another is 100 value, right, you update, then
the one with a larger value will have a large update, right, okay, actually the very big
large update could also actually cause actually instability of the linear, okay, so in the
gradient descent method actually we also should try to avoid big values, right, we
should normalize them to small values in the similar range, okay, so these are the reasons
why we need to actually perform the feature scaling, and before we, this is the last step,
okay, as the preposition, and these are two ways for feature scaling, one is called normalization,
normalization here will actually transform the data to the range from zero to one, okay,
so this is the formula which we use, this is the graphical illustration, right, horizontally
the raw data X, okay, then we can find the minimum, we can find the maximum, and then
we can perform this transformation, right, from X to X prime, and then after this transformation
all the data will be in the range, right, so actually the X minus minimum, make minimum
value, right, you start substitute, actually the numerator will become zero, so the minimum
will map to zero, to zero, the maximum will map to one, because if some maximum, right,
maximum, then the numerator cannot be the same, right, cancel, become one, okay, so
the data will, all data, no matter the original region, range, after normalization, they will
all in the range from zero to one, similar range, all the same range actually, okay,
and then another method is called standardization, standardization is to actually, to, you know,
to transform the data, and so that the mean is zero, and zero, right, and now we talk
about the central tendency, right, the mean, the mean will be zero, after normalization,
okay, and standardization, the spread of the data will be one, so this is called standardization,
so why it's called standardization, this is because the tree, now for the normal distribution,
if the mean is zero, standardization is one, this is called standard normal distribution,
right, standard normal distribution, so this is probably the reason I call it standardization,
but quite often we don't differentiate the two, they're all called normalization, okay,
so, the data preparation step, normalization, okay, normalized to zero one, or normalized
to zero mean, standard deviation of one, okay, and the tree, previously the tree, I think
here because you use the mean, right, and the sigma, and then as, they're less likely,
less actually affected by the, okay, but previously, with the mean, I think it's easier to, yeah,
okay, so these are the advantage, data advantage, so these are comparison of the two methods,
right, that normalization and standardization, but actually sometimes if we use different
techniques, we will obtain different results, okay, and sometimes the difference is significant,
so always actually we should try both, okay, then we find the better performing one, okay,
so I think there is no single method perform the best for all applications, always we should
try different method, we should finally use the best performing one, okay, so here actually
we also need to, yeah, try the two, yeah, the choice of them, normalization or standardization,
so depending on the problem, and always try the two, okay, so that's the reason in machine
learning we need to solve so many methods, right, because actually we don't know which
solution will be the best solution for the given task, we all need to try many of them,
but of course you cannot try all of them, you should analyze the data, you should have
a good understanding about assumptions for each of the learning, for each of the model,
right, then you try those that could potentially suit this specific application, okay, so that's
the reason why we need to do this exploration of the data, right, prepare the data, and
before the data could be input to the learning algorithm to fit the model, okay, I think
probably many of you actually want to rush for the bus, right, bus, okay, so now if you
actually, you want to stay here for some time, and then you can just stay, and then I can
answer your question, if you don't want to stay you can just go, okay.
Thank you.
.