.
We all have higher
standards for campus persistent
learning during socially
law and pardon I did
the test.
Normally, machine learning activities include three parts.
The first part, actually, is data, right?
The data collection.
And the second part is the abstraction.
So the objective of abstraction is to build a model
from the given data.
And then the last component, the component,
is the generalization.
Generalization is just to apply, actually, the model length
in the abstraction step and to the future data.
So application of the learning algorithm,
application of the model, which is also
considered as a part of the machine learning.
So today, I'll look at the data preparation
for machine learning.
Actually, data is very important.
Actually, in machine learning, there is one thing that
is garbage in, garbage out.
So the data is garbage, the rubbish, very bad data, right?
Why not the data?
And then the model obtained or learned from this data
could be very bad.
Of course, actually, the prediction
based on the learned model could be bad.
Bad means the performance is bad, right?
Then there is low accuracy.
So this is actually seeing to express
the importance of data and data quality in machine learning.
So we'll first look at the machine learning activities,
right?
OK.
Actually, I just mentioned machine learning actually
starts from data collection, right?
Because this is the first component in the three
components of the machine learning system.
So machine learning actually actively starts from data.
And actually, in the last week, actually, when we taught
about learning and also, we see there are three basic types
of learning.
The first type is called super high-level learning.
So in super high-level learning, when we collect the data,
then we also need to label the data.
So labeling on the data, of course,
depends on the problem, right?
So for example, we want to recognize the objects
in this classroom.
And then, of course, we can take pictures of all objects
And then we give a name to each picture, give a tag.
This tag is also called class label.
You take a picture of this screen,
and then you just know, oh, this is a screen.
You take a picture of this computer,
then you give a tag or label of a computer.
So this is called labeling.
So in super high-level learning, we
should provide the label training data.
And another type of learning is called unsupervised learning.
So if unsupervised learning, we just collect the data,
and we don't label the data.
So the data in unsupervised learning is unlabeled.
And then what the objective of unsupervised learning?
Actually, we want to discover the patterns
underlying the data.
Actually, one important learning task in unsupervised learning
is the grouping of the data called classroom.
We try to put samples with a great similarity into one group,
and samples with different similarities
in another group.
So this is a classroom or patent discovery.
Of course, we know that there is a top
of learning that is a reinforcement learning,
but that is not covered in this course.
So this course, we only cover the super high-level learning
and unsupervised learning.
For super high-level learning, we collect the data,
and also we label the data.
And in unsupervised learning, we just collect the data,
because there is no need to do the labeling of the data.
So after we have collected data and also label the data
for super high-level learning, and then actually,
we should perform the following activities.
The first, we to understand the top of the data
in a given input data set.
Later, we will see, actually, the data
can be categorized into different types.
Some data, like a categorical word,
where data, like gender.
So every student in the classroom
can have a value of male or female.
So for this gender, only two values, two portable values.
So this kind of variable is called categorical variables.
And for some variables, these variable
could be continuous, this feature.
Attribute could be continuous.
For example, and your height.
And you could be 1.175 cm, 162 cm.
So this number can be any number in a certain range.
So this kind of feature is called a continuous feature.
So we are looking at this type of feature later.
And actually, the data type directly
determines what model or what learning argument we
should actually adopt.
So at the beginning, we should actually
look at the nature of the data, look at the time of the data.
OK.
And then we need to explore the quality and some nature
and also some quality of the data.
I just mentioned, right, in machine learning,
and there is a saying, Gaby in, Gaby out.
So these are data quality, certainly, is very important.
And if the data is noisy, and then we should take measures
to address these issues.
Later, we will see some quality issues include
like auto liars and some values are extremely high
or extremely low.
These probably are noise.
And some data have missing values, even.
We don't have a value.
So this kind of data, these are issues in the data.
We should now take some measures to address these issues.
Before, we can use the data or can input the data
to a machine learning algorithm and to obtain or to learn a model.
So these are also the activities.
And also, to the explore relationship
among the data elements.
So these data elements normally means actually the attributes.
So later, we will look at these issue attributes
or features or variables.
And actually, when you collect the data,
you probably not very sure which data or which attribute,
which variable is important.
For example, we want to predict a person's salary, right?
Person's salary after your first job salary, right?
After the graduation of your MSE.
So of course, at the beginning, we have no idea
what are related to the salary.
Maybe we will actually collect a lot of data, right?
Your height, your gender, your weight, your GPA,
and your undergraduate GPA or postgraduate GPA.
You collect a lot of data, right?
But actually, some of the data may be irrelevant, right?
So your height, your body weight, your gender,
is not relevant to your salary.
But actually, your CGP may be relevant.
So during this data collection stage,
we have no idea about this.
So we can look at the relationship
between the class label and also each of the attributes
you have collected.
If some of them are irrelevant, that
means that the correlation between the class label
and, for example, the body weight, your height,
actually, correlation is very low, right?
Close to zero.
This means that this feature is irrelevant.
And then we should remove this.
And sometimes, the data you collected are quite correlated.
In other words, when you collect one feature,
and then another feature will provide very little
extra information.
So this kind of feature is redundant.
So we should also try our best to remove
the redundancy underlying the data.
And also, we should remove the significant features
from the data.
So these are the, through the exploration
of the data relationship.
So later, we will see what actually, in techniques,
we can use to explore the relationship between variables.
Then, actually, now we can try our best to eliminate
these variables.
And so we actually find the potential issues in the data.
I actually already just mentioned the issue.
This is a relative quality.
Some data could have missing values.
The missing value, that means that this data,
and for a specific feature or attribute,
there is no value.
It's a missing value.
And some actually could be outliers.
Maybe during the recording of this data,
and there are some errors.
You record down the data wrongly.
As a person, you use a cm of 175 cm.
But then later, you write down wrongly,
like a 75.5.
So this could be an error.
So we could also try our best to actually address this issue.
And before, we can input the data to the learning algorithm.
And then, of course, after we have identified the issues,
the noise, the noise in the data, the correlations,
and also actually the redundancies,
and also the insignificant features, for example.
And then we can actually take some merit to address these issues.
And then after that, we will perform an preprocessing
So this preprocessing means actually the scaling.
So later, we will see this.
We could perform normalization or standardization of the data,
and so that the data could be in the same range.
So here, for example, you record your GPA of 4.4.
NTU, actually, the system is 5.
5 is the most, actually, not 4.
So your GPA is 4.5.
Then you record down your height.
It's 170 something, right?
Your body weight is 60 something, 70 something, KG.
Actually, the data is in very different range, right?
So actually, we could have some issues.
Actually, we have data in very different range.
So we should perform some preprocessing.
So later, we will talk about this again, looking into the details.
Now, how to actually perform this scaling?
How to perform this scaling so that the features could
be in a similar range.
And then after the data is obtained,
then we can start the learning, right?
So actually, the learning normally, you know the data.
If you have data, you collect the data, right?
And you also perform labeling of the data.
And actually, normally, this data will be divided into two main parts.
One part is used as a training data.
Another part is used as testing data.
So in the last week, we have already
talked about this concept, training data, testing data.
The training data is used to estimate the values
or the parameter values in the model.
Normally, in a model, we could have many parameters,
in particular in deep neural networks.
We should have a large number of parameters.
In some large models, the parameters
could be 100 billion, so big models.
So we should actually to estimate the parameters.
But actually, normally, the data should be divided
into two parts, training and testing.
And testing is just actually used to evaluate the quality
of the model length.
So these are two parts.
Quite often, we have one extra part,
which is called validation data.
And the validation data normally is
used to determine the hyperparameters.
Normally, the hyperparameters actually
is not length-directed from the data.
And so we have some parameters that we need to determine.
So these are the validation data will
be used to determine the hyperparameters.
So in such a scenario, the data will
be divided into three parts, training data,
and the validation data, and the testing data.
And normally, 70% of the data will
be used as a training data.
15% for validation, then the remaining 15% of the data
will be used for testing.
Or sometimes, 60% for training, 20% for validation,
and then the remaining 20% for testing.
So this is the, of course, actually,
this is for super part learning.
For hyperparameters, actually, we don't have label, right?
And also, we don't divide them into two parts.
And then we should consider different models
or learning algorithms for selection.
And so for each learning task, either super part
learning or unsupertional, there are many methods.
There are many methods.
And so actually, in organization,
there is one theorem, which is called no free lunch theorem.
No free lunch.
So what does it mean?
It means that there are no single algorithm
that perform the best for all scenarios.
So these are actually a theorem, actually, of my position.
I would call it, we know machine learning also
is a kind of a my position problem.
So this no free lunch theorem also applicable
and to machine learning problem.
In other words, there are no single algorithm.
There are no single model that perform the best
for all applications.
So in your application, we always
need to try different learning algorithms
and then look to find the best performing one.
Of course, when you do the selection,
and we need to have a good understanding about the data,
the type of the data.
And normally, the data you mix contains continuous features
and then the categorical features or discrete features.
So we need to think about, in this learning algorithm,
so in this model, what are the assumptions?
Whether the data set is set by this assumption.
If the assumption are not certified in the data set,
then, of course, actually, probably this model
or this learning algorithm could produce a performance.
Sometimes the performance is good,
but it could not be the optimal results.
And then that means that we should understand,
the nature of the data.
We should also understand the details of the learning
algorithm and understand the assumptions
that we have made when we develop this model or this learning
algorithm.
So that is a need to consider different learning
algorithm or models.
And finally, after we have learned the model,
and we show that we evaluate the performance,
this is just like you learn this code.
Finally, you will actually sit for the exam.
You will sit the exam in the Latin.
So this is actually the exam where
tests your learning outcome.
So this is the evaluation.
And actually, in this course, of course,
we will cover different learning evaluation procedures.
And also, we will introduce actually different metrics
for the performance evaluation.
So this is a diagram just to summarize the process.
So we have the input data.
Then in step one, actually, the preparation work
for the modeling.
So this is just today's focus, preparation for the data.
And then after that, actually, we will perform learning.
The objective of learning is to find the metamethyl model
and to find the model.
And then we can apply the model to the testing data
and to evaluate the performance of this model.
And sometimes, actually, the performance is not satisfactory.
For example, in applications, actually,
we hope the accuracy should be greater than 99%.
Of course, this is a very ideal scenario.
Indeed, in some applications, actually,
this accuracy should be very high.
For example, you use your fingerprint,
you use the iris, you use the tree, many biometrics
as a password.
For example, to your bank account.
So this accuracy must be very high.
So by some application, actually, maybe the accuracy is low.
So the model produced, actually,
anti-satisfactory performance.
Then we need to think about, OK.
So maybe the issues could arise from the data
and could also arise from the model.
If it's from the data, and then, certainly, actually,
we should actually take some measures to address these issues.
For example, there are outliers.
So outliers, that means some of the data
has extreme high values or low values.
So how we should handle this?
And then we should actually take some measures
to address all these issues.
And then to get the so-called data,
then use the refined data to learn another model
with improved performance.
And really, linear is not actually just
actually this is a four-step.
Normally, these four steps are going to be nutritious.
We need to go through a few rounds
to produce a model, a good model.
And sometimes, you probably think,
we know it just introduced in the last week.
And there are some platforms, like the company language,
Python, MacLab, R, or even other company languages,
or platforms.
And when the machine learning algorithms actually
are built in the platform, we can
simply call the function and then learn.
Some know, maybe have already had some experience
on machine learning, right?
You get the data, put the data, call the function,
and then get a result.
Your learning task is complete in one second.
So fast.
Actually, machine learning is not so simple.
A project could last one year, right?
Could last one year.
Actually, one day, one week, one month, even a few months time.
I think you have so many long time, actually,
to produce a good model.
OK, so you know the task of just actually
put the data in the function, then get a model.
Not so simple, right?
You need to actually explore the data.
And you need to explore different learning algorithms.
And finally, actually, you will find that you want to actually
shoot your application the most.
If all the users in machine learning algorithms
do not shoot your application very well,
then you should actually develop your own learning
algorithm or learn your own model.
And you ought to produce the best performance or optimal
performance for these specific applications.
So these are three steps that normally
could go through a few rounds.
You ought to produce actually an audio performance
for a specific given task.
So let's look at the basic types of data in machine
learning.
So a data set is a collection of related information
or records.
So this is a data set.
And the information may be on some entity or some subject.
So here, maybe we look at one example.
So this is a student data set.
So it's a collection of records.
So a data set is a collection of records
which contain related or relevant information.
So these are student data sets.
So these data sets records actually
on the information of many students
on different entity or subject.
So we call the rule number, matriculation number,
and the name, and the agenda, and also to the age.
So we call all these information.
This is a student data set.
So a data set is a collection, not just one sample.
Not just one.
We have a lot of records.
So this is a data set.
And this is another data set, the student performance data set.
So we have the rule number, the matriculation number,
and then the result, the score for math, the score for science,
and the percentage.
So this is another data set.
And in this table, we have a lot of rules.
Normally, the rule normally is that each rule is one sample.
So each rule of a data set is called a sample.
A sample.
So a sample.
So actually, the rule one, actually, the matriculation
number, and also the math, the science result,
and also the percentage.
One rule corresponds to one sample.
So that means a data set normally
contains a large number of samples, not just one sample.
One sample, not called a data set.
It's a collection.
So we must have multiple samples.
And also each data actually has multiple attributes.
So in this data set, so the rule number,
so each attribute corresponds to one column in the table.
In this data set.
So we have the record number, rule number, and we have the math.
And we have the science.
And we have the percentage.
So these are the four attributes.
So each rule is one sample.
And each column is one attribute.
And this attribute is also called feature or variables.
I often in statistics, model fitting,
normally they call variables.
In machine learning, these are quite often called
attributes or features.
So in this example, we have four features,
rule number, the science result, the math result,
and also the percentage.
There are four features.
So how many features in a data set?
This depends on application.
So in the past, I used to handle some like a Gmkary data.
I read that the minority could be 40,000.
But the sample could be just a few, like a few hundred.
But the columns could be 40,000.
So this is really a dependent application.
How many features?
And to use, in particular, at the beginning, initially
and how many features you use in the data collection stage.
So these are not the sample and attribute or features.
So these are about the data.
And let's look at the data type.
So data can be broadly divided into two types.
One is the qualitative data.
Qualitative data.
Another is the quantitative data.
So what is the qualitative data?
It's about quality.
Qualitative data is about the information of quality.
And so these quality normally cannot be measured.
Cannot be measured.
So these are qualitative data.
And here, I give some examples.
For example, about the performance.
And we can use a tree like a good average or per.
Or very good.
Excellent.
All these trees can be used.
So normally, a tree with a qualitative data, the values
are named values.
Named values.
Not the numerical value, right?
Not a number.
But given, actually, this is called named value.
Named value.
So good, very good.
About gender, right?
Male or female.
So these are named value.
And talk about the university, right?
So NTU, NUS, or SMU, SUTD in Singapore.
So these are named values.
So these named values are qualitative.
So qualitative data is also called categorical.
And actually, even a qualitative data, just now
I mentioned, actually, we give some example.
Actually, it can be further divided into two types.
One type is called nominal data.
Another type is called ordinal.
There are some differences between the two.
So what is nominal data?
So nominal data is one which has no numerical value,
but named value.
Just now, very good or good.
These are all named values, right?
Certainly, these are named values.
This is one.
Named value.
So for example, for black group, A group, no, black type,
black type A, type B, type O, type AB, right?
So these are named value, nominal.
And also, call it nationality.
Chinese, Singaporeans, Indian, American.
So all these are named values.
So these are nominal data.
And another example, yeah, these are gender, right?
Male or female.
So these are important characteristics
for the nominal data.
So nominal data, for nominal data,
we cannot perform these mathematical operations
like addition, subtraction, multiplication.
And of course, actually, then we cannot have the mean value.
For example, in this class, actually, many students
have no black type of A. Some have black type of B.
Some have type of C. Oh, no, C, sorry.
Oh, sometimes I have AB, right?
Then we talk about, is that a value?
What is the average black type of this classroom?
What is the standard classroom?
We don't have these, right?
We don't have an average black type.
So this is because, actually, we cannot perform the submissions,
actually, the addition.
OK.
So then we cannot have the mean value.
Of course, we cannot have the standard of the agents.
We cannot have the average.
OK.
So these are characteristics of, actually, the nominal data.
We cannot perform these kind of operations,
or environmental operations.
So the nationality, some Chinese, some American,
some Chinese, some Indians in this classroom, some Singaporeans.
So what is the average nationality?
There is no such thing, right?
No nationality.
You can see that the average result, right?
Nearly GPA.
But we don't have average nationality.
We don't have this number.
But we can use others.
Data will see that we can use the so-called mode, actually,
for this kind of data.
But we cannot have the average.
We cannot have the mean, right?
OK.
So these are the nominal data.
See the nominal data.
Then another type is called ordinal.
Ordinal.
And ordinal is also kind of similar to the nominal data.
But actually, the data can be ordered.
The data can be ordered.
So ordinal data actually also assign name the value
to attribute, name the value.
But actually, this name the value
can be actually arranged in a sequence.
Are they ascending order or descending order?
Increasing or decreasing?
OK.
So we can also see one value is greater or better
than another value.
So this kind of data, actually, they are called
ordinal.
OK.
So here are some examples.
And we talk about the result.
Happy, unhappy, or very happy, happy, very happy, happy,
unhappy.
Or when we talk about the grid, we talk about get A, you get a B,
or get a C, right?
And we know A is better than B, that's C.
But B is better than C.
But there is a sequence.
Although they are named the value,
but there could be a sequence.
One value could be better or greater than another value.
So this is called ordinal.
And actually, this is probably similar to numerical values
to the actual quantitative data.
And that could be an order.
OK.
We have known the height of a person, right?
So later we will see 175, 160, 60.
And we can have an actually, you know,
actually arrange this in a sequence of increasing
or decreasing order.
So this is actually quantitative data.
A quantitative data.
So this ordinal, in this aspect, is very similar
to the quantitative data.
So hardness of metal, very hard, soft.
So we can put them into a sequence.
And for this ordinal data, we cannot find the mean.
But we can find the median.
Because we can put them into a sequence, right?
Into a sequence.
And then actually, we can put the median.
We can get a median value.
So what is the value in the middle?
OK.
So these are ordinal.
So you can look at these properties, right?
So these probably are the, you have
seen these kind of variables.
But probably have never thought about whether we
can perform operations, mathematical operations on them.
So this also, this probably determines
the learning algorithm or the model we should use.
In some models, normally we assume that data are continuous.
And the quantitative data.
And then we assume the following normal distribution,
for example.
And so if a data is mixed, can't do something like this,
then we should not actually assume the following normal
distribution.
And also we cannot use actually the distance calculations.
So this is the ordinal.
And then this is the first time, qualitative data.
Then that's why it's quantitative data.
Quantitative data actually knows the information
about quantity.
And it can be measured.
It can be measured.
And quantitative data is also termed a numerical data.
So categorical, not a numerical.
Categorical, that means actually the data values
are the categories.
Good, very good.
As you know, average, right?
Or per.
So these are category.
And the black type, right?
Category A, category B, category O, category AB.
So these are categorical.
And then for the quantitative data,
they are also called the numerical.
Numerical, they're called numbers.
Numbers.
OK.
OK, so for these quantitative data,
and we can further divide them into two types.
One type is called interval data.
Another type is called ratio data.
Interval.
OK.
I would actually, of course, data actually, a numerical data.
An interval data, numerical data, not only the order is known,
but there is a difference between them.
It's also known, the difference.
For example, when we talk about the temperature, right?
Now it's 25 degrees.
And then if there is a 10 degree,
another difference of 15 degrees, right?
So this 15 degree, you can understand
that this is exactly the meaning of this 15 degrees difference.
OK.
So this is an interval data.
So for interval data, I did not quantitative data.
Normally, this operation, like addition, subtraction,
are possible, could be conducted or performed.
And also, actually, the central tendency, the mean.
Later, we will look at this further.
Central tendency, or the mean of the data,
could be calculated.
Because we can use the summation.
These are numerical data, actually.
We can look at the mean, which is the central tendency.
And also, actually, we can look at the standard divisions,
the variance.
So this is actually the interval data, racial data.
Racial data actually represents a numerical data for which
exact value can be measured.
So they're similar to the interval data.
And actually, in the interval data, no absolute zero.
But in the racial data, there is absolute zero.
So this is the definition of the racial data.
And also, the data, you can perform addition, subtraction,
no multiplication or position.
So central tendency can be calculated.
And as a tree, in practice, a tree, although no, this data
can be put into different categories.
So quite often, we don't try to differentiate
the two types of quantitative data, the numerical data.
There's a big difference between the two.
But actually, not much.
So in practice, we normally don't try to differentiate
whether this data is an interval data,
or whether this data is a racial data.
We just consider them numerical data.
But for the two categorical types of data,
nominal and ordinal, actually, sometimes
need to be differentiated.
And for example, actually, in some way,
we all study a decision tree.
Sometimes, actually, when the data decision tree is a tree
structure and a classifier, in one node,
we need to put the data into two categories,
into two parts normally, based on a certain rule.
And if the data is an ordinal, then we
can use something like, if this feature is greater than some
value, if the result is greater than good,
that means even very good, then we can divide them.
Because the ordinal, we can see which value is bigger than
or greater than some other value.
If this is nominal, we cannot see using a greater than
something or less than something.
But we can use a tree if a value equals something,
and then we divide them in, then equal, and non-equal,
divide the data into two sets.
So we should differentiate the nominal and the ordinal.
In some classifiers, we should differentiate the two data.
But for the numerical data, whether the quality
is an interval or a ratio, normally we
don't try to differentiate the two types of data.
So this diagram shows, just shows the categorization
of the data.
So attributes, then we have a qualitative data,
or categorical data, then we have a quantitative data,
or numerical data.
So for each of them, we can divide them
into two types, nominal, ordinal, interval, or ratio.
So we need to understand the nature of the data,
the type of the data.
And this actually, I just mentioned,
if you know the type, whether it's ordinal,
and then if ordinal, we can use a greater than something,
it's a value.
And what is greater?
Actually, in the computer, part of it,
this is actually very good or bad.
Part of it is denoted by numerical value.
For example, good, good, now we start from the bad,
very good, for example, is a four.
And then good is a three.
And then actually, the average is two.
And then per is one.
So sometimes we can use a greater than something, right?
If this actually, like a performance,
is greater than two.
Because this is an ordinal, we can use this.
So if this is nominal, then we can only
use whether this value is equal to this.
Blood type, we cannot see that our blood type is greater
than something.
We cannot see that.
OK.
And so this is another kind of categorization for the data.
So in this data, they simply consider
discrete or continuous.
The data, whether this data, this feature or this data
is discrete or this data is continuous.
So we use this actually.
The data is simply put in these two groups, two categories.
For the discrete, discrete, that
means actually that this feature or this attribute,
we have limited possible values.
Just now we use the gender, right?
The gender.
Male, female, just two possible values, right?
The blood types, AB, ABO.
Only four types.
So these possible values are very limited.
Two and four, right?
Just now in the result, good average per three categories,
three possible results.
So this kind of data actually is discrete.
So we have finite.
So actually, countably infinite.
They mean this number could be very large, huge.
But there is a correspondence with a natural number.
Although this number is big, right?
Then this one, actually this number could correspond to a one.
This number could correspond to one billion.
Actually, that is a one to one correspondence
with a natural number.
Although this number is huge, so it is still considered
as a discrete.
So quite often we think about the discrete.
We think about the unlimited value, right?
Limited.
But this value could be huge.
Countable infinite.
So that means actually, as long as there
is a one to one correspondence with a natural number,
a natural number could be a very big number, right?
So as long as there is such a correspondence,
then actually it will be considered as a discrete data.
And so nominal data, certainly, nominal, right?
Nominal, all actually, the, you know, it's a, OK.
If this is actually discrete, actually, only two values
are male or female, right?
So or fail or pass.
So this kind of value, they call binary attributes.
So these are special kind of discrete attributes,
only two possible values.
OK, so the next actually is a continuous.
Continuous attributes can take many values, right?
Can take actually any possible values in a range.
And actually, so just actually your body weight, right?
This is all temperature of the room.
You can measure the temperature, right?
And 25 or 0.5, maybe at the beginning, later change to 26.5.
And later change to 26.3.
So any possible values.
OK, yeah, set a range, right?
So this is continuous.
Continuous.
OK, so sometimes actually you differentiate, actually,
you know, nominal, internal or racial.
But sometimes you simply put this into two categories.
A discrete and continuous.
OK.
So in general, nominal and the ordinal attributes
are discrete, right?
Because they just have a limiting value.
They are categorical, right?
Categorical.
OK.
And it will reach out to the quantum data.
So they are continuous.
Or they are also numerical data.
So these are just the data types, right?
The data types.
And so next actually we look at the exploration
of the structure of the data.
OK.
So when you give a data, right, when I give a data,
so when you collect the data, actually, quite often,
actually, you may get the data, for example,
from the website, right?
And actually, quite often, actually, the data
is also attached with the so-called data dictionary.
Dictionary.
OK.
And actually, this data dictionary, actually,
just then, actually, presents the information
of this data set, the information.
In particular, the information about the features,
the attributes, the types of attributes.
OK.
So these are the data dictionary.
But if you collect data, right?
You collect data.
And then you also want to keep the data for others
to use in the future.
So probably you also need to actually now
make such a data dictionary, actually,
to a certain data set.
So data dictionary actually introduce or express
the information about the data set,
in particular, about the property or nature of the features,
including the name of the feature, the type of the feature.
OK.
The detailed information of each of the attributes.
So these are data dictionary and the data type.
Some relevant details.
Actually, sometimes you just give a feature, right?
You must give the data.
Sometimes, actually, you introduce
how this feature is obtained.
And remember, there is some data set.
OK.
So the data set, actually, it is not very raw data.
This data actually derived from the image.
OK.
So this feature is the top out of which property
is extracted from the image feature.
A image.
OK.
And this feature, second feature,
is what feature, which property of the image.
They introduce this.
Also give the name.
This feature is about the blood pressure of the patient.
And this is no feature.
It's about the temperature, body temperature of this patient.
OK.
They not only just give the value, right?
In this dictionary, they also talk about,
oh, this feature is the name of the feature.
How this feature actually obtained.
OK.
Extra information about the feature.
So of course, actually, sometimes maybe, actually,
the data dictionary is not actually available.
And then we should use some functions in the toolbox
to discover the top of the features, the nature of the features.
OK.
So these are the dictionaries.
So here, actually, I just show one data dictionary.
Actually, if you study machine learning,
I think best actually, we should know machine learning
data repository.
This is UCI, University of California, at Avering.
So UCI, machine learning data repository.
So this is a repository.
And there are a lot of data set.
For each data set, for example, for the auto and the car,
auto, the MPG data set.
And they give this information, right?
The number of samples, the feature types, right?
And whether there are missing values.
So here, then, for the variables,
as we talked about, the variable name, like a displacement.
And then, so the type of the data are continuous.
And the cylinder and the integer types,
whether there are missing values or not,
they all give this kind of information.
So this is a data dictionary.
And it's very useful for us to understand
the nature of the data, the data types.
At the beginning, I see the data type is important.
And when we actually look for or select or choose suitable,
learning or learning or suitable models,
actually, we need to have a good answer about the data type
and also have a good answer about the model.
So this model, whether it can be applied to nominal data
or ordinal data.
So we should have this understanding.
So we have to get the information
about the type of the feature.
Actually, we can get it from the data dictionary.
I just mentioned, if not available,
then we maybe need to use some software to discover.
Actually, then we can even plot the data
to decide whether this data is continuous or discrete.
If we know the nature, this should perform very good.
And then, all we know, this is ordinal.
So through this exploration, we can understand the data.
So now, actually, we have a 10-inch brick.
After brick, then we will look further
into the exploration of the data structure.
So we can see that we have a lot of data.
So here I copy part of the
part of the
part of the MPG data set
to show this.
And this data set has a few features.
And the MPG
cylinder
displacement, horsepower, weight.
And all the
acceleration, model year
origin.
So this is actually
all actually
features.
This is a feature.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
And then the last one
is the car name.
And actually here
actually some of the variables
are already given all the numerical, right?
Origin.
And actually this origin is normally
this actually like categorical variables.
Although they are numerical
here they are not named value, right?
But they are categorical.
So because for the
origin, origin
which is the origin of the car.
One is USA,
two is Japan
and then number three maybe
Germany.
So this is the origin of the cars.
So just a limited value, right?
And also the car name
also limited.
These are the nominal values, right?
Nominal. You cannot see
one country is bigger than another, right?
Now the value is bigger than another one, right?
So like origin
and also the car name.
So these are the
nominal data, right?
So categorical.
Nominal.
But for some of the variables
actually you can see
like
cylinder, right?
Cylinder actually is
here they just show like
four, six, eight.
And actually this shows one is bigger
cylinder actually is categorical
but it is ordinal.
Okay. It's ordinal.
Okay.
And then we have some other like
horsepower and also the displacement.
So these are the continuous.
These are the
quantitative data
or numerical data.
Okay. Or continuous.
So some of them are discrete.
Some of them actually
are continuous, right?
So for the discrete
some of them actually are
nominal and some of them
are ordinal.
Okay. I just said you already analyzed, right?
Origin means the country.
So although each country here
denoted by one numerical value
but it is still numerical.
So this is categorical.
Actually this actually is
nominal. The car name here
they are given the name, the name of the value, right?
But actually
this is a nominal.
We cannot see
one name is bigger than another name.
Normally we don't see this.
So this is a nominal.
Okay. So this data
normally is called mixed.
Mixed. Okay.
If a data set contains actually
more than one type of data
then this data is set
is called mixed data.
And quite often we know
the data is mixed.
Okay. We have different types
of data.
And for the
nominal data actually
although it is denoted
by the number here, right?
And actually
I think this point, I think I want to emphasize
I talked about this a few times actually
I want to emphasize this.
Although here they are given numerical values
but normally we cannot see one value
greater than another value.
We cannot see that.
They are denoted by different numbers.
These different numbers
only show they are different.
This country, two,
is different from another country, one.
Different from country three.
So this value only shows the difference.
We don't have a sense
that one value is greater than another value.
Okay. So I think
these are very important property.
And actually so
we have a model. Sometimes
we need to analyze this nature
and then we decide actually
what kind of model we should use
actually
in the learning.
Okay.
So these are some analysis, right?
Okay. Real numbers.
Okay.
And actually the cylinder here
and the origin has
numerical values actually.
Although they are numerical,
they are denoted by numerical value.
But actually in practice
we should consider them actually
as categorical.
Okay.
So that's actually we explore the numerical data.
Now we know that data can be
categorical
or numerical, right?
So that's actually you first look
at all the numerical data.
And the first
exploration is to understand
the central tendency.
The central tendency.
Okay.
I think the central tendency,
how to measure this central tendency.
I think the most commonly used
measure is just the mean.
Okay. Mean actually the most
frequently used metric
and for the
central tendency.
Okay.
So the mean value, the mean.
What is the mean? Mean is just the average, right?
In statistics, so this is called
expectation.
Okay.
So what is expectation?
So it depends how to calculate expectation, right?
And we have formula to calculate.
But actually, you know, this is actually
I think the mean
expectation
of the mean is just the average.
Right?
So here we can put the summation first
and then divide it by the number,
number of numbers.
Then actually just get the average.
So from here, you know, for the mean,
we first get the summation addition, right?
So addition.
So certainly, you know, this addition
should not be performed actually
on the
categorical data, right?
We cannot actually get the average.
Because we cannot get the summation, right?
So we don't have the mean
for categorical variables.
Okay.
So this is for continuous, right?
For numerical values, number four continuous.
For quantitative data.
Quantitative, the continuous
is the numerical, right?
So for numerical data,
we can calculate the mean.
So mean is the most frequently used
measure for the
central tendency of the data.
Okay.
Then another measure is called median.
Median value, right?
So normally, I render data
in a sequence.
Increasing order or decreasing order.
Then the median
is just the value
in the middle, right?
So here we have five numbers.
And we render data
in increasing order.
Then the 67,
actually it's in the middle number, right?
So the 67 is just the median.
Okay.
So these are the
median.
And so mean is
impacted
if too many data elements
having values
close to the far end of the range.
In other words, actually even in a data set,
there are many extreme
values.
Many extreme values.
Okay.
So there are a few extreme values.
Extreme high values
or extreme low values.
So these extreme low or extreme high values
could be caused by
error.
So you will use
limited
average to find the mean, right?
So certainly, these are not small
numbers. Not many number of big
values, small values.
Certainly we will have a big impact
on this mean value, right?
So mean value is
easier to be affected
by noisy data.
The mean value.
Okay.
In particular, if the data has some outliers,
right?
We want to cover the average
wealth
of the people in this classroom
together with Ma Yun
and Bill Gates, right?
So they are increased.
Actually, certainly this is not
a good measure for the central tendency
of the wealth of the people
in this classroom, right?
Because they are outliers.
Okay.
So in such a scenario,
we should use actually
the median value, right?
You arrange them, right?
Arrange all the wealth
of every people in this classroom
together with Ma Yun
and Bill Gates. You still find that
actually this median value
is less affected
by those extreme values
outliers.
Okay. So this is actually
the median, right?
And actually in practice,
actually, across all the actually
we compare
the difference between the median value
and the mean values.
So normally, the median values
and the mean values should be close to each other.
Although they are not the same value, right?
Actually, but normally
there is not a big difference between the two.
Okay.
So we should use plot of the deviation between the two.
If the deviation between the two,
the difference between the two is big.
And then actually we can
look further into the data.
Okay. For example, right?
And if there is
a big difference between the mean
and the median.
So most likely, there are some outliers
in the data.
There are some extreme high values
so both type of values, right?
Will affect the mean value.
Okay.
So you can observe the difference between
the median and the mean, right?
From here, we can actually, you know,
deduce probably
the data contains some outliers.
Okay.
Then we should try to find
these outliers and then take some measures
actually to impute these outliers.
Okay.
So this is the
exploration, right?
Look at the tendency,
look at the mean, look at that.
Then we can look at the median.
Then we can some, can discover
some potential issues underlying the data.
Okay.
Another
commonly used tree, Merian,
is called Mood.
Mood is
more frequently used tree, you know,
for others, right?
For the nominal
or for the
ordinal.
So
we cannot get the summation, right?
We cannot get the summation.
We cannot get the average.
Certainly we cannot take the mean, right?
We cannot take the mean.
But actually we can take the median.
And also a tree, we can take the so-called
Mood.
Mood actually is the most frequent
value
of the tree.
For example, in the class, right?
Actually we can test
the blood type of each student.
Okay.
And we have blood type A,
we have blood type B, AB, and O, right?
Actually, of course, we know
probably, and the result is that
actually we cannot take the average.
We see every blood type
of the students' classroom.
We cannot have these values.
But we can see the most frequent, right?
Actually the blood B
has the largest number,
largest proportion. Okay.
So the Mood.
The Mood, right?
Actually it is the most frequent number.
Most frequent number here.
We can take this as
a central tendency
for actually
for the categorical values.
Of course, for continuity
we can still look at that, right?
But for continuous, and probably
mean, and the median actually are better
measures for the central tendencies.
Okay.
So this is the three measures,
mean, media, mean,
and the mood for the central tendency.
Okay.
And this diagram shows us
the mean
value and also the median
value for all the features,
right?
And as you can see, also
we can find the deviation,
the difference.
And for the MPG,
the difference is only 2.17%.
So this is
a low number, right?
This is actually a difference in low.
But for some values, right?
For some features
or attributes, like displacement,
the
median is 148.5
and the mean value
is now 9.4.
So there is a very big difference.
Actually the difference is 23.22%.
So this is very high.
Okay.
So by looking at this summary
of the
mean and the media, then we check the difference.
And then we can
know actually which feature
has a high
difference between the mean
and the media, right? Then we can
look further into the data
and see whether there are some issues
in the data
for that particular attributes.
And also in this table
we show the horsepower.
There is no value for the
median. There is no value for the mean.
Okay.
Certainly actually,
we have a run program,
the other program cannot calculate,
is able to calculate the mean
value and the median value.
Okay. Then we should look further, right?
Look into the data
to check. So what are the issues?
And then we should try our best
to address these issues.
Okay.
So for this entry, we can note a tree
like
why we have this entry, no question mark
there, right? So this is because
we look further into the data
and we find a tree
for the horsepower.
There are six
samples.
Horse power
have no values.
So six samples
have no value for the horsepower
for this attribute.
So if no value
actually this is the so-called
mission value problem.
Mission value. So later we will
actually talk about this further.
So if there are mission values
in the future, so
how we should address this
issue?
Mission values, right?
If there are mission values, normally
no question mark, right?
Or just empty, right?
For that element,
in a matrix, right?
Then actually
the program has no problem
to calculate the mean.
That's the reason why we see the question mark there.
Okay.
So, but just now do a bit of exploration, right?
Actually we have
a lot of data understanding
about the data, right?
Look at the data dictionary
and then we can understand the data types, right?
Nominal, ordinal
all actually we see the numerical, right?
Or we see the continuous.
We can look at this, right?
And by looking at the mean, the central tendency
look at the difference
between the mean and the median, right?
And we can have further understanding
about the data.
So potentially
one potential issue, right?
Like, you know, all the layers
in the data.
And also in this example
show that we probably
the data could have the mission value problem.
Then for some features
we don't have actually the mean.
We don't have the median, right?
This is because actually the program
that could cannot actually calculate this value
because of the mission values
in this feature.
Okay?
So this is a solution, right?
Just give a data set
just at the beginning or just give this, right?
Give it to you.
Give it to you, right?
I think this is it, right?
We just know the value there, right?
But after, you know,
through many steps, right?
Look at the features, the natures
and then by looking at the median
and mean values.
Certainly now we have better understanding
of the data set, right?
Better understanding.
Okay.
So that's actually,
before, certainly we should
understand our data, right?
We cannot just call a function
and then put the data in
and then get a model
based on the model to make a prediction.
Our task is to get a good model
to make accurate prediction.
It not just a get a model
get a prediction.
Your work, your job here
is not just to lend this code.
Your job is to get a good result
to graduate with a high GPA, right?
So that's the same thing, right?
So we show that you
you understand the data
in order to actually produce the best model
and the best prediction
from the model.
Okay.
So through, actually until now,
we have looked into the
central tendency,
and checked that it's different between
mean and the median value,
and we have better understanding, right?
And also we have discovered
one issue in the data,
so the mission values.
Potential issue, otolias.
Okay.
So that's actually we understand
the data spread.
The dispersion or
actually we, yeah, okay,
the dispersion of the data.
Okay. The range of the data.
Okay. So that is
the data spread.
So, beside the central tendency,
we also need to look at the
actually the range of the data, right?
Look at the dispersion of the data.
And also position
of the different data values.
So these are the
actually another aspect,
another characteristic
of the data, the spread.
Okay.
So for the dispersion,
actually, mirror,
so normally, you know,
we use the standard vision.
So here, actually, we can see
why we need to have this
mirror,
or have this understanding of the data
spread.
So here we have given
six values, five values,
right, five values,
and for
each one, attribute one
attribute two,
and actually both values,
both attributes
actually have a
mean value
of 46.
Actually, the two have the same mean value.
But if we look at the attribute one,
the value is 44,
46, 48, 45, 47,
the mean is 46.
That means all the values
are around the mean value, right?
So the spread is small.
Okay.
Actually, the range of the data is close
to actually the mean value.
But if we look at the
second attribute, right,
so 34,
now it's very far from the mean value
46, right, and also the
52, or 59,
very far away from 66.
That means the spread,
dispersion is very high.
The variation of the data
is very high.
And for this attribute,
actually number two.
And so actually,
to measure this
spread,
and quite often, we use the so-called
the variance.
So we practice how to
calculate the variance.
So, as you might see,
for the variable X, or feature X,
and so we have
n values.
So this is the average of
X squared.
For every
value for this feature,
right, so we take the
squared, get the summation, then get the average.
So this is the mean of X squared.
And then the second
part actually, so you look at the tree,
the one in the bracket, right inside the bracket,
so this is simply the mean of Xk,
the mean of X.
So this is the part actually,
the square of the mean, right?
So these are two, the variance
that equals
actually the mean of X squared,
right?
Minus the square of the mean of X.
Okay, so this is the
variance.
And actually,
certainly, actually,
we can have actually almost
an equivalent, right,
measure,
which is just the square root of the variance.
So this actually defined as
the standard deviation.
Standard deviation of sigma
actually equals the square root
of the variance of X.
Okay, so for
spread,
for data dispersion,
we use these two measures.
Okay, these two are actually identical, right?
So one is the standard deviation,
another is the variance.
So one of these is very
important, one of these measures, right?
So the general tendency,
and also to spread the variance
or the standard deviation measures
are important.
Actually, so later,
today, actually,
this week,
we'll see, week seven probably,
then we will study actually
one type of a Pennet classification,
actually, which is called actually
the linear,
just mean analysis.
And actually, we use standard
in the Pennet classification,
so what features normally we prefer?
So normally, we hope
the data in classification,
so what could be considered
as an easy task?
If, okay, the two classes
are very different,
and for all the samples
within the same class, they are similar,
then it is easy to differentiate,
easy to differentiate, okay?
So within class,
within class difference
is small.
Within the same class,
the samples should be very similar.
Between class,
the samples could be
very different.
Okay, so how to measure
actually
within class similarity?
How to measure this?
Within class, all the samples are similar.
Actually, this is
the spread of the data around the mean vector.
Normally, it's not just
the mean value, right?
So normally, we use multiple features,
so it's the mean vector.
So around the mean vector,
the spread is small.
Then, that means
within class,
similarity is high,
or the difference is small,
then to classify,
the classification task is easier.
Then, even between class,
the difference is big.
That means it is easy to differentiate
because the difference is big.
But how to measure the difference
between the two?
Actually, we use the distance
between the two mean vectors
of the sample in the two classes.
Okay, so from here, you can see
the importance of
the mean of sampling
within the same class,
and the spread of the sample
within the same class.
Actually, we try to find
even the features
and show that sample within the same class
could have a
small spread.
Okay, between class,
we could have a very big difference.
Okay, so that is the reason
why we need to look at
the central tendency, the mean
vectors, and also the variance.
Okay, and
all know,
correct metrics, even
high terminal space.
Okay, so these are
the two measures.
Through this data,
we can understand that
this problem is probably an easy task.
This problem could be
very challenging.
Even in a feature,
all the data are mixed.
If we are using the CGPA
to differentiate male and female students,
are you able to do that?
All the CGPA or male
or female students are overlapped.
You cannot differentiate.
Right?
So that is the reason why
we don't see
because of the
mean of the two,
the difference
between the classes
are small, right?
The difference is small.
So it's very hard.
It's a very hard task.
So through exploration
of the spread
and also the central tendency of the data,
certainly we can understand
whether this is an easy task
or this is a very challenging task.
Okay.
So you can also see
the reason why we need
to do this exploration, right?
Even before we perform millennium,
we need to perform such exploration
of the data
to understand the challenges
of the given task.
Okay.
So next actually is a column
data value position.
Just now we see for the
spread of the data, look at the dispersion,
look at the various,
all standard divisions, right?
Here we also look at the actually
and the position of the data.
So the position of some values.
So here the mean of five values,
the position of five values.
Okay. So this position of five values
also to describe
the characteristics of the data.
By analyzing these five values,
we can also actually
have a better understanding
about the data distribution.
Okay.
So which hold the five value, right?
Actually,
just now we talk about the media, right?
If we put the data in a sequence,
sending all the, or descending all the,
we can find the middle, right?
A middle point. So the middle value is just the media.
Okay.
So the middle value divide the whole data
in the data sequence
actually into two half, right?
The first half, the second half.
Okay. For the first half,
we can also find the middle value, right?
The middle value, the median value.
Okay. And actually the first half,
the median value of the first half of the data
is called quanta,
the first quanta or q1.
So we define this value, right?
This is actually the first quanta,
this is 25%.
You rank the data, right?
So this is 25%.
What is this mean?
This is q1, the first quanta.
Okay.
And then for the second half,
certainly you can find,
you know, the middle value, right?
So this middle value actually is 75%.
So this is called
that quanta.
Q3.
Actually, Q2 is just the median,
the overall median of the data.
So the 50%.
So q1 is 25%, right?
Q2 is 50%, the one in the middle, right?
Q3 is actually 75%,
actually, percent.
Okay.
So normally this is called percent tau, right?
25% tau,
actually, you know, 50%
percent tau
and 75%
percent tau.
Okay. So these are q1, q2, q3.
Okay.
And besides these,
the three values,
and we also have another two values.
That is called
minimum value and the maximum value.
So remember, this is the minimum value
and not the minimum smallest value
in the sequence.
And not the maximum value in the sequence.
So later we will see
how to find this, actually,
minimum value and maximum value.
Okay. So these are the five values.
Five values.
Okay.
So for example,
actually,
the auto-MPG dataset, right?
And we have, actually,
this data.
And also we have found,
actually, the q1,
q2.
Q2 is just the media, overall media,
just q2 and q3.
And also the minimum
and the maximum.
And actually, for
displacement,
we can also find the value.
For origin, we can also find the values.
Okay.
So these are the,
yeah.
So this table, you know,
just to summarize, actually,
these five values.
Q1, q2, q3,
25% howl,
50% howl,
75% howl.
Minimum maximum.
And actually, through,
actually, and like this,
q1, q2, q3,
and we can also
discover some issues of the data.
Okay.
And for example,
actually,
we look at the difference
between q1
for the displacement,
right, the displacement, which continues.
And actually,
the q1,
so here, actually,
the calculator, actually, the q1,
38.
Right?
I don't know, right, right?
68.
Sorry.
68, right?
And then, actually, the,
sorry, the,
104, 104,
the q1, right?
And then, actually,
we see the minimum distance between the minimum
and the q1 is 36.2, right?
And the difference
between q1 and the median
is 44.3, okay?
And, okay,
but actually, this is for the,
for the first half, right?
Then we look at the second half,
and the q3 is 11.5,
and,
okay, so I think q3
is
262, right?
262, and the difference
between, actually, the median
and the, this is q3
is 113.5,
and q3, the maximum value
difference is 103, okay?
You can see, actually, in the first half,
actually, the difference between the minimum
and the q1, the difference between q1
and q2, this value is small, right?
But actually, for the
second half of data, that means, actually,
from q2, q3, and the maximum, right?
Then the difference is 100
something, much bigger than the
previous part, right?
So, actually, from this difference,
actually, we can see some problems,
okay? So, that means that the data,
the larger values are more
spread, spread out in the,
okay, in the,
the larger values spread out,
okay?
Then, actually, the small values, okay?
So, actually, through data, you can also imagine
the data, right? If you previously
had experience of handling data, right?
So, you can imagine, oh, in the low data,
in low part, they are
concentrating in that part, but for the
high values, they spread out.
So, you can have some imagination, right?
You can imagine the data distribution.
This kind of data normally is called skewed.
Skewed, okay?
The skewness of the data also
presents challenges
to machine learning to modeling.
Okay? So, through this analysis,
we can discover issues with the data,
right? And then, we can
actually, you know, adopt, you know,
necessary actions or measures
to address all these issues.
But if you don't do this kind of exploration,
you cannot find the issue.
Okay? You just, oh, this is a number, right?
So,
you cannot just look
at the number to, to discover the issues.
You need to do the exploration, right?
You look at the central mean,
the central tendency,
look at the spread of the data,
look at, you know, the, actually, the
farm numbers.
Okay?
Okay.
And the next, I think, is for
illustration of the farm numbers,
and, actually,
we can use the so-called, actually, the box plot.
Give the numbers, right?
But maybe, you know,
if we can visualize the data distribution,
probably, you know, we can understand
the problem even better, right?
Okay. So, this is the box plot.
And this diagram, actually,
box plot, actually, is just a visualization
of the farm numbers, right?
The position of the farm numbers.
Okay. The mean, the M1,
Q1, Q2, Q3, right?
Actually, in the box plot,
so in the middle, there is a box.
So, this is why the reason why I call box plot, right?
There is a box. And, actually,
this boundary, the edge here,
is a Q3.
And then, in the middle,
there is a, you know,
a big line, right?
A big line.
This is just the
median, Q2.
Okay. So, we have Q1,
Q2, Q3.
Q1, Q2, Q3. So, these are three numbers.
And then, we also need to find, actually,
the minimum
and maximum.
Actually, the minimum and maximum are not
necessarily the minimum and maximum of the data.
Okay. So, naturally,
we look at, actually, how these minimum and maximum
values are found.
Okay. So,
so here, we
define a so-called
inter-quantum range,
which is the difference between Q3 and Q1.
We have Q1, Q2, Q3, right?
So, the difference between Q3
and Q1 is called
inter-quantum, actually, range,
AQR.
So, based on the one
AQR, actually, we can find the minimum
value and the maximum value.
Okay. So, from the
diagram here, actually,
now, we can extend this, actually,
further to Q1 minus
1.5,
actually, AQR,
to get the minimum.
Okay.
From the bottom of the box, Q1.
Okay. Then, we can get, actually,
so this gets a minimum.
Minimum. Okay.
So, we get 1.5, actually, times
of the AQR.
So, in this question, actually, Q1,
Q3, just to see that, and then Q,
Q3
is 79. Okay. Then, the AQR,
inter-quantum
range is Q3 minus Q1, right?
In the example, so it's
79 minus 73 is
6.
Okay. And then, we should, from the bottom,
the bottom Q, Q1, right?
Q1 is C3.
Q3, and then, from here,
we minus 1.5
times 6.
1.5 times AQR, right?
So, we should, actually, from,
actually, 73 minus AQR minus,
actually,
actually, 1.5 times
of the AQR,
then get 64.
But, this 64 is not
really the minimum.
Actually, the minimum should be found
from the data. Okay.
So, we should actually look at all the data
that is around
64. Okay. We should
find a one that is above 64.
Okay. For example,
in the real data, there,
actually, the data around 64 is
63, 70, and 60.
Okay. We should use
the value that is above
64 as the
minimum value. So, here,
actually, 1 is 70, right?
70. Okay.
So, we can use the minimum value.
Say 70 and the minimum value.
Okay. And then, if a value is
below the 70, it will be
considered as an outlier,
extreme values.
Okay. So, this is
the minimum value. And for the
maximum value, we should start from,
actually, the Q3.
Q3, right?
So, we should find the value
plus, actually,
1.5, actually,
accurate.
Okay. So, for
the Arbor Whisker, it's 10 to 1.5
in this question, right?
So, like, Q3
plus 1.5, accurate.
Q3, we already found the, know the
value, right? Q3 is 70 now.
And then times, then
plus, actually, now.
Okay. So, this should be,
actually, the maximum value.
Okay.
But whether this is, it should be
used as, actually,
the maximum value, no, actually,
we need to look at the data, right?
We should find one that is
slightly below this 88
from the data sequence, okay?
So, from the data sequence,
from the data, we find, actually,
no, like, 82, 84, 89,
close to 88, right?
The one that is below this,
should be the one as the maximum
value.
Okay.
Okay. So, we use, actually,
84 as the maximum value.
Okay. Then the value above
84 will be considered as
extreme values, or like this.
Okay. So, if you look
back to this diagram, this is the
box plot.
This is the box plot, or some values, like,
this is not the box plot, right?
K1, K2, K3, the
minimum value, maximum value.
Then above here, can you see,
there are otolias,
extreme, low or extreme,
high values.
Okay. And these extreme, low or
extreme, high values,
that could be called by many reasons.
Could not be called by many reasons, right?
Sometimes, that could be called by errors.
Okay. And sometimes,
otolias are natural, right?
Just as an example, look at the
data, original wealth, right?
The wealth of
every person here you have,
and also the wealth by the
Mayan, the Bill Gates.
So, they are the value
otolias, but certainly, these
otolias are natural, right? In no
noise. Okay. By some
scenario, this actually could be,
you know, an error when you record
on the number, called by error.
Okay. So, you know, if
we are doing different, we have
different reasons, then probably we need
to use different actions or
measures to address these
otolias issues.
Okay. So, these are
the data, right? The box plot.
Actually, a lot of the function on my lab,
they provide this function. Give the data,
you know, otherwise, to plot this
box plot. Okay.
Just use the box plot, this function,
then you can plot this. Okay.
This is actually, in the diagram,
shows the box plot of the different
attributes.
The box plot, and for cylinder,
now you can see that the
shape is part different, right?
So, these show the data characteristics,
you know, are very different
from one feature to another feature.
Okay. Because if the
box plot doesn't look similar, right?
And then,
actually,
maybe the data distribution
will be similar. But here, then, you
look at that, they are very different, right?
They are very different.
Okay. So, this box plot
is a good visualization
tool, which can give us,
you know, a good understanding
about the data distribution.
Okay.
Just now, we see, you know,
for the displacement, actually, we find
that there are big difference, right?
Between the media and the mean values, right?
And in the, between Q3,
the difference between Q3 and the media,
right? And also, between the
difference between Q2, right?
And also, the
difference between the maximum
value and the Q3.
So, we have looked at that value.
And also, we have looked into the,
this value normally not big, right? Like 100.
But for the first half of the data,
the difference between the
minimum value and the Q1, actually,
it's small. The difference between Q2
and Q1 is small. That is something, right?
So, we see all the data is probably
spread out in the, for larger
values. Okay. So, this diagram
should show the, you know, there's a
broad plot of the, you know, the
displacement. Actually, you can see the
data, right? In data, you know, this
is a medium, right? So, for the larger
range, right? This actually
indeed spread out for the larger
values, right? For the larger values.
For small values, they are more
concentrated.
For this part, a big difference,
right? Between the maximum value
and the medium and the Q3.
And also, the difference between Q3
and the, and the mean.
So, this is actually the very effective
visualization tool, right?
Both plots are very visualized tool.
Which can help us
to have a good understanding about the
data distributions.
Okay. The understanding of good
distribution of the data could
help us decide, you know,
what measures we should use
to address these issues.
For example, you know, if the data
is big value data, right?
Probably, you know, for the data, you
can take some, you know, many, many
operations. Like, you can take a
logarithm operation, right?
Then to actually reduce,
actually, to make the, you know,
to make the data less skewed.
Now, it's all known in the high part,
right? If you take a logarithm operation,
right? And then, the data
will be actually more evenly
uniformly distributed.
Okay. So,
through this operation, you can
find the issues.
Then you can take measures to address
the issues. Okay. And then,
finally, you can get a better model
which can produce a more
accurate predictions.
Okay. So, from here,
today until now,
I hope that you understand
the fitting model, not just
a core function, put the data in, right?
Actually, it's
very necessary to do this kind
of exploration, to understand
the data. And before,
actually, you know, to find the issues
also, and take some
measures to address the issues. And before
we apply input data
to the learning algorithm
to fit a model.
Okay.
So,
next, actually, visualization tool
is called histogram.
Histogram. Just now, we just
see the fine-value position, right?
Q1, Q2, Q3, minimum,
maximum, right? Then we have
box plot. They give us an understanding,
right? And actually, a histogram
is another effective
visualization tool,
right? To visualize the data distribution.
Okay. In this, actually, histogram,
normally, we divide the data
into many
beams. For example, the data
is from the value from
1 to 10,
for example, right? You
can divide the whole range
into 10 beams,
okay? From
0, or from 1 to 10, right?
From 11 to 20,
okay? From 21
to 30, okay? You have different
range. And this is called
beams. And then you
check how many data
points, actually,
fall into this range.
Then you call the number,
okay? Then you can explore this.
So this is called, actually, the histogram.
So the horizontal
shows the values, okay? So here,
you can see this, right? So this is
a beam from here to
this value, right? From here to here,
actually, the whole range
is divided into many beams. Of
course, in the function, often,
the default value is set to 10,
but you can decide the
beam number. You can also
decide, actually, the beam size,
the range of the beam, from
which, you know,
from which, starting from
which value, and
to what value, right? This other range
of the beam. You can define normally,
okay? Then, actually, we call
the number. So this diagram
shows the distribution of the data,
right? So here, the first one,
symmetric uniform. You can see
in all the beams, right? The number,
actually, horizontal shows the number
of the cost, how many data
points, how many values,
okay? How many values are in this
range, okay? So here,
they're all similar, right? Similar.
Doesn't mean the data distribution is
quite even, right? Uniform,
uniform.
Uniform is quite uniform, the
first one, right? Then the second one,
as you can see, this is symmetric,
like, you know,
this is symmetric, right?
A union model,
union model, union mean single,
right? Uniform model, just
one peak. So this is quite like,
you know, Gaussian distribution,
right? Gaussian distribution. So
from here, oh, this sample, this data
point, this is no feature,
probably the data following normal
distribution. You can look at this,
this is quite similar to a normal
distribution, right?
And then look at another no data,
this is actually skewed, skewed,
this is called left skewed,
okay? And then this is quite,
actually, this is a right skewed,
skewed, okay?
And then from here, this is actually
like a bi-modal,
because here we can see like two peaks,
right? From here to here,
then from here to here. So probably,
actually, the feature shows two
points, right? So we can see
that the two peaks are normal
distribution. If you want to build
a model for this kind of distribution
and we can use the so-called Gaussian
and Mischem model. So in the next week,
when we study actually one
approach, which is the statistical
approach for pendant classification
and actually one important part
of this algorithm is to
estimate the probability distribution
function, probability density function,
okay? It's called class conditional
normal distribution. And then we need
to find the parameter of model
distribution to fit the data, right?
But sometimes the data maybe
cannot be modeled by one single
actually, the normal distribution function.
It will be modeled by
multiple
normal distribution functions.
So that is the Gaussian-Mischem model,
right? So through
this analysis, this histogram,
we can discover the data, right?
Or there are two peaks, something like that,
probably there are two. We can use
the two normal
Gaussian functions
to actually model
this data distribution, right?
So if you don't actually plot
this histogram, actually we cannot
have this understanding, right?
Then you probably just use one.
Then you fit the model. It's like, oh,
the performance is not satisfactory.
You don't know the reason. Why?
But actually through this analysis
of the data, through this, actually,
the histogram, we can understand
actually the data
for normal distribution, but we need
to use more than one
normal distribution function, right?
More than one Gaussian function
to fit the data, right?
So we can discover
the root cause of the problem,
right? Then you can take
measures, right? Use the two
Gaussian functions
actually to model the distribution,
okay? So here probably
there are multiples, right? So there is
one Gaussian function here, another Gaussian function.
So here we need to use
more than two in multiple Gaussian
functions, Gaussian-Mitcher model
actually
to fit the data.
Okay, you can see, you know, right?
Sometimes we fit the data, get a color
function, performance not satisfactory.
We don't know the reason, right?
But through exploration
of the data, we can find actually
the issues, right? So these
issues, these phenomena, these
information can guide us
to decide the supermodels
actually for this specific
task.
Okay, and then actually
you can get a better model
to make more accurate predictions.
Okay, so we have a ten minute break.
Okay.
So both plots and
the histogram
are provided with
effective tools
and for visualization of the data
distribution.
Okay.
And actually here we can have a look
of the distribution
and all the histogram
and different attributes
in the auto-MPG data set.
Right?
And then we can see actually the
distribution, right?
Are quite different, right?
For some data set, right?
For
MPG and for all other like
model years, it's quite
uniform, right? Quite uniform.
But for some of them like
for this acceleration, right?
It follows like a normal distribution.
So you can see the different characteristics
of the different attributes
in the data set. Okay.
Certainly, through
exploration of the data, right?
Particularly visualization of the data distribution
by the histogram
or the both plots, we can have
a better understanding about the data.
So certainly this help us
to decide on the suitable models
and also the learning argument
for this data set.
Okay.
So necessarily
this is just the exploration
for the numerical data, right?
Quantitative data
or the continuous data.
Continuous
quantitative
of the numerical, right?
Sometimes actually
we use them mislead, right?
Externally, okay? So basically
we can
measure the mean. We can measure
the median. Okay.
So that's the measure of the central tendency.
We can also look at
the dispersion, the spread of the data.
Okay. And also plot
through the both plots
and also the histogram
to look at the data distributions.
Okay. And but for categorical
features
like gender, right?
Like the
gender, right? It's like
so we cannot actually use this
actually, you know, we cannot
carry the mean value. So what
the average of the gender
of this class?
We don't have the average of the gender,
right? So we don't have
average. We don't have the center
of the tendency. Okay. So then
actually how to
actually resale the data
and actually
we can actually
use a table. Use a table.
Okay. So
here actually, this table,
one table is for the
card name. Card name.
Actually we can
and the number of samples
that
take each of the values, right?
For acceleration, for this actually
this is for, I think this here
is for
card name, right? For card name.
So among all the cards, all the
samples, so how many cards actually
have this name? How many cards
have this name? How many cards have
this name? Okay. And for the
cylinder, right? So how many cards
have actually, I have
three. That's four, right? How
many cards have
four cylinders?
So these are two, four cards, right?
So this table also
can give an understanding about
the distribution, the value of
distributions. Okay. So like for
this actually, the second part
for the cylinder, we know
most of the cards have actually
four cylinders because there are
two, four, two hundred and
four cards have four
cylinders, right?
And actually one or three cards have
eight cylinders. Okay. So
very few cards have
three cylinders or five cylinders.
Okay. So this table can also
give us an understanding
about the data, the value
distribution. Okay.
So we cannot actually have this
actually the histogram
and also the BOSS plot
and for the categorical data
but we can only have this kind of
table. Okay.
Okay.
So that's actually is for the
relationship between the
variables, between the attributes
or features. Okay. And
as I said, the beginning
at the beginning of this class
we can talk about the relationship
between the features.
Right. And through
this actually relationship
actually we can explore the
interdependence of the data
or sometimes we call the redundancy
between the data.
Okay. So for this
actually the relationship is flourishing
we can use actually
actually the so called scatter plot
scatter plot. Actually
we can use one actually
to attribute
as the X axis
horizontal axis. We can
use another attribute
as the vertical axis.
So for each sample
actually we have an attribute
one value. We have attribute two value.
So the X1, X2 as a coordinate
we can find the location
in this adrenal plane.
So this is the BOSS plot
it just actually
one actually sample
okay. So this is like
a
displacement is horizontal
okay. And then vertical
actually the
mpg. So each data
each point here
circle here represent one
sample. For this sample
and the
value of displacement is this
and the value mpg and not the value.
We use these two values
as the coordinate
we can have
plot this position
coordinate is just a position
we can plot the data on this plane
so this order
and through this actually
scatter plot
actually we can find the relationship
between the data points.
If one stream case
you can imagine one stream case
the two attributes
actually are identical the same
they are coordinate the same
the coordinate is the same
and then actually
you can imagine actually
all the points actually
are on a straight line
on a straight line.
So this is an extreme case
the data
actually has severely correlated
because the data
with itself right
one attribute
the correlation between one attribute and itself
of course is one the maximum
of the two variables
so one on a straight line
on a straight line.
So this is a case that
when the samples are
when the two actually variable are severely correlated
that means the redundancy
there are redundancies
and then the two attributes
and then actually
the spread is quite narrow
along a line
but if the two
variables are independent
if you actually draw them
you can see
the data like a ball
X1, X2
or sphere shape
something like that
so these are strongly
independent
so these are the two extreme case
all the data points on one straight line
you can imagine
because the two attribute are the same
all the points on a straight line
so very narrow
very narrow
another way to spread
spread very much like a ball
this is a case
when the two features are independent
okay
so through these two extreme cases
and also we look at the true scenario
for a specific
feature
and another feature
then we can understand the
the correlation between the two
what are the
strong redundancy
or strong correlation between them
or the two variables are independent
so this is
through actually
analyzing
this scatter plot
we can have a basic understanding
about the relationship between the variables
okay
sometimes the tree one variable
another variable has a proportionate relationship
okay so again they are on a straight line
they are not
actually along a straight line
not exactly on the straight line
but narrowly along the straight line
so this means the two features
are actually severely correlated
okay
so this is a scatter plot
I think there is another visualization tool
okay to understand the relationship
between two variables
okay
so this
of course this plot plot is for
continuous
attributes or features or variables
for discrete
or categorical
or actually
the sort of qualitative
data
now we can use the so called
two-way cross-tabulation
two-way
okay so this is actually just
such a table
one origin
another model year
origin is a vertical
one denotes USA
two denotes Japan
three denotes Germany
all the car maker countries
so actually
so this middle year model year
60 70
until 1982
so this is through the number
of cars made in USA
so the model years
so for the number of cars
in 1970-1922
okay so these are
so these are the cross-tables
two-way cross-tables
actually also give us
understanding about the relationship
between actually the
two
categorical variables
okay
so let's actually talk about
the data quality
and actually
remediation
at the beginning already talk about
the importance of data quality
right
so actually
this is very important the success
of machine learning
largely depends on the quality of the data
so but in practice
we could encounter some issues
actually the data quality is not perfect
okay so we could
encounter some issues
and so there are two target problems
one is the mission values
problem
mission value actually
in the
we talked about the mean right
central tendency already
illustrate the mission value problem
for some of the features
for some of the samples
and as some features
the value are missing
okay so
actually the mission value could be caused
by different reasons
right and
for example if you ask
you to do an interview right
like an interview
of a student in NTU
and you can ask the tree
your opinion on different
policies or regulation
about NTU
you can have a tree
share your idea right
and then of course the tree
we can record down
your view on each of the
the regulation right
what is your thinking
what is your thought on this
I also give you a score as an evaluation
of this policy right
your satisfactory score on this
but sometimes the tree you ask this
but you don't want to comment on that
scenario they just
don't have a record of your score
about certain policy
so this could be called
this could cause a mission value right
for that particular sample
for that particular attribute
sometimes
you give the answer for the
the recorder forgot to record
write down this value
okay so there are many reasons
that cause the mission value problem
and
so the data
sometimes the data elements
normally the attributes
have values
surprisingly different
from the other elements
extremely low values
or extremely high values
so these are the outliers
they are very different from other values
just like an example
talk about the income right
talk about the wealth
but then suddenly some are
being in that
they are outliers
outliers also could be called by many reasons
why not they are naturally outliers
okay
and maybe in such a scenario
maybe we take the wrong
wrong data right
you just look at the average
or the normal
like Singaporean or Chinese
household income
but actually you just normal
the common right people
but you include some billionaires
so these actually
could cause by the incorrect sample
set selection
maybe you use it
you normally use some of the data
so you should not use the data
billionaires to calculate the
average income
of the ordinary people
but actually you use that
so these actually outliers
could be cause by the incorrect
sample set
and also could be cause by
errors
when you record down this value
you record it wrongly
so this wrong value
could be
outlier
okay
so these are the two
main issues actually
or two frequently encountered issues
in the data
if we have these issues
then we must actually
eliminate these problems
we must address these problems
before actually we apply this data
to the learning algorithm
okay
so next we look at
the data remediation
remediation how to handle these
problems
if we have missing values
if we have outliers
okay
first we look at
the handling of the outliers
so we already understand actually
what is outlier
extremely low or extremely high values
very different from other values
so these
values can see as outlier
okay
so one simple way is to
remove outliers
if one sample has actually
like you know
in one specific feature
value is extremely high
extremely low so I think the easiest way
to
handle this outlier problem
is just to remove the whole
that sample
to remove that sample
so we can remove the outliers
so for every sample
if there is one attribute
containing outlier value
extremely low or extremely high values
we can just remove
this that sample
okay
so of course this is the easiest way to do that
just remove that
by checking the sample
so this is also a way to improve the data quality
and also the quality of the model
right
so that is the reason why we see we need to
explore the data
we need to look at the quality
of the outliers
we must address these outliers
and the mission value problems
okay
so remove the outliers
then we can improve the quality of the data
and another is
the imputation
so we
if the outliers are extremely high
extremely low
maybe we see this could be caused by
the errors
correct this error
but how to correct this error
so what value we should use
to replace these extremely low
or extremely high values
actually we can use the average
we can use the average
actually we can use the
mean
media or mode
to replace these extremely low
or extremely high values
we just believe
we can use the average values
but now we want to use the value
to replace that
but what value to use
actually then we can
naturally we can think about
the media
or mean
or the mode
we can replace
the outliers
using these values
okay
so we don't remove the outliers
we replace them with the extreme low
or high values
but we change the values
replace the extreme low or high values
using the mean media or mode
okay another is
caping
so these extremely low or extremely high
so just now I dream when we have the
box plot we have the 5 number
summary
q1 q3 the minimum
maximum
and naturally the minimum
value or maximum value in the data
actually we have ways to calculate the
minimum maximum
based on q1 and then we subtract
actually 1.5
actually the accurate
into quantal range
and for q
for maximum from q3
plus 1.5
the accurate right
so we have this value
we have minimum and maximum
value
extreme low
we know this area
so we just
replace the value
using the minimum value to replace
if the value is extremely high
we use the maximum value
to replace
okay so this method is called
caping
okay and here
actually you can also use
different like you can use
the minimum
95%
q1 is 25%
you can use the 5%
you don't use the minimum
we use the value
that is the 5%
the maximum value we don't use the maximum value
we can use the 95%
actually the percent
okay
so this is the
okay this is
caping method
okay so this is
another scenario is that
if there is extreme signal number of
otolias
extreme number of otolias
then they should be treated differently
separately
we know among the 200 samples
or like you know
50 samples or 25%
right
have extreme value otolias
and maybe these otolias are natural
otolias right they are not caused by error
okay so here
in such a scenario
actually we should treat them
the data normal data
as one group
and then the data with otolias
extreme values otolias into another group
okay then we can build a model
separately for the two groups
okay
and
then if we make predictions
then we can just look at the data
whether this data is normal data
otolias
then we can decide which model to use
okay this is another way
to handle the otolias
problem
okay so for one single problem
actually we have multiple solutions
but actually of course each of the solutions
is a purpose within
certain context
so you always need to
analyze
the given task
to analyze the
task specific data
to find the issues
and also to take
the corresponding measures
the best measures to address the issues
we always need to do the analysis
right
so here this is just actually one scenario
a significant number
okay
so
if otolias are natural
right
actually you know they
are natural
so we should not amend them
so they are not caused by error
they are natural
so in such a scenario maybe we just put them
into two groups
that is a good solution
okay
so here is a tree we see the mission value problem
right mission values
there are some mission values
and then of course the tree we can
the simple way to eliminate the sample with mission value
right so this is the simplest way
is to eliminate records
or sample having a mission value
because we have a treasure marker
right we cannot decide the value
we simply remove this value
remove the sample
any sample has a mission value
we can remove that
if we have an extreme low or high value
otolias they can remove that
so actually this is one way to address the problem
but not necessarily the best way
it is a way
to address the otolias problem
to address the mission value problem
but not necessarily the best way
okay so the eliminate records
or sample having
a mission value
okay
so this is normally
applicable when the number
of samples with mission
mission value is limited
a small proportion
you have like
only 10% or 5% of the data
mission values right 5%
and if you have a large number
of samples then remove
of these 5% of the data
will not affect our learning result
much okay then can just remove
right so this is normally
is applicable can be adopted
and such a scenario
the removal of these samples
will not affect
the learning result much
okay so
we can remove them
just actually in this example
here I give
originally I did the data
392 samples
and actually we found
the 6th sample has a mission value
just now we see the 6th sample
of question mark mission value
of these 6 samples
we still have 380
86 samples right
so just actually
like 6
how many percent
2%
yeah less than 2% of data
have mission value
remove all this percentage
of the data will not affect
the learning much
okay then we can
take this simple way to remove them
okay
so this will not be possible
actually if many data
points have mission values
20%
392 samples
over 100 samples have mission values
if you remove
100 samples
then actually this will affect
the learning result very much
so then in such a scenario
remove
through this preset you can see
we always analyze this problem
analyze
we look at the scenario
and the different scenarios we have different solutions
okay
then of course the next actually
is imputing the mission values
okay
we don't try to remove
actually the samples because of just one mission
value right
in some many scenarios
the data collection is not easy
in particularly in biomedical research
right and actually
or just now as an example you interview
the student about the policy
interview can take maybe like 10 minutes
okay just because of one value
actually in mission
then you remove the sample
then this 10 minutes effort
is wasted
right so
so this actually in some scenarios
the data collection is very expensive
and you just have a limited number of samples
we should not remove
actually the sample instead
we should take some other measures
actually
compensate the mission value
to address the mission value problem
so here is imputing the mission values
we should just like
apply it right we should replace
we should give a value
right for this mission value
actually what value to give
actually we can of course
like I mean previously for the otlias
we can use the media and use the
mean and we can use the mode
right to replace
to assign to this
actually mission value
so this is the mission value
and actually
we kind of another issue right
and in particular
I think
for the actually for the
samples right
sometimes actually we don't use the overall
mean or overall
media but even in classification
problem we know
this sample belongs to class one
belongs to class one
and then actually we should not use
the overall mean or media
to compensate
actually to assign
the overall mean or media to this
mission value right
we should not use the overall
mean or media to assign
to this mission value
so we should know look at
this sample belongs to class one
right so it's more
similar to sample of class one
then we should use the
media or mean value of sample
of class one to replace
this question mark
but this is actually certainly
we will improve the accuracy
right so this is one method
another method is that
we even within the same class
right because
within the same class they also have a dispersion
right spread
although the spread may be small
but for some samples
actually if we look at other features
with no mission value
then we find actually the most similar samples
so based on other features
we find which sample is
most similar to this
to the sample with the mission value
then we look at the feature
and we look at the value of that
sample
we just use that value
to replace the question mark
this is probably
I think is another way right
so we analyze the problem
although we also impute the mission value
but we could have different ways
right
okay so this is the
yeah
and actually you know for another example
for the horsepower
and so
they also based on the
relationship right we actually
previously we see we can use
relationship between the
variables right between the variables
if we know the horsepower
is probably is more similar
is correlated with
with the
cylinder with the cylinder right
so actually oh then we can look at
you know if this sample
actually have cylinder like 8
right like 8
so because these two variables are correlated
and then we can look at
all the data with
8 cylinder
8 okay and then we
can look at this sample
along the
horizontal along the feature
so what are the values
then we take the average
of this sample with 8
cylinders
we use this one value to replace
the mission values
right we use the most
relevant samples based on
the relationship between
the features
okay then we can
so this again the exploration of the
relationship between the features or attributes
and then it is important right
this can help us to
improve actually the solution
and for the mission value
problem
so here you know you always need to analyze
not just see a given problem
actually just adopt that
not so easy
we always need to analyze
look at the perspective problem
look at the characteristics of the data
then apply or adopt
or develop propose a new solution
okay
so these are
I think these are the estimating
mission values
actually this
estimation is that actually
the features are not correlated
just not already see two features correlated
actually the features
can also be correlated with many variables
we can always use other variables
to fit another variable
to fit
so we can use
the mission value for this feature
we can use actually
to build a model
another model
to use other features to predict these features
with mission values
okay so that is estimating
mission values
so there are many solutions
to the mission value problem
okay
so these are like
the solution to the two main problem
the mission value problem
and the otolayer problem
so that is actually look at the data preprocessing
so you still remember
after the exploration
the last step is preprocessing
preprocessing here means the scaling
of the features
so here for scaling
we talk about two main methods
one is called normalization
another is called standardization
of the data
so scaling is
very important
in machine learning
so what is feature scaling
feature scaling is
the data preprocessing technique
to transform the values
of features of different range
to a similar range
so this is called feature scaling
so this is the purpose to ensure
that all features contribute equally
to the model
to avoid the domination of features
with big values
so later through one example
we can see
why the big values
dominate
we should try to avoid this problem
and this is
normally
in machine learning
we need to calculate the distance
between the samples
the distance
the distance is used as a similarity measure
distance
and how to calculate the distance between two features
normally we look at the difference
between
each attribute
between the two samples along each attribute
then square
then summarize them together
so for example GPA
and most of the file
4.5
then square is 0.25
but if you look at the body weight
something like 50, something like 100 kg
then the difference
square
so it's known that the body weight
actually will dominate
in the calculation of the similarities
between the samples
because this feature takes big values
we should try to avoid this problem
so
this is because
in many machine learning algorithms
we need to calculate the distance between
each sample
one of the examples is
the nearest neighbor
distance-based learning algorithm
and then
for actual learning
the K-means classroom
also based on the distance to determine the similarity
of the samples
and the support machine
they all use the distance
I think
most of them
actually
machine learning algorithms
use the distance between the samples
so we should try to avoid
the dominance of one feature
of others
and
so this is just one example
so initially
the salary in this range
all big values
the CGPA or small values
so after a brief scaling
by certain method
later we will talk about two methods
and then all in a similar range
all in a similar range
so none of them will be dominant
so we should
use feature scaling to avoid the dominance
of one feature over others
so just to not show the example
and another
many algorithms
are based on the so-called gradient descent method
like neural network training
propagation algorithm
or deep neural network
of course
so many learning algorithms
the training of the model
is based on the so-called gradient descent method
so here
the gradient descent is a kind of
incremental learning
or sequential learning
so we will use this example
then we update the width
so these are the width in the step K
and these are the width in the next step
so the second term here is update
the width update contains three
parts
one is the eta, the linear rate
another part is the gradient
the gradient of the first derivative
of the loss function
with respect to the parameter
then another is the feature
X
the feature is very different
and then the width update
will be very different
because
the X i
1 is only 4.0
you input this and then you can have an update
another is 100
in update
then the 1 with a larger value
will have a larger update
actually a very big
large update could also cause
actually
a very big probability of the linear
so
in the gradient descent method
we also try to
avoid big values
we should normalize them to small
values
in a similar range
so these are the reasons why we
actually
perform the feature scaling
and before we
this is the last step
as the preparation
we will talk about
why is called normalization
normalization here
will transform the data
to the range
from 0 to 1
okay
so this is the formula we show you
this is a graph illustration
horizontal is the raw data X
then we can use
find the minimum, we can find the maximum
and then we can
perform this transformation
all the data will be in the range
so actually the X minus
minimum value
if you substitute
actually the numerator will become 0
so the minimum will map to 0
the maximum
will map to 1 because if something
maximum then the numerator
will not the same, cancel become 1
so the data will all data
no matter the original region
range
after normalization they will all
be 0 from 0 to 1
similar range
all the same range actually
and then another matter is called
standardization
standardization is to
actually
to
transform the data
so that the mean is 0
and 0
now we talk about the central tendency
the mean will be 0
after normalization
and standardization
the spread of the data will be 1
so this is called standardization
so why is it called standardization
this is because the tree for normalization
if the mean is 0
standardization is 1
this is called standard normalization
so this is probably the reason
of standardization
but quite often we don't differentiate the two
they all call normalization
so
as a data preparation step
normalize to 0, 1
or normalize to 0 mean
standardization of 1
and
previously a tree
I think here because you use the mean
and the sigma
they are less likely
affected by the otolias
but previously the mean
I think is easier to
so these are the advantage and disadvantage
so this is the comparison
of the two methods
standardization and standardization
but actually
sometimes if we use different techniques
we will obtain different results
and sometimes the difference is significant
so always
we should try both
then we find
the better performing one
so I think there is
there is no single
method performed the best for all applications
always we should
try different method
so we should finally use the best
performing one
so here actually we also need to
try the two
the choice of them
normalization
or standardization
depends on the problem
and always
try the two
so that is the reason
in machine learning we need to start so many methods
because actually
we don't know which solution
for the given task
we all need to try many of them
but of course you cannot try all of them
you should analyze the data
you should have a good understanding about
assumptions for each of the learning algorithm
for each of the model
then you try those
that could
potentially suit this specific application
so that is the reason
why we need to do these
exploration of the data
and try the data
before the data could be
input to the learning algorithm
to fit the model
okay
I know
I didn't probably many of you actually
want to rush for the bus
so now
if you actually
you want to stay here for some time
then you can just stay
and then I can answer your question
if you don't want to stay you can just go
and I will be back