具体系的整个道理 提供你的解解等等HE IDEA 体式 펙算
感觉不会提到一个 不明护性的感觉
So today is the mid-autumn festival, so I wish I
would like to introduce you to the festival.
So here we first can see the one example and here shows two types of fish.
One type of fish is called sea bass, the left one, and the right one is salmon.
Of course, for this country we have no problem to identify the two types of fish, right?
And we can separate them.
In any manner, once the scenario, that is the Yemf Dachshundah, and there are two types of fish,
and we want to separate them and then pack them separately.
And I just mentioned human, of course, there is no problem to separate the two types of fish,
and of course we can do the separation of the two types of fish manually.
But here we want to design a machine learning system, two separate types of fish.
So for all the machine learning systems, of course, firstly we need to collect data, right?
And then we need to label the data.
So in the last week, during the data conversion part, we know in machine learning system that
we need to collect data, and of course we need to collect data.
And so we can take a lot of pictures of different salmon fish and also sea bass, right?
And then we need to select the features from the fish.
And of course, if you just compare the two pictures,
and we know the sea bass, the left one, actually is smaller than the right one.
And also the color or the latin is of the fish, which is a lot in a different, okay?
So at least we can select two features, right?
One is the size of the fish, another is the latin is of the color of the fish.
It's a feature to display the two types of features, okay?
The two types of fish, okay?
So after we have selected the features, determine what characteristics attribute we want to use,
and then the next step is to design a kind of classification,
design a kind of classification or with more kind of classifier, okay?
And of course, I just mentioned many methods.
Here we have been studying the step-to-step approach for actually the classification of different objects.
And the set of approach, let me, we make decisions,
we make a classification of samples based on the probabilities.
Probabilities.
Okay, so today I think we've studied a few concepts relating to probabilities, okay?
And the first concept would be the power probabilities.
So here we assume actually the omega-g-node class, okay?
And omega-1 actually for C-base, omega-2 the class 2, and this for the sample, okay?
And so the first concept by the probability is called the power probability.
So for salmon fish, we have power probability of omega-2,
and for the C-base, we also have power probabilities, okay?
And if there is no other type of fish, only these two types of fish,
then the summation of these two power probabilities should be 1, okay?
Okay, so these are first concept probabilities.
And there's something like this, I just give one example, right?
Actually you see in this class actually male students, female students, right?
And if the female student accounts for 40%, and the male student accounts for 60%, okay?
And then the power probability for male students is 0.6, or 60%,
and the female student is 0.4, or 40%.
So these power probabilities actually can be estimated based on the cost, right?
And then the percentage of the student male or female in this class will be 0.4.
So these are power probabilities.
So if a student, I know some of you are not coming here, they probably are on the way.
If you ask you to guess, what is the gender of the next coming in student?
You guess, right? You have not seen his face, you just guess what the next coming in student.
What gender you are guessing?
Male, right? One male.
Actually based on the power probability, right?
Because the gene, based on the, yeah, that's right.
The correct question, the prediction of the gender.
Yes, indeed.
Because the gene, the gender, the male actually has a larger probability, right?
So you make the prediction based on this, actually, larger probabilities.
And then, less likely, actually, we can make a wrong decision.
So this is the power probability.
But of course, actually, if you just make a power probability, every time, actually, you will,
actually, guess the next student is a male student.
And then you have a 40%, actually, 40% chances to make a wrong decision, right?
Wrong predictions.
Actually, that's a very high prediction error.
Okay, so in practical scenarios, so besides this power probability,
we need to have some other information, right?
So the next coming student, maybe you see his face, her face,
or you know his height or her height, and then you know this information, certainly,
can help you to make a correct decision, correct predictions.
Okay.
So here, actually, if we just make the decision based on the power probability,
then in power probability of omega-1 from class 1, greater than class 2,
then we predict omega-1, right?
But then, actually, we have a high chances, right, to make wrong decisions.
Because everyone, every, actually, you know, the sample will be classified to the class
that has higher power probabilities.
Okay.
So for this example, so we are not asked to make decisions just for some probability.
Instead, we will provide some information.
Okay.
At least we will provide some information about the size of the fish.
Okay, so how long it is.
And then we will also provide some information about the color, the lateness of the fish.
Okay.
So if this feature, if we, one of the features, we just denote by the egg, right?
So based on the eggs, based on the coming in to the eggs, based on the length of the size of the fish,
based on the lateness of the fish, we will make decisions.
Okay.
And actually, when we make decisions, not only we use the probabilities,
but also we need to use, actually, another probability.
So that is probably, actually, is called the class conditional probability density function.
So this is another concept.
Class conditional probability density function.
So what is the probability of eggs?
Given class.
Okay.
So given some fish.
So what is the distribution of the lateness of the color?
What is the distribution of the size?
Okay.
So given, actually, the male student, given this cloud,
so what is the distribution of the height, right?
For female student.
So given male student, so what is the distribution of the height from male student?
So this is called class conditional probability density function.
Density function.
And actually, later we will see, actually, given a sample with known information like lateness,
or we see the size x, okay.
And based on this x, we need to calculate, actually, another probability,
which is called, actually, the posterior probability.
So here, actually, this diagram just shows, actually, the different distribution of the two,
these two, actually, class conditional probability density functions, right?
So for the red one, this shows, actually, the distribution of the x,
the distribution of the size, the distribution of the lateness of the salmon fish.
And the black one shows the lateness, obviously, the size of the sea bass.
So this is called class conditional probability density functions.
And actually, we need both the information and also the incoming x to make predictions.
Okay.
So here, suppose we know these three information, right?
First, the probability, I just mentioned, right?
Then the second one, the conditional probability density function.
Then the third one, actually, is the information of the specific object, right?
For salmon fish, okay.
So for fish, we don't know whether it's salmon fish or sea bass.
Okay, we know the size of the fish.
This size is due to the x.
Obviously, we know the lateness, the color of the fish.
Okay, so based on these three information, we will make predictions of the class of the salmon fish.
Okay.
Then, of course, actually, how to make the decision.
Give me this information, how to predict.
Okay, so we gave an x.
Now we have an x because the information is provided, right?
We see this fish.
Okay, or the computer sees this fish.
So we know the information of x.
Actually, we can predict the probability of this object belonging to a certain class, right?
And then based on the so-called base theorem.
Base theorem.
Okay.
So, actually, probability of omega j, given x.
Given x, that means the x is provided is known.
So what is the probability of this object belonging to class omega j?
So this is the p of omega j given x.
The probability of omega j, the probability of class omega j, the probability of salmon fish,
the probability of sea bass, the length of the size of the fish,
and given the lateness of the fish.
Okay, so this is the, this is the, this part, okay.
So this p of omega j x.
Okay, and actually based on the base theorem, and this equals the numerator part here,
actually, is the joint probability of x and the omega j.
Okay, so the joint probability can be calculated by the probability of x,
given omega j times the probability of omega j.
So omega j here is just a p of omega j is a prior probability.
We just introduce the prior probability of omega j.
Okay, and then divided by this px.
This px is called total probability of x.
And actually this total probability of x can be calculated.
Actually, you know this formula.
Actually, this is the summation of two joint probabilities.
One is the joint probability of x with omega one.
And that is the joint probability of x with omega two.
So this summation is the joint, is the total probability of x.
So this is the base theorem.
Probably when you are in an integrated, right, to the integrated study, actually,
you learn this base theorem, but you don't know how to apply this, right.
But now, actually, even though you apply this base theorem,
you can apply this base theorem to Michelin.
To actually make a prediction of the class of the samples.
So this is p of omega jx is called the posterior probability.
And actually, we make decisions based on the posterior probabilities,
rather than the prior probabilities.
But the posterior probability is calculated based on the prior probability
and the class of the probability density function.
OK.
So this is actually, this is the base theorem.
So now we assume, actually, just now we already showed a diagram
about the class of the kind of probability density function for omega one and for omega two.
Now we assume, actually, the prior probability for omega one is to the,
the prior probability for omega two is one dot.
And then, actually, based on the, this prior probability and the class
kind of probability density function, we can calculate, actually, the posterior probabilities.
So this is something like that.
This is the posterior probability.
And naturally, omega, the red one shows the posterior probability
and for the class two, omega two, and the black one shows the posterior probability
for class one.
The horizontal here is just the x, right?
x.
And then the vertical one shows the posterior probability.
OK.
And actually, from here you can see, and maybe in the range, right, from nine,
from nine to around 9.8, 9 to 9.8, actually, the red one, the red, you know,
is above this black one, right?
So this means, actually, the probability, the posterior probability of class two is greater
than posterior probability of class one.
And similarly, then from in the range, from like 9.8 to around 11.2, maybe, OK.
And then the posterior probability of class one, given x, is greater than posterior
probability of omega two, given x.
So this is posterior probability, which is calculated, actually, based on the prior
probability and the class kind of probability that is found first.
OK.
So this is the base posterior rule.
So after we have calculated the posterior probability, then what to make the posterior?
How to make perceptions.
OK.
So this is the base posterior rule.
We decide omega one.
We classify the sample to class omega one.
If the probability, the posterior probability, belonging to class one, is greater than the
probability belonging to class two.
So here we, again, we base on the probability, right?
We say which probability is higher.
And then we assign the sample to that class.
Previously, we just used actually the prior probability, right?
And then the prior probability could have a higher chance of making wrong predictions.
But actually, the posterior making, based on the posterior probability, could have a higher
accuracy of that whole mechanism.
We make decisions based on the posterior probability, rather than prior probabilities.
OK.
So this is the base posterior rule.
So I think this rule is reasonable, right?
Because the probability of making, or the posterior making, based on the probability, of course,
if you look at which probability is greater than that, right?
And then we assign the sample to that class.
So these are very reasonable, and the posterior rule, right?
It's very intuitive.
OK.
And actually, just now we see the base posterior rule, right?
Actually, when we calculate the base theorem, and in the calculation of the posterior probability,
and we see in the denominator, denominator, right, is a Px.
And this Px, actually, is a common factor for both omega one and omega two.
So in practice, actually, we may not have to calculate this, actually, the Px, because
this Px is just a skin factor, right?
So whether or not we have these Px, or without having these Px, actually, this will not affect
the posterior, because this is just a skin factor.
OK.
So now we have such a few worries, right?
If you don't want to calculate the posterior probability, and if you want to ignore the
skin factor, right, the Px, we can just basically join the probability to make these series.
If the Px for omega one, tan P for omega one, this is a numerator part, right?
So now we see the posterior probability has a numerator part divided by the denominator.
The denominator is a common denominator for all classes, so we can ignore.
We just see the numerator part, OK?
The numerator part, actually, is the joint probability.
So this is the awareness of the, this awareness, right?
Actually, originally, we tried to use the posterior probability.
So now, actually, after analysis, and actually, we know, we can use the joint probability
to make these series.
So we don't have to calculate the Px, so we can actually reduce, actually, the computational
cost, right?
OK.
So just now we just actually, we have an x, right?
This x is a scalar.
Then in other words, we just use one attribute.
Just a number, right?
We just use one attribute.
So we let small, you know, in the lower case, x, right?
And so this actually is a one attribute, one feature.
So this is just for low-fission property.
When you practice, actually, you know the feature, the number will be much more than one.
In many applications, the feature will be over 100.
It will be over 100.
Actually, in some biomedical applications, like gene, no data analysis, and the demotivation
will be as high as 40,000.
So we need to extend, actually, from one attribute, one dimension to multi-dimensions, to multiple
features, multiple attributes.
So this is one extension, right?
One generalization.
So another is that just now, actually, we just have two classes.
In the example, we see male student, female student.
Actually, it's a binary, right?
Just two classes.
Now we see the fish, right?
The sea bass, a sun.
Just two classes.
So actually, of course, in many practical applications, actually, the number of classes
will be much more than two.
So we can also generalize the number of classes to multiple classes, rather than just two.
So we can extend this, right?
We can have this extension or generalization in these two ways.
So now, we use X to denote the feature vector.
So the input now is no longer one scalar, actually, it's a vector.
So not only just actually the size of the fish or the lateness, actually, we use a booth.
Or even we can use additional information.
So the number of features or the number of attributes is more than two or more than one.
So we use X.
Actually, this is a bone-faced look, is a letter, right?
Denote, actually, a feature vector.
And the number of classes here is a C.
So we have omega one, omega two, and omega C.
And then how to have the posterior probability?
So based on the base theorem and the posterior probability of omega z,
given X equal to the Px given omega z times the probability of P omega z.
The power probability of P will be omega z.
Then we divide by the total probability of X.
So now, actually, you see the Px is a summation of many John's probabilities.
Actually, j from one to C, rather than from j to one to two, right?
Because here is a C class, class-linear problem, rather than a two-class class-linear problem.
So the total probability of X, actually, is a summation of C John's probabilities.
Probability of X with omega one, with omega two, with omega C.
Then summation, that will be X, the total probability of X.
So this is actually the posterior probability of omega z given X.
So in practice, we always have X, right?
Because when we make a decision, we must know the information about the object.
So the information, actually, is contained in the feature vector X.
So based on this X, what is the probability that the object belongs to omega z?
So this is called posterior probability.
And actually, now we introduce another concept, which is called a dissimilar function.
A dissimilar function is a general concept in my shelenian.
Actually, it's a general, not just for the base-design theory.
Base-design theory is a statistical approach.
Actually, even for other approaches, we have a dissimilar function.
A dissimilar function is used to separate different classes.
So in this example, in this statistical approach, the dissimilar function can be just posterior probabilities.
And then we introduce this concept, right?
So this is a general concept.
So for given input, the input is a vector from X1 to Xt.
And then we calculate c dissimilar functions, g1x, g2x, and gcx.
Then we get g1x, g2, gcx.
Then we try to identify which has the maximum value.
If the gx has the maximum value, then we assign the sample x to class i.
So this is a general for any type of classification algorithm.
We use a dissimilar function.
So based on the dissimilar function, we calculate the current dissimilar function.
Then we compare the size of the dissimilar function for g1x.
Then we add the one with the maximum value.
Then we assign that sample to that class.
So this is a special scenario.
And then the gx is just a posterior probability.
So this is a special case.
The posterior probability is the dissimilar function.
We use a dissimilar probability.
And actually, just now we showed, we know in the calculation of the dissimilar probability.
And we have a common scaling factor, Px.
Actually, we can simply ignore this Px.
Then make decisions or make predictions based on the actually the jump probabilities.
In other words, actually, this jump probability could also be used as a dissimilar function.
So this could be like the gx, the numerator part, right?
In the calculation of the posterior probability.
This is a jump probability of x and omega j.
It could be used as actually the dissimilar function.
Another variant is the log of the jump probability.
So now it's a multiplication of the class-cannot-probability density function and the probability.
The multiplication.
If we take the logarithm operation, and then actually this becomes the logarithm of the class-cannot-probability density function,
plus, right?
Then the logarithm of the probability of omega j.
So actually, in practice, we can use both.
We can use all the three, the probability, the posterior probability, or the log of the jump probability.
And actually, we don't actually in practice, we normally just use these two.
We don't need to calculate the probability of px, the common, actually, scaling factor.
And actually, for 40p omega j, the probability, already using one example, in this class,
like 40 percent of the students are female students, 60 percent of the students are male students.
And then we know the probability for female is 0.4, and the probability for male is 0.6.
So I think we can easily estimate the probability based on the counts of the number of samples in each class.
Then we can calculate the percentage, the proportion.
So that is the probability.
But here, how to find this class-cannot-probability density, px omega j?
Because this one, we can easily obtain, right?
So how to obtain the px omega j, the class-conditional probability density function?
How to obtain this?
First, actually, density function, right?
I think even in the literature, if you know, I think even in the statistics, right,
when you study probability and statistics, actually, we know there are many type of density functions,
or probability mass functions.
And actually, in the last week, we studied the types of features, right?
The features could be discrete or could be continuous.
And actually, for continuous, for discrete, we could have very different density functions or mass functions.
For continuous features, now we can have normal distribution function, right?
We can assume the data for normal distribution or Gaussian distribution.
And if the data is discrete, then, of course, we cannot use a normal distribution,
but we can use other type of distributions, okay?
For example, we can use the Poisson distribution.
We can use the binomial distribution.
Binomial distribution or Poisson distribution are for discrete random variables or discrete features.
So now, we just focus, we first focus on continuous features.
Okay, continuous features.
Of course, continuous features can also follow and can have different type of density functions.
Some could be like a gamma density function.
Okay, but in practice, normally, we assume the data follows normal distribution, normal.
Okay, although, no stress is speaking, maybe the data does not follow a normal density function.
But we can use, we can assume, then, we use the normal distribution, normal density function.
And then, the good performance still can be achieved.
Okay, and later today, we will see if a sample, if the distribution of the data or the density function, density,
does not follow a normal distribution function.
But actually, we can use the so-called Gaussian-Mission model.
We can use multiple Gaussian functions to construct the density function.
Okay, so in the basic decision rule, the key problem is the construction of the estimation of the class-cognitive-property-density function.
Class-cognitive-property-density function.
But here, we simplify the problem.
We assume, actually, the class-cognitive-property-density function is a Gaussian function or normal function.
Okay, so we assume this.
Okay, and then this actually just shows a univariate normal density function.
Univariate, that means a one-single feature.
Okay, for a normal density function, we have two parameters, right?
One is the mu, which is the mean value, and another is the sigma, which is the standard variable.
The sigma square is the virus.
Okay, so for a normal-dimensional function, normal-density function, we have two parameters.
One is mu, and another is sigma.
Okay, so this is a univariate normal density function.
Okay, and so this is the definition of the mu, like mean value, right?
The mean, and so this is the definition of the virus.
Sigma is called a standard variant.
Okay, and this diagram just shows, actually, this is a normal distribution, right?
The mu, the horizontal, actually, is true to the value of x.
And the vertical shows the probability.
Probability, and normally the probability of the mean value is the maximum, right?
And actually, so sigma, what's the mean of mu?
Mu, what is mu? The mean value, right? Sigma is the standard variant.
Okay, so actually, either way, from mu minus sigma to mu plus sigma, actually, we have 68% of the data.
And the integration from mu minus to sigma to mu plus to sigma, we have 95% of the data.
Okay, just one example, right?
We see, after the exam, right, for any cost normally for this cost, for example, we see,
the average of the GPA is 3, the mean GPA for this cost is 3.
Okay, and then we see a standard variant, which is here from 5, right, here from 5.
Okay, and then, that means actually, the 68% of the students in this class, actually,
will have a GPA from 2.5 to 3.5.
Okay, and 95% of the students will have a GPA either range from actually like 2 and 2.4.
Right, so this is the mean, right, so this is the normal distribution of mu and sigma, the standard agents.
Okay, so this is the univariate, just one single feature, one single attribute.
And for normal functions here, for this one, we just have one parameter, or two parameters.
One is the mean value, and that is the variance for standard agent.
Okay, of course, we need to generate multiple dimensions, right, not just one dimension, we have feature vectors.
So this is the inspiration of the class canary plug density function, right?
So this is a multivariate normal density function.
Okay, so in this formula, we have this sigma, remember this sigma means actually, this is a capital letter of sigma,
just now we use the sigma, right, sigma, we see the standard agent.
So this is a capital letter of sigma, so it means the covariant matrix.
So this sigma is a covariant matrix, and this is a mu, a new bone phase, bone phase means a vector, it's a mean vector.
It no longer is a mean value, it's a mean vector, and it no longer is a standard agent of variance,
but now it's a covariant matrix, sigma.
Okay, so this is a capital letter of sigma, right, so this is sigma, okay.
And so this is sigma, the determinant of sigma, not absolute value, right, because this is a matrix, not absolute value,
it's a determinant, okay, and then this is the inverse of this covariant matrix, sigma.
So in this formula, we see one over two pi under the power d half of d,
and then the determinant, right, the square root of the determinant of sigma.
Okay, so this is the denominator of the denominator, okay, then it's a connectional x minus mu transpose,
then times actually the inverse of the covariant matrix times x minus mu.
Okay, so in this multivariate normal density function, we have two parameters.
One is the mean vector, mean vector has a denominator of d, right,
and the other is the sum of the denominator of d, then it also has a denominator of d,
because mean is just the average of all the vectors, right, so we still get a vector.
The current matrix is a d by d matrix, but this current matrix normally is a symmetric, right, symmetric.
So d by d values, then d by d by 2, we use symmetric.
Okay, so these are the parameter numbers in sigma, okay.
So this is the multivariate normal density function.
Okay, so that means that just now we see we want to need the base decision rule,
and we need to calculate the posterior probability, all the drown probability,
all the log of the drown probability, but in all of the three, actually, probabilities,
we need to have the density function, okay.
We need to have this multivariate normal density function.
We will assume the data follows normal distribution.
We can have this, okay, and in other words, we need to have this, but we are not given this.
Instead, in practice, we are given data, we are given labeled final data, okay.
And then the issue is how to estimate this class kind of probability density function
from the given labeled final data.
So this is a private estimation for the density function, right.
And actually how to estimate, if we assume the following normal distribution,
actually we just need to use the label train data to estimate the mean vectors
and also the parameters, okay.
Once these two parameters are determined, and then the Gaussian normal density functions are determined, okay.
And then we can use this density function, right.
For any given x, we can substitute into this density function
because actually for mu and sigma, if they are knowing, right, they are estimating from the train data.
Then for any data, either train you or testing, right, we have x, we can substitute into this formula
to calculate actually the conditional density function, right, p x given omega.
And then we multiply the probabilities.
And based on that, you know, we can make prediction of the class, okay.
So here we assume the density function is a Gaussian function or normal density function.
Then the key issue here is to estimate the mean vector and the corollary metric from the train data.
So this is a key issue, okay.
So that's how to estimate, how to estimate.
So this is how to estimate.
Of course, once they are estimated, we just assume the estimation,
we consider the estimation as true value, right,
for given any x, actually we can substitute into a formula to obtain the density function, right, p x given omega.
But here is how to estimate.
Probably you already know how to calculate the mean, right, actually the mean, how to calculate the corollary metric.
But here we learn one method for the parameter estimation.
This method is commonly used in machine learning.
And actually this method is called maximum likelihood method, maximum likelihood parameter estimation.
Suppose actually we have, now we just need to, we have done two extensions, right, or generalization.
Why is that we generalize from one single attribute or feature to a vector, right, to multiple features?
And also we generate the problem from a two class problem to a multiple class problem.
We have C classes.
So for each of the classes, we have a train of data.
Because the tree, the data is labeled train of data, right, so you first and then know which example belongs to omega 1,
which example belongs to omega 2, which example belongs to omega c.
Okay, so for each of the classes, we have a data set, d1, d2 and dc.
d1 for class omega 1, d2 for class omega 2.
We have this set, right.
And here we also assume that samples are joined independently.
We have this sample in d1.
Okay, and the tree, all the samples are joined independently, right,
joined independently.
And based on this tree, probably data function px omega j.
So this is a class kernel density function, right, based on this.
Okay.
And also the sample in one class is not affected by the sample in another class.
In the classification, for example, you choose a tree, you want to get some data, right,
and you want to build a tree, a model to classify a sample, right, male or female student.
When you do the data collection for female students, you are not affected by the data collection of male students.
So the data collection for d1, d2, dn, actually are independent.
Independent, okay.
And, okay, so now actually, so for each of the classes, we have one density function, right,
because for each of the classes, we have one male vector, and we have one, actually, correct matrix.
Okay.
And actually the estimation for class 1, actually the same as the, the same as the estimation for class 2,
for class 3, omega 3, or omega c.
Okay.
So actually all of these problems, it can be summarized into one single problem, that is,
given, like I said, d, given, like I said, d, right, belonging to the same class, okay.
This d could be d1, could be d2, could be dc, right, okay.
And all the, actually the sample in this class are drawn independently, independently.
Okay.
And then actually from this sample, actually, we want to estimate, we want to estimate the parameter theta.
And the theta includes, actually, the mu and the, actually, the sigma.
Okay.
So the problem is, given, like I said, d, right, d, like I said, d.
So how to estimate the mean vector and the current matrix?
So these are our problems.
Okay.
My data says how to estimate, actually, the mean vector and the current matrix?
How to estimate?
Of course, probably in your mind, you already have the formula, right, to calculate the mean vector,
which is an average, right, of all the vector, your sum, all the vector, and then you want to have a number of samples.
And also, for current matrix, you also have the formula in mind to calculate, right.
But here, actually, we want to learn a general method.
So how to find, actually, the estimate of the parameters based on the so-called principle,
principle, makes them line-in-hole method, makes them line-in-hole.
Okay.
So, here, focus here is to study this method.
I suppose d contains, so this sample d, right, d could be d1, d2, and average d, right,
average d, like I said, but all the data belong to the same class.
Okay.
And we have x, y, x2, xn, n samples.
And for example, of course, actually, no, we have probability to generate, right, we have probability to generate.
Okay.
So that is just a density function, right, a density function.
For given, no, data, and we have probability to generate this.
Okay.
And actually, just now we showed the normal density function, right.
Actually, we know actually for mu, we have sigma, right.
Actually, different mu and different sigma.
Even if we have a similar x, and then we can have a different values of p, x, omega, right.
Because actually, the position in the figure would be different.
Okay.
If the mu and sigma are different.
That means that the probability would be different.
Okay.
And so this is the, so for each of our example, like p1, or average sample pk, so this is the
probability of having this sample in the dataset.
pxk given theta, given the density function.
So what is the probability of having this data, sk?
Now, we have n samples, where sy, s2, and n.
So the total probability here is just a multiplication of all the probabilities.
Probability of having sample number one times the probability of sample two times the probability
of x3, probability until xk, xn.
So this is the probability of having this dataset, gaining the mu and the sigma.
And actually for this same set of data, right, and the different mu and the different sigma,
we will have a different probability.
Because actually, the same value of x, if you substitute into the formula, different mu,
different sigma, certainly we will, of course, actually give a different value of p, xk,
or theta, right.
So then the multiplication will be different.
And actually, this is a PED, right, this is the probability of having this given dataset
and the given, and theta, right, given theta.
And this actually is called the likelihood of theta with respect to this dataset d.
This is called likelihood.
So why we have this dataset?
This is because this likelihood is the maximum.
So maximum, so this is the best idea of the maximum likelihood time to estimate it.
So the maximum likelihood estimate of theta is the value of theta that maximizes this probability.
Why we have this?
Because you have the maximum probability, actually, you know, of having this d, probably
at the maximum, okay.
So of course, actually, given a different value of theta, we can have a different of this
PED's theta.
So we want to find the value of theta so that this probability of PED is the maximum.
This is the best idea of maximum likelihood parameter estimation.
Okay, so actually, okay, now I think maybe that's actually we have a, okay, a break.
We have a break, okay, ten minute break.
And the other break, actually, we look into the details of the deviation of the estimation
for parameter mu and sigma.
Actually, here I play music.
I think today is a festival, right?
It's a very special day.
And the treat is one of my favorite songs, okay.
And also the singer, actually, a singer, a radio singer, a singer, we play this.
I'm not very sure what the...
Let me ask you.
Can you hear?
One of them.
Oh, cannot, right?
I'm still in the middle of this.
Hey, cannot, right?
See?
Okay.
This doesn't mean that we can't put together.
These are parameters, parameters.
These things are parameters of mu and sigma.
All the conditions, all the parameters.
So it means, given this data set, we try different mu and sigma.
This combination of mu and sigma, so that's maximum.
That's fine.
Yeah.
Okay.
I can't figure where to get that.
probably there's no wine another probably no air actually the market here right
like follow about another wine right
all the sample right probably of wine sample
then probably another sample right just a few probably he'll go to the first step
and then again the wine sample
it's a wine event
consider many sample
if a submission is a property of X1 or X2 or X3
not X1 to X2
I'm going to have a concept is under
P
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
I'm not sure.
I can't read the links properly.
He's embarrassed.
I'm not sure.
So embarrassed.
I can't read fertilistic 24 hours.
The trick is I didn't have a penlap I can see it well.
That's why I'm not sure.
I'm not sure.
This is the first time I've seen a class like this.
This has aоР equation for seventeen units.
This has a Luiza equation for seventeen units.
This has a 가지고 equation for seventeen units.
This has a ox Pokemon,
This has a llama Parker,
This has a Tenemosba formula forix too.
This has the им中 fifth form.
This has the X, one isakwash,
This has two configure isokwash,
Okay, okay, a sample.
Hmm.
Okay, a data sample.
Thank you.
Okay.
Hmm.
Sure.
Ok, hmm.
OK, so this is a probability of having D data set D, right?
So the X, Y are the samples.
Not between each X,
is a vector, is a feature, is a sample.
Contain the values of each feature.
So these are samples.
And so the probability of having the data set D
actually is the multiplication of the probability of having x1,
x2, x, and until x1.
One multiplication.
Because this is under, we have this probability of having x1,
and x2, and x3, and and xc.
And the x1, x2, x, and until xn are independent.
So we can have this formula to calculate the probabilities.
Then this is a tree.
So this is called the likelihood of theta
with respect to the data set D. Why we have the data set here?
Because actually the probability, the likelihood is maximum.
So this is a basic idea of maximum likelihood parameter
estimation.
We want to estimate the parameters of mu and the sigma.
That's the maximized and this is P d theta.
For different theta and the mu and for the same x,
actually we can have different values of P, right?
The P probabilities.
We want to find the mu and theta.
That the probability P d theta is the maximum.
So now, because here is a multiplication, right?
Multiplication.
And then later we want to find the deviation of the loss function
with respect to the parameter.
It could be very complicated.
So we convert the multiplication into summation
by taking the logarithm operation.
So here, of course, we use the so-called Neckar logarithm,
right?
Lawing.
So we define this loss function as the lawing,
the logarithm of P d theta.
So previously, it's a multiplication of the n probabilities,
right?
But now, it becomes a summation of n probabilities.
So this is a summation from k to 1,
the logarithm of P x k and theta, k from 1 to n.
So this is a loss function.
And that's actually we try to find the value of theta,
including mu and the sigma, right?
So that this loss function, L theta, is maximized.
I think how to perform omission.
I think your university, Yale 1, already
studied this, actually, you already
know how to perform omission, right?
Actually, at least we know the first order derivative
of actually the loss function, object function,
with respect to the parameter should be 0, right?
OK.
So this we are going to actually solve this problem.
And so this theta is the one that makes
the maximum the loss function f theta.
And actually, initially, we want to maximize the probability,
right?
The probability.
But later, we want to maximize the log of the probabilities.
And because of the log operation,
we are converting the multiplication
into summation, right?
But actually, when we have the conversion,
whether the solution we find the same,
we are also maximizing the original P.
The y maximizing L, whether maximizing the P,
the probability.
And actually, the logarithm operation
is a monotonic function, right?
Actually, monotonic increasing or decreasing.
So the function, the theta, the value theta and sigma,
that maximizes the long likelihood function.
We also maximize the likelihood function.
So there are no problems to take this L theta,
the logarithm of the likelihood as the objective function
to optimize.
So the necessary condition for the maximum likelihood estimate
of theta is this.
The partial derivative of L with respect to theta is 0.
So this is the condition, right?
Actually, the partial derivative of the log function
or the coefficient function or the objective function
with respect to the parameter v0.
So this is the necessary condition for optimal value, right?
This is the necessary condition.
So there's a trivial, I'll try to find the truth.
What is the derivative of the long likelihood function?
With respect to the parameter v0.
Actually, the theta here includes two parts, right?
Just one is the mu, another is sigma, the mean vector
and the current matrix.
So here, we first consider the first scenario.
The Gaugrin function with an unknown mu, with an unknown mu,
we assume that the sigma here is known.
It's known.
It's constant, OK?
So let's treat with how to maximize.
So here, from this formula, we see this is the summation,
from k to 1.
Then the partial derivative of the log function,
p x k with respect to theta.
So theta here, we assume just mu.
We assume the sigma is known.
We want to find the mu.
So then, we treat the function here
becoming the p x k and the unknown parameter mu.
We just consider mu as an unknown parameter to estimate.
And then, so this is the function.
We still have sigma.
Here, we assume the sigma, the current matrix is known.
And then, so this is the log, right?
This is the log of operation and log probability.
So this is the log, right?
So this part, actually, this is not a function mu, right?
It's not a function mu.
We assume these are constant.
And then, only this part is a function mu.
So we want to find the partial derivative of this log
probability, right?
We just look at actually the partial derivative of this part.
So this part, actually, leads to the derivative
or differential action of a scalar with a vector.
Actually, this is a scalar, right?
This is a scalar.
So how to find the partial derivative?
How to differentiate?
Sometimes, different notion of a scalar variable
with respect to a vector.
I think you started this in the linear algebra course, right?
So I think this is very straightforward.
So we can kind of fix this part.
Then we look at the derivative with the mu, right?
Then we fix this part.
We look at the derivative of this part with respect to mu.
And then, actually, this is the mu.
This is the partial derivative of the log.
Actually, the log of p xk mu with respect to mu.
So this is just the k.
So actually, so k, right?
k is from 1 to n.
So we get the summation.
So this is the partial derivative of the log's function,
the log likelihood function with respect to the mu and mu.
And based on the analysis done now,
and this actually, first of all, should be 0.
This is a natural condition for optimal solution.
This should be 0.
It should be 0.
And then, actually, we let it 0, right?
So this sigma inverse, actually, is a common factor, right?
We can actually move out.
And then we multiply, actually, the current metric.
Then this will become a tree, you know?
Just like cancel, right?
So from here, from this equation,
you can either obtain this is the estimation of the mu.
And actually, just average, probably already
know the result, right?
But actually, I want to show you the method
for parameter estimation, that is maximum log likelihood
parameter estimation.
So this is a very commonly used method, actually,
in machine learning.
Maximum log likelihood parameter estimation.
So through this preset, right?
So first, actually, we construct the likelihood function.
And then, actually, for convenience,
we use the log of the likelihood function
as the object function to optimize.
So finally, through the optimization
of the natural condition, natural condition,
the frontal derivative of the cost function
with respect to the coefficient parameter
should be 0.
So based on this condition, we finally
obtain the estimate of the mean vector.
So this is a cap, where mu cap means the estimate
of the mean vector.
So it's just the average of the n vectors, the average
of the n samples.
So this is the mean, right?
This is the mean vector.
So this is the case when mu is unknown, but sigma is known.
And the necessary is this, when the sigma and the mu are
unknown.
And also, through similar process,
finally, we can get an estimate of the current matrix.
I probably already know the result.
But I think one thing I want to mention is that here is a 1 over n.
For current matrix estimation, how often
you see 1 over n minus 1?
But actually, this is called maximum likelihood
estimate of the current matrix.
If 1 over n minus 1, that is called
unbiased estimate of the current matrix.
Unbiased.
So this is a big difference, right?
Of course, nowadays normally we use data around large data,
at least 100,000.
So 1 over n minus 1 or 1 over n does not make much difference.
Because the 3n could be either 1,000, 10,000.
So 1 over n or 1 over n minus 1 does not make much difference.
But actually, of course, in theory,
we see why it's called actually the maximum likelihood
parameter estimate.
Another is unbiased estimate.
So this is the estimation for the mean vector
and the current matrix.
So gain-metronial samples, I think
this estimation of the mean vector and the current
matrix are quite straightforward, right?
So one of these two parameters are determined.
And then the conditional density function is determined.
Because we assume density function
is a Gaussian function, which just has two parameters.
One is mu, the mean vector.
Another is the current matrix.
So now these two parameters are estimated.
And then actually the density function is determined.
And then we can use the jump probability, right,
of the x and omega, which is just
the model product of the density function
with the probability.
Use this as a distribution function
to perform classification of the samples.
So I think this is the basic theory, basic decision theory.
And the core issue is the estimate of the density function.
But you will assume the sample for a normal distribution.
And then this becomes a problem is reduced
to the estimate the current matrix and the mean vector.
Although in practice, the sample may not
necessarily follow normal distribution.
But if you assume the following normal distribution,
and we use this to design the panic classifier,
I think that normally the performance is good.
So this is the primary estimate for the density function.
Now actually I show you one example.
So I generate the examples for two classes.
And so I just use the normal density function
to generate the random sample.
So we have 200, and each class has 100 samples.
And so now we want to actually build
density function for each of the two classes.
And because we assume the following normal distribution,
then the problem is reduced to the estimation
of the mean vector and the current matrix.
If you use other type of a density function,
then there could be a much more number of parameters.
Then the primary estimation could be much more challenging.
But here we assume normal distribution.
Then we're just going to estimate the mean vector
and the current matrix.
Just use a formula to calculate.
So this is just actually like we use all the sample in class 100
get a summation, then divide by n1.
So finally we get the mean vector.
So this is an estimate, mu1 cap.
So this is an estimate for the mean vector of class 1.
So this is the mean vector estimate for the class 2.
You just get the summation.
So in the computer, you know either meta-level or Python.
You just use the mean.
You can easily calculate the two vectors for the two classes.
And then based on the mu1, mu2, and of course,
if you can get the current matrix sigma 1 and sigma 2.
So of course, if you're in a function or in a turbo,
and you normally have the functions to call,
to get the current matrix directly.
So these are current matrices.
These are current matrices.
So here SK1.
So these are current matrices.
n1, sigma n1, class 1.
Here is n2, sigma n2, class 2.
100 is the example.
Out of that, actually, based on mu1, mu2, sigma 1, sigma 2,
we can construct actually the density function.
And in the density function, actually, and also, actually,
we have a trigger determinant.
A trigger determinant of a matrix is a scalar.
You know how to calculate the determinant.
So not absolutely.
The determinant of a matrix, sigma 1, actually,
of this determinant.
So after that, actually, we can obtain
actually the conditional probability density function
for class 1, px, gamma, omega 1.
So the mu1 is estimated.
So I did not call it here.
Just in previous slide, mu2 in previous slide, sigma 1.
This is determinant.
It stops here.
Square root.
So for any given x, we can simply
start to do this formula to calculate the px, gamma, omega
1.
Because, actually, the mu1, mu2, mu1, and the sigma 1
are all estimated from the data.
Similarly, for class 2, we can have the density function.
So this is actually the square root
of the determinant of sigma 2.
Sigma here means sigma 1, sigma 2 is a capital
letter of sigma.
So it means current matrix.
So the density function could be like this.
So p1 could be just a joint.
A joint probability of x and omega 1,
which is the product of the density function
with a prior probability of p omega 1.
So in this example, we have 100 samples from class 1.
100 samples from class 2.
So the prior probability for the two classes,
both equal, actually, half, right?
See, from 5.
So this is a prior probability.
1 half, 1 half times the density function for class 1,
density function for class 2.
So this is a Gisler function.
For any input x, for any sample,
either it's a training sample or a testing sample, x,
the vector is given, right?
It's known.
We can substitute the formula to calculate g1, x.
And also, we can substitute the next formula,
next ingredient, calculate g2, x.
Then we can compare the two Gisler functions
to see which one is bigger, right?
Which one is greater?
If g1 is greater, then we see the sample x.
And it's a sample in class 1, omega 1.
All the samples, g2 is greater, right?
We send the sample to class 2.
If the two, the same value, then we
see that this sample is on the descent boundary.
And it's 50-50%, right?
We cannot decide 50-50.
So this is the sample, it's on the descent boundary.
Just now I showed you the sample examples, right?
Actually, I then generated, actually, like $40,000 data
point, $40,000.
For usual data point x, I substitute the formula
to calculate g1, x, calculate g2, x.
And then obtain the corresponding class.
And finally, actually, we get the regions for class 1 and class 2.
One is the yellow region for one class,
and the gray region for another class.
OK.
So then you can see a boundary in between, right?
It's the boundary between the yellow and gray region.
So this is the descent boundary.
Any sample on the descent boundary
will have the same g1 and g2x.
So because the probability is 50% to 50%, right?
You cannot decide.
So this sample is on the descent boundary.
So from this example, actually, we can clearly show the g1,
g1, such a way, could classify the samples, actually,
correctly, right?
Of course, actually, we could have some errors.
These errors, most likely, are autolyes.
So in the last week, actually, we
started autolyes, right?
Autolyes in the value is actually very different
from the normal values.
So these are likely, likely autolyes.
So for autolyes, normally, we classify them wrongly.
OK.
So this is the basic descent rule.
Of course, I used as two examples,
as the illustration, right?
In practice, actually, the data is high dimensional.
We know that data is a high-dent 3, and 400, 500.
We cannot visualize data.
It's very hard to visualize.
Of course, we have other means we rely,
but not directly we rely on data, even in the original space.
So we cannot actually find the data dilution.
But this is just for illustration, probably.
Illustration, that means, in such a way,
to design the classification algorithm,
to design the different functions,
and we classify the sample correctly.
Based on this illustration, we should trust this method.
OK.
So this is the, actually, base decision theory, right?
A base decision rule.
And the key issue is the estimation of the density
function.
And here, we assume the following normal dilution.
And then the key issue is the estimation
of the mean vector parametric.
And actually, the both estimate has a closed form.
We have formula to calculate directly
for the two parameter, the mean vector parametric.
So then, actually, we look at another scenario.
Just now, we see the data follow normal dilution.
In practice, the data may follow normal dilution,
but it's a multi-modal.
In last week, actually, when I showed you
some exploration tools, like he said, well,
I mentioned that there are a few peaks, right?
There's something like, they call multi-modal.
Multi-modal, that means, actually,
the data may come from multiple pre-gaussian functions.
Gaussian functions.
OK.
So in such a scenario, if the data is
from multiple gaussian functions,
certainly, we should not use just one single gaussian function
or normal function to model the distribution of the data.
If they are from multiple actually gaussian functions,
and then we should use multiple gaussian functions
to construct a density function.
OK.
So this is one scenario.
Another scenario is this.
The data do not follow normal dilution.
This is absolute dilution.
It has been approved for any distribution
if the data is continuous.
We can use multiple normal density functions,
multiple normal functions, to approximate the density function.
If they follow normal density function,
we use normal density function.
If they don't follow, we can still
use normal density function to approximate.
But we need to use multiple density function
to approximate the density function,
multiple normal functions.
Each of the normal functions has its own mean vector
and correct matrix.
OK.
So this is the motivation behind the Gaussian mixture model.
Mystery, that means the model is a mix of a few gaussian
function, or a whole net gaussian function, or normal functions.
OK.
And this diagram just shows the data of class 2,
the blue samples.
Actually clearly the sample is from model 1
actually density function.
Actually it's from model 1 gaussian function.
So it is from 2 gaussian functions.
So for such a data, certainly we need
to use the two normal functions to construct the density function.
But if we don't know, of course you can use multiple,
you can use multiple Gaussian functions
to construct the density function.
OK.
So this is a Gaussian mixture model.
So this is a Gaussian, this is like a PS omega, right?
This is a density function, right?
Class conditional density function.
Class conditional probability density function.
So now actually we have a summation of a few normal functions.
M is the normal function, right?
The normal function.
And each function has its own mean vector correct matrix.
So here we assume the function, the density function contains
m normal functions.
And so the Px is a weighted summation of this m Gaussian
functions.
Usually Gaussian function has a width r for i.
OK.
So this function is a summation of a few density functions.
A few Gaussian density functions, right?
This density function is a summation of a few Gaussian
functions or normal functions.
And the summation by no direct summation, right?
It's a weighted summation.
So that means each Gaussian function
has a corresponding width denoted by r for.
And so this r for summation of r for should be 1.
Should be 1.
So this is r for.
And of course, if we assume a density function,
and then how to estimate this Px omega,
from the given sample x, the trinium sample, right?
How to estimate the trinium?
How to estimate?
That means that we need to estimate mu 1, mu sigma 1,
mu 2, sigma 2, and mu m, sigma i m.
And also we also need to estimate r for 1, r for 2,
and r for i m, right?
So you ought to determine this density function, which
is a mixture of a few Gaussian functions.
So certainly this is much harder, right?
It's much challenging than the previous scenario.
We just have one single, actually normal function,
to construct the density function.
Then the mean vector and the current matrix
could be easily obtained, right?
But now we don't know.
We don't know how many, right?
We don't know which sample belongs to capulon number 1,
which sample belongs to capulon number 2,
Gaussian capulon number 2.
We don't know.
Then how to calculate the mu i, mu 1, mu sigma 1, mu 2,
sigma 2?
How to calculate the corresponding alpha 1, alpha 2?
OK.
Of course, actually, this is just for illustration purpose.
We know this data belongs to this Gaussian function.
This data belongs to this Gaussian function, right?
But you practically just given data.
You cannot see the data distribution.
How do we know which sample belongs to which density
function, which Gaussian function?
You don't know.
If you don't know how to estimate the mean vector
and the current matrix, OK?
So how to estimate?
So here, we still need to use the so-called max likelihood
method to estimate.
We still need to use this method, OK?
And here.
So again, given this asset D, right?
This D, this asset D. This asset for class 1.
This asset for class 2.
And because the two density functions are
constructed separately, right?
So here, the D just means the sample from the same class.
So we can have the likelihood function, right?
Which is the summation and multiplication
of the many functions, right?
Many probabilities.
But after we take the logarithm of the equation,
that becomes summation.
You remember P here, actually, for each sample, right?
So now it's X, R, I, mu, I, sigma, I.
For each of the samples, right?
And it is the density function.
And it contains actually M Gaussian functions.
So here, previously, we just for 2-clad, right?
We just have mu1, mu2, sigma minus sigma 2, right?
Now, even for 2-clad kind of problem,
because actually for class 2, we have multiple
actually Gaussian functions.
And then, actually, we have more parameters to estimate,
right now, and more parameters to estimate.
But the principle of the same, we use the maximum likelihood
method to estimate.
OK.
So here, we define actually one variable.
And this OI, OI here means the Gaussian component O1.
OK, O, O, O, OI, this is the Gaussian component I.
So we have multiple Gaussian components, right?
In this density function, we have M. OK.
So each sample, because the sample, given sample, right,
in this class, we don't know which Gaussian component
is a belongs to.
OK.
So we assume this sample XK belonging to Gaussian component
in the same class.
All the Gaussian components are in the same class.
OK.
So XK belonging to the Gaussian component OI.
We denote this probably as gram IK.
Gram IK.
OK.
We denote this.
And then, OK, how to calculate this gram IK,
which is the probability of OI given XK.
And here, again, we apply them the base theorem, right?
So this is like a posterior probability, something like that.
So this is the probability of OI given XK.
So here, the numerator here is the John probability
of SK and OI, right?
So it's OI and SK times P, OI.
This is similar to what we have used before, right?
So this is the base theorem.
And then, the denominator here is the total probability of X.
So OK.
So this is the gram IK.
And so now, actually, we don't see one sample
belonging to one specific class, actually, a component.
Actually, for each sample, actually,
it has a probability belonging to each of these m components,
or Gaussian components, in this density function.
OK.
So this is actually the gram IK.
The sample SK belongs to Gaussian component OI.
This probability denotes the gram IK.
OK.
And then, actually, all of them
follows the mass-malarly method, right?
The threshold derivative to the fifth parameter,
this year, right?
Just follow the previous procedure.
And finally, we can find this is the mu I.
Mu I.
Mu I, not the class I, right?
This is a component I in this class.
OK.
Mu I.
So we use all the samples, twice me.
OK.
But the usage of the sample belonging to this Gaussian
component has a certain probability.
So some of them, maybe, the probability is very small.
That is a contribution, a bit, very small, very little,
to the calculation of the mean value.
So if the value, the gram IK belongs to this Gaussian component
is zero, then that means it has no contribution.
So here, it's a weighted summation of the SK.
It's not a pre-progressional.
Every SK has equal contribution to the mean vector, right?
But here, because of the sample, it
belongs to a certain Gaussian component
with a certain probability.
We use this probability as a weight
to calculate the weight of the summation of all the samples
as the mean weight of a Gaussian component, or Y.
OK.
So this is the weight of the summation of all the samples
in this class, right?
Weight of the summation.
Of course, the sum of the samples could contribute a little,
because of the gram IK.
That means the probability belonging to this Gaussian
component is very small.
OK.
So this is the mean vector.
And then we can also treat it similarly
to find the current matrix for Gaussian component OI.
So look at this part.
XK minus mu i, right?
And XK minus mu i transpose, then K from 1 to n, right?
So even if you ignore this term, then this is actually
just the same as my pre-progress one, right?
But now it's different.
Each sample has a contribution.
So this contribution is a weight.
It's a weight.
So this is the symbol I, the current matrix,
for Gaussian component OI.
So each of the samples has a contribution.
This contribution is just a weight, right?
This weight is just the probability of this sample
belonging to this Gaussian component, OI.
We use this weight to get the weight of the summation.
So this is the symbol I.
And then this is the alpha i, the weight, right?
In the Gaussian mixture model.
Alpha i is a weight for Gaussian component OI
in the mixture model, which is the summation of gamma i k.
Then the k belonging to OI, then divided by the n.
OK.
And actually, in this tree, we see that to calculate alpha i,
if you look at this, right?
If we know gamma i k, and then we
got q calculated mu i, right?
We have no problem.
If we know gamma i k, we can calculate, OK?
And if we know actually gamma i k,
we can calculate actually the sigma i, right?
Which is the current matrix, right?
So the h here is gamma i k, OK?
And also, if we know gamma i k, and we
can calculate alpha i, OK?
So that means the weight.
For each of the Gaussian components,
then we can calculate it, right?
We can mean vector and current matrix.
And also, for each of the Gaussian components,
we have to calculate the weight, alpha i.
So here, the main thing here is the gamma i k.
As long as you know the gamma i k,
the probability of a sample belonging to each of the Gaussian
components.
The gamma i k is known.
And then the mean vector, the current matrix,
and also the weight for each of the Gaussian components,
are determined.
Then the Gaussian-Mission model is determined.
OK, so here, the k is to calculate gamma i k, right?
So what is the gamma i k?
If we go back to look at this formula, right?
The gamma i k depends on x k, depends on alpha i,
p x k o i, right?
p x o i also depends on mu i and the sigma i.
So in other words, the gamma i k, the mu i, the sigma i,
the alpha i depends on gamma i k.
But the gamma i k depends on mu i, sigma i, and the alpha i.
So in other words, actually, we cannot have a closed form.
We cannot have a closed form to find, actually,
these parameters, right?
Because actually, gamma i k is determined by others, right?
And others are determined by gamma i k.
So the parameter cannot be estimated in closed form.
In closed form, that means we have a formula
to calculate directly.
We cannot have that, OK?
So then how to solve this problem?
Actually, we can use a so-called expectation-maximization
method.
This EM algorithm, actually, is also a commonly used algorithm
in machine learning.
EM, expectation-maximization.
Actually, this algorithm contains two parts.
One part, one step, two steps.
One is called expectation.
Another step is called maximization.
So together, it's called expectation-maximization algorithm.
OK.
And actually, this algorithm is an iterative method.
Because it cannot be solved.
It cannot be estimated in a closed form.
Then we can only use an iterative method to solve.
It's iterative.
OK.
So how do you treat iterative?
Normally, iterative method, now you say,
now we need to start the formula initial step, right?
We give the values for one set of parameters.
For example, we give values for alpha i, mu i, and sigma i.
And then based on this, we determine that the gamma i k.
Then after that, actually, this is actually
a normally called estimation step.
Based on the gamma i k, then we calculate the mu i, sigma i,
and alpha i.
Then in the next step, based on the mu i, beta i,
and the sigma i, gamma i, the alpha i,
we calculate the mu, gamma i k.
So we do this iteratively.
At the beginning of the value, maybe I run my given.
Step by step, actually, the value will converge.
It will converge.
OK.
So this is the basic idea of the expectation
and maximization method.
It's a very commonly used.
So the e-step, e-step, actually, estimates
gamma i k for the given values of r, i, mu, i, sigma i.
Because we see the formula, right?
Gamma i k is a pskoi.
O i contains the mu i, sigma i.
So for given value of r, i, mu, i, sigma i,
we calculate gamma i k.
So this is called expectation step.
Then next step is called maximization.
After we get r for i k, we should
find the values of r for i, mu, i, sigma i to maximize,
actually, the loss function.
So this step is called, actually, the maximization step.
So these two steps, I use iteratively.
Starting from expectation step, then we do the maximization.
So after we estimate the r for i, mu, i, sigma i,
we go back to the estimation step.
Based on the new r for i, mu, i, sigma i
to calculate new gamma i k.
And then based on new gamma i k, we
have a new r for i, mu, i, sigma i.
So these two steps are implemented, right?
It's iteratively.
So this is the expectation maximization algorithm.
So these are given the detailed steps of the algorithm.
And so first step is called initialization.
Initialization.
OK.
So we assume the step 0, the initial step, right?
And then for r for i, mu, i, sigma i,
and we should give them values, right,
so that we can calculate gamma i k in the next step,
in the expectation step.
So how this way value are given in the initial step?
Actually, these values, these are given randomly.
In other words, we assign random values
for this mu i, sigma i.
We have some random values.
But an r for i also give a random value.
But we should make sure the summation of r or i should be 1,
because this is the property of r for i, right?
So you can assign some of the values of r, all right?
Then finally, you need to make sure
that the summation of the actually should be 1.
So this is the initial step.
So after we have the initial step,
we have a foundation.
We have basis to calculate gamma i k.
So set the j equal to 1.
Then we start the first step, expectation, right?
Step based on the r for i, 0, r for i, mu i, 0, sigma i, 0,
we calculate gamma i k 1, right?
So this is the gamma i k, right?
This is the gamma i k.
SK, OI, so based on these values,
given in the previous step, although it's random, right?
But if it's given, so for any input, for any sample x,
SK is known, right?
SK will substitute.
Then we can get this gamma i k.
OK.
So this is the maximization.
After we get gamma i k, then the next step,
we should calculate.
We should calculate, right?
So mu i, sigma i, and r i.
So this is jamming the step, not the step.
Now it's still in the first step, right?
After the initialization, in the first step,
we start from the expectation.
And then we come to the maximization.
So jam now equals 1.
And then after that, we go back to step 2.
Again, expectation, right?
But now we need to calculate gamma i k
based on the new estimate of the mu i, sigma i, and r for i.
So then this pressure we are repeating for many times.
Until the stopping criterion is satisfied.
So the stopping criterion could be the number of iterations.
You see, or based on iterations, if I iterate this
pressure for 1,000 times, 1,000 iterations,
then we can stop.
Then we just run iteratively and perform the expectation step
and also the maximization step.
Many times until the method step is reached.
So this is one criterion.
Another criterion is that because at the beginning,
we knew the solution is very bad, right?
It's given randomly, right?
So we would have seen a solution
could convert to the optimal solution.
And convert, that means after a certain step,
the value should stabilize.
Stabbed line.
And even if there is a change, the change
should be very small, a trivial change.
So this is another criterion.
If after a certain step, the change
is of the parameters, including the mu i, sigma i, r for i,
and also the gamma i k, all the parameters are stabilized.
That means the change is very small from one step
to another step.
Then we can stop.
So this is another criterion we can use in the training
in the EM algorithm.
So these are the two steps in the EM algorithm.
These are very commonly used in machine learning.
And so in particular, it isn't like a simple problem,
because we just know it's a normal function.
But if the function is very more complex,
and then actually, normally we don't have a closed form
solution.
We don't have a closed form solution.
And then we need to use iterating method.
And then previously, you learned some organization method.
We see a partial derivative of j, a partial derivative
of the cost function with respect to the parameter,
should be 0.
Even if there's a loss function, cost function
is very complicated.
Even if you let this be 0, this equation
is very hard to solve.
Of course, this example is easy.
It could be easier to solve.
In such a scenario, we need to use the gradient descent method.
Gradient descent.
And then you all learned this before.
You're an algorithm study, right?
Gradient descent method.
We always start from an initial position.
Then we iteratively actually go to the optimal solution.
So this is something like that.
It's iterative.
We don't have a closed form.
But we can use the iterative way to find the solution.
So this is the EM algorithm.
Commonly used in machine learning.
And in particular, long-ing, if the machine learning model
develops in place, the parameter is hard to find.
We don't have a closed form to estimate
the parameters of the machine learning model.
So when to turn to the state of expedition,
expedition, it's really better to solve the solution.
OK, maybe you have a break.
Time is a break.
After a break, I'll show you an example.
I'll go down.
Go down.
OK.
So now that we look at this example,
and just now we have seen this in the example, right?
And for class two, and certainly, the data
is not from one single algorithm function.
And actually, it is from two.
Because actually, I generated the data from two algorithm
functions for the sample in class two.
OK.
So now, of course, here we know, right?
We know we assume we know.
Or we know there are two components.
There are two function functions.
And for the data in the class two.
And so in this function, Mr. Model,
we should use actually two Gaussian components.
So the m should be set to two, right?
OK.
And so now that we need to estimate,
we need to estimate the mean vector and the current
mark matrix for each of these two Gaussian components.
And also we need to estimate the weightage, right,
for this Gaussian component, for each of the two Gaussian
components.
That is r for 1, r for 2.
OK.
And so we need to use the so-called expectation
maximization algorithm, right?
And which is a iterative weight for the parameter estimation.
And so in the first step, or before we start the expectation
step, we need to assign random values
onto the two mean vector, two mean two current matrix,
and also the two weight, r for 1, r for 2.
So we assume these are random values.
So I use a mean two, right?
Because this is for class two, right?
So I use class two.
This is the first component of class two, mean vector.
And this is actually the second component of class two.
So this is the mean vector for first Gaussian component
of class two.
This is the second Gaussian component, class two
of class two, mean vector.
So these are values I generate randomly, randomly.
And these current matrix I also generate randomly.
So this is an initial step, right?
So we assume this is zero, right?
This zero means the zero step, the initial step.
And this two mean for class two.
This one two mean for Gaussian component number one,
Gaussian component number two, for class two.
These are the r for 1, r for 2.
Remember that summation of the two should be 1.
OK.
So these are the initial step.
So after the initialization of these parameters,
then we should start the iterative procedure, right?
So the first actually the expectation step
to estimate the gamma IK, the probability of each sample
belonging to omega 1, or 1, belonging to the first component,
also the probability to belong to the second Gaussian
component.
So the expectation step, right?
And estimation step.
So we have a formula to calculate, right?
So actually after one thousand iterations,
we assume actually the number of steps, number of iterations
is set to one thousand.
Then you repeat expectation and maximization,
expectation is one thousand times.
And so finally, we get this actually
the estimate for the mean vector and the current measures.
So the two mean vectors is after one thousand step, right?
So this is 3.0992 minus 0.932.
So this is the first with mean vector.
This is the second mean vector, right?
Second component.
And the first actually the current matrix,
the second current matrix, and also actually the width vector.
Actually the width vector, so the width of r of 1, r of 2,
actually so summation actually is 1.
Summation is 1.
OK.
So this is like 49% something, right?
49.5.
And this is like 15.48%.
So 50, 50 like, right?
So OK.
And so these are issues.
So after we estimate the mean vector current
measure for the two Gaussian components, right?
Then we can construct actually the density function for class 2.
Use the two Gaussian functions to construct
the density function for class 2, right?
So this is the density function of class 2, right?
Continue to Gaussian component.
And each of them has a width vector, has a width alpha,
has a mean vector and current matrix.
OK.
So you can see there are two, right?
So two Gaussian components.
And each of them has its own mean vector and current matrix.
And therefore class 1, I think for class 1,
you just want Gaussian component, right?
So we use all the sum of to estimate the mean vector,
just average for all the samples.
After we can estimate the current matrix.
So this is the density function for class 1.
So class 1 just has one Gaussian function.
For class 2, we have two.
Actually, class 2 is a Gaussian function, right?
It's a width summation for two Gaussian functions.
So these are the shows, the mean vector.
And for the two, actually, component in class 2.
Actually, from here, you can see this actually
indeed provides a good estimate, right?
For the two, actually, the mean vectors
of the two Gaussian components, right?
So this should be a good estimate, right?
You just know roughly, you know,
this is in the center part, right?
Roughly this is in the center part.
But actually, beginning of this values are randomly given.
But actually, after many iterations, right?
So they convert, actually, to the, indeed,
to the true almost, and then close to the true values.
OK.
So these are not the real one.
It's just the mean vector for the class 1.
OK.
So now, actually, we see width of probability, right?
Actually, we combine the probability
and width of density function.
And we can calculate the G-shape function, G1,
actually, G2x, right?
So in this question problem, example, class 1 has 100 samples.
Class 2 has 200 samples.
And then, actually, the probability for class 1
is 1.
Probability for class 2, probability, right?
To the, becoming a 200 samples.
OK.
Then now, we use both the prior probability
and density function.
And actually, to actually estimate to obtain the,
this, this function, G, right?
OK.
So this is G1x, right?
P1x, 1.2, G2x.
So we use the drunk probability of omega, right?
And x, that's the, this one function, right?
Now, G1x, we have G2x.
So for any given x, for any actual x,
either it's a training sample or testing sample, right?
We can always substitute each of the formula
into the equation to calculate G1x and G2x.
And then, we can compare the size of the two values,
two density functions, right?
If G1x is greater, then we solve sample to class 1.
If G2x is greater, we assign the sample to class 2, OK?
So for this function, examples are generated
at 40,000 data points in this range, from 1 to 4 to 6.
We'll put x1x to the two features, OK?
So for each of the samples, I substitute into the G1 and G2.
And then, based on G1 and G2, finally,
I get a class label, a class prediction, OK?
So finally, this is a range, OK?
For class 2, a yellow region.
For class 1, the green region, OK?
And so indeed, actually, from this example,
I'm going to show you the Gaussian mixture model,
actually build a good decision boundary, right?
For the sample in the two classes, OK?
So this is actually Gaussian mixture model used for class 2.
Because class 2 contains more than one Gaussian component.
OK, we use the EM, already, to estimate the value
of the two Gaussian components.
So these are shown, of course, in practice, right?
Normally, we cannot see the data, right?
We don't know how many Gaussian components.
Normally, we always start from 1, right?
We always assume that only 1.
Normally, at least actually, at the first step,
we assume there are 1, right?
We try this method.
We try it with just one Gaussian component for class 1,
one Gaussian component for class 2.
And then we build, actually, the, we construct the density
function for each of the two classes.
And then, based on density function and also the probability
to construct the displacement function, which
is a drunk probability, right?
OK, so then we look at the result on the training,
on the testing, OK?
And so here, of course, we assume we don't know, right?
For class 1, for class 1, we assume 1.
For class 2, we also assume only one Gaussian component.
OK, then, actually, for class 2, we
estimate this is the mean vector,
at least the current matrix.
OK, and then, based on this, only one, the single Gaussian
function to construct, actually, the density function
for class 2.
OK, and so this is the result, actually, when only one,
actually, Gaussian function, Gaussian component
is used for class 2.
So this is the result.
You can see the density of boundary is a bit different,
right?
So here, this is the density of boundary.
OK, and this is the density of boundary.
You can see the difference, right?
OK.
OK, so actually, I just mentioned,
also, one of the students asked me during the break,
actually, if we don't know m, how do you tell?
In practice, we indeed don't know the m.
Just now, in the previous slide, I already showed,
if we don't know m, we assume 1, then we can see the result.
So actually, in practice, you don't know, of course,
you can try.
We should try 1.
1 can go first, right?
Then we look at the performance.
Then we see, oh, whether the performance is good or not,
right?
If actually, we see the performance of the testing data
of our requirement, then we can just use 1.
If actually, the result, actually,
does not satisfy our requirement, OK,
we want to have a better result, or actually, we
want to have an optimal result.
Then we should try 2, right?
We should try 2.
We should try 3.
We should try more.
OK.
So here, we already tried 2, right?
Actually, 2.
Now we look at the model, too.
We assume there are three.
There are three.
OK.
So these are the iterative estimation
using the E and all, right?
So finally, we get the main vector for the three,
actually, Gauchen-Kabone.
OK.
And see, this is only for class 2.
I just pulled the sample in class 2.
So this one, indeed, is here, right?
Is it here?
And then another one is here.
Another one is here.
The two is actually, main vector,
close to each other.
If there are, we assume there are two.
OK.
And particularly, we can see, actually,
I think we should consider the value here for the R-class.
The R-class.
You can see the R-class value, R-class 1, is 0.0523.
In other words, actually, this is actually R-class.
Normally, it's weighted, right?
Like 5.
0.05, like 5%.
OK.
But look at other two Kaupo-net R-class values.
1 is 0.05, right?
And other 0.44, which are significantly greater than R-class 1.
So this is the case, my three I used.
Actually, from this example, we can see,
oh, for one of the R-class, the weightage of that Kaupo-net
is very small.
Only 0.05, 5%.
Because summation 2.0 should be 1, right?
So here, among the three, this one
is very significantly smaller than other two,
significantly, right?
Other 10 times of this weight.
So from here, we can roughly judge how many Kaupo-net
we should use, right?
We already use.
So now, actually, we can see another scenario.
We assume there are five.
So now we assume one or three, right?
Now we assume five.
And then these are the vectors, center vectors.
So we see the mean vector for the five Kaupo-net.
And then why is it here, right?
In the center, and here, this one, the center, maybe
this one just cover a few samples, right?
Then we can have a mean vector of this.
In the calculation of the mean vector,
we use all the samples.
But we have a gamma IK, right?
Gamma IK, that means the sample K
belong to this R-class, OK?
And from here, we can see if the value,
if the mean vector is here.
Actually, this is most likely the gamma, the gamma value
for the sample, right?
Belong to this cluster, it's close to zero.
Otherwise, actually, the center could not be here, right?
Could not be actually here.
Or it could not be here.
Maybe only a few samples, actually, in this region
have non-zero gamma IKs.
But then finally, the location of the mean vector is here.
And similarly, for this, this is where it's
almost in the center, right?
In the center.
And this data is far away from the center,
is near the boundary, right here.
This means that most of the gammas IK, right?
Close to zero.
Only a few, actually.
Yeah, if it's non-zero.
Then finally, maybe only these samples have a non-zero gamma
IK.
Then finally, the average is located here.
So these are the scenarios when five Gaussian components
are used for class two.
OK, then we look at the values of R5.
So R5, 1, 0.4670.
And then, actually, 0.03, very small, right?
Then another 0.05, 0.02, and then another 0.04.
You can see these values are 20 times of the small,
smaller value, right?
Or at least 10 times.
So from these, actually, we can see only two components
have significant greater values.
So from these, probably, we can judge only two, actually,
Gaussian components, which probably
are the underlying data.
OK, so we achieve, the R5 values provide information
about the number of, actually, the number of, the number
of Gaussian components.
And in the data, or number of components,
we should use to build the density function for that class.
And of course, some of you ask, oh, in this question,
alpha 1, and in that question, it's alpha 2.
I think they don't matter.
Finally, you just put that current component number 1,
number 2.
Number 1 is number 1.
Or number 1, number 2, it doesn't really matter, right?
You just finally all put them together, right?
So you don't see, oh, in the previous example,
number 1, number 2 or 3 have big value.
But in this example, number 2, 3 have small value.
Because initially, number 1, all the values
are generally randomly, right?
In the other step, OK?
So which one is number 1, number 2, really doesn't matter.
Because finally, it's summation of the two.
So these are alpha, actually, provide information, right?
Which can be used to determine the suitable number
of component or Gaussian functions we can use,
or we should use to construct the density function.
OK.
So now we look at this, right?
So actually, in this case, I showed that in 4 class 2,
for class 1, I used actually two Gaussian components.
Although, no, the true scenario, that only one Gaussian
component, right?
For class 1.
But here, we assume there are two.
Because we have no idea how many we should use, right?
We assume there are two for class 1.
There are five for class 2.
And then we build the density function.
And finally, we have the density function.
Compared with the previous designer boundary,
certainly, the density boundary is much more complex, right?
You see, zig-zag, not like previous smooth.
Then I think that, right?
So in one sense, this is more accurate.
But you can see that, actually, we have a risk
and to overfit the training data.
So you can see this, right?
You see that this is much more complex.
And actually, you can see for the training data, maybe
the error is significantly reduced.
Actually, we can cut how many errors, right?
So now, only this sample, this sample, actually,
are misclassified.
This should be in the green region, right?
Now, they are yellow region.
So this sample was misclassified.
This is misclassified.
Therefore, others, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Maybe now, only 10 samples will be classified wrong.
Previously, we have 14 or 15 samples that are misclassified.
So certainly, by using more golden components,
actually, we have a more complex decision boundary.
And then we can have a better performance on the training
data.
But this does not mean, actually, that this is actually
a better classified.
This is a better, actually, density function.
And because, actually, this has actually more complex or more
golden components are used, we have a risk
to overfit the training data, which
will lead to non-backed generalization performance
on the unseen testing data.
OK.
In particular, even the more, how much is more, right?
We see 1 is suitable, 2 is suitable.
If we use 3 or 5, maybe just actually,
this is not very excessive.
But even if the number is excessive,
like the ordinary only 2 is sufficient,
but you use 20, you use 30, you can imagine
how complex could be the decision boundary.
You can see the change, right?
Usually, it's very smooth.
If we use 2, actually, then actually, less smooth.
Now, we use 5, 2 for class 1, 5 for class 2.
You can see this decision boundary is more complex, right?
Think about that.
OK.
So then in practice, how to determine?
How to determine?
We cannot see the data.
We cannot know the decision boundary, how complex it is.
How to determine?
OK.
And actually, in the last week, actually, when we see,
we have some data, right?
And the data normally are divided into two parts,
by training and testing.
And actually, sometimes, we divide the training,
part of the field, part of the training
as a validation data.
So the data tree is basically divided
into three parts, training, validation, and testing.
And normally, the training could be 60% of data for training,
and 20% for validation, and 20% for testing.
Or 70% for training, 15% for validation,
and 15% for testing.
Then what's the usage for validation?
How validation data could be used?
Actually, I remember, actually, in the classes,
I said validation data is used to determine
the hyperparameters.
So which is called hyperparameters?
Hyperparameters cannot be directly
estimated from the data.
So in this example, mu i, sigma i, r i
can be estimated from the data.
But the number of components in the density function,
this m, is a hyperparameter.
So normally, we first set this hyperparameter, set this to 2,
set this to 5, and then based on this set value,
then we estimate sigma i, mu i, r i, sigma i, r i, mu i,
into preset data.
So this is a parameter called hyperparameter.
Actually, we use validation data to determine
this hyperparameter.
In other words, we set m to 2, then we train the classifier.
Then we look at the performance on the validation data.
The validation data is not used for the parameter estimation.
You look at performance.
And then we set r to m to 3.
Then we find the center vectors, the current matrix,
the alphas for the three Gaussian components.
And then we construct density function.
And then after that, we perform classification
on the validation data.
Then we look at the performance.
And then again, we look at the performance.
m is set to 4, to 5, to more larger number.
And finally, we find that we should use a value of m.
That the performance on the validation data is the best.
Normally, if you use less than necessary number of Gaussian
components, the performance on the validation data
could be better.
Even on the train data could be better.
If you use the excessive number of Gaussian components
in the density function, then the performance on the validation
data could be better.
Because the model will affect the train data.
So I should have a number of m could be determined
based on the performance of the validation data.
And the difference should be the number of m.
So this is the determination of m.
So these are observations.
So when you set the number, even true is 2.
If you use 3 or 4, that makes much difference.
But if you use excessive, you know it's 2.
If you use 20, use 10.
But this excessive number of Gaussian components
are used, the decision boundary becomes more complex,
which represents the best performance on the train data,
but the worst performance on the validation data.
So this is an overfitting problem.
Overfitting.
OK, so why overfitting?
Why do you do the overfitting?
You can imagine.
If you use a more Gaussian component,
actually we could have more unknown parameters.
We could have more unknown parameters.
But the number of train assemblies is just limited.
But actually when you use a more Gaussian component,
then you have more examples.
Then we could have overfitted data.
I always want to actually use one example to illustrate
what is overfitting.
Just now, we have two parameters, a1 and a2.
a1 plus a2 equals 1.
We have two parameters, a1, a2.
We have one equation.
You have numerous solutions.
You always achieve, you set about the equation.
And actually, when the parameter estimation,
normally one sample gives one equation.
If the number of parameters is more than the number of equations,
number of samples, then we could have numerous solutions.
So that's the known overfitting.
The number of, because we use a more component,
we have more unknown parameters.
And then probably the unknown number of parameters
could be greater than the number of samples.
Greater than the number of samples.
So these are overfitting.
So we can always link these two equations.
a1 plus a2, one equation, we have two parameters.
We can always satisfy this data.
Always satisfy this train data.
OK.
So this is actually the one scenario.
So another observation that the use of set number
of Gaussian components, residing some small, actually,
alpha values.
So these are not probably the mean we use to determine
the superman number of the Gaussian component.
If alpha is too small, then it means that this alpha
may only actually cover a few examples.
So this contribution of this component
is neglectable.
So we can just ignore this.
So based on alpha values, we have to determine
suitable number of Gaussian components.
But actually, in practice, no, actually, suitable number,
what is suitable number?
It could be an arrangement.
So use 2, use 3, use 4.
That will make much difference.
So it's in an arrangement normally.
So here it's called excessive number.
Excessive, actually.
OK.
So this is the Gaussian-Mister model.
So that's actually, I talked about another method.
We call it naive-based.
Naive-based.
So it's a base theorem, a base design theory.
Also based on probabilities.
But actually, it's just called naive.
Why is it called naive?
And actually, we look at this base theorem.
And this is the posterior probability, right?
Probability of omega z and the given x.
So if we look at the numerator part,
the numerator part is a joint probability, right?
px omega j, p omega j.
And so here, actually, we assume the x is a vector.
We use a multiple features or attributes.
So now we look at the px omega j.
And then you multiply it, right?
It's a joint probability of x and omega j.
So the joint probability is OK.
And this x, we expand x.
So this is x1, x2, and xd, that omega j.
So here, actually, the joint probability of x1, x2, xd,
omega j.
And so now, actually, we can, again,
we use this formula, right?
We can use, actually, like x2, x3, xd, omega j as a condition.
And then the probability x1.
Then times this px2, x3, xd, omega j.
So this is similar to this, right?
So we have this formula.
OK, now we can also, for this part, px2, x3, xd, omega j,
right?
Actually, this is also a joint probability of x2, xd,
and omega j, right?
So we can, this should be equal to the probability of x2
given this condition, times the probability of this condition.
And similarly, for x3, right?
We can calculate this part, actually, for,
should be x3 given the condition x4, xd, omega j,
times the probability of this.
So finally, we can expand this into some px1 and the condition
x2, x3, xd.
So px2 and condition x3, xd, times the condition px, actually,
d, omega j.
Then times the px, omega j.
So this is just the expansion, right?
The expansion of the joint probability of x and omega j.
It can be into such a form.
OK.
So in a naive base, we assume all the features are independent.
You remember in the last week, actually,
now we see in this progression of the data, right?
We see one of these flourishing is a scatter plot.
So one variable feature against another feature, right?
We plot the data division.
So from this scatter plot, we can judge the relationship
to the two features, the correlation, right?
Sometimes the two features are uncorrelated.
They are independent.
But sometimes they are severely correlated.
OK.
So this is the exploration in the last week, right?
We explored this.
The scatter plot.
OK.
So now we assume the data, the features, are interdependent.
Interdependent.
That means the conditional probability of x1, x2, x3.
That means the probability of x1 is not affected by x2, x3, xd.
The probability of x2 is not affected by x3, x4, and xd.
Because we assume the data, the features
are independent.
So if they are independent, so we assume the features
are independent, OK?
Then this probability, we can simply
even know this x1, just equal to x1, omega, j.
OK.
So because the features are independent, OK?
So the x1 is not affected by x2, x2, x3.
So this should be equal to px, omega, j.
And similarly, actually for arbitrary features,
right?
xi, xi, we have this result.
So now we summarize the substitute result,
actually, for the general probability, right?
Just now we see the general probability include,
finally expanding to this part, right?
But now, based on the assumption, actually, x1, x2, xd,
are independent.
Then this becomes actually x1, actually, and omega, j.
This should be x2 and omega, j.
So finally, so we have this result.
OK.
We have this result.
So the general probability of a feature vector x and omega,
j, actually, can be estimated based
on the product of each individual feature, right?
Each individual feature x1, we estimate the general probability
with omega, j.
OK.
Then the modifications.
So when you want to estimate the general probability
of the feature vector x and omega, j, OK?
Based on the assumption of interdependence, right?
Of all the features.
Finally, actually, this general probability
can be estimated based on this modification of each,
general probability of each individual feature
with actually the class of omega, j.
OK.
So this is the general probability based on the assumption.
So now we start to this result into the base theorem,
base theorem, right?
The posterior probability, actually, in the numerator part,
it's just the general probability of the feature vector x
and the class omega, j.
But based on the assumption, so this
is reduced to the multiplication of each individual feature,
general probability with the omega, j with the class.
OK.
Actually, then what's the advantage of this?
What's the advantage?
Actually, OK.
So actually, the advantage is that for now,
if you look at this, right?
For each individual feature, if we assume it
for a normal distribution, then how many unknown parameters?
Two, why is the mean value not vector?
Mean value, another is the mean, is the standard value
of the variance.
So for each feature, for each feature,
or for each attribute, if we assume for a normal distribution,
we have two parameters.
But totally, we have d features.
Then totally, we have a 2d parameters, 2d.
2d, right?
Only 2d.
But even imagine, actually, now if we think about it,
if we don't assume the unit dependence, right?
So we have the current matrix.
We have the mean vector.
For mean vector, how many parameters?
D. So vector, right?
D parameters.
But how about the current matrix?
D times D, right?
If we assume, actually, we have 100 features.
Then 100 times 100 is 10,000.
Then divide by 2, because the current matrix is symmetric.
OK, divide by 2.
So 5000 plus 100 for the mean vector.
5100 parameters.
We need to estimate the number of parameters
from the training samples.
But if we assume the interdependency, right?
Between the features, each feature has two parameters.
Totally, we have 200 unknown parameters.
If we use the feature vector, right?
5100.
But now we just have 200.
Actually, the number is significantly reduced.
OK, so although in practice, they
mean not necessarily true.
This assumption for interdependence.
OK, but actually, in practice, the result of the 9-bit
is quite good.
OK, so this is the reason.
This 9-bit, I think in all the 12-boxes,
we can find this actually, 9-bit, this method.
It's very useful.
Although the assumption, right?
Actually, simple another problem.
It seems that, actually, this assumption
may be not violated in practice.
But actually, the result is good in practice.
So although we see that one is in principle,
in theory, it's optimal.
But because of the number of training samples is limited,
we just have 1,000 data.
But we have to estimate 5,100, actually, sample,
the unknown parameter, right?
This is just one example.
If the number of features is 1,000,
so this could be not.
The explosion of the number of samples,
the number of unknown parameters, right?
So although in theory, you can estimate this.
But actually, in practice, this value
is quite far from the true value.
Because the number of training samples is too small,
compared with the number of unknown parameters.
OK, so I think, yeah, that's maybe a little bit of this.
Top of 9-bit classifier.
OK, so last week, we said the features
can be categorized into different categories, right?
Quantitative, qualitative, quantitative like,
also can be, let's say, continuous features and discrete.
For continuous features, actually,
we can assume the following number of user, right?
We follow normal user.
But for discrete features, we cannot assume the following
normal user, right?
For discrete, OK?
So for the naive base here, OK?
So for continuous features, we can have a Gaussian naive base.
And then for discrete features, we certainly cannot
use the Gaussian function.
So what function we can use?
We can have the Bernoulli naive base, where the data,
the feature, just have two values.
If agenda is a feature, male or female, just two values.
Then I use the Bernoulli naive base.
If the feature could have multiple values,
but it's still discrete, we can use the so-called
multinomial naive base, OK?
So the second one, the Bernoulli naive and the
multinomial naive base are all for discrete features,
discrete, and Gaussian for continuous.
So that is the reason why we should differentiate the feature.
Before, actually, you apply the data to the machine
system, right?
So the learning algorithm, we should explore the data.
We should identify the top of the data, right?
Which feature is continuous?
Which feature is discrete?
OK.
And then, you know, if you naive, we
should use different methods, different ways
to estimate the data functions.
OK.
I think that for the first one, I think
there are no need to introduce the algorithm,
because in the first case, we already
introduced the univariate Gaussian function, right?
So we no need for the first one.
And for the second one, the one, we will introduce in the next
week, OK?
And today is the festival, all right?
Probably, you guys are all not some event there, right?
And no?
Probably, I need a winner garden.
Not there, OK.
So we classed, actually, we classed earlier.
And can go home now?
Yeah.
Thank you.
APPLAUSE
I
Thank you
You
I'm not sure what he's talking about.
He's talking about the hair that's being cut.
I don't know what he's talking about.
I'm not sure what he's talking about.
He's talking about the hair that keeps getting cut.
I'm not sure what goes around coming from that hair.
When would you want one?
That's time then?
Or this?
Where is the, where is the, where, where would the hair come?
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure what he's talking about.
Doctor don't get into the test
The only way!
You look at this, no of this
See that trend?
I said that I be there
Where are you going?
Go home
What plan do you have to make?
Mom started to see him.
Make her你的家
because he rejected me, so I walked down here.
So what's the time?
8PM.
Hi.
It's afternoon now?
Hm.
Prepare for school.
I'm tired of that.
Speaking from my laptop.
Are you sure?
Hm.
I'm not sure what you're talking about.
What?
I'm just saying.
Oh, no.
You're not coming?
Yeah, you're not coming.
What?
I'm just saying.
I'm not going to...
So, um...
This is very big.
oh
Oh
We
Yeah
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
I'm already a 아 Ugh
I'm already a are
ouch
haven't
got
the
wait
(*
...
What is this?
It's Chinese.
What?
What is this?
It hides luggage optimum on other side of it.
Can you see it?
You still can.
No,
We're here to find out what's going on.
So what?
No.
You're a alarm.
What else?
No.
You're a alarm.