.
So in the last week, we started regression problem,
regression, and so basically we started the linear regression.
And of course, actually in the linear regression,
the key issue is how to estimate the parameters.
And actually we started one method that is L squared,
parameter estimation, B squared.
We tried to find the parameters and estimation
so that the squared area is minimized.
So this is the least squared parameter estimation.
And so besides this, actually the normal regression,
and we also started the rigid regression.
So we put actually one additional term in the loss function.
In the regular least squared estimation,
the loss function is just a squared area.
This area is just the difference between actually the
target value and the prediction from the model.
So this is called an area.
So this squared area is used as the loss function.
And then in the rigid regression,
we put one additional term in the loss function.
And that is just a penalty on the size of the parameters.
So we put L2 norm of the parameter vector.
So this is a rigid regression.
And this rigid regression penalized the size of the parameter.
And actually it shrinks the parameter towards zeros.
Because actually the zero squared, the L2 norm, is the minimum.
But actually we cannot just omit this one criteria.
We also can see the minimization of the prediction area.
So the loss function should be the balance of the two.
So these two functions, actually one of the term is weighted.
That is we put a lambda and before actually the L2 norm of the parameter vector.
And then the last one is the loss regression.
In the loss regression, the penalization of the parameter size
is in the form of the L1 norm.
And although actually the loss regression and the regression
has a very subtle difference, but actually the result is quite different.
And to push further, actually,
we put a straight requirement on the value of the parameters.
That means the shrinks have a stronger shrinkage towards zeros.
So in this loss regression, not only we estimate the parameter,
but we also select the variables.
Because many of the parameters will shrink to zero.
So this is the loss.
And after we have obtained a model,
of course we need to evaluate the performance of the model.
So in the last week, we also started a few metrics
that can be used to evaluate the performance of a regression model.
So the first one is the mean squared error.
And also the root mean squared error.
And also we treat the mean absolute error.
And finally, we also started the r squared and adjust r squared.
So this is for the performance evaluation.
And today, we are going to study, actually, look at the model validation.
Whether a model obtains a valid model or not.
So this is called a model validation.
And in this model validation, we need to check, actually,
the assumptions of linear regression.
What assumption we have made.
And actually, we have made a few assumptions for the linear regression.
So first, actually, we assume that there is a linear regression
between the target variable, which is also called a dependent variable,
and the independent variables.
We assume that there is a linear regression.
So that we use a linear regression.
If the regression shape is nonlinear, but we assume there's a linear regression.
But then, of course, this assumption is not correct.
So here, actually, we will try to check whether or not
this assumption is violated or it is true.
So this is a linear regression shape.
So this is one assumption.
When we use linear regression, we assume linear.
And then, actually, the next assumption is that, actually,
the residual should be normally distributed.
And the residual, also, the error, right?
Actually, remember, we have a noise, or error.
And this error, called residual, actually is a normal distributed.
It's a normal function.
It's a Gaussian function.
And the noise is Gaussian.
OK, so this is the assumption.
And, of course, for the Gaussian noise, actually,
we also assume that this is a Gaussian noise,
has a zero mean.
Zero mean.
OK, so the mean of the residual should be zero or close to zero.
So this assumption we have made.
And so if you want to validate a model,
we need to check all of these assumptions.
That's a fourth one, actually, the all-independent variable
to be multi-vary normal.
All-independent variables need to be normal.
OK, so these are also assumptions.
Of course, actually, in practice,
you don't necessarily know the independent variables,
actually, are normal.
If not normal, or not multi-vary normal,
then probably we need to use, like, we need to modify the regression method,
rather than the regular square error.
Maybe you can think about other regression methods.
So this is the fourth assumption, OK,
all-independent variables, multi-vary normal.
And so then let's try the homoesthetic state.
The mean of the tree is the same virus.
This means the same virus.
And the same virus, that means, actually,
the virus should be actually the same
as all the range of the input.
OK, so this is actually an assumption.
The residual is the same across all values of the independent variables,
the virus.
OK.
And that's, OK, then the tree, the opposite to this,
is the heteroscedasticity.
That means the virus is different.
OK, then in other words, maybe the virus, actually,
of the residual, right, actually is greater or bigger
for larger values of the input.
OK, so this is also a test that we need to check
whether this condition, homoesthetic state, is satisfied.
And this is actually a diagram shows this scenario.
So the two figures here, the left figure shows
homoesthetic state.
And actually, the horizontal axis actually shows
the value of the independent variable input.
And so the vertical shows the area, right?
Actually, you can see the range, right?
Actually, this is actually the same in low
and also in the high values of these independent variables.
These are homoesthetic states, the same virus.
But you look at this right hand side, right?
So you can see, actually, for larger value of the input,
actually, the virus has a bigger range, right?
It has a bigger range.
So this means a bigger, actually, virus.
OK.
But for small values of the input, the noise,
actually, in a range, in a smaller range.
OK.
So this case, actually, is actually
heteroscedasticity, the virus.
It's not the same for, actually, low values
and the higher values of the input.
OK.
So this is the, and so this is actually
a satisfactory model.
OK.
Then this is an unsatisfactory model.
So these are the assumptions.
OK.
Then we need to check each of these assumptions
so after we have obtained a model.
OK.
So these are called model validation.
And then we first look at, actually, the linearity,
the linear relationship.
And the linearity can be checked based on, actually,
the scatter plot.
OK.
And of the actual value versus, or against,
the predicted value.
The predicted value here all means,
really, the target variable.
Right?
For the target variable, we have an actual value.
And for the predicted value, and then we can have,
you know, this is a scatter plot.
You remember, in the second week, right?
In the first week, for machine learning part,
we studied the exploration or data preparation
for machine learning.
And actually, in the data exploration part,
actually, one exploration is a scatter plot.
And the scatter plot actually shows the relationship
between two variables, right?
So here the two variables, actually,
one is the actual value, the target value.
Another is the predicted value.
So these two.
So if these two actually show the linear relationship,
just like all the data points are along a street line.
OK.
Along a street line.
And then this means that the linear relationship is satisfied.
Otherwise, actually, the predicted value and the actual value
are not on a street line.
OK.
All the data points are not actually,
are not actually on a street line.
So if the relationship is nonlinear,
but you use a linear model to feed the data, right?
And then, actually, you cannot get a scatter plot like this.
OK.
So here, for this example, and we show, actually,
indeed, actually, all the data points in this scatter plot
actually is along a line.
So this means this linear relationship is true.
OK.
So this is our first assumption, right?
And then the second assumption, actually,
is noise Gaussian.
Normal noise, disputed noise, right?
OK.
And so here, actually, how to explore,
how to visualize, how to check whether, actually,
noise is normal or data is normally disputed.
Actually, we can use the histogram.
Actually, the signal pattern on the data preparation method,
we also talk about this histogram, right?
So the data, actually, normally, is first, actually,
the data is sorted in ascending order or descending order, right?
And then we divide the whole range of the data into two parts,
into many parts, many beams.
OK.
The default value normally is 10 into 10 beams, right?
And for example, the value range is from minus 5 to positive 5,
for example, right?
And then from minus 5, we can divide this, you know,
from minus 5 to positive 5 into, actually, 10 beams.
OK.
Then we count how many samples and how many values are in each beam.
The number of values in each beam, right?
So then, based on this, we can plot, actually,
the histogram just like this, right?
So the horizontal shows that the beams, right?
The 10 beams and the vertical shows the number of values in each beam.
OK.
And so normally, if you look at this, actually,
it's roughly a bell curve, right?
Bell curve.
We know the normal division is a bell curve, right?
So from the histogram, so we see, oh, roughly,
I think this residual here is normal.
It's normal.
Of course, actually, whether it's normal,
we can use another technique that is a QQ plot.
OK.
So this roughly is normal.
And then this is a second, actually, assumption, right?
And then the assumption is that, actually,
the residual should have a zero mean.
OK.
And then, previously, last week, we have, actually,
one example, right?
Remember, we have an example for the parameter estimation
using the least square method, right?
And actually, this is the example, actually,
we have the residual, which is the difference between,
actually, the target value and the predicted value.
OK.
And then we calculate the mean.
The mean, actually, is equal to 10 power minus 17, right?
So this is very close to zero.
OK.
Then this, that means that the assumption is satisfied.
So it's roughly normal and with zero mean.
OK.
And then the fourth one, actually, we need to check,
actually, whether, actually, the independent variables,
actually, are normal, right?
Independent variables are normal.
And to check this, actually, we can use another technique
which is called, actually, now the QQ plot.
OK.
The minimum Q is the quantal.
So given a data, right, you can, again, you can sort the data,
you can order the data in descending order,
or ascending order, right?
Then you can find the quantals, the quantal value, right?
Quantal.
OK.
So also, actually, you can use a standard normal,
standard normal, standard normal.
OK.
Then you can also look at the quantal.
And then you can actually draw, actually, you know,
the points or the value, right?
So if this value is, actually, normally, the round street line,
then we see, oh, this is, actually, you know, it's normal,
approximately normal.
OK.
So for this example, we can see this range, right?
Normally, I think this is, actually, the quantal of the input
sample and the standard, actually, the normal quantals,
basically, it's on a street line, right?
It's a street line.
OK.
So if on a street line, then we, actually, we see
this condition is also satisfied, right?
Satisfied.
OK.
So it's a, this is a fourth condition, right?
The input variables are actually roughly, you know,
normal.
OK.
And then the next one, actually, is the next, actually,
we need to check the one that whom I said,
taste, taste, taste, right?
Whom I say taste, taste, taste, taste, taste.
And then we look at whether the virus of the residual,
actually, increased with the increase of the,
of the values, right?
And so here we can check this.
OK.
So, traditionally, the predicted target variable is a
horizontal axis and the vertical shows the residual,
the areas, the areas.
OK.
And actually, we, we, actually, the area range, you know,
in the, in the low value of the predicted variable,
the target value, right?
Around minus four, minus six, right?
So the range is from here to here, right?
And then for the bigger values of the target variable,
and then the variant, actually, the variant is similar,
similar, right?
It's not actually like a, like a funnel, right?
As we've seen in the previous examples, not like this.
In the low values of the predicted variable,
the target variable, the variant is small, right?
And then in the larger values, actually,
the variant is big, bigger.
We don't have this.
OK.
Basically, you like this, actually,
the whom I sketched a statistic scenario.
OK.
So from this example, we can see, oh, the model,
basically, actually, you know, this is valid because all of
the five assumptions actually are true, or roughly, right?
True.
OK.
So this is a model validation.
So, that's actually, we look at the nonlinear regression
or nonlinear regression problem.
And so far, actually, we have talked about the linear regression,
right?
A linear regression tree, we assume the linear relationship
between the target variable and the independent variables.
OK.
But sometimes, actually, the relationship between the input
variable, the target variable, input variable,
the independent variables, actually, are nonlinear.
So this diagram just shows nonlinear relationship.
OK.
And the horizontal axis is an independent variable,
and the vertical axis shows a dependent variable,
or the target variable.
And I believe you can see the data basically shows
a nonlinear relationship, nonlinear relationship.
OK.
And so the nonlinear is just a curve, right?
A linear relationship, normally, it's a straight line.
You know, you have the minus beta,
it's a harbor plane, right?
But actually, for the nonlinear, this is a curve.
OK.
So here you can see, indeed, this is a curve, right?
This is a curve.
This is also a curve.
So this means that the relationship between the target
variable and the internal variable, actually,
is nonlinear.
Nonlinear, certainly, we should use a nonlinear function, right?
And if you still use a linear regression model to feed the data,
certainly, we cannot get a valid model.
And based on the invalid model, of course,
the prediction could have a very big error, right?
Could have a very big error.
OK.
Then actually, we'll say, what kind of model we can use?
So the relationship, the way between x and theta,
so here is a nonlinear relationship, nonlinear.
OK.
And so what kind of nonlinear?
There are many types of nonlinear functions, right?
So I think, my recommended use of nonlinear models
include the polynomial model.
And actually, y equals theta 0, theta y, x, theta 2, x squared.
So here, actually, the y, in the regression model,
we have x squared term, and we have the s cubed term.
So this means that it's a nonlinear relationship.
Nonlinear relationship.
OK.
But the good thing for this polynomial is that actually,
the y is nonlinear in x, x, x, right?
In x.
But it is linear in the parameter.
In the linear in the parameter.
OK.
So this kind of model is called linear in the parameter.
Linear in the parameter.
But the nonlinear actually in the independent variables.
So basically, this is a nonlinear model.
But actually, we can use the linear model estimation method
to estimate the parameters, theta 0, theta 1, actually, theta 3.
You just can see that x to x squared is another new variable.
S cubed is another new variable.
OK.
Then this is just like a linear equation, right?
Linear equation.
But actually, this equation shows a nonlinear relationship
between the time variable y and the independent variable x.
But the y is linear in the parameters.
Then we can use the linear regression method to estimate
the values for theta 0, theta 1, theta 2, and theta 3 here.
OK.
So this is the polynomial model.
And then another model is called a rational model.
Rational here.
Rational means that it is a ratio of two polynomials.
So like this.
Theta 0, theta 1, theta 2, x cubed squared divided by theta 3
plus theta 4x and theta 5x cubed squared.
OK.
So just an example.
The highest order here is the two.
So this is called a rational model.
OK.
Of course, it's really compared with a polynomial model.
And I think the rational model parameter estimation
is challenging because the y no longer has a linear relationship
with the parameters.
Then we cannot use the linear regression parameter estimation
method to estimate the parameters.
And it is a rational model.
So this is a challenge.
OK.
And also, if we look at the polynomial model, right?
So here we just have a 1x.
We can have x squared.
We can have a cube.
This is just one independent variable.
But you can imagine if the model has many or have a few, right?
Or many independent variables.
x1, x2, x3, x4, and xn.
OK.
Then actually the model.
So what actually nonlinear terms should be included in the model?
So here we just have our xs squared, x3, right?
So this is easy if we have just a single variable.
But now we just consider that we have two variable, x1, x2.
Of course, we can still have x1 squared, x2 squared, x2, x2,
x2 cubed, right?
But also we should have some terms like x1, multiply, x2.
Right?
So we can have a combination.
But if you think there are many variables here, x1, x2, x3,
maybe until x10, for example, right?
And then what kind of combinations?
x1, x2 could be a combination.
x1 times x2.
OK.
x1 times x3.
x1 times x4.
x1 times x10.
OK.
This kind of combination, right?
We could also have x1 times x2 squared.
So we could have a combination, right?
So then we also, we also bring some challenges.
OK.
You have many variables.
And when you think about all the combinatorials of these variables,
all the combinations, OK?
And then this polynomial model could have a huge number of terms.
So the terms actually is not useful.
And then in the linear regression model,
in this polynomial model modeling,
and a large portion of the, our efforts actually
will be put on the selection of the terms in the polynomial model.
OK.
And again, this program is even more challenging, right?
Because of the, you know, the rational model.
OK.
And so because of these limitations of the polynomial model
and the rational model, and for the hard terminal data, right?
We have many independent variables.
So, so in recent year that we, I think, if the model is really
for the prediction, not for explanation, not for explain,
right?
Just for prediction.
So, you know, we can use the, you know, the neural networks,
the neural networks.
OK.
And because in the neural networks, actually, the operation normally,
at the first layer normally is a linear combination of the input,
linear combination.
And then we perform nonlinear operation on this linear operation,
on these linear combinations.
OK.
Yeah.
So, so this is an issue.
Like I think about the combinations of the different x, y, x,
two, this problem is no longer a problem because we don't
consider this.
At each neuron, we just consider the linear combination of the output
from previous layers in the neural network.
OK.
If you know that a bit, OK.
So, but we, so in this course, we don't go into deep about the
linear regression.
OK.
But if you have interest, certainly you can always find the material
on the internet, right, on the nonlinear regression.
OK.
So, in this course, when we touch, in the machine learning,
we call the, normally, I think about the classification.
So, by the way, we touch a bit about the regression, but we only,
actually, you know, limit our study on the linear regression.
OK.
So, we don't study the nonlinear regression.
So, that's all for the regression.
So, that's actually what we will think about the, let's find another topic.
And that is feature selection.
OK.
So, let's look at the, OK.
So, next, we look at the feature selection for the minority reduction
and classifications.
OK.
And that, actually, is also a very important topic in pen classification
in machine learning.
OK.
And quite often, right, quite often, actually, when you are given a problem,
actually, of course, now, actually, if you are doing machine learning
problem, quite often, you look at some of the data set,
probably available data set, right.
And then you just use this data set to practice, you know, to learn, right.
But in practice, actually, normally, you don't have a data set, right.
When you are given problem, we need to collect our own data.
OK.
So, we start from scratch, right.
First step is to collect the data.
OK.
When you collect the data, actually, of course, we know our target.
And, but, actually, we have no idea.
So, actually, what information, actually, what variables, actually,
or what features are needed, OK, you know, to predict, you know,
to classify the samples.
OK.
So, at the beginning, of course, if we have the prior knowledge, right,
we can get the prior knowledge.
We can get the data from the demy as per our, whoever, right.
And we know to perform classification for this problem.
And we need to acquire what kind of data.
OK.
That's the best, right.
But, quite often, actually, we don't have this information.
OK.
So, during the data acquisition stage, or data collection stage,
we try our best to collect as much as possible.
OK.
As many features as possible.
But, actually, if we, you know, include too many features in the model,
and we could have some issues, OK.
In previous studies, we always assume all the features are used, right.
We have not talked about touch-dissue issue.
But this is a practical issue.
OK.
And given a problem, you collect the data.
But what data are relevant, what data should be collected?
And at the beginning, maybe you have no idea.
But then you try your best to collect as much as possible.
OK.
And then, actually, we can have too many features, too many attributes.
And then the data will become hard dimensional.
Hard dimensional.
And, actually, we could have some issues, actually,
related to this hard dimensional data.
OK.
And this is the problem is called, so the data is a hard dimensional.
And then, actually, we can have the so-called curse of the minority.
OK.
So the difficulty related to hard dimensional data is referred to,
actually, the curse of the minority.
OK.
So very hard dimensional kind of data can bring some challenges
for the machine learning.
OK.
And so this is a hard curse of the minority has two, actually, paths.
First, actually, the data is sparse.
The data sparse.
OK.
So sparsity is one issue.
Another is the distance and concentration.
OK.
So what is sparsity?
Sparsity of the data.
Actually, you can imagine, right?
So, we have about 100 or 200 students, right?
If all the students standing in one line,
if all of you come to the front, stand in one line,
in one dimension, then actually, you can imagine, right?
So they're all very crowded, right?
That means that the data densely actually is disputed.
OK.
So now, actually, you all see there's a 2D space, right?
At least 2D, right?
And then you have space between the students.
OK.
Not very crowded.
You can imagine if the space actually is 3D, some of the students
can see there, not 3D, right?
So the data, actually, everyone has one.
The distance between all of you, a student, will be big.
OK.
And if the data is harder, then, you know.
Then, actually, the distribution of the samples will be very sparse.
Very sparse.
OK.
And actually, previously, when we think about the tree,
we were designed or pen classified.
And normally, we assume that the samples in one class
are densely disputed.
The distribution is very compact, right?
Compact.
So in our future linear adjustment analysis,
we try to minimize, right, within class scatter.
Why we try to minimize within class scatter?
So this is because we hope that the data within the similar class
could be densely located in one region of the space.
So these are not assumptions, right?
Assumptions.
OK.
So densely disputed in one region or part of this space.
But here, because of hard deminial space, right,
hard deminality of the data, actually, the distribution of the data
is very sparse.
Very sparse.
OK.
The example that you can imagine, right?
Also, you stand in one line.
It's very dense, right?
But in two states, you have space.
You can imagine how about 3D, 10D, 100 dimensions.
That could be very sparse.
OK.
Then, actually, we have some issues, right?
And then another tree is called a distance concentration.
What does it mean of distance concentration?
So the meaning here is that, actually,
in the very hard deminial space, all the power distance,
power, I mean, the distance between the two samples, right?
The power distance may convert to the same values.
Actually, we hope a tree, just imagine a tree,
we hope, of course, we hope that the distance within the same class
should be similar, right?
So we try to minimize the scatter.
Meanwhile, we also try to maximize the between class difference,
the between class difference, right?
That means that the distance between the sample
in different classes, the difference, the distance could be big.
But now, even in the very hard deminial space, right?
The power distance, even the distance between two,
the sample in different classes,
and also the sample in the winning class,
they tend to have the same or similar values.
So this is the distance concentration.
Okay, then the data is very hard to separate, right?
Because the distance between, actually, the sample
within the same class or between different classes are all similar.
Then how to classify them, how to separate them?
Okay, so the crush on the mananulity,
the two aspects of this crush on the mananulity,
the distance concentration, and also the data capacity
all bring challenges to the pen classification,
not task or to the bring difficulties
or challenges to the classifier design.
Okay, and how to address this problem?
And of course, actually, one of the obvious solution
is to reduce the deminulity of the data, right?
And actually, whether or not that really, indeed,
then we can reduce it, and indeed, actually, we can reduce it.
And this is because, actually, during the data collection stage, right?
Maybe, actually, we have collected some features
which are actually irrelevant to the problem.
For example, if you want to classify a male or female student,
for example, okay, and with the color of the hair,
and maybe the color of the hair, at the beginning,
you collect all the information about a person, right?
You take pictures of the person, then you record the color of the hair,
you record the body weight, you record the height,
and you have every item of the,
and many items of the information, right?
You record the, but many of these features or attributes
are usually irrelevant to the classifier problem.
So this is one type of features.
Okay, certainly, now, we can remove this,
we can remove the top of features,
and then we can reduce the deminality of the data.
Okay, then another type of feature we can also remove.
So that is the redundant features, redundant.
Redundant features, that means, actually,
if one feature is included in the addition of one extra feature,
redundant feature, we're not bringing extra information,
because they are redundant.
Okay, so for this redundant feature, we can also remove.
Okay, so by removing, actually, the irrelevant,
all insignificant features,
and also by removing the removal of the redundant features,
and then we can reduce, actually, the deminality of the data.
And then, actually, these issues, like spasticity
and the traditional concentration,
actually, this problem can be elevated.
Okay, so that is just our topic, right?
Feature selection for deminality reduction and classification.
Okay, so, yeah, and of course,
besides these issues,
if we include too many features in the model,
we also have these computational issues, right?
Actually, the more features we have in the model,
the computational complexity is higher.
Okay, so computational complexity is also a consideration.
Okay.
So later we will see, actually, when we, you know, fit a model,
quite often, actually, we look at the ratio of the number of samples
to the number of features,
or to the number of parameters in the model.
Normally, for this ratio, the higher, the better.
Right?
So, in other words, if you have too many attributes,
and then you have to collect a large number of samples,
but in many scenarios, the collection of large numbers of samples
is very costly, or sometimes, actually, it is impossible.
Okay.
Because, actually, the data available could be very limited, right?
And so you cannot collect a large number of samples.
Okay.
So later we will talk about this issue further.
And another tree is the generalization capacity.
And actually, this generalization capacity,
the model, right, relates to the ratio,
the generalization of the ratio of the number of samples
to the number of features.
Okay.
If we reduce the number of features,
and for a fixed number of samples,
and if we reduce the number of features,
then we can improve this ratio.
And then we can improve the generalization capability of the model.
Because for such a model, it is less likely to overfit the training data.
And then we have a higher chance to generalize better, right,
for the attesting data.
Okay.
So these are the considerations, right,
why we need, actually, to perform the deminotent reduction
from the computational point of view
from the generalization point of view.
Okay.
We have reasons to do the deminotent reduction.
So this is the major task of the feature selection.
Okay.
So given actually a number of features,
normally the number, normally the larger number, now, okay.
And how can we select the most important one?
Of the features.
We could assume so many features, right,
so many, actually, variables, attributes.
Okay.
All of them are useful.
Not all of them are important.
Okay.
So here, actually, how do we kind of select the important ones?
And at the same time, actually, we should actually
retain as much as possible of the cloud discriminatory information,
discriminatory information.
Okay.
Actually, a feature should be discriminative or discriminatory.
And just now I use one example, like a hair color, right?
The hair color, then all of them, most of us,
male or female, can all have no black color, right?
For this feature, and this feature does not provide
a discriminative information.
Okay.
Because, actually, you all have this value, right?
The same value for male or female.
We cannot use this value to discriminate,
to separate a male from a female student.
Okay.
But when we do the feature selection, when we, you know,
remove the redundant features and then remove the
insignificant features, we remove them.
Okay.
We should keep.
Why we remove them?
Because they are not discriminatory or they are redundant, right?
So when we remove them, we should keep or retain as much as
possible the discriminatory information.
Okay.
So this basically tells us the target of feature selection,
right?
You reduce the number of features, but you also need to keep
as much as possible the discriminatory information and
allowing all of the original features.
Okay.
The selection feature should not actually lose, okay,
should not lose as much of the discriminatory information.
Okay.
That means we need to remove the insignificant or
irrelevant features and then we should keep also the redundant
features, right?
And then keep the non-redundant and also the
significant features.
Of course, how to evaluate significance or the usefulness
of a feature, we'll talk about this later.
Okay.
So here we first now have a base idea about the target or the
goal of the feature selection for the minority reduction.
Okay.
Indeed, we use small numbers, right?
We can reduce the minority data.
Then we can solve the issues, right?
And then we can also reduce the number of features.
Okay.
So we have two aspects of the class of the minority.
But how to select?
Kind of arbitrary, right?
Kind of randomly select a small number, right?
Actually, we should actually carefully select a small number
of features so that the discriminatory information is kept
or retained as much as possible.
Okay.
So that's actually another concept here we need to understand.
It is a feature selection and a feature illustration.
And actually, the feature illustration and feature illustration
are two different methods for minority reduction.
And actually, the feature illustration is actually
about selecting a subset of the original features,
a subset of the original features.
So this is called a feature selection.
Okay.
And then what is feature illustration?
Actually, feature illustration is to create new features.
And actually, we try to actually compress the information
underlying the original full features, right,
into a small set of new features.
This is called a feature illustration.
Okay.
So we create new features.
In the feature selection, we select a subset of the original features.
In the feature illustration, we create new features.
Okay.
And each of these new features is a function
of all of the original features.
Okay.
So maybe I use this diagram to illustrate this.
So this is, you know, usually we have five features,
X, Y, S2, S3, S4, S5.
Okay.
So feature selection tries to select a subset.
So subset is just an X, Y, S2, S5.
Okay.
So these features, these features are important features,
not redundant, and also, you know, discriminative features.
Okay.
So we have this feature selection.
This is called feature selection, a subset of the original features.
All right.
So in this feature subset, all the original manuals of the features are also,
the manuals are retained.
Okay.
So we retain the original features.
Of course, we retain the manuals of the original features.
So this is very important.
Actually, if you want to build a model that is, is planable, is planable.
Okay.
And feature extraction, just mentioned, create new features.
Again, originally we have these five features, right?
In the feature extraction, actually, we create new features, like V1, V2.
And each of these features is a function of the original features.
Okay.
You know, for V1, we have function F1.
For V2, this new feature, V2, we have a function F2.
Okay.
And this F1, F2 could be linear or nonlinear functions.
Could be linear, or could be nonlinear.
Okay.
And the commonly used principle of Kapun-Ny analysis, probably you heard this, right?
Or singular value decomposition.
So this technique belongs to the second type of the deminology reduction, feature extraction.
Because actually, in the principle of Kapun-Ny analysis, each of the new features is a linear
combination of all the original features.
F1, F2, actually are two different linear functions.
Two different, of course, the form of the linear function is the same, but just the
coefficient of the functions are nonlinear, are different.
Okay.
So V1, V2, actually, now, actually, the meaningless.
For example, actually, X1 is a gender, X2 is a nationality, S3 is your degree.
What is the meaning of the variable?
Your gender times 0.2, plus your nationality times 0.4, and plus your degree, plus, you
know, the new variable, right, new feature.
You don't have a meaning.
And then, of course, a model based on V1, V2 is hard to explain.
Hard to explain.
Okay.
So you want to build, actually, you know, explain them all model, and we prefer to use the super
feature selection.
Of course, actually, maybe feature extraction could be more efficient.
Could be more efficient.
Because, actually, it will use all of the information, right, X1, X1, X2, and X5.
So the limitation of this feature extraction is that the meanings of the original features
are lost.
Okay.
But the feature extraction, selection, can keep the meanings of the original features.
So in this course, actually, we focus on the feature selection.
And because in other courses, normally, when we talk about the knowledge reduction, and
what they mean, actually, is the feature extraction, like a principle of carbon analysis.
In other courses, right, you probably learn PCA, but that's the feature extraction.
So in this course, actually, we focus on the feature selection.
Okay.
So, naturally, we have a 10-minute break.
After a break, we continue to talk about the evaluation of the features.
So now, we mentioned, insignificant or redundant, right.
So how to evaluate this?
Okay.
So next, actually, we will talk about this.
So, that's actually we look at the so-called picking phenomenon.
So, this is also the reason why we want to do the feature oscillation, okay, or feature
oscillation.
So, this is the reason why we want to do the deminology reduction.
So, here we assume we have a data set with n samples.
And so, also we have a number of features, L. Okay.
Of course, based on the data we can train a classifier.
I think we can look at the performance of the classifier on the training or testing data.
Right?
Okay.
So, of course, we assume this is a linear, right?
So, this is a general form of a linear classifier, right?
Either it's a nonlinear, it's a linear suborbital machine or linear, feature linear disk analysis.
You know, the classifier have the same form, right?
Just a different method.
We have different ways to determine the value of W0 and W.
So, for this linear classifier, actually, the parameter number in this model is just
actually L plus 1.
Because we have one additional term, that is the bias term, right?
Bias term.
Okay, W is 0.
And for this W transpose, here W, here, the number of features, you know, the deminology
of this W is just the same as X, right?
So, if the number of features is L, then the number of features and parameters actually,
or unknown parameters in the model, actually is M plus 1.
Okay.
So, okay.
So, there's a tree we look at this curve.
Look at this curve.
So, the horizontal axis shows the number of features.
Okay.
And the vertical axis through the probability of an area.
You can just think, oh, this is an area on the testing data.
You can just imagine, probability of an area is just an area on the testing data.
Okay.
And actually, you can see, at the beginning, actually, the area is big, right?
So, even a small number of features is used.
For example, just one feature is used.
Okay.
And then we can have a big area.
Big area, right?
If we increase the number of features, right, from 1 to L1 for the first case, if the number
of samples equals M1.
And so, when the number of features L1, here, actually, we have this area.
Okay.
And this area is the minimum.
After this L1 critical value, and if we continue to increase the value of L, actually, then
the probability of area increase.
Increase.
Okay.
And so, the best performance achieved at this L1, actually, L1.
So, these are critical values.
Okay.
And so, these are three phenomena.
It's called picking phenomena.
Now, we have a picking performance.
We have a picking performance, right?
And when the number of features actually used in the model, they equal to a critical value
L1.
Okay.
So, from this point of, this is a non-peckling phenomenon, and we can see the reason, right,
the motivation for the demagnitude reduction or feature selection here.
Okay.
Because if we use all the features, and the generalization capability may be very bad.
And we should select, actually, the number of features.
Okay.
And so, that, actually, the best performance could be achieved.
Of course, this best performance is not for training data.
Not for training.
And we will not observe this non-peckling phenomenon on the training data.
Normally, for the training data, the more features we use, the better the performance.
Okay.
So, this is the area, the area for the generalization, generalization area.
That means the area under unseen testing data.
Okay.
And so, actually, then, in practice, how to determine this L?
How we can find out, you know, this critical value, so that the performance is the best
for the future data, for the testing data.
And actually, now, we can select this critical value L based on the performance on the validation
data.
So, this number of critical values, right, L1, this L, actually, normally, you know, it's
determined, it's considered as a hyper parameter.
And hyper parameter, that means that we need to determine the value for this hyper parameter
and using the validation data.
Okay.
So, normally, you know, we, in practice, we use one feature to train a classifier, for
example.
We have two features to train a classifier.
You have three features to train a classifier.
That is five or, you know, we increase the number of features.
For each number of features, actually, we use and we train a parameter classifier.
And then we check the performance on the validation data.
Okay.
And then, based on the performance on the validation data, and probably we can find, actually,
this critical value, which will produce the best performance for the future unseen testing
data.
I just mentioned on the training data, you won't see such a curve.
You won't see this a peak phenomenon because the, actually, the probability of error actually
decrease more and more non-tonically normally.
The more features you use in the model, the better performance on the training data.
Okay.
So, this is for the validation data, for the testing data.
So, this is the generalization error.
Okay.
Because the ultimate goal for the modeling, right, is to use the model for future data,
not for training data.
For training data, you already have the class label, right, or you already know the class
label.
There is no need to use a model to predict.
What we want is to use a model to predict the label of future data.
So, we are concerned with the probability of error of the future data, the testing data.
Okay.
So, we can determine this.
So, this is a peak phenomenon.
And, actually, from here, actually, we know this diagram shows two scenarios, two curves,
right?
And one curve, actually, that is n equals n1.
The number of samples equals n1.
And the second curve actually shows the scenario, shows actually when n equals to n2.
Actually, n2 is much greater than n1.
So, and from this, actually, we can also see, actually, if a larger number of training data
is used, n2, right?
And then, actually, the critical value, L2, is greater because L2 here is greater than
L1, right?
So, the critical value is greater if the number of training samples is greater than more.
Okay.
So, the performance is better because the probability error is better, right?
It's lower than the first scenario, where n1 is less than n2.
Okay.
So, this diagram is, first, actually, show the thing, right?
The peak phenomenon.
That means, actually, we should select a number of features so that we can achieve the best
performance on the future data, testing data.
Okay.
We don't use all of them.
We should perform feature selection.
And this number, you know, finally, the number of features including the model, the best,
actually, you know, it should be equal to this, actually, critical value, critical value.
Okay.
This is the first thing from this diagram, right?
Then the second thing is that, actually, we should use, actually, a larger number of training
samples.
If we use a larger number of training samples, then the critical value, L2, is larger.
And then also, actually, a better performance could be achieved.
Okay.
So, this is known in the machine learning program.
We always try to keep the terminology of the data low, try to collect, actually, as many
samples as possible.
Okay.
We increase n2.
And then we also reduce the terminology.
So, from these two, actually, you know, aspects, and we improve, actually, the generalization
capability of the model.
That means that we want to achieve the small, actually, probability of error for the future
data, for the testing data.
Okay.
So, this is, actually, you know, whatever we can get, actually, from this, actually, from
this, you know, figure, right, the picking phenomenon.
And also, these are, you know, figures certainly give us, Godland, right, on the future selection,
and also the training sample collection.
We should try our best to collect as many as possible, the samples, right.
For features, of course, at the beginning, we can collect.
If you don't know what features are useful, we should collect as many features as possible.
But then we need to go through the so-called terminology reduction.
And in particular, here, the future selection process.
Okay.
And so that, actually, the number of features finally used in the model, actually, would
be the, actually, the critical value.
And so that the probability of error for the testing data is the minimum.
Okay.
So, picking phenomenon.
You need to know these picking phenomenon.
And also, from the picking phenomenon, actually, the Godland lines on the data collection,
right.
Okay.
And, okay.
So, this is just the thing I just talked about, actually, N2 greater than N1, actually,
L2, critical value, L2, larger than N1, L1, and then, actually, even smaller areas are
achieved.
Okay.
So, in practice, of course, sometimes, actually, the collection of a large number of samples,
actually, is impossible.
Right.
All of them, sometimes, are very expensive.
Okay.
And then what we can get is only a small number of training data.
In such a scenario, certainly, only a small number of features should be used.
Small number, right.
Small number.
If you use a large number of, a small number of features, if you use a large number of features,
and then the probability of error on the testing data could, is not the minimum.
Okay.
So, we should use a small number of samples.
But if a larger number of training data is obtained, is available, then we should use
more features.
Okay.
But also, of course, actually, we still need to do the terminology reduction, right.
But actually, we can use more features.
And then, with more features, we can even achieve even a better performance.
Okay.
So, in practice, the number of features normally determine, actually, based on the performance
on the validation data.
So, that's the reason, in practice, actually, the data is normally divided into three parts,
right.
Training data, validation data, and then the testing data.
Okay.
So, the training data is used to estimate the parameters of the model.
Determine the, no, W, W0, right.
So, this is the use of the training data.
And how many features to include, and then we should actually, and this is a hyperparameter.
We should determine the value of hyperparameter using the validation data.
The hyperparameter are those kind of parameters.
They're not directly estimated from the training data.
Okay.
I think in the regression, for example, in the regression problem, we have lambda, right,
which is a weightage on the term for the penalization of the L1 norm or L2 norm, right, of the parameter
vector.
So, this lambda is also hyperparameter.
We need to determine the value of this lambda based on the performance on the validation
data.
Okay.
So, this kind of parameter are called hyperparameter.
So, in other more complex models, and sometimes we have more than one hyperparameter.
And then, we need to use actually validation training data to determine all of these hyperparameters.
Okay.
So, next, actually, we look at the individual feature evaluation.
So, we know that our target of feature selection is to actually select the important ones, right,
important ones.
And, say, important ones, that means that we need to remove the unimportant ones, right,
the insignificant ones, and also the redundant features.
Okay.
And, actually, normally, the feature selection or the feature evaluation is based on a set.
It's a set-based feature selection.
Because, actually, the feature set is finally used in the model.
Okay.
So, this is something like a scenario.
If you want to select some students from this class, right, to attend a competition, this
competition could, the question could actually, you know, from different fields, could from
electrical, electronic engineering, from like physical, from math, from chemistry, right.
So, you want to select a team, right, to represent the whole class, to attend this competition.
And, certainly, we should actually select the student with actually personal skills,
compensate, compensate, right, complementary.
We cannot select students just actually based on each individual one.
You are very good, right, your GPA is 4.9, or you're very good at the electrical and electronic
engineering.
And, that's like you.
So, students, you know, have the same skill with you, right.
Then, if you attend a competition, if the question about the science, about math, about
physics, right, often you cannot answer, right.
So, we should select the team, right, whose skills are complementary.
Okay.
We should not select the candidate based on each, just individually.
Actually, this concept actually is also applicable to the future selection.
Because, ultimately, the features are used as a team in the final model, right, together.
Okay.
But, actually, the future evaluation can still be first done by, you know, individually.
And, actually, the later, when we talk about the future subset selection, and actually,
normally, the future subset selection is a process, then we need to generate a larger
number of, you know, candidate feature subset.
And, then, we evaluate each of the future subset.
And, then, we identify the best performing one.
Okay.
So, if we have a large number of features of code, actually, we can have a huge number
of combinations of the features, right, of the features.
And, then, actually, this will result in very high, you know, computational complexities.
It is very computational demanding.
Okay.
So, in order to actually address this issue, at least, actually, if we use, actually, the
individual feature evaluation, which can remove some of the features, what features?
The insignificant or irrelevant features.
Okay.
So, these are the three individual feature evaluations.
Often, they are used as the first step in the future subset selection.
Okay.
So, it's a known, actually, it's used as the first step.
At least, we can remove, actually, the bad features or irrelevant features, insignificant
features.
And, then, individual feature evaluation cannot identify the redundant features, but it can
identify, actually, the insignificant or irrelevant or useless features or bad features.
Okay.
So, this could be used as the first step in a future subset selection.
In the future selection.
Okay.
So, these are the individual feature evaluations.
So, evaluate the goodness of each feature individually, separately.
Don't consider the combination of the features.
So, this is called individual feature evaluation and selection.
Okay.
So, these will be used as the first step.
And, so, next, actually, we will talk about how to evaluate the usefulness or the relevance
of a feature.
Okay.
And, actually, we can evaluate the goodness of a feature based on two, actually, interpretations.
The first interpretation is called separability, based on this, actually, interpretation, and
which, actually, can identify the important ones.
Then, another, actually, is based on a concept, is the relevance of a feature.
The relevance of a feature to predict the class label of a sample.
Relevance.
Okay.
So, we can evaluate the goodness of a feature based on these two different interpretations.
Of course, actually, these different interpretations will have different evaluation metrics.
Okay.
Evaluate metrics.
I mean, we have formula, right?
We have formula to calculate the separability of a feature.
And, also, the relevance of a feature.
And then, based on these, you know, calculated value, right?
And then, we can rank the features.
And then, we can also identify the bad features.
Okay.
So, this is the end of the...
So, next, we look at what is the class separability.
And, actually, we have already used these features.
There is no concept before.
Actually, when we, you know, studied the feature linear dishman analysis, right?
And, actually, the sample is the hard and no-speed.
We want to find a W. And then, we project the sample on this W, right?
And, of the projection, each sample is represented by one single value, right?
Is a...
Okay.
Then, all the samples actually are distributed on this W.
And then, we...
We evaluate the goodness of the W, right?
Based on, actually, two criteria.
One is that the other projection of this W, if the W is good,
then, actually, within class, the scatter is small.
That means that within the same class, the samples are actually are very similar.
So, this is called within class scatter, right?
And then, between class, the difference should be big,
of the projection onto this W.
We use this class separability to evaluate the goodness of the projection W, right?
So, finally, we use...
We try to find the W that maximizes the ratio of the between class scatter to the within class scatter.
Okay.
So, this is not...
The ratio is called separability.
We have used this concept, right?
But, actually, before we use this concept to evaluate the goodness of a W, right?
We use this concept to evaluate each individual feature.
Okay.
And so, this is actually a sample along one...
A distribution of the sample along one feature.
Along one feature, right?
Okay.
So, different samples along this feature have different values.
And if we see all the sample class 1 are located in this part of the axis,
and then the sample in another class is located in another side of the species, right?
And then, actually, we can actually use...
We can look at the, you know, between class difference.
How to evaluate the between class difference?
So, certainly, one way is that we can use the difference between the two mean values, right?
For all the sample in class 1 along this axis, right?
X along this feature, we can have a mean value.
And then, for sample in class 2, we can have a mean value.
Okay.
So, the difference between class scatter, the between class difference can be measured
in this difference of these two mean values, right?
So...
And also, for some...
Within the same class, we hope they are similar.
So, these actually should be the within class scatter, right?
Normally, within class scatter can be evaluated using the standard of the region, the sigma,
or the variance, sigma squared.
Okay.
And then, actually, normally, the separability measure, feature separability measure,
or feature ratio, it defines the ratio of these two, between class scatter to the within class scatter.
Okay.
Then, this is the feature ratio.
So, M1, M2, M1 is the mean value of sample in class 1 along this feature, right?
M2 is the mean value for sample in class 2.
Sigma 1 is the square, is the variance for sample in class 1.
And sigma 2 is sample in class 2 along this feature X.
Okay.
So, you can use this ratio to evaluate the goodness of feature, the larger the better.
The larger the better.
Okay.
So, this is the feature ratio.
But this concept here is between class difference, within class difference, between class scatter,
within class scatter.
Okay.
So, now, actually, between class scatter is evaluated based on the distance between two,
between two, and the mean values, right?
Between two.
Actually, you can also actually develop your own ideas, develop your own metrics for the
evaluation of the between class scatter.
For example, actually, I think if you think about the support weight machine, support weight
machine actually use the distance between the closed samples, right?
Closed samples.
And then, the distance between this sample and this sample, this distance, actually, like
no margin of separation, right?
Actually, this margin of separation can be, actually, it's evaluated based on the distance
between the two closed samples.
So, this is also an evaluation of the between class difference, right?
Between class difference.
So, here, we try to minimize, or maximize the between class difference.
But how to measure the between class difference?
You can have a different metrics, right?
We can use the mean difference.
We can also look at the distance between two closed samples, right?
Then, you can also create your own, your own metrics to evaluate the between class scatter
metrics, between class scatters, right?
Okay.
So, we always have this concept between class scatters should be maximized.
Meanwhile, actually, within class scatter, actually, we should minimize, right?
We hope all the samples within a similar class, actually, are similar.
So, these are within class scatters.
So, these are mean, right?
So, I think what I want to emphasize is that, actually, this concept between class scatter,
within class scatter, okay, I think we should try to maximize between class scatter and
the mean model within class scatter.
We can also try to maximize the reach of the two.
But how to evaluate the between class scatter?
How to evaluate the within class scatter?
We can have different ways.
At least here, we have two ways, right?
Based on the mean difference or based on the distance between the closed samples.
Okay.
So, this is the feature ratio.
And, okay.
So, these are two concepts.
We hope, actually, they can have a larger interclass difference.
Interclass, that means the between class.
Intra class, within class.
Okay.
So, these are the concepts.
So, we can actually talk about interclass or interclass.
Sometimes, they use between class and within class.
Okay.
So, we emphasize these two concepts.
But we can have different implementations of these two concepts.
Okay.
And, so here, the feature ratio, we use the mean, right?
We use the mean.
We use the distance concept, the distance.
Okay.
And, this is actually, you know, distance, it's meaningful only for continuous variables.
Actually, before, you know, we actually in the second part of the, the second week of
this course, we talk about data preparations, you know, cause, right?
And, in part, actually, we talk about the different types of features.
Now, we have the continuous features.
We have discrete features.
For discrete, we have the nominal and then we have the, we have the, you know, the ordinal,
right?
And, in particular, for nominal, right?
The distance has no meaning.
Actually, we have different, we have different value just to represent.
They are different.
But this value, actually, does not really reflect how different they are.
Okay.
So, here, this concept, actually, you know, this metric cannot be used for this kind of
features.
Maybe okay, and it's okay for ordinal data, but certainly not for nominal data.
Because we don't have a mean, right?
Mean value or distance, a distance metric, actually, are meaningless for nominal data.
Okay.
So, we use these features, we show for continuous features, the value continuous.
And then, what, actually, you know, we can use for discrete features, in particular,
for nominal, right?
And, actually, we can use the so-called mutual information.
And, actually, mutual information is based on the interpretation of the relevance.
Relevance, okay.
Relevance, that means, actually, how much information we can have, we can get from this feature
and to predict for the class label.
That is the relevance.
The relevance, okay.
Relevance, actually, of course, the relevance can be measured by different, we can use a
correlation.
Okay.
But we can also use the so-called mutual information.
So, relevance is a big concept.
We can have different, you know, we can develop different metrics and to measure these relevance.
Okay.
But here, we just introduced the mutual information.
So, this is particular for discrete data.
Okay.
So, a good feature should contain significant amount of information to decide the class
label, right?
Continue information.
That means it is relevant.
It is relevant.
Okay.
So, we use this relevance concept for feature evaluation.
And, the mutual information is one of the metrics that we can use to evaluate the relevance.
Correlation is also a kind of measure for the relevance.
Okay.
So, this is the definition of the mutual information.
And so, X is a feature, is a one feature.
And Y is a target variable, the class label.
Okay.
And so, Y, of course, can only take discrete values, right?
For binary classification problem, only two possible values.
In fact, for multiple, Y can only take limited values, right?
Limited number of values, right?
Possible value, limited.
Okay.
And X here is also a discrete variable.
Taking a limit, taking a different, limited number of values, right?
Just a few values.
Okay.
And then, this mutual information, M, I, X, Y, equals to E, X, plus E, Y, minus E, X,
Y.
E here is not the expectation.
Expectation is the mean, right?
Certainly, we just now, we have mentioned, actually, for discrete, in particular, for
the nominal data, the mean is the meaningless.
So, the X here is not the expectation, not the mean.
Existitation is just the mean.
Okay.
So, X here, E here, no.
E here means, actually, the entropy.
Okay.
So, entropy of the X plus entropy of Y minus the joint entropy of X and Y.
So, this is the mutual information.
Okay.
Actually, entropy, we have used this concept before, right?
In the class-finition tree, right?
And we decided which, you know, feature to use for the nest node, okay?
Or for the rule node and for the decision node, right?
We're based on the mutual information.
Okay.
So, this is the, based on the entropy concept, entropy, right?
Entropy.
So, this is the entropy.
Probability times the log of the probability.
Okay.
So, for feature X, it could take a few values, right?
Either feature is a binary feature, like gender.
This feature only has two possible values, male or female.
And if the X is like a transportation mode, you know, if you come to NTU, you can buy
a bus, you can buy a taxi, right?
You can walk to NTU, right?
And, yeah, so, at least you have three ways, right?
Then, actually, the number, we have Ui, U2, U3, U1, U2, U3.
They have three values.
Okay.
So, for each of the three values, or each of the two values, for each of the values, right?
Because discrete, we can look at the probability.
We can count, right?
And the probability, then times the log of this probability.
The summation.
Summary to that means for all the three, right?
When the probability, when the transportation mode equal to, you know, buy a taxi, right?
Then log, this is probability.
And plus the probability of taking a bus, okay?
Then times the probability, log of the probability of taking a bus.
And then plus the probability of walking to NTU times the log of the probability of walking to NTU.
Okay.
And because the probability, you know, is less than one, right?
Less than one.
Then the log will be negative.
And then, so, finally, we put a negative value here.
Then this entropy measure, actually, is a positive number.
Positive.
Okay.
So this is an entropy, X, similar for Y, right?
Y is a class label, right?
So for binary class, class value problem, only two possible values.
And then you can have a multiple class problem, right?
And then, you know, this actually, the Y can take multiple values.
But it's limited number of values.
So we can use this entropy, right?
And this formula to carry the entropy for X, Y.
And then we can take the entropy for X, Y.
So here, this may, you know, is a combination.
Combination.
So we need to take more of the computations.
Okay.
So, because we have two variables, X equal to mu J, Y equals to C, I, different values.
So combination.
This is a John's entropy.
Okay.
So we have the entropy X plus entropy Y minus the John entropy X and Y.
And we can get the mutual information between X and Y.
Okay.
So this will be used in evaluation for the goodness of the feature.
So this is for discrete.
For discrete.
Okay.
So here, I just give one example for each type of feature.
For continuous feature, we can use a feature as a ratio, right?
For discrete features, we can use the mutual information.
But actually, you know, we have the bigger concept, right?
The relevance of the class separability.
We have this big concept.
And then, actually, we have some other metrics, right?
For the evaluation of continuous features, for the evaluation of discrete features.
But here, we just give one example for each type of the feature.
Okay.
Anyway, we have means, right?
To evaluate the goodness of the feature.
No matter what feature, kind of feature they are.
Continuous, then we will continue the evaluation criteria.
Discrete, then we will do discrete evaluation criteria.
Okay.
We have ways to evaluate the goodness of a feature.
So this is the individual feature evaluation.
Okay.
So, next, actually, the feature subset.
In practice, actually, we select feature subset.
Okay.
So, this is the feature subset selection.
The feature subset selection can be defined as this.
Give a full feature set.
Okay.
At the beginning, you have no idea, right?
You collect as many features as possible, right?
And because, actually, you are afraid of missing some important features, right?
So, you collect as many as possible.
Okay.
And so, here, you assume we have a full set, full feature set, X1, X2, Xn.
And our target objective is to select a subset that Z1, Z2, Zn.
And Zn, Z1 is just one of the features, right?
X1, Z2.
Okay.
So, this is a subset of the original features.
And we still select such a subset that they produce the best class-future performance.
Of course, the best class-future performance should be on the validation, on the, you know,
the testing data, right?
But, of course, the testing data is unseen, right?
It's a future data.
So, how we know these are the best performance on the validation, on the testing data.
So, basically, at least, actually, in the training selection stage, we can look at the performance
on the, actually, on the validation data.
Okay.
So, they produce the best performance.
So, this is the target of future selection.
We select a subset that can produce the best performance.
Okay.
And, okay, so, the peak of phenomenon, right?
Actually, I'll read how about the features, actually, normally, the feature selection
tries to remove, actually, the irrelevant feature, irrelevant or insignificant features.
Maybe they are relevant, but actually, insignificant.
Okay.
So, this is one type of feature that we should remove.
Then, another type of feature is redundant, right?
Redundant features.
Okay.
And so, actually, you know, use the, you know, individual feature evaluation, and we can
remove the redundant, the insignificant features, but we cannot remove the redundant features.
Okay.
In other words, if we, you know, rank the features, and just, actually, select the top rank features,
based on the, you know, the best to the, to the, to the worst, right?
And then, we select top K features, for example, top M features, L features.
And, these features, actually, whether this could produce a good performance, I know.
Okay.
The answer is no.
The reason is that, actually, these top rank features may contain redundancies, strong redundancies.
Redundancies, that means that they have strong correlations, strong correlations.
Okay.
So, so here, actually, this is, this is, this is, is a strong correlation between the top
rank features.
So, this, actually, means that, that is, and, it's as strong as a severe redundancies.
Okay.
You include the feature, but these features basically have the same information, right,
as other features.
So, this feature, you know, discriminative information of this feature is already kept,
captured, okay, by other features.
Okay.
Then, this feature is redundant, redundant.
Now, of course, actually, you know, we shouldn't look at, you know, from this point of view,
we should remove the redundant features.
But from another point of view, actually, redundant, we should keep a bit of redundancy in the,
in the features I've said.
Because redundancy normally improve the robustness, robustness, right.
Normally, you know, in some critical system, we have two set of systems, right.
One set is, is a, is a 40, right.
We can use another set, right.
Redundancy, actually, can improve the robustness.
Okay.
So, you know, they're not absolute, right.
We should remove all the redundancy.
Sometimes, redundancy is kept in the feature.
Actually, we can improve the robustness.
Okay.
So, we should actually look at this issue from two, you know, perspectives.
So, this is the, the reason of called the tree.
We see we try to remove the redundancy, right.
And because of the pinot phenomenon.
Okay.
So, a good feature subset should have a maximum relevance and a minimum redundancy.
So, this is the, you know, a good feature subset.
And then of course, the tree in the feature subset selection, actually, you know, we
should actually use these two, actually, aspects to evaluate the goodness of a feature subset.
Re-relevance, okay.
Should be maximized.
And redundancy should be minimized.
Okay.
So, now that we consider the feature selection algorithm.
Actually, a feature selection algorithm consists of two main components.
Okay.
And one component is called a feature is a set of all of them.
And actually, the set of all of them actually, actually creates a set of all of them.
Okay.
So, we can see that the tree is a set of all of them.
And actually, the set algorithm actually creates the candidate feature subset.
Okay.
We are creating a huge number of, you know, candidate features of set.
And then the second component evaluation criterion is used to evaluate each of these generated
candidate features of set.
Okay.
And then we identify the best performing feature subset.
So, we need to have these two components.
One is to generate candidate features of set.
Okay.
So, this is the function of the set algorithm.
Then the second component is the evaluation criterion.
Okay.
And which is used to identify, right, the best performing features.
And this diagram shows these actually the two components in a feature selection algorithm.
Okay.
So, we have, first of all, we have a full feature set.
Right.
This is a full feature set.
And based on the full feature set, the set algorithm will create a large number of candidate
features of set.
All of these are possible as the, as the possibility as being selected as the final feature set.
Okay.
So, so actually we, we need to generate actually a lot of candidate features of set.
Then the evaluation criterion to evaluate is used to evaluate each of the candidate features
of set.
Okay.
Then based on the evaluation criterion, the value we calculated, right.
And then we can identify the best of the best one.
Okay.
Then we can get the feature subset selected.
So, these are the two components in the set algorithm.
So, necessarily we look at each of the two.
The set algorithm.
So, what's set algorithm we can use?
And then we'll also look at the evaluation criterion for feature subset, not for the
individual feature.
Okay.
So, set algorithm here, the first one is the result of the search.
The result of the search, we will use all possible subset.
Actually, it can see all possible combinations.
Okay.
And for example, initially, you know, the full feature subset, full feature set can see
all n features, right.
X1, X2, X3, n, Xn.
Okay.
Based on these n features, we should create actually all the possible combinations with
different number of features.
For example, for one feature, for, if just for feature subset with one feature, then
of course, we can have X1, we can X2, X3, Xn, until Xn, right.
We can have these n subset.
So, each of these n subset contains one feature.
And then we can create feature subset that contains two features.
And then we can have X1, X2.
We have two features.
These are feature subset.
X1, X3.
So, these are not the feature subset, right.
So, we have two features.
X1, X4.
X1, Xn.
Okay.
Then we can have X2, X3.
X2, X4.
X2, X5.
X2, Xn.
Then we have X3, X4, right.
X3, X5.
We can have all of these combinations.
So, these are only for the feature with three, a subset with two features.
Then we can have a feature subset that has three features, right.
X1, X2, X3.
X1, X2, X4.
So, we can have X1, X5, Xn, X4.
Different combinations, right.
So, actually these are the user research generate all possible combinations.
All possible combinations.
So, these are kind of feature subset.
Actually, this number is huge normally.
In particular, if this n is big, how big could this n?
I can tell you, okay, this n sometimes could be over a few thousand.
Actually, I used to work on the, you know, applying machine learning to the biomedical
data.
One area called bioinformatics.
And so, they use actually the G-machrylary technology to measure the genes per levels.
How many genes?
Forty thousand.
In other words, the number of features is forty thousand.
But the number of samples is just a few hundred.
Because each sample is just one patient, right, over a certain cancer, for example.
So, the cancer in the patient is very limited, right.
And so, the number of samples is a few hundred.
But the number of features could be as high as forty thousand.
You can imagine, right, forty thousand combinations.
What's the number?
Okay.
So, these are the results of the search normally.
I think, you know, it's used only when the number of samples, the number of kinds of
features, right, is small.
For example, you have ten, you have twenty features, right, you want to select features
subset.
Then you probably can think about these results of the search.
And these results of the search method will certainly not miss the optimal features subset.
They will create the features subset that are optimal, right.
Because they create all the possible combinations.
So, these all possible combinations include the optimal features subset.
So, these methods will not miss the optimal features subset.
But the problem is that if the N is large, and the computational complexity is high,
then this method is not practical, okay, for the large N, not practical.
Okay.
In theory, of course, actually, this method is optimal.
But in practice, actually, it's hard to implement for large N. Okay.
Then, in practice, we normally use suboptimal method.
This is the optimal method, is the search.
We use the suboptimal method.
So, the suboptimal method here is sequential.
Sequential, okay.
And we have a sequential forward selection.
And so, this is the bottom up method.
Sequential.
That means, actually, we select the features sequentially.
And this method is a E32 method.
And at the each step, we just select one feature.
For example, actually, in the first step, we select one feature.
In the second select step, we select a second feature based on the first feature.
Okay.
Then, at the select step, we select the third feature based on the two previously selected features.
This kind of, you know, sequential forward selection.
Okay.
And this is actually the bottom up method.
We start from an empty set.
Empty set.
Right.
Then, we re-grew the features subset from zero until a certain number.
Okay.
So, these are sequential forward search.
Because empty set, every step we select one.
Okay.
So, the features are there, groups step by step.
And so, then another method called sequential backward elimination.
This is sequential backward elimination.
That means that this method starts from the full set.
Full set.
Okay.
Then, it sequentially removes the features step by step.
At each step, it removes one feature.
Okay.
Start from the full feature set.
Remove one feature at the first step.
Okay.
Then, we remove the second feature in the second step.
And this is actually continued until the number of features or certain, you know, some criteria
is satisfied.
Okay.
So, basically, this method is a top down method.
From the full set, I then reduce to a small subset.
Okay.
So, in the forward selection, we start from an empty set.
We re-grew the features subset.
From empty set to a larger set.
Okay.
So, here, from the full set to a small set.
So, this is called sequential backward elimination.
Okay.
So, it grows, right?
It shrinks.
The features set shrinks.
Actually, one feature is removed at every step.
Okay.
And, actually, we have a break.
After break, we talk about, actually, you know, the implementations of this sequential
forward search selection and also the sequential backward elimination.
Okay.
And also, we will look at the evaluation criterion for the feature subset.
We have learned how to evaluate the feature, right?
Individually.
So, the feature selection, just now we see such algorithm, a general feature subset,
right?
So, we have criterion to evaluate the feature subset, not feature individually.
Okay.
So, next, we will look at the implementation of the sequential forward search and also the
sequential backward elimination and also the criterion for the feature subset evaluation.
And, of course, the combination of the two to form a feature selection, actually, algorithm.
Okay.
So, next, we have break.
Time is up.
Okay.
Okay, okay.
So let's see.
OK.
So let's relook at the evaluation criteria
for a feature subset.
OK, not for any video feature, right?
Features subset.
And actually the first one, I think, is like
separability measure, right?
Just now when we talked about the individual feature,
we had a separability measure.
And actually we can generalize this, you know,
separability measure to the feature subset.
OK.
And so this is kind of a measure, right?
And also, you know, we have the other measures, OK?
So this measure is called a colloquial performance.
And if you recall, our target for feature extraction
is to select, actually, a feature subset
so that the best performance could be achieved, right?
Of course, this best performance normally means
the best performance on the future data, the testing data,
right?
But actually we can evaluate based on the,
actually, you know, the validation data.
So, OK.
So this is our ultimate goal, right?
So, essentially, we can use this, actually,
as a criterion to evaluate the goodness of the feature set
or subset, right?
So the first type of the subset evaluation criterion
is the colloquial performance.
So normally this is not the performance on the training data,
not on training data, right?
So this is the evaluation criterion.
And so in this approach, actually, we train a classifier.
Because we need to have the colloquial performance, right?
So that means, actually, for each feature subset,
actually, we need to train a corresponding,
actually, you know, the pattern classifier, OK?
Then we look at the performance of the classifier
on the validation data, OK?
So this, actually, you know, is the,
this is actually method.
And, of course, actually, for some classifier,
then the training is easy, right?
But for some classifier, the training is a
computational demanding.
It involves a lot of competitions, OK?
And then, of course, this method, actually,
will have an issue of, you know,
complexity, right?
Computational complexity, OK?
And in particular, and for complex classifiers,
if you want to use, like, a neural network classifier,
OK, then you need to train a neural network
and for each of the features subset.
And for a neural network, for example,
multi-layer perceptual neural network,
we need to train a neural network through many iterations.
I think there are other iterations, right?
So each training of a neural, you know,
the training of a neural network, each neural network
is time consuming and a competition only demanding, OK?
So this is actually the limitation of this method.
And also, actually, this method, you know,
is chosen, is only, match the classifier.
This chosen classifier, the best,
because we use this specific classifier
to evaluate the performance, right?
So the chosen, actually, feature subset
matches this, you know, classifier best.
But if you use this selected feature subset
for other application classifiers,
then the performance may not be the best.
OK, so a different classifier may use a trigger,
you know, have a different, you know,
best performing feature subset, OK?
So this feature subset is selected
is specific to those, to this specific, you know,
dependent classifier.
OK, so this classifier performance
as the evaluation criterion for feature subset, OK?
So others actually,
the separability measure, separability measure.
And separability measure is used in the evaluation
of the individual feature,
but we can extend this to the feature subset, OK?
So how to evaluate the separability of a feature subset?
So here, you know, we can have two, you know, methods.
OK.
So all these, actually, now,
separability measures actually estimate
the overlap between the distributions,
overlap, OK?
And of course, overlap normally is correspond to the distance,
right, between, actually, the center points
of the two clusters, OK?
The two clusters.
In other words, actually, you know,
the center point, actually, is just the main vector, right?
So certainly, actually, this overlap depends on the distance
between the two main vectors.
And also depends on the, maybe, like the scatter
of each of the clusters.
The scatter, right, within class scatter, right?
And so this is the, the separability measure
basically, actually, measure for feature evaluation,
subset evaluation.
And in this separability measure,
we don't actually use the class feature performance.
In other words, we don't need to train a classifier
for each feature subset, OK?
So compared with the previous method, right?
Actually, this is a computational efficient, right?
Because we don't need to train a model
for each feature subset, OK?
So this feature subset is also independent
of the classifier, right?
You select this feature subset, then you can,
maybe, apply this, you can use a different,
you know, classifier, OK?
OK.
So let's, what a metric we can use
to measure this separability measure.
So the first, actually, one is called
a Mahalanobi distance-based separability measure.
So we will have two types of a separability measure.
The first type is a Mahalanobi distance, OK?
Between the two, you know, mean vectors.
So assume, you know, this is the space
span by the two features, by two features.
Assume there are two features.
There are more, right?
The concept is the same.
For illustration, it's two features, OK?
So for each of the classes,
we can have the mean vector, which is the center point, right?
We can have the mean vector.
And the overlap of these mean vectors
can be evaluated based on the distance
between the two mean vectors, the two mean vectors, right?
The centroid of the two, the two centroid
of the two classes, the distance, OK?
And here, what distance we should use?
And actually, we should use the so-called Mahalanobi distance
instead of the commonly used, including distance, OK?
And this is because the Mahalanobi distance
takes into account the correlation
into the consideration, OK?
So here, we assume we have M1 for class 1, right?
M2 for class 2.
These are the mean vectors, OK?
So given, you know, as the training sample, right,
we can just look at the mean vector along this two dimension,
right, along the dimension determined by the subset, OK?
We can have these two mean vectors.
And then we can calculate the Mahalanobi distance
between the two vectors.
So this is the definition of the Mahalanobi distance.
Actually, M1, M2, try to suppose C inverse M1, M2.
C here is a correlation matrix.
Correlation matrix, OK?
If you don't have the correlation matrix,
that means that if we don't consider correlation,
then this C is just the identity matrix, right?
Then this is just the including distance.
But here, because actually, this is an inclusion of this tree
in the worst of the correlation matrix,
then the correlation or the redundancy of the features
is considered in this evaluation.
Actually, previously, we talked about the goal
of feature subset selection, right?
To remove the redundant features and also to remove
actually the irrelevant features.
Irrational features can be removed through the individual feature
evaluation selection.
But redundant features can be removed through this tree,
Mahalanobi distance-based separability matrix,
because this matrix takes into account
the correlation between the features.
Correlation means the redundancy.
OK.
So why we need to take this correlation into account?
Actually, for example, there are two features.
There are two features in the extreme case,
two features identical, X1.
Another feature is exactly the X1, same information.
And actually, if we use actually, you're including distance, right?
Actually, the distance based on the two features
is larger than the distance based on one feature,
although the two features are exactly the same.
But if we use the monolithic distance, right,
and then the features are set, right?
Because there are no, this is the inclusion of the,
in words of the chronometrics.
And then there's no problem with the address.
OK.
So this is the one measure for the separability.
Using the Mahalanobi distance between the two main vectors.
Of course, this is only for the two class,
class-future problem, right?
If you have a multiple class, class-future problem,
then we can evaluate the goodies of a feature subset.
And based on the pair-wise, actually, you know,
separability measures.
For example, three classes.
Then we, from class one, class two,
we can have a, you know, a separability measure.
Class one, class three, we can have.
Then class two, class three, we can have.
So it's a combination of pair-wise,
actually, you know, separability measures.
Then we get a sum of them.
So this is for the multiple class, class-future problem.
OK.
So this is, you know, the Mahalanobi distance
between separability measures.
And then the next actually is the scatter
Scatter.
Actually scatter measures.
We are familiar with this, right?
When we started the Fisher-Linian Dispens Analysis,
we have the scatter matrix.
Within class scatter matrix, between class scatter matrix.
So here we have two matrices, right?
So we have SB, SW, between class, B, between class,
and SW within class.
Class one, we can have within class scatter matrix.
Class two, we can have within class scatter matrix, right?
Then we can, you know, S one plus S two, right?
We can have this scatter matrix, SW,
within class scatter matrix.
So based on this, SB and SW,
and we can derive actually a separability measure.
So a separability measure must be a scalar.
Must be a single, one scalar, right?
So here's the input here.
It's a matrix.
So from home, we can, based on the matrix,
to obtain one actually, you know, a scalar value, right?
To denote the separabilities.
OK.
And actually here we can have two.
Mine is based on the trees.
So the SB, the between class, right?
SW, within class, right?
So within class normally smaller, better, right?
So even in scalar case, so this should be in a denominator, right?
But now it's a multi-dimension.
So not put in the denominator.
So we use inverse.
You need to understand the inverse.
Inverse something like one divided by something, right?
Scalar is one divided by something.
If a matrix, a harder measure is inverse of the matrix.
OK.
So these are going to something like, you know,
the between class divided by the within class, right?
So we use the trees of these matrices.
SW inverse times SB, you get a matrix.
And then the trees of this matrix.
So what is the trees of matrices?
The summation of all the elements on the main diagonal.
Main diagonal, matrix, main diagonal,
all the elements, summation.
So this is called a tree of a matrix.
So we can use these trees, right?
So from these trees we can get a scalar, right?
Because all the diagonal elements, summation.
This is a scalar.
So from the matrix we get a scalar.
Of course, they're not the only way, right?
You can also think about other ways.
Maybe they're not the best way, right?
Maybe we can think other ways, OK?
At least I can think about, you know,
if we, for SW inverse SB, right,
if I perform like a singular value decomposition,
I get singular values, summation of the singular values,
maybe it's a better evaluation, better than this.
OK.
Then just the trees.
So, but I think this is just one of the measures, right?
It's not imperfect, imperfect.
But you can think about other ways,
but I can be in a better solution.
You can think about, OK.
So this is one measure.
Another tree we based on the reach of the two trees, OK?
The trees of the SB, the trees of the SB,
with W, within class, right?
Within class, we put a denominator, right?
SW is the numerator.
Because we hold SW as big as possible, the trees.
So we can use this reach of the trees of the two metrics
and as a separability measure, OK?
So here these are separability measures.
So from here we can see we don't actually include
a pen and classifier in the loop, right?
In the evaluation of the goodness of a feature subset.
It's independent of the pen and classifiers, OK?
So normally the computational complexity
of this separability-based measure
is lower than the classification performance-based measure.
OK.
So we have studied the set algorithm
and we have studied the evaluation criterion
for feature subset evaluation.
So next we need to combine the two, right?
Combine the two to actually produce a feature
subset selection algorithm.
OK.
So these are no feature subset selection algorithm.
And so based on the which criterion, which type of criterion
we use, actually these are feature subset selection
algorithm actually are divided into two or three categories.
The first category is called the filter method.
In the filter method, we use the separability measure.
Different separability measures.
Here I just give you three examples, right?
Monomy distance, I don't know the
scatter-metrics-based value-based matrix, right?
So we just give these three, right?
And so these belong to the so-called filter method.
We don't train classifiers.
Filter.
OK.
And then the method based on the classification performance
actually is the so-called wrapper method.
It's a wrap around actually the classifier.
So it's called wrapper method.
OK.
And then the last method actually is called embedded method.
Embedded method, that means actually we have the so-called
building mechanism to penalize the number of features
in the model.
For example, actually the last so-right, last so regression.
So we penalize actually the nonzero coefficient.
OK.
We shrink the coefficient of features towards zero.
But of course, not all the features in the coefficient
will shrink to zero, right?
If all of them shrink to zero, then actually
the prediction area will be big.
Actually, the loss function, we have two parts, right?
One is the squared area.
Another is the squared.
Another is the L1 norm of the parameter vector.
We see the absolute value of the parameter, right?
So only the important, the unimportant features
actually will shrink the coefficient to zero.
OK.
So it has a built-in mechanism to penalize actually
the number of features in the model.
So it also plays a rule of a feature selector.
So it trains the model, parameter also selects
actually the variables, the features.
OK.
So that is the embedded method.
Embedded.
OK.
So we're going to classify in the loop.
And first method, then we'll include a classifier.
OK.
So embedded method has a built-in mechanism actually
to penalize the number of features in the model.
OK.
So that's actually, we look at, first,
we look at the filter method.
OK.
And so I think the diagram is similar.
Just the separability measure is used for the feature subset
evaluation.
It might not be decent measure, or the scatter metric
is separability measures.
It can be used to evaluate actually the good
and the bad features of set.
OK.
And actually, this method, as we know, we normally don't
actually use the resultive search, the optimal method.
And because actually it is a computational,
very intensive, right?
Continually very intensive.
So normally we use the suboptimal method,
like sequential forward search or sequential backward
elimination.
OK.
And in the forward selection, so on the backward elimination,
actually it's a iterative procedure.
And we remove the features, or we select the features,
step by step.
OK.
So every step, we just select one feature.
So, and let, in theory, this is the procedure repeated.
Every step, we add one feature.
Every step, we remove one feature.
So this is actually a selection is a stop, or elimination
is stopped until the stopping criterion is satisfied.
The stopping criterion could be the preset number of features.
If you know, OK, I want to select 50 features, right?
OK.
Then you just actually select 50 features.
And so then the number reach to 50, right?
Then you stop.
OK.
Or actually, based on other, no, like, separate measure
no longer improves.
Actually, you cannot see no longer improves,
but the improvement is trivial.
It's trivial.
OK.
And so in practice, normally the separate measure
actually increase, increase with more features.
But just after critical value, the increase is trivial.
OK.
And actually, many actually, you know,
no problem have similar phenomenon.
OK.
The more features we have, the better the performance.
The more iterations we perform the training, right?
And then the better the performance.
So when to this, even in the actual annual,
which we will study next week, right?
And also, in the classroom, and also the more features
we use, and then the better the performance on the training
data.
But just in a scenario, when you add one extra actual cluster,
or you include one extra feature, or you train the model
one extra iteration, and then the improvement is trivial.
So normally, in such a scenario, we use the so-called,
you know, the air ball method.
OK.
Air ball, right?
At the beginning of the performance,
you look at this area, right?
The performance actually, you know, the area drop very fast,
right?
After this point, slow.
This point, right?
Correspond, this is the best point, which will stop here.
So this is called the air ball method.
OK.
Very fast, then slow.
So this part, actually, we show based on this.
So the performance improves, you know, based on the training
data, the stability, right?
Improved.
But at the same point, the improvement is very small.
OK.
Then we can stop.
So this is the, you know, the filter method, and the
reference method is similar, but every step is just, you know,
based on the pan-classified performance to evaluate the
goodness of a feature subset.
OK.
So also, actually, the solving criterion could be the
number of features or the classification accuracy is the
best.
OK.
Then we can stop.
So normally, we don't use the classification accuracy on the
training data.
We use the validation data.
But you can still use the classification accuracy on the
training data.
But I just, again, will, again, follow the so-called air ball
principle, right?
At the beginning of the classification performance,
we will improve very fast with more features added to the
model, right?
But after a point, this part is slow.
Air ball.
OK.
So this is a point that we can stop.
So this is the reference method.
OK.
So that's actually, we look at the differential forward
selection.
We look at the implementation.
How this is done.
OK.
And in the signal forward search, you know, we know this is
a bottom up method.
We start from empty set.
OK.
So usually, we have empty set.
They are hard to select the first feature.
OK.
And actually, we don't know.
We should try.
For each of the features, kind of features, X, Y, X, X, X,
X, we combine it with the empty set.
Of course, the combination with the empty set, we add to the
empty set, we adjust the individual feature, right?
So the first step, actually, is the individual feature
evaluation selection.
In the first step, first, in the first step, we select one
feature, right?
And this feature is evaluated individually.
Because you combine this feature with the empty set.
That's the equivalent to us.
There's a single feature, right?
OK.
So in the first step, we consider each feature as a
candidate to be selected as the first feature.
OK.
And then we create a lot of feature subset candidates.
But of course, each feature subset contains only one
feature.
Because this is the first step.
Because we combine this feature with the empty set.
OK.
And then, this is the set algorithm, right?
Sequential set.
Actually, we combine each of the features with the
previous feature.
The previous feature is an empty set.
And then we evaluate the gonies of the feature.
OK.
And so if we use the serrability measure, then we can just
base on this, the trace of the between class scalar
matrix over the trace of the within class scalar matrix,
all based on the Mach-Norby distance measure, right?
You can use only another measure.
OK.
Evaluate the gonies of an individual feature.
And actually, for individual feature, we can just use the
feature ratio.
We can just use the feature ratio.
OK.
And also, we can actually use the base on the
performance classification performance.
For each, we use just one feature, right?
To train a classifier.
For all the n features, right?
We train n classifiers.
Then we look at the performance of the n classifiers.
Then we find the best performing one.
OK.
So the feature that has the largest separability measure,
or the best classifier performance is selected.
Then this feature is just the first feature selected.
OK.
So the first step basically is an individual feature
evaluation, right?
And then we select the best performing feature.
So this is the first feature we have selected.
OK.
And then actually, come to the second step.
In the second step, actually, we select the second feature.
And how to select the second feature?
The first feature is already selected, right?
So we need to combine each of the remaining features.
Totally, we have n features.
After one feature is selected in the first step,
we have a remaining a minus one feature.
Each of these a minus one feature will be combined
with the first selected feature.
Then we can form a minus one feature subset.
Each of the features subset have two features.
And then we can evaluate the goodness of these two features.
OK.
Subset, a minus one feature subset.
Each of them has two features.
OK.
And based on either the separability measure
or the classifier performance.
OK.
Then we compare the goodness of the a minus one feature subset.
Then we identify the best performing one, right?
Either based on the separability measure
or the classifier accuracy.
Then we can select the second feature.
OK.
This is the second step, right?
So these are the presets.
We continue, right?
Continue until the stopping criterion is satisfied.
And just to mention, stopping criterion
could be a number of features you preset.
OK.
It could be based on the separability measure
increment, the improvement.
If trivial, we can stop.
Or we can be some of the classifier performance, right?
On the validation data.
OK.
So this is the sequential forward selection.
And next, we look at the sequential backward elimination.
Backward elimination.
By the way, backward elimination is the top down method, right?
We start from the full set.
OK.
Then we remove the features one by one.
Actually, each step we remove one feature.
OK.
Then the first step, which feature we should remove.
I have no idea.
We should try, right?
Try one by one.
OK.
So at the first step, each of the features
will be considered as a candidate to be removed.
OK.
Then we will create n subset.
Each of the subset actually contains n monomount features.
The first subset, I just know, remove x1.
OK.
Then we have x1, x2, x3, and your xn.
The second feature subset removes x2.
Then we have x1, x3, x4, and your xn.
So we have n feature subset.
Each feature subset contains n monomount features.
OK.
So this is the search, right?
The search algorithm creates this candidate feature subset.
OK.
Then the next, we use the evaluation criterion
to evaluate each of the features subset.
We can either, based on the vulnerability measure,
or based on the class feature accuracy.
So filter method or the wrapper method, right?
And then we can identify which feature is the least important.
Less important.
That means the removal of that feature does not
affect the performance much.
OK.
Actually, in practice, we just compare which feature
has the worst performance.
It has the worst performance.
We look at the vulnerability measure,
or we look at the class accuracy.
Which feature subset at least has the worst performance.
And then we just remove that feature.
So this is the first step.
We remove one feature.
Assume, actually, that one is removed.
OK.
And then, next, actually, we should actually
remove other features, right?
We should remove other first features removed.
Then the next step, second step, we
have M1 and 1 kind of features, right?
So we will remove, actually, each of the candidate features.
We get M1 and 1 features subset.
Each feature subset has M1 and 2 features.
OK.
Then we evaluate.
We repeat this, probably evaluate the performance,
based on the vulnerability measure,
or the classification accuracy.
OK.
And then, actually, we can identify the feature, right?
The feature subset.
And then we will continue this process, right?
And until the summing criteria is satisfied.
OK.
So this is, actually, the sequential back-wet elimination.
Sequentially, step by step, each step remove one.
Of course, this is the classical forward search
and the back-wet elimination.
And sometimes, they combine the two together.
OK.
For example, they select one, two, three features.
Then, based on the three features, they apply the back-wet elimination,
remove one features.
Then we can get two.
OK.
Then from two, then we select that fourth, fifth.
And then, based on the fifth, they apply the back-wet elimination,
remove one features.
So they combine the forward and backward together.
So these are some variants, right?
They combine the two forward search and back-wet elimination.
So there are some variants, actually,
in the literature.
OK.
And this is the second, actually, type.
So in practice, which one we should use?
And then, dependent applications.
OK.
For example, I mentioned before, right?
Assume, actually, we have a very large, very hard-minor data.
Just like, for example, 40,000 genes.
But we know, only a few genes, actually, are related to cancer.
OK.
So in the transfer scenario, actually, we should use a forward search.
Forward search.
Right?
Because, actually, if you want to identify 10 genes,
you just need to repeat the process, right?
10 times.
Then you select 10 genes.
If you use a back-wet elimination, you need to remove,
you need to repeat 10 times.
40,000 minus 10.
You need to repeat so many times.
OK.
So this is another skill.
Another is that, actually, if you know the feature subset,
very few features are redundant or insignificant.
And most of them should be kept, should be retained,
in the final features subset.
In such a scenario, we should adopt the back-wet elimination.
Because the back-wet elimination, just only we need to perform
these a few steps, then we will stop.
If you use a forward selection, you need to repeat many, many times.
You need to perform this selection process many steps.
So which to follow, which to use,
and then depend on the specific application.
OK.
So this is the tool, actually, back-wet elimination,
forward search, right?
Forward selection, back-wet elimination.
And the last one is the embedded method, right?
Actually, we already landed in the regression, right?
The last old regression.
So we penalized the size of the coefficient, right?
Absolute value of the coefficient.
So the penalization will shrink the unimportant,
actually, or redundant features, coefficient, towards zeros.
OK.
So this is a Buri-E entry mechanism.
But actually, we know for the L2 norm penalization, right?
For the L2, this is L1 norm.
L2 norm, actually, we know the solution is easy, right?
It's easy.
We have the analytical solution.
Analytical solution.
We have a formula to calculate the theta value, right?
But this, actually, we know for this, actually,
L1 norm penalization, we need to use a numerical method to solve.
We don't have a formula to calculate this parameter directly.
We need to also use a non-neutral method,
a iterative method to find the values of theta.
Then based on theta, we know which is zero, right?
Or close to zero.
Then we see these are important.
Are they redundant or insignificant?
Then we only keep those features whose coefficient theta is big.
OK.
So this is an embedded method, right?
So, yeah.
So last old, yeah.
I think that's all for the feature selection.
And so feature selection is a denominator reduction technique, right?
And we can keep the meanings of the original features.
So this is very important for applications that need explainability of the model.
OK.
But in some applications, actually, we don't need this.
We just want to use the model to predict.
OK.
We don't want to use the model to interpret, to explain.
And then we can use a feature extraction.
And in some time, actually, scenario, feature extraction, which combines all the features,
right?
Actually, it's more efficient and effective than feature selection.
But feature selection also has its advantage, right?
Keeping the meaning of the original features.
OK.
So that's all.
So next, actually, maybe I briefly talk about our quiz number two.
Right?
Quiz two is on the Saturday, right?
The night of November.
And I read the topic covered in the quiz.
There should be those.
There have not been covered in the assignment.
In the assignment, we have the basic decision rule, right?
Then we have the nine-year base.
We have the support vectors.
This have already covered in the assignment.
Then we will not test this part in the quiz.
Then in the quiz, we could test, actually, like the classification tree and the feature
linear different analysis.
And then the evolution of the classification performance and also the feature selection
and also maybe the classification, right?
Classification will be studied next week.
And the time duration is one hour.
And the question type could be like some could be computation, calculation.
You need to calculate something, right?
Some like descriptions.
I ask questions and then you describe them.
Then you are understanding of the question, right?
You are understanding of the concept.
So there could be description questions.
It could be like a calculation question.
And the topic should be those that have not been covered in our assignment.
Okay.
So later, actually, I think, yeah, maybe next week I will actually email you again about
the location of each student.
Actually, I will put a tree.
And because actually we have three lecture theaters, right?
So we'll assign you to different lecture theaters.
And you can also write your lecture data and the venue for the quiz.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you.