Okay.
Good evening everyone.
So in the last week, we started the piece decision theory.
So in the piece decision theory, we need to make decisions based on the posterior probability.
Or we can use the variant of the posterior probability, such as the drawn probability of the input and the class labels.
So this is the formula for the posterior probability.
Given the x, given the input, given the feature vector, what is the probability of belonging to class omega j?
Okay. And actually, so in the numerator part, it's a drawn probability, right, of the x and omega j.
So this equals to the given omega j, the probability of x times the probability of p omega j,
and the probability of p x. p x is the total probability of x.
So this is a common factor.
And for all the posterior probability of omega 1, omega 2, and omega c, right?
Okay. So normally, we can ignore this part.
And for the numerator part, actually, so we have a p x omega j, which is the class conditional density function.
And actually, we assume actually the x, the feature, the continuous feature, and the following normal distribution.
So we use a multi-variable, multi-variable normal function to construct or to build or to approximate this density function.
Okay. And either multi-variable normal function or Gaussian function, we have two parameters.
One is the mean vector, and then another is the current matrix.
Okay. So whether the minority is low, for example, like a few dimension, right, a ten dimension, okay,
I think the number of unknown parameters is not much, right?
I think because actually the unknown values or unknown parameters in the current matrix, d by d, right, divided by two.
Okay. d, if d is just ten, d by d is 100 divided by two is 50, and y divided by two because the matrix is symmetric.
Okay. So that's the current matrix.
And then in the feature, in the mean vector, and we have two, and we have ten values, right?
So totally, we have about 60 unknown parameters.
Okay. So I think this is low dimension data.
And there's no problem, no issue to estimate these two type of parameters, the mean vector and the current matrix.
But you can imagine if the data is a high dimensional, for example, d, like 100, okay, this is actually quite normal, right, in pentacletic equation in machine learning.
Okay. And then d times d, 100 times 100, and then 10,000, and divide by two, 50,000, 5,000.
Okay. And then in the mean vector, we still, we also have actually like a vector, 100 dimensional vector, right?
So there are 100 unknown parameters.
So together, we could have actually like 5,000 and then 100 unknown parameters.
Okay. And actually, if we just have a small number of, you know, training samples, like even a few thousand, right?
The estimation of these parameters could be inaccurate.
Although, you know, in the last week, we have not derived the maximum likelihood parameter estimation, right, from the mean vector for the current matrix.
But if the number of samples is small, and this estimation for the current matrix, I think could not be accurate.
Okay. So in practice, if the demagnitude is very high, and normally we don't use the, you know, the Gaussian function, right, to estimate the density function.
Okay. But in such a scenario, actually, we can actually assume the interdependence between the features.
Okay. And then for each interdependence, and then the class kernel of density function becomes the multiplication of these, actually, d-density functions.
For each dimension, we have a density function.
Okay. So, I mean, each density function, we have two parameters, because actually for one scale and for one feature, actually, one parameter is the mean value, right?
Another is a variance or standard deviation. So, totally, we have two parameters, right?
So, if we have a d Gaussian function here, so, totally, we only have a 2-d, right? 2-d parameters.
Okay. You can see for each kernel, this number from, you know, d squared divided by 2 plus d, reduce 2-d.
Okay. Even the d is 100. Then we only have about 200, actually, unknown parameters, right?
Okay. So, actually, in practice, if the demagnitude is very high, and often we don't use the multivariant normal density function to estimate the distribution of the data.
Okay. Instead, actually, we can use, actually, the naive base.
Okay. And in the last week, actually, we have talked about this point, the naive base, and we assume, actually, the independence of the features.
That means that we all need a current matrix to, all the, you know, the off-diagonal elements are zeros.
Of course, this is not the scenario, right? In practice, the data could be, you know, the features could be independent.
But, actually, even this assumption is violated in practice. But, actually, the naive base shows good performance.
Okay. So, that's the reason, you know, I think in most of the toolbox, they have the naive base that we classify.
Okay. And so, last week, I've talked about the three types of the naive base.
One is the Gaussian naive base. So, here, this, you know, we assume the features are continuous, right?
And then, for each feature, we can use Gaussian function to construct, actually, the density function.
Okay. And then, another is, you know, Bernoulli and naive base.
So, this is used, actually, when the features are discrete, in particular, when the features are binary.
For example, when we talk about features, right, if a gender is a feature, we only have two values, right?
Male or female. So, actually, this is a binary.
Okay. And if it's about another feature, for example, like weather students, they come today or not coming, right?
So, yes or no, right? So, also, two values.
Okay. Then, we can use the Bernoulli naive base.
And then, if the features could take multiple values, and then we have the multinomial naive base.
And this method is quite often used, actually, in the test class, efficient task.
So, later, we will look at all these methods, okay, through the examples.
Okay. I think the first part, actually, for the first method, naive, Gaussian naive base, actually, we assume the features are continuous features, right?
Continuous features. And then, we already know, you know, actually, for continuous features, and for one dimension, we can use the univariate normal function, right, to build, actually, the density function.
Okay. So, this is actually, this is the class conditional density function, right?
Given omega j, the class. So, what is the distribution of the x? What is the density of x? What is the probability of x?
So, here, this is the Gaussian function, right? We have two unknown parameters.
One is the mu j for class j, right? Which is the mean value, okay, of the feature, right, of my specific feature.
And sigma j is a standard division of covariance square, right?
Sigma square is a variance. Okay. So, I think this is for univariate. I think we have no problem, right?
So, okay, so we just, yeah, I think we, you know, these are very special cases, right?
Actually, of a multivariate normal function. This is the case when the denominator equals one.
Okay. Let's look at the Bernoulli-Naeve base. Okay.
So, the features can only have two possible values, right? One is the, one, another is minus one.
One is zero, one another is zero. So, one is a fill, another is a pass. One is male, another is female.
Okay. So, this is kind of a binary feature. And for binary features, and if the probability that the random variable takes one value, it's r.
And then the probability of taking another value is one minus r. Okay. Because the summation should be equals one, right?
Should be equals one. Okay. So, this is the Bernoulli distribution.
And, okay. So, that's actually, we, we explained this Bernoulli-Naeve base through one example.
Okay. So, here, we have actually one, two, three, four, five, actually, training data for illustration purpose, right?
We can really have a small number of samples here.
In practice, no number could be, you know, a thousand, right? A hundred, a thousand. Okay.
And then in this data set, we have three features. And each of the three features actually is a binary feature, discrete.
Okay. So, the feature name is Confident. And then, study, a SICK. Okay.
So, whether a student is a Confident, yes or no, right? Two values.
Whether a student spends time on this work, on this course, study or not, right?
So, it's a yes or no. And then, during the exam, whether a student is sick or not, right? Yes or no.
So, each of the features is a binary feature. Okay.
And then, the last column, the result, actually, is a class label. Okay.
It's a result that students feel or pass the exam, right? Okay.
And so, now we have a new sample. This sample, we can see a testing sample, right?
So, whether or not a Confident is a yes, a study is a yes, SICK, no.
It's not SICK during the exam time. Okay.
So, we want to find the probability that this sample, okay, pass the exam or fill the exam, right?
So, finally, we can predict the result of the exam. Okay.
So, actually, here we assume actually, you know, the three features, right?
Confident, study, SICK, adenutrient by X1, X2, X3, right?
So, these are the three features. Okay.
And so, based on the theorem, so, we need to calculate the posterior probability.
So, the X is a vector and the value is a yes, yes, no, right?
So, this is the X, okay?
And so, here, actually, we want to use the naive base.
Okay. And so, we assume the interdependence between the features, right?
So, whether it's in the confident, whether it's in the studied or whether it's in the SICK, actually,
they are uncorrelated, right?
So, these features are actually independent, okay?
And then, we can use the naive base method.
Okay. So, we don't need to calculate, evaluate this, you know, density function.
Instead, we can evaluate the density for each feature.
Okay. Then, multiply the three functions.
Okay. And then, time the p omega j.
p omega j is the probability.
Okay. So, we want to solve the problem, right?
So, here, actually, we need to find, actually, the pxi omega j.
For p omega j, I think it's easy to estimate, right?
To estimate, okay?
So, actually, now, if we look at the table, like, if we look at the table,
and, actually, the probability, you know, we can count the number of samples that pass the exam,
the number of samples that fill the exam,
and then, we can calculate, you know, the probability of passing the exam or fill the exam.
Okay. So, actually, if we look at the example, and so, there are five students and two students fill,
and so, three students pass.
So, if we assume omega y is the path, and omega 2 is fill, right?
Then, the probability of omega y is 3 fifths, so, 0.6, right?
And then, the p omega 2 fill, the probability is 2 fifths, is 0.4.
Okay. So, from this table, now, we can easily, you know,
count the number of samples fill the exam, and the number of students pass the exam.
Then, we look at the percentage, okay?
Then, that is just the probability.
So, this is easy to estimate.
Okay. And then, let's assume, to estimate the class conditional probability,
class conditional, let me assume, actually, this student fill the exam.
And then, we look at the distribution of the values.
Okay. We look at the probability of X1, you know, take a value of yes,
and the probability, you know, of X2 to the value of yes.
The probability of X3 takes the value of no.
You can look at this. Okay.
So, we'll calculate this.
When the student fill the exam, what is the probability of X1 equal to yes?
What is the probability of X2, right?
Study equal to the value of yes, and X3, whether it's in the 6 or not, right?
And take a value of no. We want to look at these probabilities.
Yes, yes, no, right?
And the different, given different conditions, pass the exam, fill the exam.
Okay. So, let's look at the table.
Okay. So, we want to calculate, you know, the conditional, the class conditional density,
or class conditional probabilities for pass.
We just look at the three students that pass the exam.
Okay. Just look at the three students.
The first student, the second student pass, the fourth student pass, the fifth student pass.
Only the three examples.
Okay. The three samples, the passing exam.
The three samples in class omega one.
Okay. And we look at, and then among the three students, then actually the first student,
the confidence, actually the feature number one is yes.
And then the second student pass the exam is no.
And then the third pass the exam has a value of yes.
Okay. So, under this condition, the student is a student passing the exam.
And under this condition, the confidence, actually two has a value of confidence.
One has a value of no.
So, that means actually the value, actually the probability that the confidence,
take a value of yes is to the, under this condition,
given the student pass the exam.
Okay. So, we just look at the student pass the exam in this class omega one sample.
And then we look at the third part, right?
How many have a value of yes and how many have a value of no.
And then finally we find the percentage.
So, that is the probability.
Okay. So, for the first feature, and the student pass.
Okay. So, we look at the third sample.
The first feature that take a value of yes, actually is to that.
Okay. And then we look at the second feature, studied.
And among the three students pass into one value of no.
And other two values, yes, yes. Right? Yes, yes.
So, again, actually the value, the probability of taking a value of yes for feature number two, studied, is to that.
Okay. So, this is the second, actually, probability, right?
The class conditional probability for feature two, that is studied.
And then for feature three, the sick, right?
The sick, actually, we look at all the three samples, actually, once, yes, another no, right?
And then another yes. Sooner sick, probability, actually one done.
Because only one student, no, did not sick, right?
Is not sick, actually, during the exam, soon as no.
But this is yes, this is yes. Okay.
So, the probability of taking a value of no for that feature sick, actually, is one done.
Okay. So, actually, from the table, from the given sample, we can easily estimate, actually, the probability and the class conditional probabilities.
Right? Okay.
So, we don't use a tree like a Gaussian function.
Instead, we call the number of samples in each class.
Or the number of samples are taken on one of the two values.
And then we look at the percentage of taking one of the two values.
So, that is the class conditional probabilities.
Okay.
Okay. So, now, actually, from this, actually, no table, we can easily find a tree, this, no, tree fifth, right?
Because three single parts are two single fields.
So, this is the probability of one, six, okay.
And also, just now, we have analyzed and we have calculated, right?
The probability for feature one to take a value of yes to that.
Feature number two, taking a value of two, and the yes has a probability of two, that.
Feature number three, taking a value of no, has a probability of one, that.
Okay. So, we have, similarly, for class two, we can also estimate the probability, right?
Of x1, take a tree, value of yes, x2, take a value of yes, x3, take a no.
And, or given, the samples are between the omega two samples.
Okay. So, I think then, just look at the table, right?
Again, for class two, we have two samples here.
Field, field, right?
And then the value of taking yes, 50%.
Because one is yes, one another no, right?
And then for feature two study, the two field students, no.
And then another is yes.
The probability of taking a value of yes is also one half, right?
One half.
Then for the third one, take a value of no.
So, here is one, the part is sick, another is yes.
So, it's also actually one half.
Okay. So, we can easily estimate all these values, right?
So, this is conditional probabilities for class two, right?
Class two, conditional probabilities of taking yes, yes, and no.
Okay. And then based on these, actually, you know,
conditional probabilities for each individual feature, right?
And then we can multiply them together, right?
The three, actually, you know, conditional probabilities.
We multiply them together, right?
Because here we assume the interdependence between the features.
And then we can calculate the joint probability of x and omega one, right?
Yes, yes, no.
Actually, this is x.
So, to that, to that, okay?
And this is the joint probability of omega two with a given x at 0.05.
Okay.
And actually, we can make decisions based on this joint probability, right?
Without having to use actually the posterior probability, okay?
Because the Px is common, it's a scaling factor, right?
We can, you know.
And then we compare the two values.
And actually, we can find that the joint probability of the x and omega one is greater, right?
So, we can find that the joint probability of the x and omega one is greater than 0.08.
Okay.
Another 0.05.
So, actually, we classify the student to class omega one.
In other words, the student, we predict the student will pass the exam.
Okay.
So, I think this is just, this is the, see the, now based, okay, when the features,
okay, let's look at the multinomial, nine base, okay?
And actually, here the features also discrete, discrete.
But the value they take is more than two, not just binary.
Can have different values, right?
And they have different values.
But it is discrete.
Discrete.
Okay.
And this is quite often, actually, they use, actually, in the test classification.
And so, here, now, we have an example of test classification.
So, these are labeled in detail.
Okay.
So, the first rule is test and is an input, right?
And the second column, the first column is an input.
The second column, which is the class label.
Okay.
So, the question of the class is, this is, we only have two possible values.
One is the spot, not the non-spot.
Okay.
So, this is the two class classification problems.
And the inputs are tests.
Okay.
So, this kind of classification is quite, you know, is a quite a standard question in
the natural language procession, the classification of a given test.
For example, we have news, right, the news from different categories.
Now, we kind of classify a news into, like, a category of education, into a category
of, you know, sports, into a category about, you know, the fitness, into a category about,
you know, the entertainment.
And then, it can be put into a category of technology and science, right?
So, we can put them in different categories.
This is a news classification.
Okay.
So, based on the content of the, based on the word, the wording of the, of the, of the,
of the, in the test, right?
And we classify.
And also, like, you know, like, sentiment analysis.
Okay.
So, based on your comment, right, on a certain policy, and if you can classify your opinion
or sentiment into, like, positive sentiment, a negative sentiment, or neutral.
Okay.
These are actually, you know, standard, actually, class class, feeling problem.
So, here, we are given this tree, one, two, three, four, five, training samples.
And so, these are the label training samples, because it's a learning problem, right?
And based on these training samples, we want to classify a new sample, a test sample.
Okay.
So, this sample is to classify the testing sample, a very close game.
So, this, so this is the input.
So, we want to classify this input into one of the two categories, sports or non-sports.
Of course, for us, you know, we have no problem.
We're trying to look at this, right?
We have to classify.
Okay.
And now, we want to use, you know, use a machine learning model, right?
And to classify, and this actually input, this test, okay, into one of the two categories,
sports or non-sports.
Okay.
And so, here, again, we can start from the posterior probability, right?
So, we need to know, calculate the posterior probability, or the general probability of
this input.
The input is just a very close game.
So, this is the input.
Okay.
And we want to calculate, you know, this actually the probability, the posterior probability
of class one, sports, and the posterior probability of class two, non-sports, okay, given this
input.
So, this is just the X.
The X here is a short sentence.
Okay.
So, here, based on the, actually, Na'yi, based, based on the, based on the, based
theorem, right?
So, actually, the, you know, the omega one, given X, so the X is a various, you know,
close game, right?
So, this should be equal to the general probability of X one, X and omega, omega, sport, right?
Omega one.
Okay.
So, a very close game, given sports, and times the probability of sports.
And so, here, actually, of course, actually, a very close game, right?
Given sports, and we have a few words, one, two, three, four.
Okay.
So, we assume that these four words are independent.
Are independent.
Of course, in the generation of a sentence, then they may not be no independent, right?
Actually, normally, actually, we know the words that follow, actually, you know.
It's, actually, the word, actually, like a game, right?
Maybe, and it's related to some of the words, you know, like close.
Okay.
So, they are not really no independent.
But we, here, we assume they are independent.
Okay.
And, actually, they are not, right?
Because the large-lang model, the model, the language model, we use the sequence of words
to predict the next word.
So, that means, actually, the words are not really independent.
But here, we assume they are independent.
Okay.
And then, these, actually, just equal to the probability of a given sports, probability
of a very given sports, times the probability of a close given sports, probably of a game,
actually, given sports.
Okay.
Then, times the probability of a sports.
And, soon, that's actually, we need to estimate the probability of a, right?
And, the probability of a sports.
I think this, actually, can be easily estimated, right?
And, based on the number of samples in the category of sports.
And, then, we calculate the percentage, right, of the sports news.
Okay.
And, then, actually, we can find this, actually, the probability of a sports.
And, then, how to calculate a given sports?
How to calculate a given sports?
I think, just now, we already, you know, answered this right through an example in the classification,
the single field part, right?
So, given the class sports, that means we're just going to look at the sample in the sports
in this category.
So, what is the probability of a, right?
So, how to calculate probability, that means that we need to count how many words, actually,
in this, you know, all the news, all the tests, under the category of sports.
And, we look at the total words.
And, then, we look at the percentage of words, a.
So, this is the probability, right?
This is the probability.
So, for a very given sport, right, we also need to look at all the news under the category
of sports.
And, then, we look at how many words, and the words appear how many times.
Okay.
We count, actually, the word, the word, right?
So, then, we also look at the percentage.
Okay.
So, this is the estimation of the class conditional probabilities.
So, then, we go back to this, right?
Okay.
So, for the sports, number, sample number one, number three, number four, right?
Number one, number three, number four, okay.
So, how many words?
One, two, three, right?
For sport, the first one.
The second one, very clean match, three, right?
And, now, we have six words.
And, then, for sports, one, two, three, four, five.
So, together, we have, you know, six plus five, 11 words.
We have 11 words.
And, for the training samples, right, in the category of sports.
So, these are total number of words.
Okay.
And, then, we look at how many is here.
A very, a great game.
We have one, right?
And, then, we don't have here.
We don't have here.
And, then, also, we have a clean but forgettable, actually, a game.
Actually, the answer appears twice.
Okay.
So, totally, we have 11 words, right?
And, by this A, actually, now, the count is two.
Okay.
So, the probability of A given sports, actually, is a two, 11th.
So, we just know the estimation of the class, actually, you know, conditional probability.
And, similarly, we can calculate the worry, right?
What is the how many worry here?
No worry in the first sample.
And, no, one worry in the second sample.
Only one worry, right?
So, the count is one, 11th.
Okay.
Close.
No close.
The count is zero.
So, whether the probability is zero.
If the probability is zero, then the multiplication of the three, actually, no, four, actually,
class, conditional probability, actually, will be zero.
Actually, this is one issue, actually.
Okay.
And, then, the next, actually, is for the game, right?
Game, actually.
The first, we have a game here.
And, then, the second, actually, we don't have a game.
And, then, actually, we have a game.
Okay.
So, it's twice.
So, it's a two, 11th.
Okay.
And, but, actually, the first word, as the word close, actually, did not appear right here.
Then, the probability is zero.
And, then, we could, you can't have a problem, right?
Because of the mission of these words.
And, then, the probabilities of a very close note, these would be zeroes.
Okay.
So, this, actually, is a problem that we need to address.
So, how to address this problem?
So, these are the count, right?
So, you've already not seen in the training data.
And, then, the conditional probability, actually, will be zero, right?
Will be zero.
So, this will lead to the zero plus zero probability.
So, this is, actually, a problem.
Okay.
So, to address this problem, actually, we can use the, actually, the so-called Laplace,
Laplace, you know, smoothing.
Laplace smoothing, actually, so, we can, you know, add one.
We can count, count the word, right?
And, the category of omega-j.
Spouse.
Okay.
We, we all know plus one.
Then, now, we have, well, no, no longer have a zero, right?
A one.
Okay.
So, we have, actually, we're all into a constant.
So, here, constant xk, d.
Okay.
So, d, actually, is a unique word.
Unique words.
Okay.
Actually, a unique word, we have defined this d.
D is a number of unique words in all the training data.
The unique words.
Okay.
And, actually, if we count this, actually, in all the training data here, all the training
data here, the unique words, actually, is, you know, 14.
It's 14.
Okay.
So, so here, in this formula, and then, actually, this, actually, so the numerator part, for
each word, we plus a one.
And then, the denominator part, actually, so this, actually, the total words, and then
plus a d.
The words, okay, in this class, okay, then plus a d.
Okay.
So, then, you know, to calculate the class, a conditional probability of close, you know,
given the spot, right?
So, now, it should be the, in the numerator part, we should plus a one.
Okay.
In the denominator part, we should plus the d.
The d is the total number of unique words in all the training data.
So, here, in all the training data means the training data in both classes.
Okay.
So, actually, there are 14, actually, unique words.
Then, so, finally, there's a probability equal to one over 25.
Okay.
So, through this way, actually, now, we can address, you know, the zero problem, right?
So, similarly, for all the words, right, based on a, you know, two, right, then we also
need to modify, right?
Although it's not zero, right?
Actually, we modify for all.
Okay.
Then, two, for, you know, two plus one.
And then, 11 plus 14, right?
Yeah.
For very, only once, right?
Only once.
One plus one.
Okay.
For every node, close, also plus one, right?
And every one, call it one.
Okay.
So, we can modify, actually, the class-cannibal probabilities.
And this is the probabilities after the Laplace smoothing.
Okay.
And then, now, we can calculate the probabilities, right?
And so, for the new real part, which is the John probability of the X, a very close game
with the, you know, sparse, you know, the John probability, right?
Equals this.
I think, you know, I think I missed a value here, right?
This should be times the p probability, p, p sparse, right?
P sparse equals, I missed a one, one value.
I think p sparse equal to 0.6, right?
Because there are three sparse, three, sparse news.
And then, it's 0.6.
Okay.
So, here, maybe I missed some value.
So, this is something, and then, this should be multiplied by 0.4, 0.6.
0.6.
Okay.
And then, similarly, we can calculate another value, 0.4, also times 0.4.
And, actually, we can find the John probability in the new real part, right?
So, here is a 4.61 times 6, 10 power minus 5.
So, here is a 1.43 times 6 times 10 power minus 5.
So, certainly, I read the posterior probability or the John probability of the input x, a
very close game with the omega 1 sparse.
Okay.
So, this John probability is greater, right?
So, based on this tree, we can finally classify this test into the class sparse.
Okay.
So, I think through this example tree, we can see, you know, if the x is discrete, so
we no longer try to use a function, right?
Like a Gaussian function to build, to find the class-calibri probabilities.
So, instead, you know, based on the cost of the values, right?
Based on the cost of the values, based on the percentage of the sample that are taking
a value, taking a specific value.
We first count this and then look at the percentage.
Okay.
The proportion.
So, that's just probably estimation.
Okay.
So, yeah, so this is the multinomial, not your base.
That is, you know, we have a discrete, right?
The features actually are discrete.
Why discrete?
Because the number of features, right, can have different values.
One can take different values, can take two or can even more, right?
So, actually, you know, discrete.
So, you can take more than two values, not binary.
Okay.
And then, you can use this method to estimate the class-calibri probabilities.
But then, based on that, finally, we can make the decision, right, to predict the class.
Okay.
So, that's actually the summary for the 9-base.
So, a 9-base, actually, we know, is based on the assumption, right?
So, that is all the features are independent.
Okay.
And so, sometimes, you see that this assumption is a kind of oversimplified assumption.
And so, in other words, assumption is actually, the assumption is a violated in practice.
Okay.
But actually, the performance of this kind of model, right, simply from our model, often,
I think, you know, is better than our expected.
Okay.
So, we think, oh, this model is based on this assumption.
And then, actually, you know, we, the practical data, what is this, actually, you know, condition,
this assumption.
And then, the performance could be very bad.
Okay.
So, it's not a bad expectation, right?
But in practice, the result, actually, is surprisingly good.
Okay.
So, I think in the hard-denome data, and if you want to use the, you know, statistical
approach, so probably you can think about it as a 9-base.
Okay.
And so, here, actually, also, actually, 9-base, actually, can be extremely, you know, faster.
So, you know, if you count the word, right, so, of course, this operation, I think, could
be very fast.
Okay.
And so, there's a reason, you know, we need to understand the model.
And also, actually, in our assumption, right, the assumption, actually, I also, actually,
ask you, you know, to, to, to, to practice, right, to practice.
Okay.
But actually, when you look at the data, maybe the data, you know, is all continuous, but
continuous, and then you don't use the count, right?
You don't, we use another Gaussian function, you will read Gaussian function to, you know,
calculate class conditional, conditional probabilities.
Okay.
But these methods, I think, we need to understand it, and also, we need to know how to use it.
So, the example, I could give you, give you know, one example like this, right, as you
to calculate.
Okay.
So, this is the set of our approach for classification.
So, basically, we know we make decisions, right, and based on the probabilities.
Okay.
So, it's a base decision theory.
And we can see the difference in our, right.
So, the continuous features and also discrete features, discrete features, when you take
binary values, oh, no, you can take multiple values.
Okay.
Next, actually, we study the second method for, you know, pattern classification.
So, of course, this approach is not based on the probabilities.
Okay.
And the ideas are these, they're very good for these linear adjustment analysis.
So, linear adjustment analysis, linear.
So, certainly, you know, this actually classifies a linear classifier.
So, for all the classifiers, actually, you know, actually, we can put them into two categories.
Okay.
Why is it nonlinear, right?
The nonlinear classifier, you know, of course, actually, the simpler method is a linear classifier.
So, the linear adjustment analysis belongs to the second group, linear classifier.
Okay.
So, the nonlinear classifier doesn't mean that this function is a linear equation of
the input x.
Okay.
And even if a nonlinear classifier, the dissimilar function, actually, is a nonlinear function
of the input x.
Okay.
Based on this, actually, we can think about the base decision rule.
If we use normal function, right, we use actually the Gaussian function.
And to approximate the density function.
Okay.
And then we know, actually, the x is either Gaussian function, right, in the isponera function.
In other words, actually, the dissimilar function is a nonlinear function of the x, the input
vector, right.
So, in other words, actually, the base decision rule, right, if we adopt the Gaussian function,
right, as a density function.
And then, actually, the classifier is a nonlinear classifier.
A nonlinear classifier, actually, then the decision boundary, actually, is a curve.
It's a curve.
Actually, we have noted this, right.
In the last week, actually, when we show, actually, in the example, we know, actually,
the decision boundary is a curve.
Although the curve could be very smooth, but it is a curve.
Okay.
So, it is because this is a nonlinear classifier.
And in the linear classifier, and then the dissimilar function is a linear function
of x.
A linear function of x could be a straight line in the two-dimensional space, or a hyperplane
in the two-dimensional space.
It's no longer a curve or a hyper surface.
Actually, it's a hyperplane in the hard-dimensional space, or just one straight line in the,
actually, the two-dimensional space.
Okay.
So, for this problem, and if we use a linear classifier to classify, and then, actually,
we just need to have such a straight line, right, to separate the data in the two classes.
So, this is a nonlinear classifier.
This straight line is just a decision boundary.
This is a straight line.
So, the classifier is a linear classifier.
So, linear classifier corresponds to a hyperplane, or a straight line, here.
Okay.
Nonlinear classifier is a curve or a hyper surface.
So, this belongs to the second category, right, linear classifier.
The dissimilar function is a linear function of the input x.
Then, what function can be a linear function, right?
Something like that.
If we have x1, x2, right?
x is a feature vector, and we have x1, x2.
For example, x3, any number, right?
And then, the dissimilar function should be a linear function.
Linear function, that means, actually, it could be like a function like y equals to a, w1, x1, plus w2, x2, plus w3, x3, right?
And then, plus w0.
So, this is a linear combination of all the features.
So, this is a linear function of the input x.
Okay.
And actually, for all linear classifiers, you take this form.
The dissimilar function is a linear function of the x.
It is the form of w1, x1, plus w2, x2, plus w3, x3, plus until wdxd, and then, plus w0.
So, this is a general form.
Okay.
Any nonlinear classifier has this form.
Of course, actually, we can write this form into this, w1, x1, plus w2, right?
Into the product of this width vector and the feature vector x.
Okay.
All linear classifiers, all linear classifiers have this form.
But just different classifiers have different ways, have different methods, right?
To find, actually, this w and the w0 by optimizing some different loss functions.
Okay.
And actually, now, the classification problem can be interpreted from many perspectives.
From each angle, you can summarize a certain loss function.
And then, now, we try our best to find the parameters of w and w0 to optimize this loss
function.
So, this is a general procedure, right?
And for designing, you know, a linear classifier.
Okay.
Any other problem within what should be a good classifier?
And we have this concept.
And then, finally, we use this concept into a mathematical expression.
Okay.
And then, finally, we convert this into an optimization problem.
And then, we solve this optimization problem to find the values of w and w0.
So, that is just another process of designing a linear classifier.
Okay.
So, in this course, we are introduced to a linear classifier.
Why is a linear discipline analysis?
Okay.
Because it is a linear support-bound machine.
And both, not just these two, right?
Oh, I have this form.
But just that we have found the w and w0 based on different methods, right?
Based on different ways.
Okay.
What time?
Maybe that's actually, we have a break.
For other break, actually, now, we study how to find actually the values of w and x.
And so that, you know, they can separate the data into two classes.
Of course, actually, here is just one example, right?
In the space, we can, in this 2D, right?
In this 2D space, we can see the distribution.
And we can find a line to separate the sum of the two classes.
But the practical problem is the high-dimensional, right?
So, we cannot see the distribution.
So, how to find this line to separate the sum of the two classes?
So, this is the objective of, you know, the classified design.
You cannot see the distribution, but you need to find the tree, a line, to separate the
sum of the two classes with high accuracy.
Okay.
So, that's how we have a break.
We have 10 minutes break.
Okay.
So, we have to find the, you know, the distribution model.
And we can do better performance.
But I don't have the answer, so I don't know how many, you know, how many questions.
Yeah, this is what you need to do, right?
You don't know the answer, right?
Yeah.
You need to find the tree, the single number of the problem, and the question from the
question.
If you want to use the question, you should know that.
Yeah.
Based on the question, you need to find the tree, the single number.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, I'm already, but I miss the very, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Yes.
On this linear class file and the decimal function Gx equals w transpose x right, plus
w 0.
There are two parameters.
Why is w?
Which vector?
classes.
And actually, this straight line is called the decision
boundary.
The decision boundary.
And actually, this decision boundary is a line,
or hyperplane.
Why is the direction or orientation of this straight line?
Or this hyperplane?
And actually, the orientation or the direction of this straight
line is determined by the width back of the w.
And then for this direction, you can imagine a straight line.
Actually, we have the same direction,
but we can have many lines in different location positions.
And actually, this line position is determined by the w0,
which is called a bias term.
Bias.
OK.
Actually, these are constant terms.
This also equals the w0 times the constant 1,
the input is the 1.
So this is the two parameters in this model.
And later, we will see to determine
the two parameters in the linear adjustment analysis.
And then we normally determine the w first.
We determine the direction, orientation of the line first.
And then, next, we will determine the location of the line,
or the hyperplane.
And for a two-class continental problem,
and actually, we here, we just have one actually,
a dissimilar function.
Actually, in the last week, when we
introduced the concept of dissimilar function,
actually, for each class, we have one dissimilar function.
The dissimilar function could be the posterior probability,
could be the general probability,
could be the log of the general probability.
So all the three functions could be used
as a dissimilar function.
So each class has one dissimilar function.
In the Fisher-Linux linear dissimilar analysis,
we have only one dissimilar function.
This can be considered, this dissimilar function
is the difference of two different dissimilar functions.
So here, we just have one dissimilar function.
This different function can be interpreted
as the difference of two dissimilar functions.
In the normal case, we see g1x greater than g2x,
then we classify into class 1.
So you assume this gx is just g1x minus g2x.
That means when this gx, which is the difference between g1
and g2, is greater than 0, that means g1 is greater than g2.
Then we classify the sample to class 1.
So here, we design omega 1 if the gx is greater than 0.
gx can be interpreted as the difference of two dissimilar
functions, g1 minus g2.
And if gx is less than 0, that means g2 is greater than.
So actually, then we see that x belongs to class 2, omega 2.
And gx could be 0.
So gx could be 0.
That means actually the probability belonging to class 1,
class 2, the same.
Actually, we cannot classify.
We cannot decide.
And actually, this point is on the dissimilar boundary.
Just now, we have seen the dissimilar boundary
with the straight line.
Any point on this straight line have a 0 gx.
So the dissimilar boundary, so just now,
we see actually, is gx equals 0.
If this gx equals 0, this is just
the equation of the straight line.
W transpose times x plus w0 equals 0.
So this equation is just the line.
Just the line.
The line equation is just gx equals 0.
So in one side of the line, actually, gx is greater than 0.
In another side of the line, actually, gx is less than 0.
In other words, in one side, just greater than 0,
the sample belongs to class 1.
And then another side, actually, the sample
belongs to class 2.
So quite often, in the two-class problem,
and the class label for omega 1, class 1 is 1,
the class label for omega 2 is just minus 1.
So we can just, based on the sign, positive or negative,
to decide the class label.
In positive class 1, negative class minus 1,
is 0 on the dissonant boundary.
So actually, the equation for the dissonant boundary
is just gx equals 0.
Because any points on the dissonant boundary, actually,
gx is 0.
So this is the equation for the dissonant boundary.
So I didn't use this.
So I used to plan this, actually, from the,
this is a geometric interpretation, right?
In the geometric view.
And so we plot the data in a feature space.
And then we explain this concept.
And this side, also, actually, the positive side
of these three lines.
So here, these three lines, any point on these three lines,
actually, could be 0.
The dissonant function is 0.
And this side, gx is greater than 0.
So this side is called the positive side.
And then another side is called negative side.
Because in another side, for any arbitrary x,
the dissonant function, actually, equals g is negative.
So this side is called negative side,
or the positive side.
And then on the dissonant boundary.
And then now we assume there are two vectors.
Two vectors.
And one is x1, another is x2.
And both vectors are, or both vectors,
is just a data point.
Both points, actually, are on the dissonant boundary.
On the dissonant boundary, that means
if we substitute x1 into the dissonant function,
then this should be 0.
That means w transpose x1 plus w should be 0.
x2 is also on the dissonant boundary.
That means, actually, w transpose x2 plus w0
should also be 0.
In other words, w1 transpose x1 plus w0
equals w transpose x2 plus w0.
And equal 0.
So now, actually, this w0 in the 2-th side
can be canceled.
Then we move this w transpose x2 to the left-hand side.
Then we can get this result.
So what does this mean?
W transpose times x1 minus x2.
x1, x2, actually, are on the dissonant boundary.
And x1 minus x2 is a vector, also, on the dissonant boundary.
So now, w transpose multiplied a vector on the dissonant
boundary equals 0.
So this means that w is perpendicular to x1 minus x2.
Or xw transpose w is perpendicular
to the dissonant boundary.
This is a menu.
So these x1, x2 are two points, right?
Two points on the dissonant boundary.
S2 minus x1 is also on the dissonant boundary.
But now, we see w transpose multiplied by this x1 minus 2
or x2 minus 0.
So this means that w is perpendicular to s2 minus x1.
S2 and minus y are actually the same direction
as the dissonant boundary, right?
So this means that w is perpendicular to the dissonant
boundary.
When you look at the equation, right?
So w transpose, actually, x plus w is equal to 0.
We see that w determine this dissonant boundary.
But that does not mean, actually, that w
is the same direction with the dissonant boundary.
Actually, the w is perpendicular to the dissonant boundary.
So this is a w.
And actually, the w, of course, when we talk about a vector,
we have a direction.
And actually, this w point to the positive side,
point to the class 1.
So this one, we just now know, this is a positive side
of this.
This is a negative side.
And actually, this w point to the positive side.
And it is perpendicular to the dissonant boundary.
So next time, we think about this w, right?
Oh, this is the dissonant boundary, right?
But actually, w is perpendicular to this.
W is not in the same direction as the dissonant boundary.
OK.
So yeah, so here, this is the reason here.
We say w is normal, or perpendicular, right?
Yeah.
OK, so this is w.
Now, we are going to send the meaning of w, right?
W, actually, determine the direction of the dissonant
boundary.
Because the dissonant boundary should be perpendicular to this
w.
And so actually, when we add time, actually,
when we have arbitrary x, then we substitute this x
into the dissonant function, gs.
We can have a value, right?
We can have a value.
This value could be negative value, could be positive value.
So what is the meaning of this value?
What's the geometric meaning of this value?
And actually, this gs is kind of a measure
of the distance from the point to the dissonant boundary.
OK.
So that's actually we analyze this.
So this is a point to the positive side, right?
Just now we analyzed.
So this region is the positive side,
this region is negative side.
OK.
So that's actually, we look at what
is gs w times s plus wj.
What is the meaning of this, right?
And actually, now we analyze.
When we calculate every time, we substitute x
into a dissonant function, we can get a value.
And we know when positive, we put it into the positive class.
When negative, we put it in negative class.
But this positive, sometimes the value could be big.
Sometimes the value could be small, right?
And for negative, sometimes the value
could be closing to zero.
But sometimes it could be very negative.
So what's the meaning of these values?
OK.
So that's we analyze this meaning of this gx.
And so here, actually, x, we have x here.
And then, of course, we kind of project
this x onto this dissonant boundary, onto this dissonant
boundary.
So this is the, and this projection is just xp.
This point is on the dissonant boundary.
And this is a projection, a perpendicular projection
of x onto this xp.
So x here is arbitrary, no, these are points.
So this xp.
So if you know for geometrically,
we know this is a vector x, right?
This is x.
So this is the x.
OK, so this is x, right?
This is x.
And actually, these are vector from this origin, right?
From origin to this.
So this is the origin, you know, this x is a vector, right?
We can, this actually corresponds to a, you know,
this line, right?
This is a vector, OK?
This is a vector.
And actually, from this, this vector
equal to this vector xp plus another vector.
This vector is just x minus xp.
Of course, actually, if we just based on the mathematical
calculation, xp equal to x equal to xp plus x minus xp,
right?
So of course, actually, this xp is canceled, right?
But actually, we know this xp is just a projection of x
onto the, onto the decision boundary.
So even geometrically, we know that the vector summation,
right?
So this vector x here equal to this vector xp plus another
vector, this vector.
Actually, this vector is just x minus xp.
And when we talk about a vector, actually, normally for a vector,
first, actually, we have a length of the vector, right?
And then we have a direction of the vector, OK?
And actually, just now, we see w is perpendicular to this
decision boundary, OK?
And here, xp is a projection.
It's also perpendicular, right?
So this x minus xp should be actually parallel to w.
Should be parallel to w, right?
Should be parallel to w.
And then, actually, this x minus xp can be expressed by two
things.
First, actually, the length of x minus xp.
So we use the length r here.
The r could be positive, could be negative here, OK?
And then another is the direction.
The direction here, we'll use the w.
Just now, we see parallel to w, right?
And actually, so this is in the same direction of w.
And then w, of course, actually, even now, we just use the
direction of the w.
We don't consider the length of the w.
So we normalize the w.
So w divided by the normal w.
So now, this vector just represents the direction
with a unit length.
Then we times the length of x minus xp.
So this, we just know from this, actually, we
express x into a different form, right?
x equal to the projection of x onto the projection,
onto the decision boundary.
So we use the length of the vector, right?
That is, xp plus, actually, the distance of the length of the
vector, right?
From x to xp.
Then times the direction.
Direction parallel to w, right?
So w divided by the normal.
OK.
So this is x.
So now, we substitute this x into the discriminant function.
Into this gx.
So this is a 3D view.
So we substitute.
W trying to put x plus w0.
So this x is xp plus r times w divided by the normal of w.
Normal length, right?
So w divided by the normal of length.
Just know it's a vector, a directional vector, with a
union length.
And then plus w0.
And then we can put w trying to put xp, w trying to put
plus r, w, and then w from normal.
Because r is a scalar, right?
So we can w trying to put w together here.
And w trying to put xp plus w0, it's just a gxp.
And then plus r, w trying to put w actually
is the square of the norm.
And then divided by the norm, so become r times
the norm of the w.
And the xp is on the descent boundary, right?
So gxp actually is 0.
So finally, actually the gx equal to r times the normal w.
So r is a distance from the point and from the sample x
to the descent boundary.
So actually, in other words, actually, so every time when
you get the gx, if the gx divided by the norm of w,
we obtain r.
This r actually is a distance from the point
to the descent boundary.
This r can be positive.
It could be negative.
If this r is on the native side of the hyperplane,
then actually this sample, then this r is negative.
If r is positive, then this point is on the positive side.
But this represents a distance.
So next time when you calculate gx in that equation,
the gx divided by the norm of w is
a distance from x to the descent boundary.
Normally, this value is bigger, right?
So that's a further away from the descent boundary.
And then we have a higher confidence
to classify the sample into the classes.
If gx is very small, or the r is very small,
that means the sample is very close to the descent boundary.
We classify them into one of the two classes,
but with low confidence.
So this is not this r.
So this r, the gx, actually give us the confidence.
But of course, we need to divide by the norm of w, right?
Actually, the w, we just see the main function
is to the determination of the direction
of the descent boundary.
And for this w, if you multiply a constant value,
you can change the value of w, but you
don't change the direction of w.
So after that, we must normalize this gx
by the norm of w.
If you don't divide by the norm of w,
then the gx, actually, sometimes it's not that meaningful.
You must divide by this gx by this norm of w.
Then you can get a distance from the x
to the descent boundary.
And then based on this value, whether you're
very close to zero or something like that,
or very negative or very positive,
then this can decide not to give us a confidence.
Just like you apply 20, you assume
we have a threshold, right?
If a GPA is greater than 3.5, then you pass, right?
You get offered, right?
If your GPA is lower than 3.5, then you fail, right?
Then you cannot get offered, right?
Just this is like classified.
If your GPA is far away from this, then your GPA is 4.
Very far away from this 3.5, right?
Then you have high confidence.
Even if you actually have a very low value line, very far away
from 3, then you have very high confidence
to be rejected, right?
So this is not like very close to the boundary.
So this is a meaning, right?
So from the GX, actually, we can judge.
Actually, in practice, actually, all the data
in the hard-demolished space, we cannot see the distribution.
We don't know where the position of each of the sample.
But actually, through the GX, we can roughly understand.
We can just imagine, right, in the space,
there is a certain boundary.
Or the GX is very small, or it's very close to that,
just like a 2D case, right?
And very far away, all of this, very high confidence.
It belongs to class, 1 or class 2.
OK, so this is a meaning of GX, right?
GX divided by the W is just the normal W, just the distance
from the point X to the distance boundary.
And actually, for a special point,
for a special point, that is just the origin, right?
For origin, actually, the X is 0, right?
It's a 0 vector, right?
0 vector.
Then we substitute W transpose times 0.
Of course, 0.
Then the GX equals W0, OK?
And so actually, the W0, of course,
can be positive, can be negative, right?
Can be positive, can be negative.
And if this W0 is positive, that means
when we look at W transpose X plus W0, W0,
which is a scalar, right?
It's a scalar.
When we look at this value, and then we can also
imagine the position of the line, right?
Except the hyperplane.
If W0 is positive, and then this means that the origin
is on the positive side of the distance boundary, positive
side, OK?
If W is negative, that means the origin
is on the negative side, right?
W0 negative, the origin is on the negative side, OK?
So from this, actually, there's a W0,
we can get this point, right?
So this, actually, so the W0 determine, actually,
the location on the position of the hyperplane, OK?
And W determine the orientation of the hyperplane, OK?
If W0 positive, origin on the positive side, OK?
If W0, 0, then the hyperplane passes through the origin.
And so, actually, we know when we perform the data separation
by a line, right?
So the line position, not necessarily,
will pass through the origin.
So that's the reason why we're always
to include a bias term, W0, OK, in the dismal function.
And actually, this is often, even in other models,
like in neural networks, of course,
this class is not taught by neural networks.
But in neural networks, normally, I think for a neural,
the first step is also to perform
a kind of linear operation like this.
W transpose X plus W0.
And then we perform a nonlinear function
on this dismal function.
In dismal function, it's called activation function,
activation value signal in the neural networks, right?
So we also need to put a W0.
But some don't really understand why we put a W0, right?
So if you don't have a W0, that means W0 equals 0, OK?
That means, actually, you are designing something
that passes through the origin.
Actually, the location is almost determined, right?
It must pass through 0.
But this is not a reasonable assumption, right?
So we must use a W0.
We use data to determine the value of W0.
So we can see the function of the W0, right?
The use of W0, then the position or the location
of the hyperplan can be any point.
We can, at this point, the position
is decided by the data.
If you don't use the W0, this is a bias term.
And then you are designing something
that passes through the origin, OK?
OK, so that's actually what we're talking about,
the determination of W and W0.
And first, we're talking about the determination of W.
So these are key points, right?
So here, I'll object to design a pen and classifier
and the linear dismal analysis on classifier,
the FD classifier, to separate data in the two classes.
Design a classifier, actually, the main objective
is to determine the value for W with vector and also the W0.
So that's actually how we decide that.
We learn how to decide this position W.
And so here, I show you some data points.
The sample in the two class, OK?
So this sample in this class, this one
is another class.
And actually, we actually want to find a W, right?
What is W transpose X?
And actually, we can have such a W. So this is W.
And then we can W transpose X, actually,
come to something where we put this, right?
Make this project, I did the X, onto this W.
That's the meaning of W transpose X, project X,
or map this X on this W. OK.
So for then, after project on this W,
and the value and all the location of the sample
in this class on this segment of this axis, W axis, right?
And the project, the sample of the projection,
the sample in this class on this side of this W.
And actually, from here, we can see, after projection,
the samples are well separated.
Because we can see a gap, right?
There is a gap.
So from here to here.
So there is a gap.
In one side, OK.
So this side, all the samples are actually from this class.
And then another side, all the samples are from this side.
So this is the 1W.
So now I show you another W. So this is another W.
And then W transpose X is also against the projection of X
onto the axis W. So this is the case.
After projection, and then the values
that we project to this part.
And then the sample in this class
also project the sample here.
The project sample here.
And actually, after projection, we
see the samples actually are mixed.
Amidst of the project of W. So which W is better?
Which W is better?
We don't have a W, right?
Actually, our goal, our objective,
is to find a good W. But this year, first thing
we need to know what is a good W, right?
So what is the carry-on ratio of a good W?
So among the two, the two, right?
So which is better to think?
Which is better?
Which one?
The left one or the right one?
The left side or the right side?
Left side, right?
So why is the left side actually better?
So of course, we can see better.
If you're in practice, we will see something better.
We must have an evaluation function to measure the goodness.
And then based on the evaluation function,
then we can see one is better than another one, right?
So here you see the left one is better.
Then how to, based on what criteria,
you see it is better?
Based on what?
We can see actually the samples actually in here,
they are separated, right?
And by here, you know, after the project on this W,
this is actually the sample, actually a mix.
Mix.
So you know, they're separated.
But how to use practice?
And actually in the first one, actually after projection,
and the sample in the two classes are separated.
When we talk about the separation, here,
actually we see actually the distance
or the difference between the samples of the projection.
This difference is big.
They are very different after projection, right?
Because of the other projection, all the samples in this,
actually in one class are located in this segment,
or in this part of the axis.
And in this part of the axis is for another class.
They are separated.
They are very different.
Of course, actually we cannot just use one sample
to measure the difference, right?
Whether the sample is very different from another, right?
So here, actually, we can use the difference
between the two mean values.
We can look at the mean value of the sample
after projection, maybe position here.
And then after projection, the sample here,
the mean value here.
These two mean values are very different.
So this is a good value.
This is actually a difference called
between class difference.
The bigger or the greater the better between class.
So this is the one, actually, the between class difference,
right?
We hope, actually, the right hand side.
If you look at the case in the right hand side,
which is the data mix, right?
The mix, actually, then you look at the mean value,
maybe for one class, for this cross sample class,
the mean value is here.
And then for the sample in another class,
One is the mean value is here.
Another mean value maybe here.
The difference is small.
So when we see one is better than another one, right?
So in the tree, we must use a mathematical criterion
to evaluate the goodness.
So here, in the pattern classification,
first, we need to have an idea of what is a good classifier.
So what is a good W?
You must have some ideas, right?
Doesn't mean that you need to have some understanding
of the pattern classification.
Second, based on the understanding,
how to summarize this concept using mathematical equations?
Because you see one is better than another one,
we must have some measures, right?
This measure could be the between class difference.
This is between class difference, right?
Because there is a gap.
It can be measured based on the difference
between two mean values.
So here, actually, the x is a vector, right?
But I have a projection onto this W,
you know, the W transpose x.
So this is a scalar.
So we have a mean value for sample in class 1
for sample in class 2.
So this difference, the greater the better.
So this could be a measure for the separability, right?
This measure could be used to judge
whether W is good or not.
The difference between two mean values,
this is called between class difference, the larger the better.
The larger, the easier to separate the sample in the two
classes.
In the second case, the difference is small.
And then it's quite challenging to separate the sample
in the two classes.
OK, so this is one point.
And then another point is that when we,
for easy classification, and just now we
talk about the between class, actually,
there are also some requirements on the all
measures on the within class difference.
Within class difference.
And even the within class difference, actually,
the smaller the better.
We see this class, they all were similar.
For another class, they all were similar.
Then the classification problem is easier.
OK, so this is actually another measure, right?
Another expectation, another measure for good,
actually, now, W. That means after projection,
we hope the sample has a small within class difference.
The difference is small.
So here, OK, so this is another measure,
within class difference.
And we hope to find that W, the between class difference
could be big.
The within class difference could be small.
But we want to find such a W. OK?
So this is our objective.
We want to find a W so that the within class difference
could be great, could be big.
Between class difference could be big.
The within class difference could be small.
And actually, we want to find a W that
could maximize the ratio of the two,
the ratio of the difference between class difference
to the within class difference.
Because we hope the numerator part could be
the greater the better, right?
The denominator, within class, the smaller the better.
So why not to use the ratio of the two
as actually the measure for the goodness of the W?
OK, so this is the basic idea of the Fisher-Linus-Jiffm-Lenz.
And so the Fisher-Linus-Jiffm-Lenz analysis,
that try to find a W, actually, it
could actually maximize this M1 and M2.
M1 is the mean vector of samples in class 1
under projection to the W. M2 is the mean value for samples
in class 2 under projection onto the W.
So this difference, the better, the bigger, the better.
Of course, this is known.
M1 tied, M2 tied, both are functions of W.
Because when we have different Ws,
and then we can have a different projection,
of course, the mean value would be different.
And actually, this is the mean tied, right?
Mi, M1, M2, right?
And this is the projection.
W transpose X are the projecting on this.
And actually, W transpose is the constant.
We can move out of the summation operation, right?
Then move out, then that is the summation
of X divided by Mi.
That is just the mean vector, mean vector
of the sampling class i.
So in other words, actually, the mean value
for the sampling class i, actually,
equal to the projection of the mean vector of class i
to the under W. So this is Mi, right?
So Mi just the average of the mean vector, right?
So based on this, actually, then we
see the difference between the two mean values.
Of course, M1 could be greater than M2,
or M1 could be less than M2.
So actually, we use the absolute value.
So later, we don't use the S blue value.
We use the square of this measure.
So to see the difference between the two mean values.
So this W transpose Mi minus M2.
So we look at the difference between the two mean vectors.
And then we map or project the difference of the two mean
vectors on this W. So this is just
the between class difference.
And that's actually what we look at within class difference,
right?
Within class difference, here, they
use the so-called concept of scatter.
And this scatter tree is something like a variance.
So further, the projection of x belong to class i, right?
So in the data set, the di.
Di is the data set for class i.
So this is the Gx projection onto the W.
Minus Mi minus the mean value, then square, summation.
If they divide by the number of samples,
this would be the variance.
But here, they don't divide by the number of samples.
They just a summation.
So this is called a scatter.
The scatter.
The scatter tree is a measure for the spread.
Actually, you remember, in the week two,
when we talk about the data preparation for modeling,
actually, we need to explore the data.
And for data, we have a tool.
One is in the central tendency.
That's the mean value.
Another is the spread.
The spread of the scatter.
So that is a variance of standard of agent.
So this is just a measure of the standard of agent,
of the variance, the spread.
But here, they use the concept of a scatter.
Not the variance.
If this is divided by n or n minus 1, actually,
it's just a variance.
OK.
So this is called scatter.
For unit class, we can have a scatter.
A scatter, the scatter here, is just a spread.
It's just a measure of the samples with the different,
the similarity or difference of the sample
within a semi-class.
The bigger or the greater the s i squared,
the more different the samples.
Actually, we hope the s i squared, the scatter,
could be as small as possible.
That means the sample in the semi-class
are quite similar.
Then it's easier to classify.
OK.
So this is the scatter.
And this scatter, of course, is also a function of w.
Because the gx is a function of w,
the mi-tide, which is the mean value,
are present on w.
It's also a function of w.
So this is a tree.
For the class 1, we can have a spread of scatter.
For class 2, we can have a spread or a scatter.
So we can put them together.
So this is called the total scatter.
Total scatter, the scatter for two classes.
For each of the two classes, we calculate
the within class difference, which
is measured by the scatter.
All the spread, actually, the variance, no variance,
variance times the number of samples.
And OK, so this is the total scatter.
For unit class, we have a scatter, right?
Total scatter.
And actually, we hope this scatter could be as small as
possible.
And we hope the mi-m2, the difference,
could be as big as possible.
Why is it as big as possible?
Another is as small as possible.
So actually, we can try to maximize the difference
between the two and the ratio of the two.
So the numerator here is just the between class difference,
the greater the better.
And the denominator part, actually, the within class
scatter, right?
And the smaller the better.
The within class scatter is a matter of the within class
difference, the smaller the better.
So now we try to actually find the W so that this ratio could
be maximized.
Racial could be maximized, right?
And actually, this ratio is called a fissure ratio.
So that's the reason why this matter is called fissure
linear decimal analysis.
Because this ratio is called fissure ratio.
And this measure is often used actually in feature selection.
I think in one week, I think we will talk about,
for which week, we will talk about the feature selection
for the minority reduction.
And we want to select good features, good attributes.
So how to measure the goodness of the attribute?
Actually, we can use this fissure ratio to measure, right?
So here, we know that data is projecting on W, then we measure.
But actually, in feature selection,
we don't do the projection, right?
We measure the separability of the data directly
along the features using this fissure ratio.
OK, so this is a ratio.
And this ratio is a function of W. OK,
we need to find such a W so that this W is maximized.
You see from this process, right?
First, we have some understanding
about the pentacletophenic problem.
We think about what is a good classifier.
So what is a good W?
OK, then we express our ideas using mathematical equations.
OK, then finally, actually, we summarize the problem
into an homo-azition problem.
So this is machine learning.
Machine learning is an homo-azition problem, right?
But you need to have some foundation knowledge
about pentacletophenic.
Otherwise, you won't be able to summarize such a function.
We should have knowledge of pentacletophenic.
And then, because of knowledge, we
can summarize actually a loss function.
And then, actually, this is an homo-azition problem,
actually, it's converting into an homo-azition problem, right?
So next step, the objective is to solve this homo-azition
problem, right?
And then, we need to find the W so that this JW is maximized.
And so next, actually, when we look at what is s,
tides squared, s2 squared, how each of these are related to W,
right?
Then we substitute this as the total scatter
and also the square of the mean difference into this JW.
We express JW into a function of W.
And previously, we already have seen this M1, M2, right?
Actually, this is the difference.
It's just a difference after actually the difference
between the two vectors.
And then, project this difference of the two vectors
into the tablet.
So for the scatter part, right?
Here, we define a scatter matrix.
Scatter matrix, this.
So for each class, actually, we have mean vector, right?
So x minus, these are in the original space, not projected
yet, right?
And so x minus Mi, so this is a column vector.
Then x minus Si, trying to put this in the matrix.
Summation of all of this, this is called scatter matrix.
Scatter matrix for class i.
We have class i and class two, right?
So the summation is just the total scatter.
So this scatter is called within class scatter.
Because S1 or S2, right?
Measures, actually, the within class i,
within class two, no scatter.
So this is called SW here.
This W mean within class.
Within class.
It's 1 plus S2.
OK.
So this SW is called within class scatter matrix.
And then let's look at the relationship, right?
Between Si times square and with the W. And actually Si times
square equals to W, trying to put Si, W. So this is the Si times
square is related to the W. Through this, actually, the
scatter matrix Si.
And then this, and we get a summation of Si,
S1 times square, S2 times square, right?
So this, actually, finally, this is equal to W transpose SW.
So this SW, just the summation of S1, S2, right?
This is the total within class scatter matrix.
OK.
So now, for the official ratio, right?
The married part is expressed into a function of W.
And for the denominator part, actually, we also
express it into a function of W, right?
So, yeah.
Also, this is actually SR times, right?
So this is actually the difference.
It's related to the W by this SB.
SB is the between class scatter matrix.
And Y minus M2.
This is a column vector.
And Y minus M2 times transpose.
So this becomes matrix.
So this is called between class scatter matrix.
So, actually, based on the two mean vectors,
we calculate the scatter matrix.
So this is called between class scatter matrix, between class.
OK.
So now, actually, we can see this cost function, loss
function, Jw, the numerator part,
which is between class difference, right?
The square of the between class difference.
The square of the difference between the two mean values
of the two classes.
So this W transpose SB, W. SB, B, the mean between.
So between class.
OK.
And then, the numerator part is the within class scatter,
right?
Within class, no difference.
So W transpose SW times W. OK.
So this is the Jw.
So finally, through the medical manipulation,
we found that we have this form.
So this form, the Jw, is a function of W's.
Numeric part, right?
So we have the between class.
Because the between class is the bigger the better, right?
Difference.
The numerator part, actually, evaluated within class scatter,
within class difference.
The smaller the better.
So we have W transpose SB, W, right?
Then, SW transpose SW, SW here, mean within class,
between class, SB.
So our objective, Ness, is to solve this homogenization
problem, to find the W, so that the Jw is a maximized.
So this is the homogenization problem, right?
So actually, Ness, actually, we have, after break,
we look at the solution to this problem.
So I think the, why I introduce Fisher's ratio,
I think this, the idea here is great.
Actually, in many classifications,
we need to emphasize, actually, the within class,
between class, right?
So this matter, I think, is very basic.
So this gives us a very good foundation,
good understanding about pattern classification.
So what is considered good classifier?
So what is considered as a good W?
So here, we have the concept of between class difference
and within class difference.
The between class difference should be as great as possible,
right?
Should be as great as possible.
And within class scatter should be as small as possible.
So in many scenarios, actually, we need to use this concept.
OK.
So Ness, we have a break.
Time in this.
OK.
So based on the within class scatter
and also between class scatter and finally,
and we have summarized the desire actually
the W into such an omniscient problem, right?
And we want to find such a W so that the JW is a maximized.
And so how to solve this omniscient problem?
And actually, I think good thing that no mathematician can
help, right?
Actually, they have found this problem.
The way that they maximize this question
must satisfy this condition.
SB is a between class scatter matrix.
Times W equals to lambda SWW.
OK.
Lambda here actually is a constant.
Constant.
OK.
And this W actually lambda should
be a positive real constant.
At least 0 greater than or equal to 0.
OK.
And actually, this problem actually
is called a generalized eigenvalue problem.
So probably you are familiar with the eigenvalue problem.
Maybe I show you this slide.
OK.
So actually, we are very familiar with this for vector,
if this x times x just equal to actually lambda times x.
So this x is called eigenvector.
Lambda is called the eigenvalue of the matrix A. OK.
So this problem is the eigenvalue problem.
And this question is a bit different, right?
So we have SBW equals to lambda SWW.
So we have two matrices in this form.
Ax equals to lambda Bx.
We have two matrices here.
And this actually is called a generalized eigenvalue problem.
And actually, if the B is a non-singular,
then actually we can multiply them
in worst matrices of B in the two sides.
And then this will become actually an eigenvalue problem.
OK.
So normally in the topos, we have functions for both.
For generalized eigenvalues for the normal eigenvalue problem.
So we can always find solutions for this generalized
or the normal eigenvalue problem.
And so here, if the SW, the within class
of the matrix is non-singular, and then we can multiply them
in worst in the two sides, then this is just
the A write AW equals to lambda W. So this
is just a normal eigenvalue problem.
Actually, in practice, there may be no need to do this conversion.
Convert this generalized eigenvalue
into the normal eigenvalue problem.
Because we have functions normally in the topos to solve both.
OK.
So this is no fun.
And we see we summarize the solution of W
into an omniscient problem to omit the JW.
And this solution can be found by solving
actually the eigenvalue problem.
Egenvalue, right?
All generalized eigenvalue problem.
In the generalized, we use SB.
This A is a B. And so in the normal eigenvalue problem,
this is the A. This is a matrix A.
In a function normally, eigenvalue, right?
For example, in my laboratory, for general eigenvalue,
you need to input A, you need to input B.
So A is just the SB.
B is just SW.
Or in the normal eigenvalue problem,
you need to enter matrix A. So matrix A is just
the inverse of the within class scatter matrix
times the between class scatter matrix.
OK.
So this is a matrix A. So this is a matrix A.
This is a matrix B. So this is a matrix A in the normal eigenvalue
problem.
OK.
So we can find the solution right through solving
this eigenvalue problem.
OK.
And as a tree, we introduce another method
that we don't need to solve the eigenvalue problem tree.
We can also calculate.
And so we can calculate it.
So this is because a tree can do some mathematical manipulation
for SBW, which is the one in the Rahasad, right?
In the eigenvalue problem.
This is equal to M1, M2.
So this is the definition of the between class scatter matrix,
right?
Based on the two mean vectors, M1 times M1 and M2,
M1, M1, M2 transpose.
And then actually, so M1 times W, actually this part,
actually is just the projection.
The projection of the M1, M2, right?
M1, M1, M2 along the W. So this is also
the difference between the two mean values, right?
The difference between M2 mean values.
It's M1 minus M2.
M1 times M2 times.
The two mean values for the samples
are the projected onto the W. OK?
So we assume this is the rule.
This is the rule.
OK.
And so this rule is just known, the projection, right?
The projection of M1, M2 on this W. OK?
And then now, actually, we substitute this SBW
into the original general eigenvalue problem, right?
So these are known as SBW.
And so this is the original general eigenvalue problem, right?
Now we spread this SBW into such a form.
M1 minus M2 times the rule.
OK.
So this is equal to the raheyser lambda SBW and W. OK.
And actually, from here, we know the rule and lambda
are just constant, the constant, right?
The constant.
And so of course, the W values are affected by this rule and W.
But actually, when we think about W,
actually, our main concern is the direction of W,
not the specific values.
OK.
So if we just ignore this rule and the W,
we just let rule 1, lambda also 1, right?
We just ignore this.
OK.
And then, if the SW is non-singular,
then we can multiply actually the SW in worst metric
in the two sides of the equation, right?
Then this SW in worst will become identity metric, right?
Then the raheyser just W. Then the left hand side,
that will be the SW in worst times M1, M2.
OK.
Actually, this tells us another way to find the W.
We use the within class geometry in worst, then times M1, M2.
OK.
So this is W. And actually, this W,
I think it's easy to understand this W. Why this form?
Actually, you remember, we always
try to maximize the within class difference, right?
Minimize.
And then we need to maximize the between class difference,
right?
And actually, M1, M2 is something really
to between class difference.
But this, of course, is our original speed, right?
M1, M2.
This something different between two classes.
OK.
And then SB in worst.
In worst, actually, in the extreme case,
if SW is a scalar, this should be divided by SW, right?
Divide by SW.
Then in worst.
This should be smaller, as small as possible.
So this is just not within class.
Difference should be small.
So with SW in worst, right?
And then the between class difference should be big.
This is between class difference.
It's M1, M2.
OK.
If you understand this point, right,
we have repeated this concept.
And then it's easy to understand onto this W. It's not SB,
not SB, right?
Not SB in worst.
Why not SB in worst?
Because within class, this is in worst.
Should be within class.
So with W in worst, not SB in worst.
Then M1, M2 represent the between class difference.
SB, W in worst, represent actually the within class
between the difference.
So we can find W using this from the within class
kind of matrix in worst times M1, M2.
OK.
So there's another way, right?
There's another way.
And in practice, of course, actually, if you have some data,
we can use the machine learning toolbox.
All the, like, my lab, we have a lot of functions.
And then we can solve this invariable problem,
just using the toolbox.
But sometimes in the exam, I give some data,
you cannot use actually the computer, right,
to solve the problem.
But then you can use this formula to find the W, right?
And this formula to find the projection W.
And OK.
So this is the second way.
And so in the exam, we could test this part, right?
Not the invariable problem.
But we can test using this formula.
OK.
And then, you know, here we need to use the inverse matrix
of SW, right?
So sometimes SW is singular, or close to singular.
That means the determinant of this matrix
is very small, close to zero.
OK.
Maybe, like, it's less than 10 power minus 15 or 17 in my lab.
So you value is less than this value.
And then you show this matrix is singular.
And then the inverse of this matrix does not exist.
So how to address this problem?
Actually, we can use the so-called singular value,
the regularization technique.
And actually, the big idea of this
is to add one small positive value on the diagonal elements
for the SW.
So this is a small value, positive number,
a very small positive real number, beta.
It's a small value.
OK.
And in practice, actually, if you just
want to address the singular value problem,
the beta can be set to 10 power minus 5, 10 power minus 10.
Very small value, actually, will address this singular value
problem.
So this R is an identity matrix.
Actually, the operation here, you just
need to put a small value on the diagonal elements in the SW.
OK.
Then you can address the singular problem of this SW.
And actually, in practice, actually, sometimes,
actually, even the SW is not singular.
But we still use this regularization.
And actually, regularization is a kind of technique
in machine learning for improvement
of good generalization.
Actually, the introduction of this non-regularization technique
aims to address the graffiti problem.
Or graffiti.
OK.
And so even the SW is non-singular, for example.
Even the SW is non-singular.
So you read the beta is 0.
So this is the optimal solution for the training data.
But maybe not naturally, this is the best solution
for testing data.
OK.
So we can put actually one of the beta here, right?
Even SW is non-singular.
But by introducing this regularization term here, right?
Actually, we can find actually a solution that
is suboptimal to training data.
But this solution could generate well to testing data.
So this is called a regularization.
OK.
So in practice, even SW is non-singular.
Quite often, we introduce this regularization term
by adding actually the beta i, right?
By adding a small positive number on the diagonal elements
within class-catametric SW to improve the generalization
capability.
OK.
So this is SW.
The W. OK.
We have solved the W, right?
And actually, in the discriminant function,
we have two parts, right?
For the hyperplane, we have two parts.
Why is the direction, right?
That is determined by W. And that is the location.
Location is determined by the W0.
So where the W0 should be?
So that's actually, we look at a way to find the W0.
And actually, the best idea for determining the W0
is that we hope actually the middle of the M1, M2,
the middle point for each class, we have a mean vector, right?
So this is the middle point.
OK.
And so this is the mean vector, right?
The two mean vectors, the centroid for each class.
And certainly, we can have a middle point
for these two mean vectors.
That is M1 plus M2 divided by 2.
This is the middle point.
OK.
We hope this middle point could be on the hyperplane.
On the hyperplane.
That means that if the middle point here is M1 plus M2
divided by 2, right?
This is actually the average of these two mean vectors.
If we substitute this as x into the W transpose x
plus half is 0, this should be 0.
Because we hope this point is on the decimal boundary.
That means if we substitute this point, this x,
into the discriminant function, then the discriminant
function should be 0.
OK.
So based on this principle, and so we, this x, right?
W transpose x.
This x is just in the middle point of the two
two mean vectors.
And plus W, this should be 0.
This means this point on the decimal boundary.
OK.
So based on this principle, we can find W. So M1 plus M2
divided by 2.
The middle point, W transpose.
OK.
So this is the negative sign, so this
is the way to determine the W is 0.
The position, the location of the hyperplane.
Just now we determined the direction, right?
The W, the orientation, right?
Actually, the hyperplane is a perpendicular to this W.
Once W is determined, of course, the orientation of this
decimal boundary is determined.
But where it should be, the direction should be, right?
The direction should be determined by W is 0.
OK.
How do we determine W is 0?
Based on this principle, that is, the middle point of the two
mean vectors should be on the decimal boundary.
OK.
So based on this principle, we find the W is 0.
So the W is 0.
And actually, this is W is 0, so we need to actually know
that this W is 0, we, this point should be on the decimal
boundary, right?
This is based on W assumption.
That is, the scatter of these two classes are the same or
very similar.
Or very similar.
The scatter, right?
The scatter is very similar for the two classes.
After present on this, we can find the standard vision, we
can find the variance.
The variance is very similar.
And then, actually, this is the optimal point.
It's the same.
They are similar or similar.
But in practice, this may not be true.
And the spread of one class could be big.
The spread of actually another class could be small.
OK.
So the variance or standard vision of the spread or the
scatter of the sample in the two classes could be very
different.
If they are different, and then such a way to determine the
W is 0, it's not the optimal way.
Then you practice how to solve the problem.
First, actually, we can, based on this principle, find the
W is 0.
So this W is 0, although not optimal, should be close to
optimal value.
The next step, actually, we need to, through a great
search, we can try a few values that are above W0,
calculate W0.
And also, below this, calculate W0.
We try a few values.
Then, through a few trials, then we repeat the one that
performed the best.
So we do an adjustment of this W0 in practice.
Because this may, before determining the W0, is based
on the assumption that the spread of the two classes are
the same.
But in practice, if they are different, so this W0 will not
lead to the best class result.
So in practice, actually, this W0 can give us the rough
range, the rough value.
Then, along that value, we can do some adjustment.
We try a few values of W0.
And then, we look at the performance on the training
data.
Then, we find the one with the best performance.
So we try W0.
So in the second assignment, and I give you a problem, maybe
the same data set, but you need to use this method to
classify the sample.
Then, to find the W, you need to find the W0.
And W0, you can use this way to adjust, to find the best
performing W0.
So this is the determination of W and W0.
So once these are determined, then we can just write out
the Gisler function, the Gx, W transpose x plus W0.
For any given x, then we can substitute into this Gx.
Then, based on the Gx, we can determine the class.
Gx greater than 0, class 1.
Gx is less than 0, negative, class minus 1.
If we equal 0, that means the point is on the
descent boundary.
We cannot decide.
So this is the design of the Fisher-Linus-Dieselman analysis
and classify.
So here is a summary procedure.
Given some train data, in particular, in the Fisher-Linus,
we always provide the train data.
The data is the label train data.
We know all these data belong to class 1.
These data belong to class 2.
So we know the labels.
So for each class, we can calculate the mean vector.
So this is the first step, right?
Mean vector for class 1, mean vector for class 2.
And then, based on the mean vector, we can calculate
within class scatter matrix for class 1, S1, for class 2,
S2, right?
Actually, we need to use the mean vector to determine
within class scatter matrix.
And then we find the total scatter matrix
within class scatter matrix, right?
It's SW.
Within class, sometimes it's also called
actually intra-class, right?
Between class, it's also called an inter-class.
Between class, inter-class.
Within class, it's called actually intra-class.
Sometimes you will read paper, often they
use another set of concepts, right?
Inter, intra, and within, between.
So this is SW.
And after we determine SW, then we
can find the W using the formula, right?
In words of SW, times M1 minus M2.
OK.
M1 is the mean of the class with a label of 1.
M2 mean the vector for class of sample with a label of minus 1.
Remember, minus 1.
M2.
So this is KFW0.
Then, actually, based on the W0 calculated,
you can do a bit of adjustment, right?
Adjustment.
OK.
So then, finally, we can construct this in a G-cell function.
So based on the value of GX, right?
And GX, actually, we also know, actually,
GX divided by the norm of W means
the distance between the X to the distance of the boundary,
right?
So sometimes we do the classification
if the value is very small, right?
Very small, close to zero.
So that's the reason why you adjust W0, right?
You adjust a bit.
And then, because if the sample along the distance of the boundary,
right?
Could be classified into a different class
if you adjust W0 a bit.
OK.
For those samples close to the distance of the boundary,
that means that GX divided by W norm, this value, R,
is small.
When you adjust the W0, you can put them
into different classes.
OK.
But for those with a big R, GX divided by the norm,
actually, this adjustment of W0 will not affect
that classification result.
OK.
Only for those that is close to the distance of the boundary
with a very small R, GX divided by the norm of W. OK.
OK.
So this is the summary of the procedure, right?
For the designing of the Fisher linear adjustment analysis
classifier.
So that's actually we show an example.
So this is an example.
The example we already seen is an example, right?
So two class.
And we want to find a decent boundary.
And so of course, actually, even if we
don't see that you're around the data,
we can still classify, right?
But here, we use this example to illustrate.
And then, actually, we can have a better understanding.
And OK.
So for class, sample in class one and class two,
and each of them have actually 100 samples.
And then we can take the average and the vectors, right?
And then the mean vector for the two classes.
So these are the mean vectors.
Actually, based on the data, actually, I calculate, right?
These are mean vector, mean vector.
And this is the within class scatter metric SW.
Based on the mean vector, we can calculate the scatter metric
for each of the two classes.
Then summation of the two scatter metrics,
we get the SW, total scatter metric.
Then based on this formula, we calculate W.
And then based on the principle, the middle point of the M1M2
should be on the decent boundary, right?
We can calculate SW, W zero.
So once W and W zero determine, then the decimal function
determine.
W transpose X plus A. So this is just
minus 0.0071X1 minus 0.0153X2 plus the W zero here.
So this is the decimal function.
For any feature, for any sample, we have a value for feature Y,
X1.
We have value for feature 2X2.
Then we just substitute into the decimal function.
We can get a GX.
Then based on the GX, the positive or negative,
we can decide the class, right?
So for this class, actually, we can look at the GX.
So based on this, actually, for all the training samples,
here we have totally, we have 200 samples.
The first 100 sample is from class 1.
The second 100 sample from class 2.
So from here, we can see from here until 100, right?
I believe these horizontal axis here
mean the index of the sample.
Sample number 1, number 20, and number 200.
And the vertical axis is through the GX.
And actually, from 1 to 100, we can see the values are most
of the value above 0, right?
Above 0, that means all the samples
will be classified to class 1.
So this is correct.
But there are some exceptions.
Only 1, 2, 3, 4, right?
So these four samples, 1, 2, 3, 4, these four samples,
actually, have negative GX.
So they will be misclassified.
They will be classified to class 2
because they have negative values.
And for the sample in another class, right?
From 1 to 200, then you look at the GX.
So negative, this is 0, right?
So this is line 0.
So only 1, 2, 3, 4 samples actually have positive GX.
Then they will be classified as class 1 sample.
And some of the samples actually are close to boundary, right?
You can see this data, right?
The GX is very small, right?
Close to boundaries.
So this sample actually is very small, right?
Close to 0.
That means this sample is close to boundaries.
And then if you change the W0, so this sample may be put
into different classes, different classes.
So this is the GX.
And we look at the data.
I also generate a lot of data in this range.
For X1 from 1 to 3 to 6, right?
For X2 also from 1 to 3 to 6, I generate a lot of data points.
For each of the data points, I substitute the GX.
And then I perform classification based on the GX value,
right?
Positive or negative, OK?
And then I find that all the data points in this yellow range
are classified into class 2.
All the samples in the green region
are classified to class 1, right?
So between the yellow and the green regions,
there is a line here, right?
So this is the decision boundary.
This is the decision boundary.
The decision boundary is a straight line, right?
And certainly, actually, we know that some of the points
are actually 1, 2, 3, 4, right?
So these are class 1 samples.
But they are now in the right-hand side.
They are in this negative side of this decision boundary.
So they will be misclassified.
So these samples most likely are outliers.
OK, so they are misclassified.
And in this side, we know that a few black sample,
black sample samples, right?
1, 2, 3, 4.
So these four samples certainly will actually
misclassify.
They are sample of class 2, but they are
classified into class 1.
OK, so also along the decision boundary,
there are some samples, right?
You can see these are them, right?
Some of the samples along this side.
They could be easily misclassified.
If you change the W0 a bit, so you change the position,
you move above a bit, then some of the samples,
you know, the black sample will be classified in the class 2.
If you move the decision boundary a bit above, right?
If you move a bit below, right, some of the red samples
will be actually put in the negative side
of the decision boundary.
So this is determined by W0.
The W0 is important, right?
For those samples, close to boundary.
OK, close boundary, the W0 is very important.
For those samples, actually, normally,
I think we won't make them pretty at the morale, right?
Because they are far away from the decision boundary.
The Gx divided by W0 could be a very big wedding.
OK, so this is the decision boundary.
And this is the class 2 result.
And based on the W, right?
And also W0.
So there's a tree.
Now, we use another way to find the tree, the W.
So we try to solve the generalized eigenvalue problem,
or just the normal eigenvalue problem, right?
So in this question, even SW within class
got a metric is nonsingular.
And then we can actually multiply it in worse metrics.
So the two sides of the equation, right?
The generalized eigenvalue problem,
then this become a normal eigenvalue problem.
So this SW in worse SB is just the A, matrix A.
And in my laboratory, you can just use this EIG
to find the eigenvalues.
And you just need to input the matrix A.
Then you can find the eigenvalue and also the eigenvectors.
So this is the matrix A. So this matrix A,
just the inverse of SW, INV, times SB.
So this is the matrix A. The eigenvalue,
you find the V and the D. So this is the V and the D.
And D is a diagonal matrix.
Actually, the diagonal elements actually
are the eigenvalues.
The first eigenvalue is 0.0001, close to 0, right?
The second eigenvalue is 0.058.
And correspond to the two eigenvalues,
we have two eigenvectors, two W's.
So correspond to this.
We have the first one, minus 0.858, 0.151517.
So this is the vector, V1.
So this can be W1.
This is W1.
Correspond to the eigenvalue 0.000, close to 0,
and then correspond to this eigenvalue, 0.058.
We have this eigenvector, minus 0.418, minus 0.9076.
Then which vector we should use?
I treat the here, the two eigenvectors, right?
Which vector we should use?
Actually, we should use a vector corresponding
to the larger eigenvalues.
So that's a treat.
OK, so that's a treat.
We look at we test each of the two eigenvectors.
We look at if this is actually the first eigenvector,
the first column in the way is used at W. So what is the effect?
Then we look at what is the effect
if we use the second column as W.
What is the eigenvector?
OK, correspond to the eigenvalue.
So this is the projection of all the samples on the W,
which is the first column of the way,
corresponding to the eigenvalue, very small eigenvalue,
close to 0.
So again, the first 100 samples are the projection
of the projection, right?
Of the class 1 samples.
And actually, we know many of them actually
have a value, zero value.
And many of them below value, no, GX, right?
So this is actually from 1 to 100.
Some of them have positive values.
Some of them negative values.
And therefore, some in class 2, that is from 101 to 200.
And many of them have positive values.
Of course, some of them have a negative GX.
So from here, you cannot differentiate.
If you compare with the previous, you can see, right?
So this part is big.
This part is small, right?
So you can see the difference after projection.
That's the output of the Gismar function.
But here, we have this.
Actually, what is the mean value for the samples
after projection GX?
Around here, right?
Around 0.
The mean value of another class sample, also around 0.
So different, almost 0.
In other words, this W, actually after projection,
cannot separate the sample in the two classes.
So certainly, this is not a good value.
Necessarily, look at the second W, right?
The second column corresponding to the larger or greater
between the eigenvalue.
So this is the result.
From the first sample to 200, and the GX, most of them,
actually agree that 0, right?
Positive.
Only 1, 2, 3, 4 actually have negative values.
And so from 1 to 200, only actually 1, 2, 3, 4
have positive values.
All other have negative values.
So certainly, we can easily separate them, right?
So from this tree, we can see we should use the eigenvector
corresponding to the larger eigenvalue.
But if we have a few, right?
And the first one with the corresponding to the largest
eigenvalue is the best one.
The best one.
And maybe sometime the tree, maybe like in this one,
we have 1.
But in some scenario, maybe we have more than 1.
Then we should, based on the value, eigenvalue, right?
We should select the one with the best, the largest value,
then the one with the second back, the second largest value.
Then we look at the corresponding eigenvalue test.
And so here, this is a question result based on the new W.
And actually, if we compare the two Ws,
this is the W based on the eigenvalue problem.
So the eigenvalue problem, we get this W minus 0.4198,
minus 0.9076.
And previously, we have found a very different W.
OK.
And actually, we have found a very different W.
But actually, these two W, although they appear very
different, but actually, they are the same.
And actually, so this W, when we look at the W,
the direction is the most important thing, right?
Not the specific values.
And how about the direction?
For this vector, actually, this is
the one we found previously by solving the SW in words,
times M1 minus M2, right?
We find this is the W. So 0.0071.
But if we get the reach of these two, 0.4625, OK?
And now we have a new one, right?
We have a new one by solving the eigenvalue problem.
This is the one.
Very different from the first W.
But if we get the reach of the two values,
the two elements in the vector, right?
This W1 means the first value.
W2 means the second value.
Also, 0.4625.
Actually, it didn't mean that the two vector have
the same direction.
Although they appear, or they seem very different,
but actually, they are the same.
OK.
In other words, actually, we use the two different methods
by solving the eigenvalue problem,
or use the formula to calculate directly, right?
We actually got the same result, the same W.
Although they appear different, but they are actually the same.
Before W, we are concerned with the direction,
not the specific value of W. OK.
OK.
So next, actually, I think this is the generalization.
Just now, we talked about the two-class classical problem,
right?
But in many real problems, actually,
we have multi-class classical problem,
more than two classes.
And for example, when you're setting analysis,
we can have positive setting, but we can have a negative setting.
We have a neutral.
So it's a three-class classical problem.
And in the categorization of news,
we can have categories of sports news.
We can have a category of education news.
We can have a category of technology and science
of technology.
We can have a category of entertainment.
We can have multiple classes.
So certainly, we can generalize the two-class solution
to the multi-class classical problem.
So this is just the multiple-discriminate analysis.
And actually, just now, when we talk about the classification,
for two-class classical problem, we just
have one-discriminate function, GX.
But for a C-class, or you have three-class, four-class,
common-discriminate function, we should have a C minus 1.
So my C equal to 2, right?
With C minus 1, just 1.
So we have a 1-discriminate function.
We have 1W or W0.
So for C-class, we should have a C minus 1, actually W.
And W minus 1, no, W1, W2, and your WC minus 1, right?
Each of them corresponds to one-discriminate function.
And also, of course, for each W1, W2,
we have a corresponding W0, right?
So actually, in the G-discriminate analysis,
actually, we use here as a classification problem, right?
Classified.
And actually, linear G-discriminate analysis
often used as a terminology reduction, actually, in method.
Because actually, we predict the data right from 2D to 2W.
So the data reputation is GX, actually, so one dimension.
Orally, it could be a multi-dimension.
According to the example, it's two-dimension, right?
Actually, the dimensionality could be arbitrary.
Could be two, could be three, could be $100,000.
But the other projection by the GX,
the representation of the data is one dimension.
That is the GX.
So the data from high-dimensional space,
d-dimensional, to 1D.
So this technology is also actually kind of a dimension
reduction technique.
So from multiple D to 1D.
Actually, this is only for two-class classification problems.
From two, from arbitrary D into 1D, right?
But for actually, the C-class classification problem,
we can design a C minus 1 distribution function.
And then the projection of the data
is from arbitrary D dimension to C minus 1 dimension.
C minus 1.
So if we consider this is a dimension reduction,
then this D, this C, should be much less than D.
Because after the projection, the dimensionality C minus 1,
we see the dimensionality reduction.
That means the D should be greater than C minus 1, right?
So this is actually a digital analysis,
not just for classification, because it's
often used for dimensionality reduction.
And I think the details of multiple digital analysis
I think will be explained in the next week.
So today, we just stop here.
And I think it's very important to understand the concept.
So not just remember the formula.
That's of course actually meaning to remember that formula,
right?
But most importantly, we understand the concept.
So how machine learning problem should be solved, right?
And how to interpret a good data
value for linear classifier.
OK, so I think that's all for today.
Thank you.
OK, thank you.