you
we are close to the end of this video.
So in this kind of research videos,
we are going to talk about the
robots
that move quite slow.
There can be multiple reasons for this.
One reason is the image processing.
Because it takes a lot of
computational power to process
images.
So it can be
slow.
But now these
computers are becoming
much better.
So this program
is
not that
critical, not this.
So
just now
in
all the three examples that we saw,
cameras
are used as sensors
for those robots.
So
they are
camera-based
vision-guided
solutions for
the
performance
localization, navigation
and control.
So here we still have
two more examples, which I will show
to you guys a bit later.
So here we cover
some concepts
and geometry.
So these two examples
are recent examples with more advanced
applications.
We'll come back later for these two
What is
vision-based control and
estimation? So based on the name,
we can just
use the camera for this.
So vision-based control
and estimation is about
use of
image data
in feedback control
and state estimation
of
moving agents.
So here we make it quite general.
So these moving agents
include
ground robots, such as
mobile robots
on the ground
or
leg robots
or robot arms
or
UAVs.
The difference is that
these different robots
have different
dynamics.
You will make this frame
in general, where you will make
this frame in general.
We can use this block diagram
to show the main idea.
In this block diagram
we have four blocks.
Plants,
sensing,
estimation
and control.
So you can see this is a closed loop.
So we close the loop
so that we can integrate
a different task together
to fulfill
certain applications.
The plant can be
a mobile robot
or can be a UAV
or can be a robotic arm.
To handle this
plant or robot well,
usually we should know its dynamics.
So we know
how its behavior can be changed
based on input.
Either
a torque input
or force input
or velocity input.
So when we give this robot different inputs,
its motion or behavior
can be changed.
So even when there are dynamics,
it will be easier for us to handle.
If we do not know the dynamics,
we have to design
very
robust
or adaptive methods
to handle its dynamics.
So then the performance
may be
compromised.
So that is not as good as the case.
We will have
exact dynamics knowledge
for a robot.
So to do this
we should basically control an estimation.
So first we need to
find the dynamics
of the robot.
This area
covers
so it
involves physics
and dynamics.
The second block
is sensing.
Some people also call it sensing and perception
or just perception.
It's about getting useful information
from
the sensors.
In this lecture
we focus on
vision sensors
or cameras.
So this sensing is about
deploying cameras
and processing images from
cameras.
Here we have two pictures.
First picture at the bottom,
we can see a lot of
very small
green boxes
on the images.
They show us the features
extracted
from the images.
So the features
can be used to help
computer programs to understand
images.
So for humans
we understand images
in very intuitive ways.
And quite often, even we don't understand
why we can understand
images.
But for robots, we cannot do this.
For robots, we should teach
the computer program
how to handle the images.
So usually, quite often
the first step
is to find the feature points
from the images.
So whether we can find the feature points
or features from images,
then we can have some algorithms
to do some tasks, such as
this multi-view
geometry.
So here, let's say we have multiple
images or multiple views.
And from them, we can
construct a 3D
3D
scenery.
Here it is
a house.
So from the images, we can construct
a 3D
image of
a house.
And this is based on
multi-view geometry.
It is one topic in the area of
computer vision.
So to do this vision-based control
and estimation, the second
area
is computer vision.
So how we can get useful
information from images?
So
once we can handle the
images, the next
we can do
estimation, which is the third block.
It is estimation.
We can estimate a lot of different states,
such as a position,
velocity,
and sometimes even acceleration.
So this kind
of states can be estimated from
images using
various
algorithms,
such as camera filter-based
measures.
Nowadays, because of the
emerging of machine learning,
so
some people
use learning algorithms
to do state estimation.
For example, some deep learning
algorithms to do this.
So
all right.
The first block
is control. So here I use
what is control, but it can be more
general. It is not just
level control. It can
include
motion planning,
trajectory planning,
coordination between robots
or human-robot interaction,
et cetera.
So we have a quite a broad
topic.
So for this control, let's
just use control here.
So to do this control,
we need to close the loop.
We need to use
the measurements
from cameras
to provide feedback.
Then we can close the loop.
There are many different control
measures.
Like model-based, model-based
measures, model-free
measures.
Nowadays, we have this
learning-based measures or AI-based
measures.
There are various
But no matter what we use,
there is one thing
in common between them,
which is feedback.
So that means
we use the measurements
from cameras
in an iterative way.
All right?
At each
sampling
period, so we
take images from the cameras.
We'll process the images
and then figure out
the actual state.
Okay?
Then we compare the actual state and the
desired state and use the error
to
change
the motion of the robot.
So this is a kind of...
This is an iterative process.
And we keep making
corrections
in
each
control period.
Okay.
There are many
different sensors.
Such as
cameras,
isn't it when you find
them, and we use
encoders, etc.
Okay.
So why do we want to
study this area?
Vision-based control.
Why is this useful?
So
here we have one picture.
in this picture
there are several
objects, such as
airplanes,
bigger ones,
smaller ones,
UAVs,
and also
the round of vehicles,
round robots.
So there can be
more machines,
more robots.
To handle these machines
so that
they can coordinate
and they can
complete certain tasks,
usually we need to know
their pose.
This means we need to know
their position
and the
orientation.
Let's consider an airplane.
So
the position is x, y, z,
three-dimensional.
And for orientation
is
your picture row,
three different angles.
So in total,
we need three state variables
to represent
the
state of the airplane.
And we call this pose,
which means
position and orientation.
So usually this is
required
for navigation and control
of autonomous vehicles
or autonomous robots.
For the outdoor environment,
we can use GPS.
But if the GPS is not
available, they will have to find
alternative solutions, such as
vision-based solutions.
Let's say in this picture,
even if it is
an outdoor environment,
so let's say
when the vehicles
are very close
to top buildings,
GPS may be blocked.
So people call this
GPS
concentrated environment
so GPS deny the environment.
So GPS doesn't work
in this kind of environment.
They will have to use
another type of sensor.
For
indoor environment,
in this classroom,
we do not have GPS.
We should use some sensors
to provide measurements and feedback.
So vision provides a good
solution in this kind of environment.
M-Use can be used,
but M-U sometimes
have
error drift
so we cannot use it alone.
All right, so
these two points show us
the motivation to use vision
in navigation
and control for autonomous vehicles
and robots.
So here we have four different items.
They show us the advantages
of using
vision in robots
and vehicles.
Number one,
vision is
a rich data set.
It has a lot
of potential
information.
Okay.
So let me show you one example.
Let's say if we use a vision
to control a robot in this classroom.
So pretty much
we can
see
how many students
are in this classroom
and where they are.
We can even
figure out who they are.
So let's say if you just use
a laser or UWB,
you do not have this kind of information.
And nowadays,
for some robots
or vehicles,
they are
teleoperated
by humans very far away.
Okay.
Next example, the UAVs
are used in one country.
All right.
And the operators are in another country
very far away.
So for this kind of teleoperation,
all right, so the human
need intuitive information
of the environment
or will need a lot of information
so vision provides
a good sensing
for that kind of
applications.
And number two,
vision is
a passive sensor.
It can't be
detected like Sona,
radar, laser,
etc.
All right.
So this means we can use camera to detect
some targets.
But the targets
do not know that
they're under
perception
or monitoring
by some sensors.
All right.
So this has
quite good applications
in certain
scenarios.
Number three, vision
is intuitive
to humans.
So this makes it
possible for teleoperation
of
autonomous vehicles,
robots.
And also this makes it even
possible for human and robots to have
better and better interactions.
Number four, cameras
are relatively cheap
and versatile.
There are many different types
of cameras that we can choose
for different
applications.
So they have different
resolutions,
different
sampling frequency
or frame rate.
And the prices
are also quite different depending on
the resolutions and the functions
provided by the cameras.
This picture shows
some industrial
cameras
which can be used for
robotic arms or ground
robots.
So in the first class
I passed some cameras around
in the classroom
and you guys took a look.
So for those cameras
the prices are not
very expensive, just several hundred
dollars and
they have quite a high
resolution and also quite good frequency
rate.
So this slide shows
the advantages
of cameras.
It is not easy
to use a camera's
vision in a
robotic project.
So let's say if we want
to do vision-based control
for a robot,
if we want to use cameras
to get the motion
of a robot
we have to address
quite a few challenges.
Number one,
robust
and real-time
vision estimation.
In about 40 years ago
people started to use
cameras
to get the motion of a robot.
But
at that time
the applications
were very limited.
One reason is that
the computers at that time
were
very poor.
So
it's very difficult to process
images obtained by
the cameras.
But nowadays
the hardware
is much better.
Even 15 years ago
if you want to process images
you may have to use a very powerful
server to do it.
But nowadays you can just use
a normal laptop
to handle it very well.
With better hardware
we can now do real-time
image processing.
Usually images
have noises.
Especially for low-cost cameras.
In 1990s
for one camera
the cost may be more than
5,000 US dollars.
So very expensive.
But the performance is not that good.
So nowadays the cameras
are much cheaper.
With much better resolution
higher frame rate.
So that
we can have
robust
feedback from
the cameras.
This is a challenge
with the development
of technologies, with the development
of hardware.
This one
is not that critical anymore.
Number two.
Feedback
through a transformation from 3D
to 2D.
So we live in a 3D world.
It is a 3D space.
Images
are 2D information.
It is a 2D space.
So in our model
or in the closed loop
so we have to
handle this feedback from
3D to 2D.
So in this process basically we have
lost
some information
in this imaging process.
So in the
vision-based control
framework, we have to deal
with this loss
of information.
So this is one challenge.
Loss of
depth information
during imaging projection.
So this can be kind of combined.
Number four.
Camera calibration
uncertainty.
So the camera calibration
actually
gives us the camera calibration
model.
The camera model serves as a bridge
between the 2D space
and the 3D world.
Or between the 2D images
and the 3D applications.
If this calibration
is not very accurate
so that means
this bridge
has some problem.
They will have to deal with this
problem in the control framework.
If the calibration is perfect
they will have to worry about it.
So this is
one point
that we have influence on the
performance.
Number five.
The field of view.
For a normal camera
it can only
measure
objects
in certain
angles.
And that angle is called field of view.
So it can be 60 degrees
or 90 degrees.
If the obstacles
or objects
are outside the field of view
how do we handle it?
This is also a challenge for vision
based control and applications.
I'm not sure
why some of you visited a Jurem point recently.
In Jurem point
I noticed
there are some robots
who deployed there for cleaning.
I took a look at the robot.
On top of the robot
there were four cameras.
And these four cameras
face different directions.
So this is
1P200
this limited field of view.
Like I said, if one camera can provide us
90 degrees
field of view.
If you use four, you can cover
all different
directions.
Number six,
relative motion
between
targets.
We can take a look at this picture
with multiple
airplanes
and multiple ground vehicles.
If we
let them coordinate, next example
to let the airplane track
ground vehicles.
So we have 100 relative motion between them.
Some of them move faster
some of them move slower.
So we have to deal with this
relative motion.
I believe that most of you
have watched
this kind of air show
somewhere.
So people can
show
pictures
using a large number
of small
UAVs.
So to handle
that many
of UAVs.
So we need to make sure that they don't
collide into each other.
So we have to control the relative motion between them
very well.
This is also one challenge.
Number seven,
nonlinear
multiple differential equations
with unmeasurable states.
Basically this means that
for different robots, the dynamics
can be quite complicated.
They can be
nonlinear with even
uncertainties in the dynamics.
If we want to handle
the motion of that robot
or vehicle well, we should
know their dynamics.
We should know those differential equations
very accurately.
So if we do not
know some uncertainty
or some nonlinearity
in the dynamics,
we will have a design in very advanced
control measures
to take care of that nonlinearity
or uncertainty.
This quite often is very challenging
or very difficult to do.
So these are the
challenges for vision-based
control.
This topic has been
an investigation
for over 40 years.
People all around the world
have already found many different
measures to handle this topic.
In week five, we will talk about some
measures for vision-based control.
Okay.
So next, I will show you
one framework
for vision-based control
and estimation.
So this kind of shows us
the big picture
of this technology.
So how
we integrate
different pieces of techniques
and provide a complete solution
for vision-based control applications.
We can start
from
the control object.
It can be
a UAV
or it can be
a
ground vehicle.
This picture is actually
the mass rover.
So it's autonomous robot
used for mass
exploration.
And this picture was
taken many years ago.
Okay.
So in the past,
it was just imagination.
Like I said, someday
people may explore
Mars.
Okay.
And now this
kind of
vision
is getting closer
to reality.
Okay.
In this framework,
the main sensor
is
a camera.
But here we have space
for other sensors.
Like if you want to use a laser-reinforcer
if you want to use UWB,
if you want to use MU,
you can place them
into this framework.
From the camera,
we can have images.
So the images are obtained
at a certain sampling frequency.
Usually we call it
the frame rate for the camera.
Then for the images,
we can use
image processing algorithms
to process the images
and get useful information
such as
feature points,
detection
and tracking.
And then from images,
we can do
all kinds of estimation.
State estimation,
motion estimation,
geometry estimation,
3D scene,
reconstruction, etc.
The objective
is to
get
useful state variables
that can be used
in
robotic manipulation,
motion planning, control, etc.
After we get
useful information,
then we can
use this information
for control.
OK,
now let's take a break.
We'll start at about
750.
During the break,
if you have any questions,
you can come here and let me know.
Thank you.
.