you
.
Okay, good evening everyone.
So this project appears to be not work.
So anyway, I think these two are
sufficient for you to see the notes.
So we will start with the
first one, the
deep machine learning based on the
convolutional neural network.
So first we will study what is the neural
network. So we first introduce the network
structure and a neural
model.
So we will start with the
neural network. Then we will study
much more perceptome, it is much more neural network.
So then we will introduce the
convolutional neural network to understand
what is the deep learning.
So we will start with the
neural network.
So we first show a network structure
and a neural model. The left side
show a network structure.
So from this network structure it is pretty
clear what is the output in terms of the input.
So the output starts with the
output and a neural
network is done by a weight sum together
. And then we get the output of one
neurons and in the network structure
all neurons have exactly the same function
or same structure. So here
output of a neuron is weighted by the parameters,
then sum together, then this submission result
will compile with bias or choice,
then go through activation function,
then get the output.
So this model is applied to all neurons.
So all neurons has exactly same model.
Of course, the input will be different, right?
But of course, the parameter value are different,
but the model are identical to all neurons.
Okay.
So this is a graphically show a network structure
and a model of a single neuron.
Mathematically, it is even simpler to say
what is the neural network in terms of the input and output.
So from the previous slides, it is pretty clear.
So for all input xj, j from one to p, for example,
we have input p component in the input vectors, right?
All component of the input vectors are weighted sum together.
And then this submission result will compile with the choice
of all called bias.
We have different name, right?
Anyway, minus constant, then go through activation function,
then get the output.
This is applied to all neurons.
Okay.
Now, if we want to further work on this neural network,
sometimes we need express the neural network
in simpler form, right?
To simplify the expression, we can integrate this trisor
or this bias into this submission.
This is very easy.
For example, we suppose we have a constant component x0,
it is a constant one.
Then this trisor is similar as this weight as a minus theta.
So if we're doing so, then we can integrate
this minus trisor into this submission, okay?
To make the expression simpler.
So this is just to simplify the mathematical equation
so that we have the, for all neurons, right?
The output is just if a function if the input
of this function is just weight sum of all inputs.
That's all.
Okay, of course, although we can use this model,
don't forget the trisor.
Okay, this is very important for all neural networks.
If without the trisor, it will have a lot of limitations.
Because to make a decision, we know the Bayes class field
from the Gaussian assumption, right?
Nuclear distance, Mach-Henry distance,
all together must, together we have a trisor,
we have a constant, right?
Without this constant, then somehow the function
is greatly limited.
So never forget this constant, this trisor, okay?
Although we express a neural network
is just the weight sum of all inputs.
Okay, so this is W0 with a constant input minus one,
include in the input so that we can simplify the expression.
Okay, now for the activation function,
we have a few activation functions
in the development of the neural network.
In the earlier stage, we use the so-called binary function,
zero or one, that means if the input of this activation
function is larger than zero, then its output is one,
if smaller than zero is zero.
So this is just a step function, right?
So I guess why people utilize this function
as the activation function is because usually we use
this neural network to do the classification.
For the classification, what we need is class label.
So we need clearly what the output is zero or one.
One is this class, zero is not this class, right?
So because of that, somehow to make the output
be pretty clear, then we utilize this so-called
binary function.
Okay, but this binary function is very limited.
So later, we almost all neural network does not
utilize this binary function.
Okay, now a slightly improvement of this so-called
binary function is a piecewise linear functions.
It is a binary function, but in the middle part,
we introduce a linear function, fv equals 2v.
Now the very important activation function is the next two.
One is the so-called sigmoid function.
The definition of the sigmoid function is here one,
over one plus the exponential function,
and the index of the exponential function is minus av.
v is input, a is parameter.
Because this function is a smooth function, okay?
It's differentiable everywhere.
So this is a nice property of this so-called
sigmoid functions.
Now the sigmoid function, although it's differentiable
everywhere, it is nice to derive the learning rule,
because in the learning, we need to compute the gradient.
We need to take the derivative of the functions.
So this is a sigmoid function, it's very nice for
this application.
But this sigmoid function could have some limitations
because it is somehow close to this binary function.
Okay, so this is why in the deep learning,
C and N and the transformer, now all activation functions
utilize the so-called renewal functions.
So the renewal function, the mathematical definition,
is the maximum value of zero or input v.
So basically if v is larger than zero, then it is a v.
If v is smaller than zero, then it is zero.
So basically it's this one.
So this function in fact has, although it's very simple,
but it has very nice properties.
All deep learning utilize these activation functions.
Because later we will learn that for
multi-layer of the neural network,
the activation function must be nonlinear.
If it is a linear, then the multi-layer is just
equivalent to a single layer.
So it must be a nonlinear.
Well, this nonlinear function, I believe,
is the simplest nonlinear function.
So for example, if we plot all this activation function,
we will see this graph.
It is a linear, right?
The first one is a binary function, okay, zero or one.
The second one is somehow modified binary function,
where so-called piecewise linear function here
is a part of the linear functions, right?
Now this is a single mode function.
The single mode function is a smooth curve.
We can get the derivative or it is a differentiate
everywhere, every place we can get its derivative.
Well, this node is determined by this parameter a.
Okay, obviously, if we take a large value of the a,
then we have somehow a sharp jump.
Then the single mode function
we are close to the binary function.
Okay, if we take this parameter a small value,
then it is more flat.
Then it can be almost a linear function, right?
So this is a single mode function.
But the most important sense is a single mode function
is a continuous function.
It's a smooth function.
It is a differentiable everywhere, okay?
Now we come to a renewal function.
Now in all deep learning, we use the renewal function.
From this mathematical expression to plot,
it is quite clear it is zero or way, right?
If way is equals to way.
If way is smaller than zero, then the output is zero.
So this renewal function has a very nice property.
First of all, I cannot imagine we can have
a larger nonlinear function can be simpler than this one.
Okay, it's a simplest nonlinear function.
And it is a linear function if the input is positive.
Now if input is a negative,
then output is a constant zero.
So because of that, all deep learning,
the output is nonnegative.
Now because of it is a nonnegative,
then we can always based on the value of the output
to determine if this neuron is a significant
to the network or not.
Okay, if it is close to zero,
then this neuron is insignificant.
That's not take much lower in the whole network, right?
But if it is not as always zero,
then we cannot use this simple way to identify a neuron
is a significant contribution
or insignificant contribution, right?
And also if the input is nonnegative,
is input of this nonlinear function is positive,
then it is just a linear function.
Okay, linear and nonlinear has significant difference
because a linear function,
it's very easy to handle it.
So this is some nice property of the RELU functions.
Of course, we have,
we always have a huge number of the researchers, right?
Even this function is first utilized in the deep learning.
Some researchers try to improve it.
For example, utilize some kind of another small slope
in the negative way and negative range
to produce another modified RELU function,
but this does not make any sense.
In my opinion, this zero or always zero
and a linear function,
this is a very nice property for the deep learning.
This simple nonlinear function
enables the network can work
in very large number of the layers.
So we have no problem
because the activation function is very simple.
Okay, now anyway, this is some activation functions.
Now, then we will study this neural network.
Okay, first we will see,
given a network structure,
how to express the output in terms of the input.
So this is a first step, right?
So here, we use some symbol
to indicate the input and the output.
Input is X, of course,
usually we can arrange all inputs into a vector, right?
So input is X is a vector.
The component X, Y, X2 and X and output is also a vector,
so Y, okay, we have Y1 up to Yc, okay?
Then from the mathematical model of the neural network
or the model of the neuron,
we know that the output of one neuron
is the linear, which the sum of all inputs,
then goes through an activation function, right?
So if it's a weighted sum of the all input,
then we can express this weighted sum
as the multiplication of one weighted vector
contains all weights linked to a single neuron
multiplied by input, okay, vector.
Then we get the weighted summation, okay?
But all this vector of the,
a vector can only contain all weights of one neurons, right?
Because one neurons has multiple input weights sum,
so we need multiple weights.
All these multiple weights contain in one vectors,
but we have multiple neurons, apparently, right?
So we have multiple these vectors,
so we can put all these weighting vector
each for each neuron together into a matrix.
To this matrix contains all parameter of one nails,
our neural network, right?
We can put it into a matrix.
So if we put a matrix,
then all output is a matrix multiplied by input vectors,
okay?
So similarly, we can understand if we put all weights
in a matrix, what is the dimension of this matrix?
If for this layer of the neural network,
we have input, un-input, and output is D,
then this matrix must be M by D matrix, right?
M by D matrix.
Similarly for the second layer,
if input is D, output is C, C number of the output,
then the matrix V that contain all parameter
in this second layer must be D by C matrix.
All right?
Okay, so we have input, we have weighting matrix,
then we have output in the hidden layer,
in the first layer is Z, okay?
Then we have the weighting matrix of the second layer,
then produce the final output Y, okay?
Now, this is an expression from input and output,
but for training, for machine learning,
for this network learn from the training data,
for each training samples, we must have ground tools,
or the desired output, T, here,
in the initial phase of the neural network,
we call it a teacher, okay?
So it is a T, anyway, this is ground tools of the Y, okay?
So that is the ground tools of the training sample.
Given a training sample, we know the input,
and for this input, what is output is T, okay?
Given a network, the real output Y
may be different from the T.
Then the machine learning is to learn the parameter W
and the way to make this Y close to this T.
Then this is a training process, right?
So this is all variables and parameters
of a multi-layer neural network,
or we call it M-A-R-P, multi-layer perceptons.
Of course, here, we just show a two-layer network.
Okay, now, then mathematically, to express output
and the input, we can use three different ways.
We can use the scanner way, or vector way, or matrix way.
The scanner way is each, every variable is just one,
one venue, one venue is just one single variable.
Then we can use this scanner way
to express the output and input.
For example, all input, although input is a vector, right?
But a vector contains meaning component.
So each component are weighted by the weights
of the first layer, then sum together.
Then goes activation function to produce the output
of one single neuron, right?
So all this variable are scanner variable.
Scanner variable.
Of course, you may say we should start from zero
to include bias.
This is just to simplify it.
We can also put the bias as i equals to one,
the real signal x, the real input start from the two
and right, so no problem.
Okay, so anyway, this one, we use all scanner variable
and the parameter from the input to produce the output.
Now, this is pretty clear.
This is come from the structure of the neural network.
And this weighted sum, we should be able to know
that this weighted sum is in fact,
the multiplication of the two vector, right?
Okay, so we already started so many content.
You should be able to immediately know
that the multiplication of the two vector
is a weighted sum, is this one, right?
So if we represent the output in terms of the vector
multiplication, then go through activation function.
So this is a vector way to represent the input vector
to a single output.
Of one neuron.
But if we want to have, this is a first layer,
then the second layer for each of the output
of the first layer, then further linear combine them together
goes activation function, then produce a single output
of the second layer, right?
Here, this is j from one to D.
This one only produce a single j, right?
Similarly, for the second layer,
we can also use multiplication of the two vectors
to represent this weighted summation.
Okay, now this is a vector way,
but use a vector as the input can only produce
a single output, right?
Now if we want to express all output,
then this output will be a vector,
then this vector becomes a matrix.
So all that form a vector will be this matrix
multiplied by x, go through an activation function.
This one will be a vector of the z.
Okay.
Then a lot of matrix goes through activation function,
then produce a vector of the final output
for two neural network.
Okay, so from here we can see,
we can express the output in terms of the input
of two layers.
Of course, we can also do three layers
or more than three layers, right?
Based on the scanner way, this black color,
or vector way in this blue color,
or a matrix way in this green color.
Now which way we use depends on
which way is more convenient for our work, right?
They are equivalent to all these different way
are equivalent.
Okay, now we first study it,
what is the role of this activation function?
If the activation function is a linear function,
for example, if r equals to r, then what happened?
Here we use a matrix way to see the effect.
Now, if the activation function is a linear function,
we can very easily say, we get this one.
Even a linear function,
if r equals to a constant c times r,
then all this c can put in the beginning, right?
So to simplify it, we just use if r equals to r,
anyway it indicates a linear activation function.
So if it's a linear activation function,
then this a4 can disappear.
So we get this expression.
From this expression, we can see the v transpose
times w transpose can be just one matrix, right?
Maybe a matrix, one matrix.
Well, for this two layers of the neural network,
we have two matrix.
Okay.
Because all matrix are known from the training data,
and then from the training data,
then to utilize this learned parameter
to compute the output given an input.
But two matrix, if you learn from the training data,
is equivalent to just one single matrix.
So that means it is the same as just a single layer
of the neural network.
So from here, we can see,
for much layer of the neural network,
the activation function must be nonlinear.
If it's a linear, much layer is equivalent
to just a single layer.
Okay.
So at least this function,
so-called the activation function of the hidden layer
must be a nonlinear.
So that we can separate the w and v
to make them cannot merge together
into just one written matrix.
Okay.
So the hidden layer, this f must be a nonlinear.
Otherwise, the multi-layer does not make any sense.
It's just same as a single layer, right?
Now, next one, we will first study a single layer
neural network.
As I mentioned that for single layer neural network,
the activation function can be linear.
If it's a nonlinear function,
it does not make any role.
It does not make,
it does not contribute any sense to the neural network.
So for single layer network,
because we have only,
we can have only one layer of the activation function.
So this activation function,
it's a nonlinear or linear,
does not make any difference.
So if we first study a single layer,
then we can express the output by,
in terms of input just by a matrix multiplication, right?
Okay, now, from this single layer,
expression of y and x,
if we have such kind of the model,
then how to change this single layer neural network?
Okay, so we can have a north function.
We can build up a north function or cost function, right?
Although now we are usually use the cross entropy and so on,
but it does not make much difference.
Here, I just gave an example
to use the mean square error as the north function.
Okay, so because it's easier to understand.
Okay, so anyway, given input goes a network,
we get the output.
This output could be different from the ground truth
for training data.
Where for the training data,
we have the ground truth t, right?
So then the difference or the error will be t minus y,
or t minus this one.
This is equals to y output, right?
Then the mean square error will be this square,
then takes the average overall training sample.
Mathematically, it is some kind of expectation, right?
Expectation is just average, okay?
So we have the mean square error as the north function.
So the machine learning to train such a network
is just to try to find the w to make this y close to this y,
close to this t so that that means we will minimize
the mean square error, jw.
Okay.
Now, so we utilize the mean square error
as our north function of this network.
So to optimize the network is to determine w.
W contains all parameter of the neural network, right?
To minimize this north.
Now, this north is mean square error, right?
So if we expand this perfect square,
then we get this expression.
Now, obviously, we can see the north function
is a quadratic function of the w.
W will have the second order of the w, right?
This is a quadratic function of the w.
We know what is the shape of the quadratic function.
A quadratic function will have only a single minimum value
because this is a shape of the quadratic function, right?
Of course, to visualize it,
we just plot the north function against one parameter
in one dimensional case.
Otherwise, it is not so
obvious to visualize it, okay?
But anyway, all quadratic function
will be such kind of the shape.
In such kind of the shape of the north,
north against the parameter,
we have only one single minimum, okay?
So to optimize the parameter w is to get the value
of the w, this north function is a minimum, okay?
So for this linear, single, linear work,
we have no problem to get closed form of what is this w.
So how to optimize it?
We just take the gradient of the j against the w
and then net gradient equals to zero.
This is a common way to solve the optimization problem,
or minimization problem, right?
Now, if we take the mean square error as north function,
we take its gradient against our unknown parameter w
and make this gradient equals to zero.
That means we make this expression,
differentiation of this expression against w equals to zero.
We can very easily get this result.
T, differentiation against w is zero
because this is a constant against w, right?
This one against w is a two e x, e to x.
This against the w, differentiation is also two w e x x.
So we have get this equation.
Now, from this equation, we know what is the solution, right?
We can have closer solution.
This w, this all parameter of this network
is just the inverse of this x,
the expectation of the x times its transpose
times this expectation of x and t.
Now, this is in terms of the mathematics.
So all this mean square error is in terms of the expectation,
right, of a random variable.
Now, in the training phase, we can use our all training data
to estimate this expectation.
We use the average.
So we average this x times x transpose
over all training samples.
For example, we have to queue samples
in our training data set.
Then we average all of them.
Then this is the estimate of the expectation, right?
Similarly, for here, we can also use the training data
and the ground tools of the training data.
Or for the classification, it's class label
of the training data to compute this one.
And then after that, we can get what is our w, right?
So given a training data, all training samples
are the column vector.
If we arrange all this training sample into a matrix,
one sample is a vector.
All samples then will be a matrix, right?
So we can very easily see that this is just
a matrix multiplication.
Okay, similarly here, we can also,
it is also a matrix multiply by a vector.
One training sample has one class label.
Okay, so if we put a class label of all training samples
together, then it will be a vector.
So we can get the estimation of this term
in terms of the matrix multiply by a vector.
Okay, so we, to solve this equation
to get the optimized parameter, network parameter w,
is just solve this equation.
We utilize the training data to estimate
the expectation value.
Then we get this solution.
This is a solution of the optimum network parameter.
This parameter will minimize the mean square error
of the output, of course, on the training data, right?
Now, after we have the w parameter,
now what is output?
Output, of course, is a w transpose times x, right?
So, its output is this one transpose times x.
Then this one transpose, if the transpose go to inside,
this term will come to later,
these two items will come to,
become to before this item, right?
So roughly we have the t times x times this inverse
then times x.
Now, then from this output, we can see
the optimum output of the network
is always meet an inverse of a matrix.
Now, we call what is the Mahanubi distance?
Mahanubi distance is also an inverse
of the covariance matrix.
While this one is almost the same as the covariance matrix,
right?
So, of course, this is not minus its center, right?
Here we utilize the teacher or utilize the ground truth,
but in the Mahanubi distance,
we don't utilize the ground truth,
but we utilize the center of the two graphs.
But I believe these two solutions are equivalent.
Okay, roughly from this expression,
we can see they are almost equivalent.
If you are interested,
you can try to mathematically prove it.
Okay, Mahanubi distance will be optimal
for the classification if assume the data is a Gaussian, right?
Here for single layer of the network,
the solution is also very similar
to the Mahanubi distance here.
We also need an inverse of the matrix.
And this matrix is very similar to covariance matrix.
Okay.
And there must be equivalent,
otherwise it cannot be optimal
because anyway, this is a neural network.
We optimize it, it's just minimize the mean square error.
Minimize the mean square error,
we only utilize the second order of the statistic.
Okay.
If we only utilize the second order of the statistic,
not use a higher order,
then this is only optimal if the PDF is Gaussian.
Because the Gaussian PDF only specified
only by second order of the statistic.
Covarrance matrix is a second order,
mean is a first order, right?
So there must be some somehow equivalent.
Okay.
Okay, now we know that the North function,
okay, for single layer of the network,
you use the linear activity function,
the North function is a classic function.
Then from the given a training data,
we can get a closed solution.
What is the optimum parameters of the network
to get this minimum point?
The North function, the value of the North function
is minimum at this W position.
Okay, we can utilize the training data,
we can directly use this matrix multiplication
to compute what is this optimum W?
Okay.
Now, we can also use a larger way
to try to find this W,
optimize the W without this matrix multiplication.
Here, we introduce a so-called gradient descent method.
Now, for example, given a current parameter value
of the network at this value,
then the North function is not minimized,
it's much higher than the minimum one, right?
Now, we can compute the gradient of the North function
against the W.
If we know the gradient, the gradient has direction, right?
So what is the meaning of the direction of the gradient?
The direction of the gradient is the direction
the function value will increase rapidly.
Okay?
Then at opposite direction of the gradient,
where the value of the G will decrease most.
Okay?
So given any value, parameter value of the network,
we can modify its value to produce a new value
or update its parameter value by plus a change
of the parameter value,
where this change will be in the opposite direction
of the gradient.
So if this step size eta is small,
then this change will reduce the North,
reduce this value of the North function, right?
Graphically, it will see that,
for example, we have such kind of the North function.
At this point, the gradient must be at this direction.
Okay, because it increase.
Okay?
Then at the opposite direction of the gradient,
then it's this direction.
So if we change the W in this direction,
then it will reduce the G value, the North function, right?
Then if we can do that iteratively at the end,
it will, the W, the update the W,
after much iterations, then this W will close to this value.
This G will be minimized.
Well, at this value, the gradient of the G will be zero.
Right?
Okay.
So we can update the W given any initialized W
or current W.
We update it to change the value of the W
in the opposite direction of the gradient
of the North function or mean square arrow here.
But anyway, we need to compute the gradient, right?
So we, to get this gradient for the single layer,
it's quite simple.
For example, the gradient of the G against the W is,
the G is a mean square arrow.
So G minus is one square mean, right?
If we take the gradient,
it is a two times E times this one,
and this minus this one is the arrow.
It's the arrow.
So it is just E times X.
E is a scalar.
X is a vector.
This vector will determine the direction.
So we can get this as a gradient.
So we utilize this gradient to update the parameter.
So if we do so iteratively at the end,
this value of the W will come close to this point.
So this is a iterative process, right?
So many people only understand this is a machine learning,
okay, machine learning from the data gradually.
But in fact, this machine learning,
it can only close to this solution.
Okay, this solution,
you don't need the iterative updates.
We just use the all training data
to compute this matrix modification.
Now, of course here,
the gradient is a gradient of the north function.
North function is the expectation of the arrow
because it's a mean square arrow, right?
So the real gradient is still here,
but the expectation is just average
over all training sample.
But we can also update the W for each training sample.
Okay, for each single training sample,
we just use each training sample to update.
For next training sample, also update it.
Or we can use all training sample
after we average them together,
then to do the update.
Depends on which way is better.
So we can use each individual training sample to update it,
or we compute this one,
then average all training sample,
then to do one update.
Okay, so this is why in the network training,
we can choose some batch size.
How many sample we use to compute this one,
average them together, then to do the update.
There are some advantage or disadvantage
in different way to do the network training.
Of course, for a single-layer network, okay,
you may say, why we need this update,
this iterative algorithm to change it gradually,
we can directly compute it, right?
What is the optimal way, W?
Where the gradient to approach it
may not be exactly same as this,
depends on your step size.
If this step size eta is larger,
then it could also be alternate around this minimum point
where they will reach it, right?
If this eta is small,
then it can go to the minimum,
but we need huge number of the iteration,
it can very, very slowly come to here.
So the learning process will be very long, right?
Okay, this is also advantage of how to choose this step size.
Okay, depends on the amount to update the W.
Now, you may ask why if we can utilize this one
to get the exactly minimum value,
why we need this update,
use the gradient descent method.
Now, in 30, 40 years ago, okay,
our computer computation is not sufficient powerful,
so the computer cannot compute
a large matrix inverse and the modification.
Okay, if we have a small device,
we want to get this W,
then we can use this gradient descent method
to avoid to compute the inverse of large matrix.
So this is one way is possible,
we utilize this update in terms of this closed solution.
Okay.
So this why, this learning rule,
in fact, it is just a simple gradient descent
in the mathematics, it is a very simple one, right?
But this method is called
visual learning, visual half learning rule,
applied in the adaptive syndrome processing.
Okay, this algorithm is proposed by a professor
in Stanford University, Weiju and Hof in 1950s.
Oh, 1950s, yeah, 1950s,
then apply it to adaptive syndrome processing.
Adaptive syndrome processing is to process a signal,
we need a filter, right?
But the filter parameter is adaptive to the signal
to minimize the error of the output of the filter.
Okay, then how to update the filter parameters,
then utilize this one.
Okay, so this is a very famous,
air M is learning algorithm.
Very famous in the so-called adaptive syndrome processing.
Now, this is for single layer,
we can do, we can in such a way to train the network, right?
Now, so because from the gradient descent,
we know that the update is a process, it's iterative, right?
So we can have a so-called learning curve.
That means at the beginning,
given any arbitrary parameter of the network,
the error could be larger, right?
But during the iteration, we update,
we change this W based on the gradient descent method,
then the W were close to the minimum value,
so the mean square error will decrease
against the number of the iteration, right?
So usually it is always decrease, decrease, decrease
on the mean square error on the training data,
because in the training of the network,
we can only use the training data,
we only have the training data, okay?
And the training data, it is used to compute the gradient
to make the gradient decrease, okay?
So not to make the north function decrease.
So north function is a mean square error,
so the north function or mean square error
is always decrease along with the increase of the iteration.
Of course, at the sufficient number of the iteration,
it can be a very flat or a constant value, okay?
So this curve is very famous called learning curve
in the machine learning.
Now, this decrease of the mean square error,
we can only guarantee each way decrease
of the mean square error on your training data,
because the machine can only learn from the training data,
right?
Now, if we use the data not exactly same
as the training data is the test data,
then the mean square error on a larger set of the data,
for example, test data, it may not be always decrease,
it can increase, because this data is not utilized
in the optimization.
Of course, this is not difficult to understand, right?
So if this happened, then this range is called overfitting,
because your network parameter W is overly fit
your training data, so that it will perform poorly
on the test data.
So this is overfitting problem, right?
Now, overfitting problem is the most difficult problem
in all artificial intelligence, in all machine learning.
It is a very difficult problem,
because in the machine learning,
we only have the training data,
we don't have the test data, right?
So we don't know the trend result
is overfitting or training data or not.
We never know that, okay?
So if it is overfitting, it can cause a very severe problem,
that means the network can perform very, very poorly
on your test data.
But the purpose of the machine learning
is to make the machine trained for the test data,
not for the training data.
Okay, after the training of your system,
it must be utilized for the future data,
for the test data.
Okay, the training data,
we already know what is output, right?
So that we can utilize it as the training data.
So this overfitting is the most difficult problem
in all machine learning.
Now, again, here we introduce this learning rule, right?
The Wigelhoff learning rule or MS learning rule
or the gradient descent method.
This is just for the single layer of the network.
Single layer of the network,
we know it's a linear function of the eggs.
So if we utilize in the classification,
it can only have a straight line of the class boundary.
So the capacity of the single layer network
is greatly limited.
It can only implement a linear class fear.
The class boundary can only be a straight line
in two dimensional case,
or a hyperplane in three dimensional space,
or more than three dimensional space.
So the capacity of this single layer network
is very limited.
So this is why we need to study
matinee network or called matinee perceptome, M-A-P.
Now, here we will study the matinee perceptome,
matinee neural network.
Matinee neural network here,
we only study two layers of the network,
because we have the theoretical proof
that two layers of the network
is sufficient to implement any nonlinear function.
If we have sufficient number of the hidden neurons,
and if we can find the optimized parameter.
So two layers is already sufficient
to implement any nonlinear function.
So here we only study two layers network.
Now, for two layers network, of course,
we have to get a study,
we will study how to train two layer network.
For two layer network, as I mentioned that before,
that the actuation function, at least in the hidden layer,
must be nonlinear, cannot be a linear.
If it's a linear, there's no use, use matinee, right?
Okay, so if this hidden neural network,
hidden neurons of this network
use the nonlinear activation function,
then how to get the solution of the optimum parameter?
Here, we will introduce so-called back propagation,
algorithm tool training matinee neural network,
or MLP.
Now, for matinee here,
example is just two layers, right?
This F must be a nonlinear function,
cannot be a linear.
So if we just use the mean square error
as the north function, we have this expression.
Now, to get the optimum parameter V and W,
matinee to minimize this north function,
we need to take the gradient
and the net gradient equals to zero,
and then solve this equation,
then the solution of this equation,
this W and the W,
we are minimize the north function, right?
But unfortunately, because this F is a nonlinear function,
any nonlinear function here,
if then we cannot get an analytical result
of this equation, we cannot solve this equation,
we don't have the closed solution.
This is caused by nonlinear function F here.
Now, because of that,
the neural network research starts from the 1940s,
and then up to 1980s, I believe 14 years,
the people can only research on a single layer
of the network, cannot extend to matinee network,
because people find the optimization has no solution.
We cannot find what is the optimal parameter value W
and the way to minimize this north function
by solve this equation.
This 14 years, so many researchers work on that,
cannot find the solution.
I also feel very strange, I don't understand why.
So up to in 1980s,
Hinton invoked an algorithm called back propagation,
so that we can train a matinee network
to get to learn this parameter V and W.
Then we can somehow extend the neural network
from single layer to matinee in 1980s, after 40 years.
And this back propagation is invented
by Hinton, okay?
And then later, the CNN is also invented by Hinton.
Today, I just read the newspaper.
Hinton got the Nobel Prize of this year,
because of this two contribution.
Okay, just today I learned from the newspaper.
Now, what is a back propagation?
Now, the deep learning is also used
as a so-called back propagation.
So here, we will learn what is a back propagation.
Now, just now I mentioned that I also feel very strange
why in the 14 years of the research,
from 1940s up to 1980s,
people don't use the matinee neural network,
because from here, this we cannot find a closed solution.
Then we will see what is the back propagation.
The idea, in fact, is very simple also.
Also, we will see the method is very straightforward.
Now, to solve this equation, it is impossible.
Take the gradient of this north function equals to zero.
We cannot get the analytic solution.
But it does not mean we cannot utilize
the gradient descent method.
Well, in the gradient descent method,
we don't need to solve this equation.
Solve this equation means we should get what is the w,
what is the w, right?
To solve this equation.
But if we only utilize this gradient descent method,
we don't need solve this equation,
we only need compute the gradient,
the numeric value of the gradient,
given a current value of the parameter w
and the way to compute the numeric value of the gradient,
then we can utilize this gradient descent method, right?
This is already applied in adaptive single processing
in 1940s or 1950s.
As we study the single layer of the network, right?
But we can also apply to multi-layer neural network.
There's no problem because to compute this gradient
mathematically, it is not difficult.
We just utilize the so-called chain rule
of the differentiation.
We can get the expression of this gradient,
although we cannot solve this equation,
we can get the mathematical expression
of this two gradient.
And then we can compute the value of this two gradient.
Then we can utilize this gradient descent method.
So here, show how to get the expression
of this two gradient.
Okay, it is not difficult, it's very straightforward.
Just utilize the chain rule, for example.
Now we define our core, north function
is a mean square a, right?
We have this expression.
We can very easily to come.
This y is this one.
If we define some intermediate variable qk equals to this one,
we can very easily to get the expression of the gradient.
The differentiation of the j against the v, right?
Is equals to differentiation of the j against the q.
And then times differentiation of the q against this v.
Right?
Well, this differentiation of the j against the q from here,
it is two times, of course, we define our north function
that multiplied by one over two,
so that the gradient, we don't have the two.
This is just for convenience.
So anyway, the gradient of this expression against this q
is just this one, right?
This square, the differentiation is this one,
this one, multiply the differentiation
of this activation function.
And then multiply this term, the differentiation of the q
against the v.
Then the result is just that.
So this blue color one is the gradient of j
against the v, the second layer parameter, right?
Now the gradient of the j against the w,
I will not go through the details,
it is just a normal differentiation.
You can very easily to get,
it's just a basic calculus.
Now, if we want to get the gradient of the j against the w,
it is also not difficult,
although it appears to be complicated
because we have many such kind of a summation,
but the gradient is also,
we just apply the chain rule of the differentiation.
Okay, the differentiation of the j against the v is
j against the z, j, delta j over delta z,
and then times delta z over delta q,
then times delta q over delta w,
then we get delta j over delta w.
Then for the first items, where is that?
That is here, is this one.
The second items is here,
it's just the differentiation of the activation function.
The third term is just the xi.
Okay, you can check this one, it's very straightforward.
Just apply the chain rule of the differentiation.
We can get this expression of the gradient.
Now, after we have this expression,
then we can compute what is the gradient,
then utilize this gradient to update the network parameter.
Right, then this is expression of the gradient.
Now, from this expression of the gradient,
of course, we need to know what is the derivative
of this activation function.
Here, give an example, if the activation function
is this thing more than function,
we can very easily see what is its derivative
against the q, right?
It is this expression.
This is just very easily, we can get this one.
And it happened to be this one,
it's just a times fq one minus fq.
So we just utilize the value of fq
to multiply them together to produce the value
of its derivative.
Now, the Hinton core is a back propagation,
but in fact, it's just the gradient descent method.
To compute the gradient descent method,
we just need the mathematical expression of the gradient.
The gradient is the differentiation.
If we utilize the chain rule of the differentiation,
we can very easily get the definition
of the gradient.
But basically, conceptually,
it is some kind of the back propagation,
because from here, we can see,
from where we can see it.
Okay.
We need to update the parameter of the first name
So the update of the first name,
basically it is, we need the gradient of the mean square arrow.
Whereas the mean square arrow,
this is the mean square arrow of the last name, right?
Then we can see this is the mean square arrow
of the last name.
Now, if we multiply all this together,
this part is the mean square arrow of the first name.
So we transfer the arrow in the second name
to the, this is the arrow of the second name,
to the arrow of the first name.
Okay.
So we transfer the arrow from second name to first name.
So we back propagate the arrow from last name
to the previous name, and then to the previous name.
This is just a physical meaning,
but mathematically it is just a chance rule
to get its differentiation.
So here we call this learning is called back propagation
because we have two process in training the network.
The first process feed forward,
given the current parameter of the network,
give a training sample,
we need to compute what is output nail by nail.
This is the information from the input feed forward
to the output.
And then after that we need to learning.
Then the learning is from the last nail we get the arrow
because we compile the output with the ground tools.
Then we get the arrow.
Then to update the networks parameter,
we need to transfer the arrow from last nail
to the previous nail.
So this is the arrow signal we are back propagate from
and of the network to the previous nails.
So because of that, this is called back propagation method.
Now because of that,
the Hinton utilized this to train the network in 1980s.
40 years after the research of the neural network,
then the neural network research becomes very hard topic.
In 1980s, it's very hard topic,
meaning general new general appears
in name of the neural network.
We have a HRP transaction on neural networks.
And another general is called the neural networks
and neural computing and so on.
All of this appear in 1980s
because of this back propagation algorithm.
Enable us to training a multinational neural network.
Because multinational neural network is very powerful.
It can implement any nonlinear function,
any arbitrary nonlinear function.
So the neural network, the capacity is huge.
It is very powerful.
Okay.
Now anyway here introduce the learning process.
So to really train such a network,
we first need to initialize the parameter value.
Then after we initialize parameter value
given the training data, x input and its ground tools
or its desired output for each training sample,
then we can present of this training sample
to the inputs of the network,
then compute what is output.
Utilize the initialized parameter.
Right?
Then we can use that output to compute the error,
then to use this gridding descent method
to update the network parameter.
So we have two process,
phase forward from the input,
compute the output, then from the output,
utilize the output to compute the gradient
to update the parameter of the last layer,
second last layer, the third last layer.
So we have a backward computation.
Of course, this process must be
iterating to many, many times.
Okay.
So this is a back propagation.
Even now the deep learning,
the CNN, the deep learning network
still utilize this back propagation basically.
Of course, we may have some improvement
to solve some problem.
For example, one problem is the local minimum.
Now, because the machine neural network is very powerful,
it is a very highly nonlinear.
So the north function or mean square error
as a function of the parameter,
it is no more just a square, a quadratic function.
It can be very complicated nonlinear curve.
Okay.
Here, just show the north function or mean square error
against one parameter.
If we can plot several times or hundreds of the minimum.
Well, in all this minimum,
some minimum has very high error, right?
Okay.
Now, if the back propagation is basically
just a gradient descent method, okay.
It will update your network parameter
following the direction of the gradient.
Of course, it's opposite direction of the gradient, right?
But in the local minimum, what is gradient?
The gradient is zero.
Okay.
Because in here, we know,
my semester, we know in the minimum point,
the gradient is zero.
So during the learning process,
if the network reach to some parameter value
is a local minimum, then the gradient is zero.
So we don't know how to update further the network.
So this is the big problem.
How to stop the nonlinear network,
much linear network because of this non-low-convenience.
This problem can be also very severe
because we can have many local minimum.
Some local minimum, the error rate,
the error could be much higher than the global minimum.
This is just for one parameter.
You imagine the parameter is not just one.
We have two, three, four, even millions of the parameter.
You can see how complicated is this north function
against its parameter.
Back propagation is gradient descent method.
Gradient method is always a local method.
It updates the parameter based on only a local information.
Okay.
Now, if we just base a local information,
if this curve is very complicated,
somehow it is a problem, right?
Now, because of that, thousands of researchers
published hundreds of the research papers
try to solve this problem.
Or at least to improve the algorithm for this problem.
So the researcher has a job to do, right?
Try to use different methods.
Of course, we have some method is called a momentum
or better initialization.
So because my PhD is also in this year,
so somehow my research is also try to solve this problem.
I also published one paper to construct the neural network
so that the construct neural network
has only very close to the global minimum.
Okay, to try to solve this problem.
Okay.
But this is not the only problem of the neural network.
The local minimum, if the network stopped the local minimum,
that means your network is not a real trend
because you cannot further let the error go down, right?
Because it will stop at some local minimum.
This is just under fate your training data.
Okay.
Even you solve this problem to approach to the local minimum
to get a very small north function,
reduce the north function even to almost zero.
But never forget this north function
is measured on the training data.
Does not mean it will perform good
for the unknown test data.
To solve all this local minimum problem
cannot solve the overfitting problem.
Okay, so because of that,
so somehow how to make the training not overfit
your training data one way,
of course there are many different way, right?
It could have many different way.
Every this different way cannot really solve
solve this problem, but somehow it can prove it.
One way is utilize the so-called validation data set.
So the validation data set is,
suppose we use the training data to train the network,
so the north function north value will decrease,
with the increase of the number of the training iteration.
Okay.
But if we train this network very long,
it could overfit your training data.
That means the test data could be somehow north
and the test data could be much higher than your training data.
So that your training network is useless
because the purpose of the training network
is never for your training data.
It is work for your test data.
Okay, so to overcome this problem,
we can try to somehow stop the training at some position,
not the small value of the north value of the training data,
but the small value of some other data,
not used in the training.
So we call this is a validation data.
The validation data we are not used in the training,
but we use it to compute what is the north,
what is for example, mean square aero.
Then if we compute it or find it at this number
of the iteration, that validation data go to the minimum,
if we further training it,
the validation aero will increase.
Then we can stop the training at here.
Hope this can cause the north
on the test data is also small.
Okay, so this will partially solve
the overfitting problem
because the validation data is not used in the training.
But still your validation data
and the test data is also different.
We can still cannot guarantee
it will perform good for your test data.
By the way, don't forget,
the validation data is also part of the training data
because the validation data to say how is the performance
of the validation data,
we must know the ground truth of the validation data.
Okay, so that means how to get the validation data.
After we have a training data set,
we purposely to put part of this training data,
not use in the training.
We use a subset of the training data
to we call it as a validation data,
not used in the training,
but used as to see compute what is the north value
and this data not used in the training.
So the validation data is part of your training data.
Okay, it may also be different from your test data.
Now one good sense is anyway,
we can solve the training at some small value of the north
and some data not used in the training.
We hope this can partially solve
this overfitting problem, right?
Okay, now here I will show what is the real problem
of the neural network.
Neural network is very powerful because of that,
the people is very exciting in 1980s and the 1990s.
Because it's so powerful,
it seems a neural network can solve every problem.
Every machine learning problem,
we can always use the neural network
because neural network is very powerful,
it can implement any nonlinear function.
So it is a so-called universal approximator,
it can approximate any nonlinear function.
So people are very exciting,
but somehow people forget what is the problem
of the overfitting.
Overfitting can be very serious.
Here give an example to show what is overfitting.
Now suppose in the function regression
or the classification,
the real optimal class boundary is this curve.
Okay, but it is unknown, right?
We need to use the training data
to learn this nonlinear curve.
But the training data is only discrete point.
Whatever huge number of the training data,
it must be discrete.
But we need to learn a continuous curve
because the learned curve should utilize for the test data.
Test data can be any value, we don't know, right?
So to handle the test data,
we must have a continuous curve.
Now to learn this continuous curve,
we have only the training data is a discrete point.
Suppose we have such point is a training data.
It's same as the ground truth.
Ground truth is this continuous curve, right?
How to use this discrete point of the data
to learn this continuous curve?
Now if we just use a single layer of the network,
it can only be a linear class field.
The class boundary can only be a line, right?
So if we use just a single layer network,
then the network can just learn
what is the best line to feed your training data.
Then your mental result will be this straight line.
Then this learning result to get this straight line
is under feed your training data
because we have large arrow, right?
Okay, the mental results compared to the ground truth
training data, the arrow could be very large.
So this is under feeding.
Now if we use multi-layer,
so increase the capability of the network, okay?
So that the network can implement the nonlinear function,
then it could be we will learn somehow a curve,
a nonlinear curve in state of just a straight line.
Learn from this training data.
We can see the arrow will be smaller, right?
It will be more close to the training data,
compared to this straight line.
So the north value or the mean square arrow
of this green curve will be much smaller
than this straight line.
So this is good, right?
But we still have some arrow, right?
We still have some arrow, even use this curve.
Now, if the network is very, very powerful,
it can implement a very highly nonlinear function.
It can make your north function decrease
to the minimum zero.
Of course north function usually is non-negative, right?
So that means all training data is perfect in your learning.
Then it will form this red curve.
Now this red curve goes through all training data.
That means the arrow is zero.
The mean square arrow is zero.
But is this red curve better than green curve or not
in terms of the whole continuous space?
It can, if we utilize this green curve,
or this red curve, the arrow on your training data is zero.
It can perform worse on your training data,
even worse than this straight line.
We can imagine it is pretty possible, right?
Such a powerful sense can be worse
than a simple single nail just to form a straight line.
This is a great problem of the neural network,
although it is very powerful.
So this is why we can get the conclusion
of this traditional neural network.
It is very powerful.
The two nails, just use two nails,
can implement anything, can solve any problem.
But this is just the capability.
To solve any problem just means we can solve any problem
on your training data,
because we can only measure the training data.
Test data is unknown, it's not on,
it's unavailable in the training.
So this will cause overfitting problem.
And this overfitting problem, in my opinion,
is much, much severe problem.
Difficult problem than underfitting.
Because if it is underfitting,
we know the arrow is high.
Then we can always try to reduce the arrow
on the training data, right?
To improve the underfitting.
But overfitting problem we don't know.
We only have the training data.
We never know if it somehow overfits your training data.
Can perform very poorly on your unknown tested data.
So this is why the neural network,
although it is powerful in 1980s,
people are very exciting.
So it caused a huge size of the research community
working in neural network.
But after 10 years or 20 years research,
people found neural network is a usefulness.
Although it is very powerful,
it can perform very highly complicated function,
but the neural network cannot solve the real problem.
If we utilize the neural network to the real problem,
it cannot, always cannot work.
For tested data, some tested data in the practice
just slightly different from the training data,
then the result is wrong.
Okay, so this is why we have the problem.
The neural network research start from 1950s,
but more than 40 years, it is just starting single layer.
Because people find that multi-layer is there's no solution.
Okay, then in the 1980s,
Hinton invented the back propagation
to make multi-layer perceptron,
multi-layer network is trainable.
We can train the multi-layer network.
And the multi-layer network is so powerful,
just two layers can be used to solve any problem.
Then the neural network research activity
goes very, very hard in the 19th and the start of the 2000s.
But gradually the neural network research activity
go down, go down, go down, go to the middle of the 2000s.
Almost nobody care about the neural network.
In this years, okay, the top conference, CVTR
and the top general, where reject all paper,
if your paper submission is research on the neural network.
People don't believe the neural network
because it cannot solve the real problem.
But then Hinton invented the convolutional neural network.
And then people find the use the thing
and solve the real problem, use the real image.
For example, image net, a huge data set.
If we use this convolutional neural network,
train the network, it can work very well
on the unknown test image.
The accuracy on the test image
were increased from for example,
just 70% to 95%.
Such a big change is really revolution
in the machine learning.
So CNN is a real revolution of the machine learning
so that the deep learning activity go to high.
Now it must be in this position.
This curve is a curve I copy from some media
somehow eight years ago.
Okay, in that year people think that the deep learning
will go to some, will also somehow stay at some platform.
But in fact, now the deep learning go to very high.
Because it really solves the real problem.
Okay, so because of the CNN,
because of the deep learning,
now we have the current artificial intelligence AI.
So after break we were studying how the CNN
solves the problem of the Martina NEO network, MAOQ.
Okay, so we now have 15 minutes or 20 minutes of the break.
I believe you can collect your quiz paper from your TA.
Okay, we have 20 minutes of the break now.
Thank you.
Okay, so I think we can resume our lecture.
Now, deep learning becomes a so hot topic.
or AI system where utilize the deep learning,
use some saying all the transformer
as the machine learning part in the AI system.
Okay, so if we study our recondition system
in the traditional way,
we have several different steps
to complete the recondition task, right?
Because in the traditional way,
we need pre-processing feature extraction,
dimension reduction, and classification, and so on.
Then in all these different steps,
most of the steps are determined by the human knowledge,
are designed by the human,
such as some kind of the handcrafted feature
is designed by our human.
Only in the last stage classification
use the training data to estimate some parameter
in the class field.
Okay, but now because of this deep learning
perform very well,
now it is the machine learning is not just
for the last stage of the recondition system.
Now the machine learning will come to from last stage
up to the previous stage
and at the end up to the beginnings.
So in the deep learning area,
we have the so-called end-to-end system.
That means all the system use the machine learning.
Give any raw data input into the system.
We just input it into a deep learning network.
So the deep learning network can perform all this
pre-processing feature extraction, dimension reduction,
and classification to get the final result,
to produce a so-called end-to-end system.
Now how this machine learning is,
the deep learning is so powerful.
Let's see, it seems we don't need our human knowledge
to design the handcrafted feature.
And so every task is performed by the network,
neural network by the machine learning.
Now if in such a way,
then that means everything can be done by machine,
learn from the training data.
Where is our human knowledge?
Our human is useless.
Everything can be done by the machine learning from the data.
Right?
But in fact, it is not true.
The human knowledge still play a very important role
in the system, even in the machine learning system.
Now to understand that,
we need to understand what is a machine learning.
And then what is the problem of the traditional neural network
or traditional machine learning?
Then we can understand how this deep learning
will solve the problem.
Okay, so as I mentioned that the machine learning
is used some discrete finite number of the training data
to estimate a function that map the input to the output.
We need a prediction, right?
Okay, but XI and YI in the training data,
even we have large number of the training data,
it is still discrete or finite.
We need a continuous function.
Okay, so use the training data,
we can minimize some kind of the north function,
such as the mean square error.
But this north function can only measure it
on your training data.
Okay, so what we get is the estimate of this F, F hat.
Then the neural network is some kind
of the parametric approach.
We have a network, we have a network,
that means we have the mathematic model,
then we use the training data to estimate
all these parameters.
Okay, so all this network, in fact,
in the mathematic form is just this formula.
Okay, they are equivalent, right?
Input, multiply by written matrix goes
through a activation function, then repeat
in the next layer, repeat in the next layer and again.
So this mathematic model will include all network structure
of the fully connected, matinee neural networks.
Well, this H is activation function.
Now, to study what is, how this CNN,
as a deep learning software problem
of the traditional neural network,
we need first to see what is the main problem
of the neural network.
Although the neural network, the problem
of the neural network is not,
neural network is not powerful.
No, neural network is very powerful.
So the problem is not the underfitting your training data.
You use the training data, we can always try,
a neural network decrease the north function
to make the error almost zero, okay?
Well, we can always try to do that,
but this is only on the training data.
And we have a theory study that the two layers
is already sufficient to implement
any highly nonlinear function.
Then we have the deep learning.
What means the deep learning?
Deep learning in fact is just means this aim,
the number of the layers is much more than two.
It can be several times, several hundreds.
Now the large model could have thousand layers.
So why we need so many layers
if two layers is already sufficient,
has powerful capability to implement
any nonlinear decision function?
Why we need many layers?
This is because two layers is difficult
to find the solution.
We need much, much layer to find the solution
to minimize the error.
The answer is no, okay?
The fully connected network is already very powerful.
We can always reduce the error,
but the error is on the training data.
So the problem of the neural network
is not its limited capability.
The problem of the neural network is overfitting.
Here I will show an example, what is overfitting?
And how powerful is the neural network?
For example, in the 1990s,
somehow the people always study this problem,
the classification problem.
So the data is just a two-dimensional.
Okay, two-dimensional data is just one point
in the two-dimensional space, right?
So here we have, each point is one sample.
So we have, this sample has two class.
The white point is the sample of one class,
black point is sample of another class.
So we can see the white sample,
white class and black class,
they are spiral, almost fully overlapped.
Now, to do the classification,
to classify the black dot from the white dot,
then the class boundary must be very highly nonlinear.
It must be also a spiral, right?
Between these two class of the data.
Now, if we use this data to train a neural network,
even just two layers of the neural network,
we have no problem to train the neural network
that classify all this training data perfect, correct,
arrow free, although we need a very large data.
Very highly nonlinear decision boundary, right?
But we have no problem to train
just two layers network to perfectly classify
all this data into two class.
But if we look at what is the decision boundary
or decision region, we can see this three different solution
of the three neural network to get the decision boundary
or decision region.
We can see the decision region is very funny.
From this decision region,
we can see that some decision boundary
is very close to the training data.
That means if the test data is just slightly different
from the training data,
then immediately the classification result
and the test data will be wrong.
Although it classify all training data correct,
does not mean it can perform well for the test data, right?
So this is a problem of the overfitting.
So if we understand this,
the biggest problem of the traditional neural network
is this overfitting,
then we can understand how the Cn can solve this problem.
To study how the Cn to solve this problem,
we need to see that for this overfitting problem,
what is the general rule idea
to solve this overfitting problem?
How to solve this overfitting problem?
The overfitting problem cannot solve
based on the information of your training data.
Because in the training data,
we already have the north function.
The training process is reduced the north function, right?
So the training data does not get the information
of the test data.
So in the training process,
we cannot solve the overfitting problem.
Overfitting problem cannot be based on the information
on the training data to solve it.
Then to solve the overfitting,
in my opinion,
we must utilize some of our human knowledge
to do the regularization in the training process.
So what means regularization?
Regularization is use our human knowledge
to constrain your machine learning,
not net the machine freely learn from the training data,
to constrain the learning or restrict the learning.
This is some kind of the so-called regularization.
This regularization cannot be based on the training data,
must be based on our human to design the model
to constrain the machine learn from the training data.
Now, before we go to the sitting end,
we will see what is the other possible way
to do the regularization.
Here, I just show some examples.
For example, the machine learning or training
is to minimize your north function, right?
Okay, or here is a mean square arrow.
Now, this is a machine learning,
the purpose of the machine is always to make this decrease
to decrease the value of the north function.
Now, during the learning process,
we can constrain the net function f hat
to certain boundary.
For example, we constrain the f must be a linear function.
Okay, so this is one way to do the regularization
to constrain the machine,
net function must be a linear function
or must be just a classic function.
It is possible we can constrain the linear function
or none a classic function.
This is some kind of the regularization.
Now, another example of the regularization is
we can use the dimension learning reduction
to first reduce the high dimensional data
into a no dimension.
And then after that, to net machine to learn,
this to reduce this north function only
in the no dimensional space.
So the dimension learning reduction, in fact,
can take a role of the regularization
to recognize the machine learning.
Okay, not to net the machine freely,
but to learn everything the machine wants
from the training data.
Now, the last way is somehow during the optimization
or machine learning process to minimize the north function,
we don't just minimize the north.
We can utilize some form of the learned,
some regularization of the learned function f hat
to minimize them at the same time.
For example, we can make the coefficient of the function
or the parameter of the function is a sparse,
such as sparse coding or sparse representation.
This is also a very hot research topic
before the deep learning.
Okay, before the deep learning in the machine learning area,
we have a hot research topic.
One is sparse coding,
another is dimension learning reduction.
Although many research working in this area
don't aware of what is the purpose
of the dimension learning reduction or sparse coding,
in my opinion, they will take some role of the regularization
to make the machine learn the result
not to overfeed your training data.
Then let's see what is the solution of the CNN.
Now to find how the CNN solves the problem
of this multi-nuclear neural network or MARP,
we need to study what is the difference
between the CNN and the MARP, right?
Then to study the difference between the CNN and MARP,
we will simplify the MARP to just one relation,
O equals to W transpose X.
Although the MARP has this multi-nuclear structure,
but as I mentioned that all this network mathematically
can be expressed by this one, right?
Now from this one, we can say each layer,
every layer is always the same model,
input multiplied by a weak matrix
goes through a activation function, gets the output.
For input K, and output K is K plus one.
So this is applied to every layer,
every layer of the network.
So we only study one layer.
Okay, we can study just one,
because all layer are identical,
the mathematical model are identical.
Well, in one layer of the network,
it comes output and input, right?
So the most important sense is this multiplication,
matrix multiplication,
because this activation function, it is not learnable.
The activation function is fixed.
The activation function is not learned from the training data.
The learned parameter is just this W, okay?
So the key role of this neural network
is just the input vector multiplied by a matrix,
because after that it's just go through
a fixed non-linear function.
This activation function is fixed,
not learnable, not learn from the training data.
It's nothing to do with what is your training data.
Okay, the learnable part is just this W.
This W is a matrix.
It contains all parameter of one layers, right?
Okay, then we can use,
utilize this relation between input and output
to represent the basic function of a multi-layer neural network.
Then what is the thing?
Now, of course, we know the structure of the CNN,
because CNN is first very successfully utilized
in the image processing, image recognition.
So we represent the CNN in terms of recognize the image.
Now, I just very quickly go through the principle
of the CNN.
Okay, so basically from here we can say
given an input image,
if we have a filter just a small three by three filter,
if we need apply this filter to the image,
then of course we can produce the output image, right?
Given a filter, then the filter running through all position
apply to the input image or get the output image.
Of course, the relation of the output image
and the input image is a convolution.
The input image convolve with the filter mask,
then produce the output image, right?
Now, given an input image and a filter,
we can produce one output image.
If we use many different filter apply
to the same input image,
then we can produce many output,
different output image, right?
Okay, so this is a convolution.
In the CNN, the convolutional layer
is just an input image goes through a filter
to produce the output image.
Of course, we can produce many output image,
use different filter.
And all this filter parameter, this filter mask
is not designed by our human,
is learned from the training data.
Okay, then this is a convolutional layer.
Now, from here we can say for the convolutional layer,
one input map can produce multiple output map.
A map is just an image, right?
Here we call it the map, okay?
Then we increase the number of the image,
we can increase to a very large number of the image, right?
So the information in the output image
could be redundant, okay?
So because we increase the number of the image
in this convolution process,
then we can reduce the size of the image.
So we can have a so-called pooling layer.
Here I show a pooling layer is a two by two,
it's just for every two by two window,
we take one pixel, we take the maximum value,
we then this two by two neighborhood,
so that we're sampling the image
into the half of the size.
This is a pooling, okay?
One way to do the pooling is the maximum pooling,
we take the maximum value,
we then a small window to just take one pixel value.
So this is the pooling.
The pooling will reduce the size of the image
or reduce the size of the map, right?
Now, if we use the convolution that is a field output
and then to do the pooling to reduce the map size,
then after several layers,
we can produce many output image or output map.
For example, here is a 500,
more than 500 output image,
but each image or map, the size is reduced
by could be 15 by 15 or even smaller.
Okay, so this is the process of the convolutional neural network.
This is a convolution part.
After that, of course,
at the end we need to do a classification.
At the beginning, people also use the two layers
or multi-layer neural network or fully connected network
to do the classification.
But now, because the convolution layer is very powerful,
after that, the class, final layer is just a linear
combination.
We can do the classification.
We don't need the neural network.
We just use a linear classifier.
It can classify the output feature
of the convolution layer very well.
So you can ignore this part of the convolution
of the neural network.
We can just use a very simple linear classifier, no problem.
Now, the very powerful one of the convolution neural network
is this convolution and the convolution and so on, right?
To get the output from the input go to a theater.
Now, of course, we have the pooling layer reduce the size.
Now, what is the role of this one?
We first need to understand the convolution
is not exactly same as the convolution
in the image processing or single processing,
but very similar.
One difference is in the convolution,
it is not very strictly convolution
because as I mentioned that for all neural network,
the output must have a bias.
Any field, besides we have for example,
three by three field, we have the three by three field
mask convolve with the input,
we must also use a bias.
Okay, so don't forget the bias.
This is very important, okay?
Another difference is that usually we apply the convolution,
apply the field only to one image, right?
But here the input could have multiple image.
We need all this multiple image together go to a theater.
Okay, well for all different image,
in terms of the theater, it is fully connected.
So this convolution process in fact mathematically
can write in this one.
Okay, given the input is image xij is one image,
but we have many image or many map as an input, right?
So we have xijk, i and j is a different spatial position,
k is a different channel or different image, different map.
This one goes through the convolution process,
the produce yijk, where ij same is the position,
spatial position, different picture,
k is a different image or different channel.
Okay, now then to produce the output image or output map,
the i and the j is a spatial position, right?
This i and the j is utilized in the convolution.
So w a m multiplied i minus a j minus a m.
This is a formula of the convolution, right?
And then the k and n here is the sum overall
so that along the channel it is fully connected.
Okay, fully connected, but spatially it's just
connect a local area of the, within the theater window.
Okay, so anyway, this is a mathematical expression
of the input output and the input
of the convolutional layer, right?
Now this convolution just slightly different
from the normal convolution for the image processing
or singular processing, but anyway each way,
in terms of the i and the j, the spatial position,
it is a really a convolution process or fielding process.
Now, because we have multiple inputs into the theater,
so in this kind of the convolution,
it is, we could select or we could choose a theater,
the spatial size is just one by one, one by one.
So in the convolutional neural network,
it will make sense we have so-called one by one convolution.
One by one convolution is just spatially,
it is just one point from input come to the output,
but one point is just spatially one point, okay?
But we can combine, we combine different channel,
use a different filter parameter along different channel.
It's still a weighted sound, right?
So here we understand we can use one by one convolution.
Okay, now in this network structure of the convolution,
basically the network structure,
it seems architecture different from the fully connection
network and then the output and the input,
basically it is some kind of the convolution, right?
We also use a simple nonlinear function
and we also somehow reduce the size.
We also utilize many layers,
but all this is not very critical.
The critical one is the convolution.
So to see the difference between the Cn and MaRp
is to study the difference between the convolution
and fully connect the weighted summation.
Okay, so here we can study the one dimensional case.
Suppose we can give even the input
is a two dimensional image, right?
We can always arrange all this picture into one vector.
Okay, then we can, or mathematically it is possible
to even for the two dimensional image,
we can use a one vector to represent it.
For example, we can arrange all these two dimensional
picture into just one nonvectors.
Okay, so because we want to compile the difference
between the fully connected network
and the convolution network.
So that means if we study just one dimensional convolution,
then what is the difference between the convolution
and the MaRp?
Now we will study the definition of the convolution.
For all convolutional layer,
the output picture is the input convolve
with the filter parameter.
This is the convolution.
Well, from the definition, this is a convolution.
Okay, from this definition of the convolution,
we can see if we choose a small convolution kernel,
that means this G is only a few nonzero element.
If we, the filter window is small,
but we can always increase the filter window
to a same size as the X,
but we take the zero value as the filter parameter.
They are equivalent.
So it is not difficult to say
that the convolution process in fact is also a weighted sum.
Only this weighted sum is within the filter window.
Within the filter window is weighted sum.
If we extend the filter window
into the same size of the input,
then this weighted sum can be right as
two vector multiplied together.
It's a convolution.
But this vector of the filter, we have meaning zero.
Only within the filter window,
it is nonzero filter parameter.
Outside of the window is zero.
But we can still express the convolution result
by the multiplication of the two vector.
Now, if we're doing so, we can see
this multiplication of the two vector,
the weighted vector or the filter parameter
and all input multiplied together
just produce a single pixel output.
A single output, right?
Now for different J, then this WJ will be different.
Then from the convolution process,
we know that for different J is we move
this filter window into different position.
So what I want to say is the convolution
can be represented by the multiplication
of the two vectors.
One vector is input, include all input value component.
A lot of vector is a vector of the filter parameter.
We extend the filter parameter
outside of the filter window by zero, right?
So this vector multiplied, this input vector
will produce a single output.
This is the same as a convolution,
but produce a single output.
For other output is just move this filter window
into different position.
So if we shift or translate this filter window
into different position,
then we'll produce different output J.
Now, if we want to put all this output J
for different J into one vector,
okay, then we need have mainly this WJ
for this filter at a different position.
So we have a matrix.
This matrix, each column is the filter at specific position.
Different column is same filter at a different position.
Then this matrix multiplied by input
will produce the output vector.
This output vector indicate all output of one image
because one image produced by one filter.
Okay, so we can see that for one output map
can be also represent by input multiplied by
weighting matrix.
Now for other output image use different filter.
We can just put all this different matrix,
this kind of the matrix,
but this G are different to increase size of this W.
Then all output, even different map
can be expressed by the input multiplied by matrix.
But this matrix is come from mainly this sub matrix.
Where each matrix, sub matrix is one filter.
Where one filter indicate within the filter window,
small window, it is non-zero,
or other outside it is zero
because this size is same as the size of the input image.
The filter window is very small.
Now the different output is just moving this filter window
into different position.
Then we can express the convolution network.
The output is also the input multiplied by weighting matrix.
So in such a way we can see that both the convolutional
layer and the fully connected layer, the MARP,
both can be represent by a same mathematical expression.
But what is the difference?
If we express the output from the input
by same mathematical expression,
then what is this W for?
What is this W for the MARP?
What is this W for convolutional layer?
For MARP, all element in this W
is learned from the training data.
Well, for the convolution network,
this W is in this shape.
Okay, so that means for the convolutional layer,
this transform matrix W, we have many zeros.
We force the network parameter zero,
not learned from the training data.
And even the learned from the training data filter
filter parameter, we make this same filter,
same parameter repeat in many different column.
Okay, all of these are exactly same,
learned from the training data.
This is the difference between the convolution
and the fully connected layer.
Now from here, we can see what is the difference.
First of all, we see the same is just a simplified MARP.
We simplify the learned parameter
into very sparse network, sparse matrix.
We force many element not learned from the training data,
force them into a zero.
We only need a few parameter learned from the training data.
And this few parameter will further constrain them,
must be identical same.
This is a very strong regularization.
We recognize this machine learning,
the way of the machine learning.
Okay, force the machine learning following this rule
to learn from the training data.
So this thing is to simplify this freely learned network
into a constrained network to learn from the training data.
The simplification is some kind of the regularization.
This regularization will not have the parameter
not learned from the training data,
is some kind of the regularization.
This effect is somehow reduce the overfitting problem.
Okay, now how this thing is different
from the traditional neural network before we go to,
further go to this regularization,
it will reduce the overfitting.
We first introduce some nice property of the CNN.
So first the CNN is some kind of a filter, right?
Output is input goes through a filter,
where the filter is a small window.
So this small filter size will force all other parameter
outside of the filter window zero to produce the output, right?
So because of that, the output of CNN
always captures the local structure of the input image.
Because given an input image,
we have many local structure,
such as corner, edge, and the different shape,
the shape of the small blob, right?
So a filter where output will capture this local structure.
How it captures a local structure?
Because the filter is learned from the training data, right?
The convolution in fact mathematically
is the same as the correlation.
So because it is a correlation,
then somehow the filter parameter,
filter is also a small image.
It will learn from the training data
so that the filter mask is similar to some local structure.
So that the output of the filter in the output image
will be much value if the filter move to some place,
the structure is same as the filter structure.
Okay, so it will capture the local structure.
If the filter is trained from a particular structure,
then it will move the filter into different place.
If the place is in the place, the input image,
the local structure is similar to the filter,
then the output is much.
If for some place, the input image,
local structure is totally different from the filter structure,
then the output will be very small.
Okay, so it will produce such kind of the effect.
So this effect is because the convolution process
is some kind of the correlation.
Now, the filter is learned from the training data,
try to extract the local structure,
such as the corner nine-h curve and so on,
as much as possible.
Here, we can show an example.
Now, as I mentioned that the filter is also an image.
We can display the filter mask,
it's a similar to an image, right?
Now, we have a CNN to
make the CNN learn from the training data.
Now, if the training data is the so-called,
this example shows this training data
is a so-called CT database.
That means all training image is a picture
of taken in the street of a city.
So all the picture consists of many buildings, right?
The buildings has a window, has door,
but the structure of this window and door
are almost corner nine-h and vertical-h,
many such kind of the structure, right?
Now, if we use such kind of the dataset
to train a CNN, we will see the filter mask
in different layer, or we'll show this pattern.
This pattern are similar to the local pattern
of your training data,
the corner-h or the vertical-h.
But if we use the same CNN,
but train this CNN, use another dataset of the image.
This dataset of the image is come from
some kind of the food or fruit,
because the food has many circle, round one.
Then the trained CNN, the filter mask,
the shape are totally different.
We have many circle or some kind of the round structure.
So here we verify that the CNN learning process
is try to learn the filter mask similar
to the most local structure of the training data.
So that after the learning, if we give input to the CNN,
then the CNN will capture the local structure.
If the input image has some local structure similar
to your trained filter, then the output is large.
If the input has no such local structure,
the output of the convolution will produce a small value.
Okay, so this is why we call,
we say that the CNN will capture this local structure.
Well, local structure is very important
to identify the different content of the image.
Now, also the CNN, one filter is one local structure.
Because one local structure in the input image
may appear in many different positions.
Well, the output image is a convolution of the input
with the filter mask.
So the filter mask in the convolution process,
it will move to all possible position of the input.
So this convolution process will extract
all local structure at a different position, right?
Because it is a convolution process.
Now, input image has multiple structure,
different local structure.
So this is why CNN need produce multiple output image
to learn multiple different filter.
Okay, so this is why the CNN structure
always increase the number of the channel,
increase the number of the output image, right?
So at the end, one output image will have much value
only at the position for this local,
for particular local structure.
So one output map only contains information
of one local structure.
And one local structure cannot appear at everywhere, right?
So that we can to see if the size of the data,
we can reduce the spatial size of the image.
So the size of the spatial map
is always reduce the size.
If we use the maximum pooling,
the reduced size image always keeps a large output,
where we move the small output.
So it will keep the local structure
and remove the information where there's no,
such local structure show in the filter mask, right?
So this is some kind of the good property of the,
of the CNN.
Of course, this is somehow we show that the pooling process
will need to some kind of the spatial insensitivity
because after we pooling to produce a small image, right?
A small map.
Then this map where one map will capture
the specific local structure at a different position.
But because we have a small map,
so the exact position of this local structure
does not show in this small map.
Okay, it will reduce the spatial sensitivity of the image.
Well, the spatial sensitivity reduce it is good
for the recognition because as I mentioned that,
the image has large variation, right?
So for different image,
the same structure may appear into different position.
So we need to reduce the spatial sensitivity
of some local structure.
This is also implemented by the CNN.
Now, why is this deep learning needs a mailing nails?
First, the structure, local structure can have small scale,
can have large scale.
If we use a small window, a small filter mask,
we can only extract the small scale of the structure.
For a large scale of the structure,
we need a large filter, right?
Then this large filter can be implemented
by multi-mails of the convolution
because if one filter has three by three window,
then after that, then to do the three by three window,
then effectively we have a five by five filter window.
Then next three by three,
then the effective filter window is seven by seven.
So we use multiple layers.
We can capture the structure of small scale
in the low level of the output
and large scale in the high level of the output.
So we can capture many different scale
of the features and structures of the image.
And also, if we want to learn a very complex functions,
if we directly learn these complex functions,
it will always cause the problem.
Overfitting or into the local minimum
or somehow the solution cannot really find
a reasonable solution.
Well, the same is each layer is just a simple convolution.
The activation function is almost linear, right?
So each layer only learn a very small part of the information
so that we need a large number of the layer
to learn the information of the training data progressively,
slowly one by one to learn the information.
Okay, so that it's much more stable.
Now at the end, I will address the,
so the renew function is a very simple nonlinear function,
right?
So each layer is very simple.
It only learn a small amount of the information
so that we have many layers together
to get a complex information.
Well, this complex information is more realistic
information of the image because each layer,
it is just a convolution,
it's just capture some kind of the image features.
Well, this renew activation function is very simple.
It's enable, it's possible we can train this network
to have a very large number of the layers
because to separate different layer,
we just use a nonlinear function
almost the same as a linear function, right?
But we must use a nonlinear function.
Otherwise the two layers is just affecting one layer.
Now, the very critical point is how this thing
and really solve the overfitting problem.
Now, as I mentioned that in the fully connection network,
the waiting metrics, every element is learned from the data.
That means in this, in the MLP,
one parameter is fixed to link one input pixel
with one output pixel.
This link is fixed, okay?
So that in the training process,
one training image, only one pixel
of the training image are used
to determine one single parameter, okay?
So one parameter only determined by some specific pixel
of the input image.
Well, in the convolutional network,
it is a filter, it is a convolution, okay?
This convolution in terms of the prediction
or filter the input image to produce the output image,
it appears to be nothing new, right?
But this concept in the machine learning,
it will bring big difference.
Because in the learning process,
the parameter will move into all positions.
That means one parameter will move into all pixel.
Then in the learning process,
then all pixels of an image is used
to determine a single parameter.
Now, this is the critical difference
of CNN learning and the MLP learning.
I hope you understand, right?
Because a single parameter in the CNN,
we are moving to all positions,
moving to go through all pixels.
Then in the training process,
also it will move into all pixels.
So each parameter moving to all pixels,
then in the training, all pixels is participate
to training a single parameter.
This greatly overcome that the learned parameter
will over-fit to a specific position.
Okay?
Because in the learning process,
each parameter will move into all positions.
So all positions in the training
were used to determine a single parameter.
This is the big difference.
So that the convolution moving the parameter,
the field parameter goes through all positions
in the training, that means all position information
is together utilized to determine
what is the good parameter.
Now, because of that, in the learning process,
the learning of the CNN and the learning of the MLP
are totally different, right?
This makes a big difference between the performance
of the CNN and the MLP.
So this is why the MLP is over-fitting the training data,
but CNN will not over-fit your training data.
Okay, now, because next week will be,
I completed this topic,
next week I will study some limitation of the CNN
and introduce the transformer.
Okay, this transformer is currently the best model
in the deep learning model.
So we will study what is a transformer.
Now, because next week is the last week for my lecture, right?
So next week I want you to solve any doubt
or questions of you for the final exam.
So before the next week comes, you can raise your questions.
So this week I will talk about a little about
the final exam so that if you have the problem
or questions we can discuss in next week,
the final week of my lecture.
Okay, now here I will,
what I want to do here is try to reduce the scope
of the final exam so that you don't need to spend
much time to prepare the final exam
because I know all of you take three or four courses.
So it is a very heavy work note for you, right?
Okay, so here I try to somehow reduce the scope
of the final exam so that you can just focus
on the topic included in the final exam.
Okay, to save your time, right?
So basically in the final exam,
the question is only related to very fundamental questions.
Okay, based on your understanding of the mainstream
of the theory, the mainstream of the concept
so don't come to some very complicated sense, okay?
If you really cannot understand it, you just forget it.
Try to understand what you can
and try to understand the mainstream,
the big theory or the theory we needed
to different parts of this topic, okay?
So basically the final exam only focus on the basic concept.
Okay, don't be troubled by some specific technique
or some specific tricks, okay?
We only test your understanding of the big pictures
in this course.
Okay, now in terms of the topics,
in the beginning I missed out the 15 topics of this course,
right?
Of course the final four topics were taught,
were teached by some other lectures.
I will stop at the next week at the topic in even.
So I will talk about in these topics
what were exclude from the final exam
so that you just focus on three or four topics.
Okay, now the first topic is just fundamentals.
So this is not including the final exam.
Now the second topic, AI-SIS system and transforms.
Now we know the filter, the convolution
is extremely important even for deep learning.
So I want have one question also in this topic,
AI-SIS system and transform.
Of course in this topic, the most important sense
is convolution and the filter, right?
So you must really understand what is the filter process?
Okay, how to do the convolution
from the input to produce the output?
Okay, so the second topic will be include
in the final exam.
Now the topic three, image denoising and enhancement.
Now in our quiz, we already have one question,
the first one equalization, right?
So the third topic we are not include in the final exam
because in the quiz we already test part of this one, right?
Now next one, the morphological image processing.
This one in this year were exclude from the final exam.
You don't need to prepare this morphological image processing
for your final exam.
Okay, my philosophy is not to learn a lot of the sense
is you focus on some topic you really understand,
go too deep inside.
So I have no problem to just reduce the scope
of the final exam to a very small part.
No problem, you just focus on that,
try to really understand this topic.
Okay, so morphological image processing
were exclude from the final exam.
Now next one, topic five is basically help you
to intuitively understand the recondition process, right?
This is some kind of introduction.
So this is not include in the final exam.
Next one, MAP decision and class fear.
This is already, I already test you in the quiz, right?
So in the final exam I will not use this topic.
Okay, now next one start estimation and machine learning
for this year is also not included in the final exam.
The handcraft feature generation and feature selection
such as this, this Wila-Jong's approach
and this Ada Boost is quite somehow tedious.
So you don't care about this one to prepare your final exam.
Now we show data dimension reduction
and the feature extraction, although it is the topic
of the assignment, okay, but it's still very important.
Then this topic is in the final exam.
Then neural network and deep learning CNN and transformer.
As I mentioned that the final exam is only focused
on the basic concept.
Let you really understand the basic concept.
So here the transformer one we are not including
the final exam.
So that means the next week, the lecture content
of the next week we are not including the final exam.
So my part, the remaining is only three topic,
very small, very narrow topic, right?
So in the final exam you have four questions
to complete answer the four questions within three hours.
Okay, each question is 25 marks together, 100 marks.
Of course your final exam is closed booked test.
So for the four questions, the question one
come from the AOSI system and transform.
Question two come from the dimensionality reduction
and the feature extraction.
Okay, then question three come from the general
neural network and CNN.
This tonight's lecture.
So this is three questions from my part.
Now from the last four topics because it is not a lecture
by me but another one.
So this question I cannot give out what is,
we come from which topic.
But I just tell you the question four is also
very, very basic one.
It could be related to both video and 3D
but a very simple basic questions.
You just understand the very fundamental one, okay?
Now although we also use this dimensionality reduction
in both assignment and the final exam
but for the assignment it's most likely you do the programming
to get the result to compare the result, right?
The program you may utilize others program
or just use the library use the function.
So because of that in the final exam,
sorry for the final exam for this topic
is really very basic ones of the dimensionality reduction.
What is the very fundamental basic ones?
Minial algebra, right?
Matrix multiplication.
What is the meaning of the matrix multiplication?
How to do the reduced dimension?
What is the projection of the data to some
no dimensional space?
How to express them in a linear algebra, right?
Then in the linear algebra,
what is the concept of the covariance and the variance?
Okay, all of this very simple, basic one
is very important where I be tested in question two.
Okay.
I think that's about all for the final exam, right?
So if you have further concern about the final exam
you can raise your question or discuss with me next week.
Okay, my final lecture in the next week.
Okay, so that's all for tonight, thank you.
Thank you.
armored
you