you
You
All available except for one view.
there's rear seats.
.
Okay, good evening. There's a set of the
machine review for video.
So, for machine vision for video, right, so there covers quite a lot of topics and here
I just list a few.
And actually in, I think actually in in-dutch application, right, so much of the case in
recognition related tasks are essentially dealing with videos.
So later I will explain why the in-dutch application is talking about the video instead of pure
image.
So, the first and probably one of the very popular application is object detection and
tracking.
So, and this is going to be one of the important.
Hello?
The second is action recognition, right, so for example you want to shake hand with someone
and you want to wave, right, so it's action recognition, right.
But action recognition is actually quite different from object detection and tracking.
And later we will also have some example.
And the third is probably the video event.
So I see many of us may watch football or watch basketball, right, and when players shoot
the balls, so you want to catch that moment for the shooting event, right, or scoring
event.
And I've seen long time ago when I came here and I also hear some topics like in swimming
pools.
We monitor the swimming pool to detect the possible people who maybe had risk of drawing.
And also for anomaly detection, let's have one example for anomaly detection based on
video.
And of course for besides recognition and understanding task, enhancement is also important
application.
And the last one is the optical flow because it's a processing technology but it's very
related with video, especially in machine side where the computation course is quite
limited.
So I believe there are, there may also have other courses like deep learning or computer
vision.
But in machine vision, one of the special requirement is that I need the AI to be down in the edge
side or at the machine side.
You know where we have a machine, right, so like robotics or mobile phones.
Our computer resources is very limited.
Of course in many applications, the machine can also be connected to the cloud.
But not every application will allow you to have access to the cloud.
And also even if you have the cloud access, right, you may still have some processing at
the machine side.
So let's see one of the examples.
So, I see the first one is the video.
So this top left is a case where we may have some, put some camera in a shopping mall and
try to monitor the entrance of the mall to see how many people is coming to the mall
today, right?
And so how can we achieve the function of counting the people?
So you can see the people walking into the mall.
For example, we can set up a virtual door along this line, for example, right?
We can set up a virtual door from this line, right?
So we may need to count how many people cross the line, right?
Because obviously we cannot count based on images because every minute is right.
So normally we have every second, actually we have many, many frames.
And if you count the person per image, right, so you have an issue or you may count the
people multiple times during one second, right?
So let's say a video normally, hello?
Let's say a video normally have 15 frames or even more per second.
So that means you have to deal with 15 images per image per second.
And from these images, right, you need to count how many people are crossing the lines.
So the second application is surveillance in the power or utility industry or many other
places.
And whereas workers are less, whereas hammers have some suits to be wear, right?
And you may see, right, we have some...
Hello?
We may have some bounding box, right?
So we will detect each person and we will detect whether the person wears a hammer or
wears a uniform.
So this application, so it's the same, it's...
It's the image.
Because you will have one camera put for example at some corner of this scene, right?
And this camera look at the person.
And every second you have many, many frames, right?
So and once you detect a person without hammers, you know there's a...
There is a...
Where the inspection should be reported.
So there's one person without hammers.
But there's a reality, right?
So you give the report, you give the alarm to some central system.
But this person is still there.
He's still no hammer, right?
So in the next second, you still get the same detection.
So that means your system will be keep reporting.
So this definitely there are some issues in terms of implementation.
We will show how this will be solved based on video analysis.
And this is the case where we may use video lens to monitor whether the elderly people
fell down in the toilet or example.
And this is quite different from here.
Because how to describe a video where the people is fell down, which is not that clear
from computer.
It's very easy for us to see it.
But for computer it's not easy.
And this is a case for...
Now I let you watch this video.
You watch this video.
Okay, we can stop here.
So we can see that for each person, right, we have a bounding box that represents detection
of the person, right?
And we also see for each different person, the bounding box has been assigned with different
colors, right?
But from the normal video, right?
So this box is not there.
So what do we...
That means...
It means we are detecting the person and also differentiates different person, right?
And then you look at the video, right?
The bounding box for each person has a unique color.
Right?
So from the video, you can tell so that human detection seems quite accurate, right?
And then you look at this video carefully.
I'm not sure whether you can observe something quite strange.
For example, now you look at the...
Besides the human detection, right, we also detect the face, right?
And this represents the camera.
And this represents the age and the gender of the person.
You look at here, right?
This way is something 18 or 16?
And you look at here, right?
This is 23, right?
Now you're 17, right?
So you observe something very strange, right?
So for each person, it's one person, right?
The fixed person, the age as mentioned is changing from one frame to another frame, right?
Of course, for gender, it's related more accurately, so it stays as a male.
And imagine you are developing a system to do this thing, right?
So from the user point of view, right, what you will be expecting, maybe it's very difficult
for me to tell what's the age of this person.
But what I can know is this person should be the same age, right?
It should be changing.
And you may also see the facial expression.
Sometimes she's happy, sometimes she's neutral, right?
So let's see if there's some change of the facial.
You can see the happy sometimes discussed, right?
So if we are working naturally, so normally my facial should change much, right?
Unless I'm popular to do it or I'm doing something else, I'll suddenly become happy, right?
It's very seldom we will be jumping from, I'm happy and very angry.
Of course, you may feel something, you can fall from that roof.
Then you get angry, it's possible.
But it should be jumping from one state to another state, right?
So this tells us, for video, besides we are looking at the accuracy per image,
we will also look at the accuracy in the time space, right?
So for the human detection, and we try to recognize this as the same person
and assign a same color, right?
So this is actually detailed by the first texture we introduced just now.
Got detection and tracking.
So now let's see how detection and tracking is achieved.
So here we just shoot a short video, actually it's a G file.
And one of my child is walking along the street, right?
This is what we see, right?
But although we can see a video from human,
but we will send this video to computer, right?
So from the computer, it just reads one frame by one frame, right?
So that means what the computer sees is a sequence of images.
Of course, some strong correlation between images.
And a lot of times, people ask, we are also seeing these images.
It's just our human perception makes us feel that we are looking at a video,
like continuous.
But actually, you see a sequence of images.
Now the question is for a computer, if we want the computer to understand this,
what can we do?
Or what should we do?
So this is to support the detection tracking.
So I assume you have some knowledge on how the object detection is done.
Yeah, usually I may have some slides later.
So in order to let the computer to understand this, right?
So we have to object detection.
Of course, in this case here, we are defined as a human object.
So in the first frame, right, so we can detect two persons, right?
And then we apply the same thing to the next slides and the next frame,
third frame, and fourth frame.
And we will get two persons from each frame.
Assuming we can detect the human correctly, right?
So after this one, right, so in our detector,
it's just human and non-human area, right?
So in order for the computer to understand this,
there's some association between the consecutive frames.
We need to tell whether this person and this person is the same person,
or this person and this person is the same person.
And by association, the same person with a unique ID, say person one, right?
So we are actually doing the job called tracking.
So by detecting and tracking, we will get,
and after tracking, we will assign a unique ID for the person.
So we can get the blue line to be the person one,
the yellow line to be the person two.
So counter or the development history, right?
So the first or the earlier technology detection and
tracking is doing it by two steps.
Why is, we do detection first, detection all frames.
The second is compare the detection outcome and
that's called the tracking.
So it's detection followed by tracking.
It's two separate steps.
So we call the step to associate the detection as one or
multiple objects as the tracking.
So, of course, I am not going to detail how the tracking can be done.
There are many, many approaches and some are very traditional approach.
And the typical way you just remember is detection.
But of course, some work may do segmentation, which is not really quite
different from here, but it's just with segmentation, you will try to get
the exact boundary instead of bounding box.
So again, you associate that.
Now you look at this video again, right?
So you understand?
So in order to get assigned the same color, right?
So we actually have down the track to the same person across the frames.
And of course, this task, right, is besides detection and detection,
we also include facial detection and facial landmarks and the age,
the skin, the expressions and also the skeleton of the human.
And also includes a distance estimation.
Or can be considered as part of the detections.
Because for human detection, if you have learned about the object detection,
it's top left corner and bottom right.
And for facial, right, so it's also a point.
So in terms of object detection, image level and also in video level,
there's one of the major differences whether you consider as called temporal continuity.
The approach, I should just now or you can just now, the detection tracking, right?
So we actually didn't consider the temporal continuity in detection.
We detect in each image or each frame is independent, right?
But we know there's a perduous.
The machine actually can be used to improve the detection.
But so far in commercial use, my job is to look.
Mainly because the...
I can do the job.
And in order to achieve the continuity, right, we can do a simple process like smoothing.
This will solve our problems.
But in terms of doing research, right, there are definitely works that can use the continuity in the detection.
But here is a demo of the different face detection algorithms.
Let's first answer the question.
Face detection is a computer vision task in which we detect the presence of human faces as well as its location within an image or a video stream.
Face detection is applied in multiple fields from healthcare to security, authentication, entertainment.
The list goes on.
Some of the well-known applications are auto focus and digital cameras, crowd analysis and social media filters.
With such a wide range of applications, it also has a lot of hurdles that it needs to overcome.
In this video.
Okay.
So you can see that this nine different cases is detection output of different algorithms.
You can see that different algorithms may have different output or different performance.
These six plus this one, they all can detect face from the red to the large angle.
These two, they fail to detect, right?
And this actually appears quite often where we are detecting in a video because...
You can imagine your video is around the boundary.
Oh, being detectable or not detectable.
That means within one second, many, many frames.
Some frames detect the object.
Some frames you fail to detect, right?
If you want to try to experience that, you can find some challenging cases where you do some object testing.
You may face that.
And this is the main challenge in detection attractors.
And we should just now, right?
We are...
We are detecting the object in each frames and try to associate.
But if my detection here is not successful, then you will have challenging association with these things.
So, of course, our solution is...
...to improve the performance of the object detection.
However, you can never get an object detectable that's here, achieve 100%.
So, an alternative solution is once we detect object here, right?
We automatically move the box here and try to move or slide in the window, the box here, to an object that's max or best matches with the object here.
So, this is a valid way they can do it.
Of course, this will go deeper into the research.
So, in detection tracking, objects are very mature and relative very mature.
Because in drones and robotics, they have a lot of applications.
There are still some space to improve, especially the tracking.
And so far, the commercial tracking algorithm, right?
So, they are still based on the so-called camera filter.
And...
So far, the speed is about the issue for machine vision or machine sight.
So, when I detect and try to check, right, this computation is about the magic concerns.
But with this course, right, I'm not going to talk too much on this, but you may have faced such tasks where you go for an interview.
But in academic, this is not really a very important topic now.
It used to be quite hot in the last 10 years, maybe.
But now, we are saying the object detection is relatively mature, especially with YOLO series.
So, I guess this video is from one of the professor websites from NCHU.
So, this technology we talk about is called re-identification.
And it's very often be used to... let's say we have a CCTV camera in different places of the country, right?
And we want to detect the person whether the person wants to read the...
the school in the university, right?
And we may have images of the same person from different side, different angle.
And the purpose of REID is to identify whether this green one is the same person, this red one is the same person or not.
And how it is done by detection and tracking.
So, detection is easy, right?
And after detection, we will...
For each human detected, we try to represent as a vector and compare them whether this same person or not.
So, this stuff by the sort of tracking.
But within... I think not many years ago, they realized that the previous approach for REID has some limitation.
And they invented this new approach called joint detection and embedding.
So, the top part, if you are familiar, you will know this is just the feature of tracking, our FPN structure.
So, with the feature being collected, then we have the prediction head to do different tasks, including classification, regression and embedding.
So, the classification is to tell whether this is a specific object you are interested.
The regression is actually for the detection of the coordinate of the object.
What's new here?
Or what's really new from the previous is this embedding.
So, the main difference between joint detection and embedding in short GDE with previous REID or detection tracking is here we do the embedding.
We have an actual reputation called embedding, which is used to identify whether this is a same person or not.
While the previous approach is equivalent to object detection first, then calculate the embedding.
Of course, they use... In the academic, they use a new name called embedding.
But you can just consider this, understand this as a feature of tracking.
So, just remember this concept, right?
So, the previous approach of REID is by detection and then tracking.
Or detection, then represent that object, or person or whatever.
Now, we detect and at the same time, we want to describe the person.
So, this is a major difference.
Of course, there are many, many ways to implement this. This is just the illustration of the concept.
But you remember this because one day you want to go for a job, right?
So, they may ask you what's the difference between GDE and REID?
I hope you can answer that.
Of course, in terms of how many, how to design a GDE, how to achieve joint detection,
how to train a model that we achieve that is much deeper.
But at least you should know this basic concept.
So, this is a valid purpose of Delta I introduced this here.
Okay.
Here I'm showing, this actually is done by the DJI, his previous REID technology.
And I don't know how many years ago, but this technology was about two years ago
because when I teach the video system setting, I get this from one of my previous members.
He was working with DJI.
And unfortunately, we are not able to get the same test of two different algorithms.
But here I want to show that this is a REID technology, right?
And okay, just now you see the tracking from the lady, right?
Now they switch to a different person.
So this means REID actually fair to work.
Let's work.
Check it out.
So you can see we get the, detect the curve.
And just now the very, just now there's a loss of the object.
Now you see it's changing to another person.
So this is the limitation of the previous detection tracking.
Where this is achieved by FairMode JD, you can search this keyword to find the algorithms.
And you can see, right, even if there's some accruing and the argument can still be able to detect the person
and track the person correctly.
Of course, I believe in your showtime, it won't be easy for you to understand why JD is better than REID.
But intuitively I can explain and the reason is when we do the REID or the previous REID or joint detection,
previous detection tracking, right?
We are doing it in two steps, detection and tracking.
And these two steps are optimized individually.
So when you are, when you are changing the object detection, you didn't really think about how do I do it for tracking.
When you are doing device, develop the tracking algorithms, your detection algorithm is already out.
You cannot change it.
But in JD, your detection and your embedding is optimized simultaneously, right?
That's the, and because of the simultaneous optimization, you get better achievement.
If you have interest, right, you can study the JD code.
If you're looking for a job in JD.
So the second topic we want to talk about is the video or sometimes they call action-recognition.
Or video event detection.
So you can get, there's one dataset from this link.
You can go and play with it.
There are many detection tasks.
And some are relatively, relatively easier, let's say, to detect a push-up or ride a bicycle or ride a horse.
Because these are normally done by, you have a video clip.
You are going to classify whether this video click is riding horse, is it people running or is it shaking of the hands.
And another case is, looks similar, but it's actually different.
Like here, right, so the person's face is blocked.
And is a video, is a wedding ceremony.
And for this kind of case, right.
So the understanding of the event is actually based on, you have a right here.
And therefore you can detect this, right.
Essentially it's not really based on action or something.
But here is a lot of based on some action.
So in video event, I remember when, okay, so now you see the player shoots the basketball.
And this is a football case.
In video event, right, so the task is, if you have a video, can you detect whether there's a goal or not.
Right, or give you the video, can you capture the moment where the player shoots the football.
So in terms of technology, right, so the video event or action recognition or some different case,
or more complicated video detection, video recognition, right.
They are using quite similar strategies.
It's not really based on a clip or video sequence.
And we will to extract the features from each frame and concatenate together.
And pass the features to a classifier to tell whether this is a specific action or a specific event.
These are defined by the training data.
But if you look at only this part, right, facial tracking and classifier, this is almost identical to the object recognition, right.
In object recognition, if you play with the image net, and they are desired to be learning to train the network to extract the features and then map that to object classifying.
Here is also the same.
But we do realize that in video, right, because we have many, many frames.
And if we get some videos and change this one, and we realize that this model is quite sensitive to the sampling rate of the videos.
This, I can play like this, right.
So I can wave in a slow speed.
I can also wave very fast.
So if my training data is 100 different videos, I wave very fast.
Now if you give me a testing data where I wave very slow.
What?
We train the model and wave very slow. We can also still detect the recognize.
But the computer is not that smart.
The computer models, they actually can detect the data that is similar to your training data.
So if you are training the model with very fast movement and detect with a slow movement, it's going to fail.
So this actually is equivalent to the video sampling rate.
So a lot of effort in video recognition, right.
They are trying to design how do I do the video sampling such that different videos can be normalized.
So this is one of the topics here, right.
Another is how do I extract the features?
Because here is a video sequence. This is not a single image.
So compare with image recognition, right.
I have to consider the association between the different frames.
So just a mention, right.
So why is sample this?
There's a real, so a raw video sequence to a video clip.
And in many of the research, right, so I see the video clips maybe eight frames or 16 frames if I'm not wrong.
And the task is I, in order to change this, right, so I can get many training data where each training data is 16 frames.
And we have a level of the data and then eventually you can change the algorithm.
And so this, if we do not consider this part, right, so this is very similar to the object recognition.
So here are just some examples of the technology in video recognition.
Why is the long term recurrent convolution network?
So,
Nishing in the sequence as input, right, so we may have several images.
Just now I showed that computer see a video is a few frames, right.
So we may have, for example, three frames.
And from each frame, right, we try to extract features that can represent these frames.
And this long short term memory is a structure that can show the different frames.
And by combining these features together, we can make a decision or classification whether this is a high jump or other actions.
Well, a slight difference is image caption.
We may have an image as input, but we are trying to use text to describe these images.
So of course, they also use long short term memory.
And it covers these same features to this.
And this is often done by, now they are so-called contrastive learning.
So they can do by trying the feature from this text.
Of course, they call it a text encoder.
And try to, because this is text is describing this image, right.
And they are believe that text encoder will be extracted features and image encoder will be extracted.
These two features should be the same.
And that's called the contrastive image language learning.
And this is actually the, I think it's some kind of the foundation of the recent foundation models.
The foundation model was trained or inspired based on this.
And here, instead of based on single image, we can do the description based on video sequence.
And of course, a lot of research is just to design different network here, try to describe the video.
Here is another approach.
Of course, that's just for you.
This is not really a quite state of art.
You charge.
So let's say we can have three consecutive frames, right?
So normally we, in image based feature from the issue image.
But here we can do a convolution across the different frames to get the features from the time of special temporal features.
Of course, this is not really a very, it's not really a very high efficient algorithm.
But this is one of the early arguments that researchers are trying.
Here is one of our own work, my own work.
And what you are showing here, you can see here is a Cini MRI data captured from the heart.
Yeah, so you can see the movement of the heart, right?
And what our computer sees is a set of frames.
The purpose is this, is from this video moment.
Can you tell whether this is from a healthy subject or unhealthy subject?
Of course, this microvascular obstruction is one of the conditions of the disease.
So what do we do?
How to achieve that?
So we actually make use of the 3D convolution.
So of course, your data is a set of frames.
And we use a 3D CIN to extract the features from this one.
And this R2 plus 1D is another motion feature extraction.
And then with that we can extract some motion features.
And here is the classifiers.
Here is, you don't need to look at this because this is a specific track,
methods dealing with this specific data.
So this actually is our latest...
I'll show this one.
How to design the feature extraction here is one of the hot topics in dealing with video data scenes and offsets.
Doing the classifier here.
But here the part, if you are active in the area, you may have heard it.
It's just some existing algorithms.
So in some of the network, right?
So the overview...
This, they may have two streams to process the data.
Because we know that for video, right?
So we may have image, the first frame.
You can just consider the image, right?
But from the first frame to subsequent frames, we have the motion, right?
So we may consider each video as image plus motion.
Then you can follow...
Okay, I extract the image features, I extract the motion features, and then combine them together.
And in deep learning, right?
How do I get the data to change my model?
Right.
So I think if you hear about there are three basic elements.
That is your data, your computer resources, and network structures.
That will be the three basic elements for deep learning or for AI.
But here, if we are doing the special...
...the motion, we may change these two parts individually with other data.
For example...
This is the case for the heart disease.
This data you have to capture from human.
You can't ask anybody to do the scan and give you the data.
So when we train the deep learning, we definitely hope large amount data.
How do we do it?
Instead of relying on pure medical images, I may use other images.
Could it be... or videos, could it be non-medical domain to train the motion instructions?
And then use medical images to find the model.
So we call this the training.
So you train the model with very large data related or non-related with your task.
And fine tune the model with the data from your...
...and you can actually get better results.
Okay, I think we can have 15 minutes break before we talk about the enhancement.
If you have any questions, you can approach me.
So we come back at 7.45.
Okay.
So, the idea is that if you can do it, you try to do it.
Because to do that, at least you need some GPU resources, but I believe maybe not every
student can have the access in short time.
But if you can, you try to implement that.
The reason I asked you to do this is for this, definitely by the generous network, right?
And now the generator is very, very hot topic in both academic and in industry.
So just share something, right?
So maybe a few years ago, many companies, start-up companies, say, I'm an AI company.
Now if you go out, they say I'm an AI GC company, AI generator content company.
So they are paying more attention on the generation, so instead of purely AI.
And then you get familiar with this.
We are definitely helping you in whatever future work you may dealing with.
If you're looking for an industry job, if you want to apply for a PhD with this kind of
experience, it will be good.
But with this course, you just submit a two-page document to explain how you plan to do it.
You'll be sufficient.
Yeah.
So the second part is we will first have the video enhancement.
Here we also have video sanitation.
And the last week, we talked about the generative network, right?
And I believe the last lectures is more important to you.
In terms of research, video enhancement is, or it has been there for quite a long time
ago.
Yeah.
Because I've seen in many ago, there are some like films, for example.
And these films, they have been saving for some time, and then they have some noise,
and they already have been dealing with the noise in videos.
But we include this topic so that it's more complete in this lecture.
So our course denoises one in the unit.
Another one is the motion blur.
Because motion is almost everywhere.
And I believe when many years ago, or 20 years ago, when we were using cameras to take pictures,
if we are shaking, then you will get blurry images.
I think when I'm young, those cameras are not as good as now.
So you take the images.
You're only the expert, the expert, the expert person, we can be able to take images.
And now, of course, we have the mobile phones can take images.
They have some special design in the phones, such that even if you are shaking, the images
are still being shot.
But that denomines the motion is not there.
It's there.
It's just they have already processed it.
And this motion blur is one of the very important things we should deal with.
And now if you want to try to take an image at low light conditions or at night times,
you will face more challenges because of the motion.
So to understand how the motion may affect the image quality, it's actually very straightforward.
It can be modeled by a point spread function.
Let's say this is the original signals.
And this is a point spread function that represents the motion.
And the conversion of the two will plus some additive noise will be leading to the motion
blur.
So, in case there's no motion, right, so actually the point spread function is equal
to one if for N1 and N2 equal to zero and zero elsewhere.
But in practice, right, so this point spread function is want to be like this and it will
be leading to the, actually it means overlapping of the images from one space to another space.
So I see where I'm working on image processing.
This is the image, it's one of the standard images we are using.
Many people just use the image and the test, the algorithms and show the results, they
publish the paper.
But I think the last year or something, they are saying I should be general, we are not
allowed you to use these images.
Anyway, you can still use this image to show how the different blur may appear or looks
like.
So now if we know the point spread function, we actually can do the recovery of the images.
But in real life, right, so you don't know what's the motion corners or the point spread
functions.
So, give me use this image, right.
You don't know what's the point spread function.
And if you happen to use point spread function that is not accurate, then you will not be
able to recover the images.
So this is the potential result when your point spread function is wrong.
And so a lot of cases, the work is how to estimate the point spread functions.
So and with the deep learning being available, so we no longer try to estimate the point
spread functions.
And instead we use encoder decoder structures, which is I think it's used almost everywhere
now and try to give the encoder the blur image and give the decoder, hope the decoder can
get the, recover the image.
So using the deep learning.
Of course it's very difficult to understand how it works, right.
So this is also the reason why we say this deep learning is a black box.
But this kind of approach, right, is in terms of academic research, it could be something
that can be published somewhere in practical use, right.
So I believe I have tried this before to deal with something, right.
In real life, the blur and this could have become from various many, many reasons.
And therefore this approach, if you use it in real life data, you actually, you will
be disappointed in the result.
Even though in lab where the data follow some idea assumption, it works.
But in reality it's not going to work.
This is another case of, another application of the video, we can also say it's a video
enhancement that is to remove the turbulence effect.
So basically if you, I think if you throw something into the water and you try to take
a video of the scene, right, you may get something like that.
And in this case, right, it's, the noise is not the main issue.
The main issue is when the water is, have some turbulence, the scene is changing.
And the change is actually, it's not really a linear change or rigid change.
So, it's not rigid.
So like from one frame to another frame, there's a non-rigid deformation.
And let's say if you have a world document under the water and you make the water, you
do some dispersion of the water, then you may see the world like this, right.
So how can you recover this?
So for such approach, right, so that there are actually people using more experimental
approach.
So anyway, we, for this video frame that we actually get a sequence of data and we try
to using some non-rigid registration algorithms to register this data.
And after registration, right, you actually can use an approach called low rank decomposition.
So I'm not sure how many you can still remember low rank record.
What is a low rank means?
How many you can know what's the meaning of low rank, you can raise your hand.
Anybody know?
Nobody know?
So, the low rank is, so I feel we have dealing with linear algebra, right.
So in undergraduate, you definitely have a linear algebra.
And for each matrix, right, actually our, each image is, is typically represented by
the matrix, each matrix you can compute is a rank.
While where we have the, this sequence being registered and for each pixel or each location,
a long difference sequence.
If it is really well aligned, it should be have the same value, right.
So now if we have a vector of all the ones, so, okay, I give an example.
So let's say we have a matrix, the first row is all the ones.
The second row is all the tools.
And the third row is all the trees.
What do you think is the rank of this matrix of all one, two, three?
Okay, so the rank is one.
Why?
The second row can be represented by the first row, right.
And if we, here is a matrix, right, each sequence is a matrix.
If we just really represent this one as one vector, let's say this is 200 by 200 image.
We change it to be 40, 40k a vector.
Just image, I put it straight into one vector.
And I put the first image in the first row, the second image in the second row, and the
third image in the third row.
So in ideal case, if all the frames are identical after registration, what's the rank of the
matrix?
Because all the first row, the second row, and third row actually will be identical.
So the rank is also one, right.
So that's why we do a low rank decomposition.
We will be able to solve for the reference image.
So low rank, I didn't include the detail here, but the low rank representation is, I give
you a matrix which may not be low rank.
You decompose it into two metrics where the first matrix is low rank, the second matrix
is noise.
So this is how they do it.
And so the next we are, I would like to introduce the optical flow.
So this technology itself doesn't look like we're using video, but actually it's used
to compute how the flow, what's the flow from one frame to another frame, or to check the
movement.
So let's say we have one frame IT and the T represents the time, right.
And then we have another frame IT plus one.
So how do I know the flow at each point here or each point box here?
So using the optical flow, we are trying to compute the, we can say it's a velocity vector,
or you can say, what is the motion here at this point from frame one to frame two, it
moves to this direction or this direction.
So how the motion moves will be determining the so-called optical flow.
So in terms of definition, optical flow is a relation of the motion field.
And it's capturing how what's the displacement of the pixels of the image plane from one
frame to the next frame.
And the most optical flow is based on some assumptions such as spatial coherence and
also time coherence.
The special conclusion is that we assume that two neighboring pixels or very close pixels
neighboring points in the same thing.
Typically it's not every time, but in the majority case maybe the same surface, right.
So like we have this pointer here, right.
So any two points, they are constrained by the surface.
So if this I move, right, all the points move with similar directions.
Another assumption is the temporal persistence, meaning the image motion of a surface patch
change from one frame to another frame or a change over the time should be very gradually.
So this gradually there's no clear definition of how gradually is gradually, but it's quite
related with the sampling rate of the video.
So normally we watch video, some video I've seen is like 60 frames per second.
And in terms of real time, we normally at least 15 frames per second.
So from 15 frames per second to 60 frames per second, there's four times of difference
sampling rate.
So this sampling rate will be related with whether this is considered gradual or not.
And in Optifluida there's one famous constraint that called brightness constraint.
So the basic assumption is that from a point x, y to one frame, we have a small displacement
to x plus data x and y plus data y, right.
So the brightness of this point should be maintained.
This is approximation, it's not really a very strict condition.
So this means if I have a point at time t and a frame of time t with a point at x, y,
if this point have a vector on this direction and move to x plus data x and y plus data
in time t plus one, these two points should be the same intensity.
So this gets the equation here.
It's called the brightness consistency assumption.
So I believe you have learned about the Taylor series how to expand the Taylor series, right.
So we can do this.
So the intensity of i x plus data x, y plus data y and t plus data t, right, will be equal
to i x, y, t plus the variation items.
So y is the derivative of i with the pressure of x times data x plus the derivative of i
with data y times data y with y and also the derivative over t times data t.
So we can do this.
And then we can also add the second order and third order and high order items.
But normally we can assume the high order items are ignorable and just put as zero.
And since we have the assumption of the brightness constraint, right, this one equal to this, right.
So this one to be here, that means these two can be counter each other.
That means this item will be equal to zero, right.
With this equal to this, right, so these two items can be structured and the high order items are ignored.
So the top will be zero.
And if we put the data t in the, to divide the, here, we divide this item with data t, right.
And then we will have the i with derivative of x, data t divided by data, data x divided by data t, right.
And also here data y divided by data t.
The last item of the data t divided by data t will be one, right.
So this one will be equal to zero.
And if we let the data t be approaching zero, this item will be the differential of dt by dx of dt, right.
So this equation is called the brightness consistency equation.
So you can rewrite this one to this item or this items.
So this equation is often used in the optical flow.
And if we rewrite the items, you will realize this, right.
So the delta of the i dot product with uv, uv actually represents the speed of the x and y directions.
And plus it will be zero.
This actually means the motion perpendicular to the gradient.
So here the motion perpendicular to the gradient cannot be measured because the inner product will be equal to zero.
So this is the equation.
Next let's move to the video simulation.
Compared with video enhancement, I believe video simulation will be more of the interest to the research.
And this actually is compared with the video object detection and object detection.
The video simulation is also similar to the image simulation except that we need to consider the time domain coherence.
So before that, we first understand what is the simulation.
So we often say this is you give the net deep learning, you give some pictures in and if you give some picture out.
So you can have a person riding a horse try to segment the boundary of the horse and also the human.
You can have animals and cheese try to segment the boundary of this.
And of course besides sanitation, right, the picture in show can also be in the case of depth estimation.
So this is a table you try to estimate the depth from the cameras.
So when deep learning was first invented for classification tasks, right, so the people were thinking, so let's say how the community can be done, right.
So we basically give an image and it just features and gradually compute a vector of 1000 dimensions.
So this is actually a bit down in the image net data set and there are 1000 class of objects.
And this vector, each element in the vector represents the property of the object.
This image to be the object could be cut, could be dog, could be any of the 1000.
And then because this is a card, right, so they are expecting the coefficient for the cut to be the highest among the 1000 vectors.
So, actually RCNA is one of the classic object detection algorithms, right.
So you have the image input, you try to extract some, they call the region proposals and then for each proposal, right, they compute the same features and try to classify whether this is human or any other objects.
So this is how the very early version of the method for deep learning based object detection.
So, RN is doing a given image, right, I'm trying to get only box of dog and cut and other objects.
So, people will have the question, right, how do I use this deep learning network for the purpose of simulation, right.
Simulation compared with the difference just now, right.
If it's recognition, it's just a class, whether it's cut or dog or anything else.
And object detection is to take the bounding box of the object.
But simulation is, you need to give a map to expect, tell me where exactly is the cut and the dog.
And this matrix and of course the rest will be background, right.
So this matrix, we have the same as the input images.
And this is why we call this pixel and it picks out because you get the same amount of pixels output compared with your input.
And for those people who work on deep learning, right, they always like to make the network be end to end learning.
So that means my input and output are fixed.
Try to optimize your network to best approach this output.
So now we look at the very early network.
So you have some features, convolutional network to each other features.
And after feature, you try to help to fully collect the lasers to get the classification.
So how to modify this network for sanitation.
So the motivation is instead of using the fully connected network, they just use convolution and replace that with convolution.
And the final vector, which makes this vector be the same size of the h times w and we can reshape into this.
And that's achieved the purpose of, picks out.
So if we give the network, we train the network with this kind of ground shoes and we will be teaching the network to do sanitation.
So UNET is one of the very popular network.
It was, I think it's originally published in MEEK, I think, is one of the network applied for medical image sanitation.
And I think at the same time, so there's one paper in CEPR or something, it has very similar structure as UNET.
But I think at the very time, UNET is not that popular compared with the, I think it's called FPN or something.
But recently years, they just find this UNET structure is, so it's very simple and it's very useful.
And they are using this in the diffusion models.
In diffusion models, they are just UNET one, UNET two, UNET three and the connected with each other.
It becomes a diffusion models.
So simple but effective.
So they use it in many, many places.
So this UNET, right, so the structure is, you first have image input, right.
So you have a structure features in by two convolutional network and then you're done sample.
And another two convolutional network and done sample and the convolution again and done some more convolution.
And this stage, right, we call it the contraction phase because after each measure, the dimension of the, so let's hear, right, my input image input is 5.7.2 times 5.7.2, right.
And after convolution, if we do this one, if we do not consider the padding, it will reduce by 2.
And this done sampling here will be reduced by half and here another half.
So you can see the image dimension here is or feature dimension here is reducing.
But at the same time, right, when my feature dimension is reducing, I definitely have discussed some information.
If my channel number is maintained.
In order to not to discuss too many information, so in the contract phase, right, so you can see here is 64 features.
But come here, you got 128 features.
So in the contract phase, we are reduced the image dimension, but increase the number of channels from 64 to 102 to 125, 256 and 512.
So here we are on the second phase, right, on the right side.
On the right side is, we call it expansion phase.
And here we are trying to create higher resolution mapping.
And this arrow here means we will take the map here to be appended here, so that some of the information can be maintained.
This overall structure called the unit.
It's look at the U-sheet, so this is why they are called unit.
So this is one of the basic structures for the image level simultaneously.
Of course, in the past 10 years, there are many, many different variations of the work that have been done to change the unit.
For example, we may do something here, and we can also add some units along this arrows.
So I'm not going to the different variation of the units, but I hope you at least know the unit.
So this is the meaning of the arrow.
So it's to concatenate the features here with the features here and in the outer here.
So this unit structure, you can use for sanitation, you can use for image generation, you can use for many other purposes.
So from high level understanding, right?
So in the concrete phase, we are reducing the spatial dimensions, but increasing the abstract levels, so-called work.
And in the expression phase, we are recovering the details and the dimensions, which actually equivalent to the various objects.
And we show that the research shows that concatenate the feature maps from the concrete phase will help to recover the location information.
So with some background on how the image sanitation is done.
Now let's look at what's the difference between image sanitation and view sanitation.
So this stack former is, I think it's one of the, because originally the unit is based on signal structure.
So in the recent years, there's new structure called transformers.
And based on transformers, they have designed a network called stack former.
So when stack former is applied to a video, right? So we are just applying sanitation on frame by frame, independent.
So the sanitation of the first frame and the second frame and third frame, they are totally independent.
We never consider the correlation between the conceptual frames.
And this cost to find future mining for video smelch is one of the approach in publishing CVPR.
And they have considered that frame to frame.
And this approach is actually from one of my colleagues.
I'm not sure whether they really publish the work or not.
But the results, you should better.
You watch the machine output.
You may see now, right? So there are some flickering, right?
So from one frame to another frame, the result is not stable, right?
And here is quite consistent here, but the center is not that good.
And here is very obvious, right?
So you can see that from for video sanitation, right?
So we will care about the consistency from one frame to another frame.
And the purely image based, you will have the jumping from one frame to another frame.
Of course, you can try to improve the sanitation of each individual frames.
With that accuracy, it will improve. You will get some improvement.
But unless you can achieve 100%, right, you will always face this kind of issue.
Whereas the sanitation boundaries or levels may be not that obvious, maybe near the borderline or not that clear case,
you will have this, we call it flickering artifact.
Whereas video, right, they are trying to solve these issues.
So this flickering artifact is repaint the one we see from one frame to another frame.
So of course, the potential solution is you can still based on image based sanitation,
but you try to apply some smoothing in continuous frames, right?
Here I am to show one of the videos.
Welcome to the world's first on device learning demo for temporarily consistent video segmentation,
presented by Qualcomm AI Research.
Semantic segmentation is a popular computer vision task that assigns every pixel of an image to a label.
It enables many emerging use cases, including autonomous driving, smart cameras and XR applications.
However, existing segmentation solutions often have flickering artifacts and lack temporal consistency between video frames.
Related work addressing these challenges still have limitations, including inaccurate temporal consistency between frames,
the lack of an accurate metric to model consistency and difficulty deploying real time on smartphones.
In this demo, we showcase consistent and robust video segmentation using on device learning.
To address the limitations of related work, we propose three solutions.
The first one is OGS ADAPT, our novel on device learning method.
OGS ADAPT consists of two networks.
First, a base network main net, which performs segmentation for the input video.
Second, a tiny auxiliary network OGS net, which accomplishes efficient on device learning.
Both outputs are combined to generate the final prediction and to update OGS net,
which in turn helps enhance the temporal consistency of the original output.
To enable real time adaptation on a smartphone, we utilize heterogeneous computing on snapdragon processors to distribute AI tasks to the DSP and GPU,
efficiently accelerating AI computations.
We also propose a novel temporal consistency metric.
It evaluates the similarity and perceptual features between two video frames.
Let's take a look at the results and see how our OGS ADAPT technique improves temporal consistency.
For the video frames without OGS ADAPT, you can see flickering in the base network output.
With OGS ADAPT, no flickering occurs.
Using our full stack AI research approach, we utilize hardware acceleration to efficiently run in parallel,
the OGS net model on the Qualcomm Adreno GPU and the main net model on the Qualcomm Hexagon processor.
With our optimizations, we reduce the inference time by over five times to 37 milliseconds and achieve real time performance.
Quantitatively, we show clear improvement in segmentation performance,
with temporal consistency and mean intersection over union scores increasing.
And this concludes the demonstration of our temporally consistent video semantic segmentation demo.
Stay tuned for more advances and efficient perception. Thanks for watching.
Okay, so because this course is about the machine vision, right?
So on the machine side, I just mentioned earlier, right?
Speed is one of the important things.
For video, you need to consider the special or time consistency or from frame to frame consistency.
But you also need to make sure this processing can be done in real time.
For video, right? So I remember when I do these things, like we normally need to process each frame within 50 milliseconds
or even a shorter time of 30 or 20 milliseconds.
And in terms of frame per frame rate, normally at least 10 frames per second,
you need to make sure your AI can be able to process that.
And this is not processing in your cloud GPU. You need to press in edge side.
And this is depending on the computing powers at the edge side.
So I see in China, right?
So they are doing a lot of things that's using automatic algorithms to detect, for example,
whether there are people doing that, jail working.
And this one lady was captured.
And they...
But they realize it's from out of place on the bus.
So the best way to try to...
I believe most of the people from China may know this lady, right?
It's from the Goli Air Con.
So they are doing advisement.
The lady's picture is there.
And when this bus is crossing the zebra and the zebra cross, right?
So they capture the images and they have a face recognition, recognize...
Oh, this is the lady.
And this is all the case of the...
It's actually done by detection and tracking and recognition.
And so you guess what has been missing?
Why they have this wrong detection?
So the first thing is...
Although the bus is moving, right?
The camera is maybe fixed.
But we can also consider this from the camera point of view.
And from the video and each frame, right?
It didn't...
It does not tell whether the video is taken from a real human or taken from a photo, right?
So this...
That's how people try to detect if I'm taking a video from a real person
or take a video from pictures.
So this is one potato issue that has been missing.
The second issue is...
For the 2D...
For the image that is 2D, right?
But if it's a real human, right, it should be a 3D structure, right?
So in reality, right?
So where we are doing object detection and tracking,
if we remember just now the video, right?
We may...
We remember the RID case, right?
We have a lady walking in that direction and you check along the lady, right?
And suddenly there are some blocks occlusion, right?
And therefore the tracker will lose the person
and actually detect the other person, right?
But in reality, right?
So this lady walking in that direction, yeah,
it will get far, far away from my cameras, right?
If we make use of this distance information,
you will know this lady suddenly disappears,
it will search in that direction with the same movement.
So 2D versus 3D is...
The real world is always 3D.
But our cameras is taking 2D information.
So our object detection and tracking is done by 2D images, not 3D.
So this is one of the information missing.
And in another case, possibly that can be used to correct this case is motion.
So if this is a human, right?
So I believe that in hard list,
stung there are no movements, muscle.
I definitely will move, my eyes will blink, right?
But if there is a picture in the chain, in the bus, right?
It won't have many movements.
If there are any movements, it's because of the bus,
and it's moved in the same directions.
So this could be another scene.
So this multi-verse that 3D is very, very important,
and this will be the focus in the next two lectures.
And for today, I want to play this video again,
because at the time there is some issue with the sound.
Some progress, at least within the small confines of the legal community,
I think it's real important.
President Barack Obama, when you're giving a speech,
make sure you use a lot of pauses.
America's businesses have created 14.5 million new jobs over 75 straight months.
We're developing technology.
Every technology can be used in some negative way,
and so we all should work towards making sure that it's not going to happen.
And one of the interesting directions is that once you know how to create something,
you know how to reverse engineer it.
And so one could create methods for identifying edited videos versus real videos.
So this video was managed already,
and at that time, this foundation model for video generation is still not popular yet.
And it's popular only in these two years,
and the generation of this fake video is not by a single foundation model.
It's more based on... I try to mimic how the lips move.
So I make sure the sound and the lip movement should be consistent,
and make these lips look like the Obama's face.
But now the... I think you can...
I did see some of the videos in popular media,
like TikTok and other places.
You can see it's a fake video because the content doesn't make sense.
What they say doesn't make sense.
But if you don't look carefully, you actually can hardly see that that's the fake video.
And the next lecture about the treaty, right?
So it's actually connected with the videos and connected with the video generations,
because the technology behind it is actually quite similar actually.
And when we generate video, right?
So we actually should consider the treaty aspect of the data.
And now they are... I think in Singapore, they have spent some money to...
to... got a deep fake.
So at one time, you may have video be generated by AI artists, which could be a fake video.
And in order to fight against that, right?
So we need to develop technology that detects the fake video.
Yeah, so I think that the technology of fake video could be one of the hot topics in the coming years.
So if you... some of you may make a pie for PhD,
or some of you may go for some study of the...
as your research topic, you can look for such opportunities.
Okay.
There's still some... have some time.
I think I may go some for the treaty today.
And I don't think the slides haven't been shared on the course side yet, but I will share very soon.
And I start a bit of the treaty today so that in the...
especially in the last lecture, we can have some time to...
to have a review and all the course and to highlight what are the important points in this subject.
So in terms of treaty, right, there are many, many approaches for treaty.
So one is time of flight.
So I see it's like Microsoft Keynet, so they are using this kind of approach for treaty.
And one is LIDAR.
So LIDAR actually is a special form of time of flight.
But the light frequency of LIDAR and the normal time of flight camera is different.
Another is structural light.
So that light is not a general uniform light.
It's a light with structures of special patterns.
And another one is called motion from structures and also the sterile.
And with this course, right, so I will be more focused on motion from structures and the sterile.
And these are more for your information only.
So time of flight by the name, right, you can understand this.
We have a light source.
You check some light and reach an object and get a reflection and come back to the detector.
And the time here will be the two times of distance divided by the speed of the light.
So this approach, right, so you can imagine, right, so I have a light detector.
It says that besides the light from this reflection, it can have light from other reflections or other light sources.
So this is actually the major weakness of the light, time of flight cameras.
So for example, the sunlight, the outdoor sunlight will affect this.
And therefore the time of flight cameras now you can use, right, you cannot walk in outdoor.
And even for indoor scenarios, it may fail.
Let's say, of course, in this room it's okay.
But if we have a window, very large window, right, the sun may come in, right, so it will affect.
So when I was in my previous company, which is a robotic company, we developed humanoid robots
and do some demos in a place where many guests come, right.
And that place got a window, very big window.
We do have cases, certainly robots cannot recognize because the camera is fair to walk.
Yeah, so this is one of the limitations of the time of flight.
Leida in full name is called light station and arranging.
And it's a type of time of flight.
But normally we don't call it camera, it's just Leida is called Leida.
And it has two weakness.
One is called Leida ghost, meaning my Leida is the time of flight.
And my detector of the light, right, may detect some reflections or some steps, scatterings,
and mistake that as an object like here.
So you see the video?
This actually is due to the reflections.
Another case is called Leida blooming, meaning if we have some very strong reflective surface,
and it will reflect very strong light, so it will be affecting the accuracy of Leida.
And of course Leida also have issues in rain.
So now the autonomous driving is quite popular.
I think it's approaching commercial use.
And I think the very early people are trying to use Leida.
And I think the Tesla is trying to use pure camera based.
So pure camera to face some issues, they cannot recognize the white vehicles versus the clouds,
because all are white, they mistake as the clouds.
But this is actually the vision recognition problem.
But the Leida got a problem because of the rain.
Because the rain will make the Leida light to attend very fast.
So with that strong attenuation, it's a, it face an issue.
But of course they are, those people work on the Leida, they are also trying to improve the Leida
such that they can be robust or walk in rain conditions.
And the structure light is a different way for the depth.
So you can, I believe this case maybe not that easy to understand.
But you just imagine my light inject to a hand, for example, is a special pattern.
So we have different frequency or different colors at different place.
So normally I have a uniform or different colors.
But if I project this one to a surface with 3D surface, right, it will cause some distortion.
What we look will be no longer be uniform.
And based on the detection of the cameras, you will be able to calculate what's the distance from here to here.
So these are the basic principles of these different depth cameras.
So you don't need to understand how this is calculated.
It's not really required for you.
Unless you, in the future, you work on designing a new structure light, then you do work on that.
But normally you just understand what's the principle of these different depth cameras and what's their beginnings.
So the structure light also cannot work on outdoor because the sunlight is so strong.
It's just no matter what color is, right, I have a sunlight, it's all bright.
All the color is covered there.
So there is all white.
So your pattern will be disappearing.
I think I will stop here because just now the three different depth sensors is for your information.
And from next lecture, I will talk about the structure from motion.
And then in the last lecture, I will talk about stereo, stereo matching.
And the structure from motion and also the stereo matching, right, so they are quite similar principles.
It's based on matching or all you can say is based on tracking.
But today we did talk about object detection and tracking, right?
And the structure from motion and the stereo matching, they are based on tracking of the features.
In nowadays, I would like to use more appropriate words called key point.
So, and to me, right, so next two lectures will be more important than today's lecture.
And the first lecture I see is also important than today.
Because today is seen for video recognition, right?
So it's so similar to the object recognition.
And in the AI, we have many different areas.
And as a video recognition is one of the slowest areas in the development.
So a lot of innovation like how a normal structure like transformer, how they are invented,
it's not in the video recognition.
It's in NLP, it's in image recognition.
So that could be a one of the reasons is because the video sampling is one of the issues.
It can hardly uniform the videos because the videos are sampling rate or how fast I move is one additional features.
And this will make your recognition, changing the network much challenging because you have two dimensions,
you have some data required.
You have one more additional dimension of the data, right?
Your data will be also increasing significantly.
Okay, so that's all for today.
So if you have any questions, you can approach me.
Thank you.