you
Okay, good evening. So I
think I from the list I this class should have you over 400 students, right? So, so
so I just confirm I so you guys are many students maybe look at the video recordings, right?
Okay, so you are lucky in the time when I am here. So when I'm here, there's no video recordings. You must be here. So if you're not here, they may attend sign the
attendance list. If in the ups and for many lectures, you will fear the cost. Okay, but this is not what we are doing now. So I think that until it's protected students are very well. So
so first I want to introduce myself. So my name is Chen Jun. So and I actually graduated from Chiba years ago and and I my super is at school. I think he's here with the school. So and at that time I my
my PhD area is more on image processing and I do have many friends who who work on video signal processing and I happen to teach video signal processing for last year. I think and but this year the
professor John approach me say want to this course right so it has something related with 3D and something with with machine vision based on video and so so he happened to read my slides is a video signal processing. So he told me they this class may also
require similar technologies causes or content. So and I'm currently doing research in the in a start recording. There's one I call Institute for infocom research and my own research actually cover quite a lot actually I used to be work a lot on medical image computing or medical image analysis and from that right so
and at the time I started to work on medical image right so there are a lot of people working on machine computer vision and but for medical imaging at the very beginning right is not really computer vision is different from computer vision. Yeah, but the reason is that
the main difference is that in computer vision my daughter work are dealing with natural images but here is more medical images so but with the AI or especially deep learning coming become popular that the research method in medical image computing and the computer vision is become very very small now.
So I also work on robotics focus on the robotics perception and vision so that's the machine vision part computer vision part and actually right so that for deep learning people right so you are you are in the past I think turn or turn actually from 2015 right to to to now so it's actually the machine
learning people is killing the area of computer vision and the medical imaging or you're not the word right if you are not touched machine learning your method in computer vision or in medical imaging will be look like a bit not that novel or in other words if you
Hello you may apply the machine learning technology in computer vision tasks and then in my medical image tasks and doing very good results so if we want to
defeat those steps called a state of arts in computer vision you must be familiar with machine learning.
So and currently I'm also working on several projects one project is quietly read with the the part of the course here is 3D vision deep learning for 3D vision is while the quite fundamental research and the the second is more medical images is also related with 3D but it's for 3D reconstruction and the last one is
just finished this earlier this year and it's actually also a 3D but it's a it's a special 3D reconstruction.
Okay so this.
Yeah.
I work on and this is just to show you that the size I get is may come from lectures from other courses and I and some papers and also content from public papers so.
So I will be with you for for lectures so today I will be focused on so there's two parts one part is video one part is 3D so it's machine vision for video and machine vision for 3D but for video part right so.
I look at the current trend of the research I will think about what should I share with you on video part so I decided to share more on the generation of the videos right you may have now you actually can see the some of the fact the video from.
Popular media like.
Like a tick tock I believe you should be able to find some.
So, so I want to make sure you can understand how the video generation now is.
Effect by using the recent technology.
And of course I also need to share on for videos how how the people do the analysis and how to do the some enhancement.
Another course video system assessing.
So the use for focus a lot on video coding so.
But the video coding is where I teach that course right so I hope to add more content on the AI part instead of video coding part.
The reason is the code is the is kind of mature very mature now so it's commercially use very well so they for the researcher right so.
Once this thing is.
And mature we are we are not it's very difficult for you to find additional know what to do what kind of value can create to to put more effort on or video coding.
Of course, yeah, people will call it but I understand this course right so many students are taking master degree and many some maybe go for PhD right so.
So, while my focus is I will try to choose more concept or more domain areas to you.
And and this also relates how the examination will be going for for my part of the work.
So the second part is more on the treaty.
And I will more focus on the of course there are many many treaties.
So many many different approach for for the treaties so I will focus on the part I fear is more important or quite popular in industry and also in academic research.
So here I will for the treaty I will share the how the key points are detected and used to.
For the treaty and how the stretch for motion is applied and also I will share on the stereo matching.
Which is while the.
May focus in the in my research actually now.
Okay, so now let's talk about video generation.
We first watch a video.
My full time employees.
My full time employees and their ability to survive on $8 an hour in New York City and foremost in all of our minds has been the loss and the grief felt by the people of Orlando.
Most of us don't get our health care through the marketplace through our job or through Medicare or Medicare.
What you should know is that thanks to the Affordable Care Act your coverage is better today than it was before.
Women can get free checkups.
Can get charged more just for being one to give his employees together to pass a commoner's bill that would boost America's very very hard times.
Some progress at least within the small confines of the legal community.
I think it's real important.
Here we go.
When you giving a speech.
You use a lot of pauses.
America's businesses have created 14.5 million new jobs over 75 straight months.
We're developing technology.
Every technology can be used in some negative way.
And so we all should work towards making sure that it's not going to happen.
And even one of the interesting directions is that once you know how to create something you know how to reverse engineer it.
And so you can and so one could create methods for identifying edited videos versus real videos.
Okay. So this is just a video.
Actually this video where we show one of the video is two Obama speak and one is a fact one.
And but this video fact video actually is is not based on the recent AI technology.
It's actually is this many time many years ago.
But that doesn't mean there are people already starting to to make a video a few years ago already.
But the recent like a solar and those things right so they can make much better video.
Fact video.
And in Singapore I understand I know there's one case someone put a fake video or previous PM.
So in order to understand right how the the fact the video is.
So I will share the links to all this video links to you.
Since the sound is not quite good now just now.
So in order to understand how the video is generated or fact right so we first to to know why was a concept called auto encoder.
And and this is actually where the AI actually starts from one of the technologies for AI to start from.
So for auto encoder right so we basically have a original image.
So we go through we call it a neural network encoder.
So encoder this if you take the video coding right.
So it's like something a compressed video.
But here with the video not knowing how you encoder right.
This neural can be many many layers and if you convert this image right to a code this code right.
Can be visually right can be look like a random noise.
Or a vector with a random noise.
Or a vector with for example 16 bits better or 8 8 bit vectors.
So from this code right you look at it is not it does not show anything about this images is not a down some of the images is you can say is this can convert to become a random code.
So and then we also have a neural network decoder to recover an image.
Where the auto encoder I will try to.
Change this network such that reconstructed images here is be close to the original input image as much as possible.
So after changing right after changing we take the decoder out.
We take we make use decoder right will give this decoder.
An input code this code that not have to be set by this one.
Yeah but of course if if it's very close to this one right if you will be able to recover image like this right.
So that means after this change right this can be used to change a code here to become an image.
Similar to the training input.
So.
I'm sure how many of you have been.
Have the knowledge of AI already.
I was convolutional neural network.
Anybody know neural network.
Neural network just you have read the neural network so we just structure like this.
Hit.
Okay okay I got it.
So since you have learned the thing in the first part right so you just imagine those are different things in the networks and from the input x right you reduce the dimension to become zero so and the Z could be a random noise.
Okay this one is just so.
So.
Let's hear where I'm teaching the video coding so I just find that you really coding right this is a diagram from a video coding so you actually have the similar things.
You have the video input you have the encoder and the end you trust what you trust both of the.
Compressed data through a channel to the other part and then you recover it right so this process is like encoding and decoding right so it's it's very similar to auto encoder.
Of course they are like and that's they are quite a lot of difference because how they design this part how they design the part is totally different.
But based on concept you realize that our video come from here is go through an encoding process.
And here I got the coding processor and our auto encoder is is also encoder and decoder.
So.
A quick test.
So when we change encoder.
And decoder to reconstruct the original training image as close as possible.
Why why this one.
Can be.
It's like this neural net decoder is it to restore the some of the information here.
But based on the code but as I mentioned just now right this code can be a random.
Can be looked like a random noise so why you can recover an image from a random noise.
So here the potential reason so why is.
This image itself have a lot of redundancy right so we actually know right if you.
Have ever learned image processing so image have a lot of redundancy because neighboring pixels tend to be very similar intensity.
So this is the first reason the second reason is that when we change this neural network right this decoder may contain some of the domain knowledge of the training image here.
So my question is how many things.
The reason is a maybe raise your hands how many things.
I try to be interactive.
Nobody thinks is a is correct.
Okay here for some students a is correct.
No else a.
Okay.
Okay a few students a correct how many say B is correct is the reason.
How many things both and be accurate.
So the rest of students say now the correct.
Okay so the answer is this this is a question I think so I believe both are the reasons here.
So I understand right if my input image here is a random.
That means every picture is value could be a random noise.
You will not be able to recover this.
Okay that's why you can easily get this result from based on information theory.
If every beat is a random right so the information from here is dependent by the number of beats.
Let's say we have let's say is a 200 times 200 image here for example right.
That means I have 40,000 pixels or 40,000 beat and each beat is random so that means 40,000 random.
This here and the information actually is is the maximum at that time and after encoder your code is become smaller right.
So your information here will be definitely smaller than this.
So that means you will not be able to recover this one.
So if you don't understand you will try to look for the information theory.
I think you should have learned that on undergraduate.
And the B is also correct because when we are changing the decoder we are learning how the code here are linked with that.
So you can see the image here.
So if you really find this very difficult to understand you can just imagine right.
So I may have a box with many cards inside each card may have some article but each card may have ID right 1234 right.
So when I draw from a box to find the car the right car so each car will show the corresponding text article here right.
So that's that's how the model decoder here is try to learn the information from the training images.
Of course this is because the training image itself has has redundancy.
So I'm going to show you how to do this.
Now so MBA knows what's the what's the limitation of autoencoder.
What is the limitation so when we train autoencoder right we are training we have an input image.
And to train become a code and decoder it and we get the output right.
So let's say we our training image is an image of the number seven right.
We want this output to be as close as this as possible.
And very often how do I measure these two are close.
So for example very often we use the mean square error.
So just compare these two how many are equal how many are different for you know right.
And of course there are many other options but in autoencoder based on the difference.
So this actually the way we calculate the how close it is is a lot in training this decoder.
So we may have one third be connected to this the end of the seven right stroke.
We can also have a thought maybe anybody anywhere in the space in the wide space right.
So of course we here we put it a different color.
But if you look at this one right so it still looks like a seven right because all the seven like this.
But if you look at this one you may say this is seven plus a dot right.
So visually if you are careful enough you say there's a dot right.
This is dot means the end of the sentence or mean something else right.
If you are working with a bank right so I'm going to have a financial number right.
Many many number and seven many number right.
Here you have many many number and seven and they have a dot.
That means it may seven point one or seven point two right.
So it will change significantly in the actual meaning.
So if we are doing machine vision for example try to recognize what's the number here.
So we will say this is a really seven right.
But this look like a fake one because a true number of seven should not have a dot here.
We said them right a seven like that.
So that means my difference between the output and the input training image right.
Where the difference is it matters right.
But auto-encoder because they are just computer difference and computer mean square error.
It doesn't care about this.
Of course there are many other approaches to for example I may change how I calculate the distance like I may compute a structure measurement like a structure similarity if you ever hear about it.
So it may change a bit but the main cause main message is that we know different location of the dot or difference affects your result.
So therefore people think of the adversarial learning.
So in adversarial learning right.
So similar this we have a we call it a general model.
You can consider this is a generative model is a decoder model we just now.
So we want this decoder model I can generate for example an image of a face.
A facial image right.
And compare with the auto-encoder just now right.
So we also have some training images of the real world face images.
And instead of we try to reconstruct this one.
The general image to be as close as to this one as possible.
We change a different model a discriminative model.
This is like a classifier.
So that means we are training one generative model and one discriminative model or one classifier.
So this one is try to generate something this one is to do classification classifier what so classifying between the image here and the training image or real world images.
So in another word right so what do I do.
I'm trying to generate an image such that from the discriminator point of view these two if I cannot tell the difference or easily tell the difference.
There I may say this generation is quite good right.
So I'm trying to generate an image that make you feel this is a real image.
So that means we have be considered potential clues.
When you generate this one you may generate it with some clues that are very easy to tell.
This is not a real risk facial images.
So you come back to the auto encoder.
So we are here we are trying to use the encoder to generate a set if the realist image like this right.
If I generate an image with a dot besides the seven.
So why we can easily tell this is a fake one.
It's because this pool visually looks quite different.
If I put the dot at the end of the choke right you may not notice it right because you.
You're naturally this the where the end of the stroke ends is they have some variations.
So this is within the reasonable variation right so let's say from here to here maybe 10 pixel.
Or someone is 10 pixel or someone is 11 pixel some is 9 pixel.
So you add one dot here you really don't know whether you just actual dot.
But you know scary should be white and you add one dot here visually very different.
So.
So this because this.
Generative as an anniversary or.
How to learn a generative model.
And just now we mentioned that there's also discriminator right.
So there's a generative model there's a discriminator and these two are trained as a versus we way.
And both the generative model discriminator are based on.
Deep neural network.
So.
So let's look at the structure of the.
Generative work.
And with this one maybe you can understand this better.
So.
This part right we have.
Random vector input.
They write so these are the equivalent to the coder with a code in the open.
And.
The generator is trying to convert the.
Input.
To an output.
Of course it's output let's just use the image as an example it can be image.
But it also can be a video or anything else.
Or speech or whatever.
So and the best of now is almost can generate anything.
But here we just use image as an example for easy understanding.
And we have a training images which is the images you are.
You are used to training it can be facial images it can be.
An image of.
Our buildings or and it depends on how you want to train this one.
What's your objective of the.
Generating.
Generative network.
The.
We can give this many many different random.
And the.
Here it will be different samples.
Hello.
And we will have some samples right.
So.
For for.
Generator as a network right.
I am what I hope.
So.
For for.
Generator as a network right.
I hope this can generate something sample here.
GZ right and the X.
Cannot be.
Easily differentiated.
So.
It's like for example I want to do some.
I lose older than you right.
But if I can do some makeup make me looks younger right.
I may sit here say I'm a student though.
2024 class right.
So this is a generator doing so try to get a sample sample.
That can be look like a real.
Here.
Disseminator try to be the enemy of the generator.
Try to.
Share a class file here.
That can differentiate whether the data is from X.
Or is from the GZ.
So it's like.
I'm sitting one of the here right.
There's one disc.
I'm not in the age of yours right.
So try to see who is the one.
Not really from this class but sitting here.
So now you see right to our task is.
We were going to train both the generator and the discriminator.
We change the generator.
To produce samples that cannot be differentiated by.
The discriminator.
And we change the discriminator.
Such that I can always.
The sample.
Perfect images.
Right so.
And of course based on this right.
It's all discriminator we can have some and generate we have some loss.
And.
Here that.
We require this discriminator and this is generator to be.
Differentiable module.
So I know what's the meaning of different.
You learn the thing right in the first part.
Of course.
Okay.
I know.
I know why with this one.
What does it mean.
Differentiable module.
I know.
Okay.
Yeah.
Short word.
It means these two parts can be trained.
Well we can.
Gradient descent right.
Use a great decent algorithm to train right.
But.
Not every.
So.
So that we will I will show you why.
Why why we say this.
Yeah so.
So that means that if you're actually.
So.
We have.
One generator we have one to some a letter.
Right so and why is try to.
Produce fixed down samples why is try to tear whether it's true or not.
So these two.
I should have.
Two.
Objectives right why is.
Why is.
Where where there is true true or not why is try to make it.
Looks like true.
So how do we change this overall.
System.
That works.
For example we can change that this matter first.
Then change that this letter generator.
And after generally trained then we change this matter again.
Then.
Generator again.
Keep this iteration until we find convergence.
So how do we change right so just now we mentioned is.
We need to make sure that this matter is.
Differentiable.
That means it can be trained.
So.
We have some random variable we get some.
Generate some data based on.
Here with the generator will be keep frozen here.
Where we can.
We get some examples because some random some from the real world image here.
And we will try to.
Compute the difference based on the.
Or the score the loss right and based on this loss we do a buck propagation.
To update the way of the.
That's.
The loss it can.
So after.
After the disseminated chain.
We will.
For the.
The way of the two metal now we change the.
Generator.
Because we require the generation of differential module right so it also can be.
And we do the same buck propagation.
To update the way inside here.
And then keep this.
So.
The.
Here is the mass emitter formulation of.
The gas training objective.
So let's say we have a reward.
Hello.
The discriminator try to.
Differentiate the.
True sample and the fake sample right.
So it is trying to.
Maximize the.
The loss.
Right.
On the other side.
The generator is trying to.
Make the difference.
Or the.
That.
Discmented reward.
Smaller.
So it is trying to minimize this.
So that's why this is the formulation is.
Is a mean max of the.
Of the reward function.
So.
This.
This is.
Assume the.
Input X.
And the.
The D.
The input training data is have a.
Distribution of X and with the.
Discmentor they are.
We call their entropy actually is.
The input.
Yeah.
Entropy actually is.
Information theory will be like this.
And.
The.
So we have one.
Triton maximum reward on one.
Minimize the reward.
So when we do the minimizer reward.
We should be.
And.
Those are.
Gam.
So.
This is actually.
Based on the Nash.
Euclid.
And.
So now I have a question right.
Assuming this.
Guy network is fully trained.
And it's converged.
What are we going to be the.
Output of the discriminator.
What's the value.
Actually.
I see this one was.
One was a question exam questions.
In the last year's video signal processing.
The.
Will not appear again in this course.
Is.
Here is.
Assumption that.
Of course.
That you have an output of.
Zero to one zero means.
Is fact.
One means is true.
And when the network is fully trained right.
I will hope this generator can generate image.
That can.
Create.
That looks like a real risk image right.
Because these two images are.
The general image and the real world image.
Close to each other.
Disimulator.
No.
So.
When you cannot.
What that means.
Your output.
Between zero and one.
Right.
Ideally.
Point five.
This.
Is.
The training data.
And the general data.
Of the same distribution.
Right.
Otherwise it's not.
Only when.
Equal.
Generator.
Converged.
Of course if you try.
Encourage you every one.
You.
Can network.
To see.
How the.
Loss.
Changes.
Training.
Training of the.
Is it much different.
Compared with the training of the.
Simple.
Network.
Art.
So if you don't have experience you may not be able to change it very well.
So.
You just.
Take this as a.
Optional homework.
Yeah.
So.
I want.
Because.
I believe this is really very good.
So.
This is just.
The detailed.
So do I have to change this.
So.
Every time when we change the.
Model I we just get a.
Mini batch of the samples.
And to change.
The.
Dictator first.
And.
Of course.
Change all that you can make text steps.
And after this.
Change.
We change the generator.
And these two are.
Keep.
It.
Ration.
So.
An artist.
And we see.
The left one is a real one.
Or the left one is the fake one.
How do you know.
I'm making one and tell yourself.
Tell me the answer.
Yeah.
Okay.
So this actually is.
And each each.
It actually is.
It should not be the.
Limitation of the gun theory.
But it's actually because of the.
Implementation of the actual.
So.
Why is this one.
Why is this happens.
It's actually because of the generator.
So.
The generator can be used now.
Very often we use.
So called encoder decoder.
Or, or unit kind of structures.
And these are structures.
Right.
So.
They cannot maintain some of the high frequency information.
Although it.
Maintain maturity of information.
It's not.
Some of the high frequency vision is lost.
That's the details you are.
Cannot be seen now.
I should have been.
I thought some.
Some.
Several years experiencing in one of the companies.
And at that time we once developed some.
Some.
Arquisms to teach.
Or teach the younger students.
So what do we do?
We.
We actually.
Give a whiteboard.
And let the student the child to.
Joe something on the board.
And then we will generate.
An image that.
Partially controlled by how they generate.
Joe the controls.
For example, if they draw.
Dirty line like that.
Right.
We will have a mountain be generated.
This is the shape of the mountain follows.
That's here.
And we can.
Joe something green.
It will help the creator green grass.
We do something blue.
It will help your blue sky.
So this is how.
The AI.
Can't do.
Right now.
But how you can see.
So at the early time when the guy is.
Invented.
So.
I think they first try to generate.
The face.
So of course for face here we are.
Using the cropped face and.
Different faces.
And the picture issue just now we have a low quality right.
So they.
The people was trying to.
Figure out.
New which to improve the quality.
So.
Yeah.
But you follow interest you can.
find the paper is some other published paper and quite famous.
And the quality being image or quality be generous.
Is higher than.
The very original gun.
And this year we saw this picture, right?
So, and I think in 2006, there was three papers
and all the AI.
So one of the work should be this Boseman machine
and the one with the Nobel Prize is this.
So, so now just briefly you choose again, right?
So later we will show that gun can be used
in many, many different applications.
But one of the advantage of a gun is that
during the training of the gun, the generator
never sees the training data.
So let's go back to the beginning.
So, let's say we have a machine that
has a machine that can be used in many different applications.
So let's go back to the slides just now.
Okay, we look at here, right?
Our real world image as a training data,
it was an input to the discriminator, right?
But it was never an input to the generator.
Right, that means when I choose the generator,
I do not have a direct input,
do not have access of the, or direct access
of the real world images.
So that means the generator,
let me see,
you only see based on the feedback from the discriminator.
This is actually different from the normal
seeing a network, right?
When we check seeing a network,
you can just consider this discriminator
and the network, right?
Did not see the training images.
This actually was at the pages of gun that is,
it's make it more robust to avoid overfitting.
So, now let's compare the gun with a normal deep learning
or normal seeing or chat warmers.
So a normal deep learning is try to train a network
based on those functions of the network.
And so let's say we, if we want to share
a simple common network, G, right?
So we are trying to meet my loss of G.
Full players, why is this matter, why is generator?
Instead of a simple,
here only one players, right?
Now I give, let you have 10 minutes to try.
If my objective function is designed to be,
have input X and Y, my objective is X times Y.
You try to see why this function is not differentiable
or not converged.
I give you 10 minutes to try.
Okay.
Of course you can look at yours.
So you have a couple of notes, right?
You can have a look at the notes
and follow the notes to try to understand this.
Okay.
Let's go through this together.
So to change this game with this objective function, right?
So we will need to maximize this value
to find the Y, to maximize value first.
Then find the X to minimize this value.
So let's first assume a set of one.
Where both X and Y are positive.
Therefore the V is positive, right?
So at this time, if we want to adjust Y,
such that this V XY is maximized, what do we do?
We will increase Y, right?
And after Y is increased, it's still positive.
And the next step is try to minimize this V XY
by decrease X, right?
So we will need to increase Y first and decrease X.
So by increase, if the status is still XY positive, right?
We will keep increase Y and keep decrease X.
So and this is the end of the game.
So we will increase Y and decrease X.
So until what time?
Until X smaller than zero, right?
So from set one, where both X and Y are positive,
we keep increase Y and decrease X.
We will eventually come to set two,
where X is smaller than zero,
because we are, because Y is keeping increasing, right?
So Y will still be positive.
But at this time, V will be negative.
And instead too, right?
We will try to do the same thing,
because this is negative.
Now we try to maximize the V XY.
Maximize the V XY.
We will want to, because it's a negative value,
we want to reduce Y, right?
Because if Y is, since Y is positive,
we reduce it, we will make the overall product smaller.
And because this is a negative sign here,
the X is negative.
So we will reduce it, it will,
overall value will be increased.
And easily you can draw that.
At this time, we want to decrease X,
because make the X smaller,
it will make the overall V smaller.
So you continue this from,
you continue decrease Y and X,
and here it goes to the step three,
where the, because you are keep decreasing the Y
until you decrease X, then both XY will be negative.
And at this time, V will be positive again.
And then you repeat this, you will get step four,
because here you are, you will need to decrease Y
and increase X, you make X become positive,
Y is negative, and then you will have to increase Y
and increase X to optimize this function.
Eventually you will come back to,
come back to step five,
which is actually same as step one.
So that means you want to change this function, right?
If you are doing a cycling,
going back to original steps,
so it will never converge.
Okay, so now we have 15 minutes break.
And after that we will talk about the variation of the guns
and eventually how guns apply to the videos.
Okay.
You will come back by 7.57.
During the break time,
if you have any questions on the first part,
you can approach me.
Thank you.
Let's continue the second part.
Just now we choose the basic concept of the
generative network, right?
So that network will ask you to give a random input
and generate something, right?
But what if I want to give some,
ask the generative network to generate a certain thing
or certain type of object,
or some object in certain locations.
Let's say I want this generator to generate
a picture of an apple or a picture of a human.
How do I do it?
Because you, or your other words, right?
Which random variable I should give the generator
such that it can generate an apple or generate a facial image, right?
So it's actually very difficult for me to tell that.
So to overcome this issue, right?
We, and new concept or a variation of the gun
is called conditional gun.
Which is, I want to make the generator to generate
something conditional to an input.
So if my input is to say, I may give the input like,
I want to generate an image of apple.
So the generator will give me an image of apple.
So now you have the chat gpt, right?
So I'm not sure you can try.
I think you can, it's able to generate some images.
You can try chat gpt, even the basic free version.
So if we remove this C class part.
So here we have real world data.
We have a random variable noise.
Go through a generator to generate fake data and the generator.
This is the classical gun, right?
And the conditional guys, we have a mission here.
This is also input.
And this condition will be connected to the,
give to the, actually will be combined with the training data here.
And also give the input link to the generator.
So that means the generator will take the input of both the
condition and the random noise.
It's actually simple, right?
So you give a condition, you give me your condition.
And I'm going to give this, pass this condition to both the
training data and the generator.
So look carefully at, so this one will be give to the,
both the training data and the generator.
So let's say we want to use the minister digits data to
chain a generator, again, generate a digital number.
So if we use the original guy, right?
So it may take a random input to generate a number.
It could be any number from zero to nine.
But with the conditional, we will hope that we give this,
your input, give an input of one zero zero.
I can generate different variation of zero.
I gave a second input of zero one zero zero.
I will be able to generate one and until last zero zero one,
different initial nine.
So this is called conditional generation.
So what can we do with the conditional generation?
So for example, if I give you a input which is a label of,
or a symmetric labels,
let's say we use this blue color to represent the potential cars.
The green represents the trees.
Blue represents the sky.
A street immunizes.
So this is called conditional generation.
Right?
So here, the boundary of these labels of the car will defy,
or is like condition, where this car should be located.
It won't be a car here or here,
because my condition here is say this car should be here, here, here.
And the road should be here, right?
And the sky should be here.
So this should be sky.
It shouldn't be road.
And here it shouldn't be sky.
It should be road.
So this labels street.
Output.
At the same time, right, we can use this input.
Labels are the input on the street seen as output.
So this is a label to street.
But let's say if we give this as an input.
If the street seen as an input, this is the output.
What I'm doing?
If this street is an input, I pay this gun to get this.
What is the operation?
We call this symmetric representation, right?
So in the first part of this course, right, you may have learned,
we can use a different network to do a symmetric representation.
Conditional gun to do a symmetric representation.
Okay.
And there will be some difference between
for convolution network approach and the gun approach.
So if you have some experience, let's say do a segmentation of something.
So here, right, this is the satellite view images of the city, for example.
Or this may be white one, maybe the road.
The rest may be the trees or other fields, right?
From this input to the output, what we are doing.
We are trying to segment what are the road, right?
So if you ever have tried some training, some deep learning,
or you ever do segmentation approach,
there are some segments.
You may face what?
You may face where you do some things.
Your output may be discontinuous, right?
Let's say we do an edge detection, right?
A simple edge detection.
A lower line, right?
Some of the lines are very clear, but some place the line may be not that clear, right?
This quite often will appear, right?
So what will happen?
Your detection will be broken.
You will be able to detect easily in the background where the line is very clear.
But you may get disconnected or miss some lines as a place where the line is not that clear.
So you can see here, right?
We have a back.
If we use this as an input, we try to detect the lines, right?
You see here it's broken, right?
But we know in this back here the line is actually continuous, right?
We do a...
You will be...
have a better result in terms of the connectivity.
So you look at the...
If we check a gun, all the roads are actually continuously detected.
I want to say it won't be broken, but you get a chance of a broken road here will be small.
But if you want to check a direct sanitation, even we ask you to annotate where is the road, right?
It will be able to annotate correctly, right?
You know why?
The reason is...
Okay, you listen carefully.
The reason is when we are checking a gun with this input to get this output, right?
Our output, our training data, all are labeled with continuous levels.
If my output is not continuous from the discriminator point of view, right?
I can easily tell.
My ground choice is continuous, but my detection output is just continuous.
Later, we will make the gun to segment the road.
That has a distribution or visually looks similar to the training data.
And because of the training data is...
Because you annotate that, right?
So you will definitely...
You know it's all connected.
So because our training data is continuous, so your result from the gun will also be continuous.
And so this actually...
This is a task, an explanation.
We use the best approach, we will be better.
But of course, it will also come with consequence.
Just now, we mentioned, right?
The guys try to learn a distribution.
Let's go to the slides.
The guys are good at capturing the models of the distribution of the training data.
So my training data is all continuous, so my detection will be continuous.
Because if my detection is not continuous from the discriminator point of view, right?
I will just tell whether your output is continuous or not continuous.
Based on that, I can easily tell you whether your detection output is true or correct or not correct.
Okay.
Come back to here, right?
So we also have labels of the buildings or windows and structures and come back to the...
Converting to a true building.
If we go the other way wrong, right?
From these are the inputs, these are the outputs.
It will be similar to symmetric simulation.
And this case, right?
From color to gray scale, right?
Easy, right?
You have a simple equation to do that.
But from gray scale to color, right?
So...
Actually, from color to gray, some information is lost, right?
So from gray, come back to color, right?
So here we use scan or image-to-image translation.
We can achieve this.
Of course, we call this image-to-image translation is because my input and output are both like images, right?
Even though the schematic labels is...
You can display the images.
Also try night to day.
But I have some experience on this, right?
From day to night, you normally can do very well, right?
Because your day image normally have full information.
But from night to day, right?
You can try.
There are some chain network outside.
From night to day, you...
Major case, you want to get very good result.
Because at night, a lot of information here...
It's not well captured.
Here, like this...
We also call this a saturation.
Of course, over exposure or under exposure, both are too bright or too dark.
Both are called saturation.
Because this is a saturated, so you want to be able to see what's information here.
So you want to be able to recover this.
Here, from this sketch to the back, we call it...
Add the color into it.
The other way, from the back to the...
This one is equivalent to edge detection.
So you can see, right?
From image to image translation, you can do a lot of things.
You can do symmetric of sanitation.
You can do greater color coloring.
You can do day to night or day translation.
You can do edge detection, right?
So I'm also working on this to use image to image translation to...
Let's say we have different camera, right?
Of course, a camera will have so-called image processing to convert the raw input or raw data in the sensor side to the image you are seeing.
In this process, they have removed the noise.
But actually, different sensors may have different noise.
So we can also do the image to image translation such that my data captured from device A can become data covered by device B.
So...
Image to image translation can be categorized into actually two different categories.
One we call paired image to image translation.
Of course, the other is figured out, right?
It's unpaired.
What's the difference?
The difference is in paired image to image translation.
We will have an image input with corresponding output.
So let's say we have a...
Downsampling, right?
We have a factory image.
Downsampling, please.
Or do segmentation, right?
From a street image to a...
...segmentation labels.
Or from the labels to the synthesis of street images.
And from a single image, right?
To aspects.
What's the depth of...
Back to the images.
So in paired image to image translation, we actually have one to one mapping between the...
...synced images.
Now a quick test.
If we...
...enraitor and to get a...
...back.
And we also have a discriminator to tell whether it's true or not.
Is this conditional?
How many say yes?
You can raise your hand.
How many say no?
Is it either yes or no?
Okay, someone's...
Try to be active, okay.
So this actually is a...
...conversion of a gun.
Here?
Yeah?
I give you the X.
And we have a network G and TRD to generate this GX.
And my network is like this.
This one is not conditional gun.
Which part is missing?
I don't know.
Not included what?
No, not this.
Actually, class is one kind of condition.
Here, my condition is this.
You know the answer?
You try. Anybody can try.
Remember, just now we were talking about gun, right?
What's the input?
Okay, you got some of the answers?
Yes?
So because the discriminator don't have the condition of the X.
That's one reason is...
Where is the random variable?
So...
This comes with the so-called X.
We are...
Conditional gun, right?
So this X is a condition.
And it comes with the generator.
It also comes with the discriminator.
This is the reason why the network just now is not conditional gun.
Because the X is not given to the discriminator.
Okay, this one I may want to skip.
So this thing can be applied to supra-lucine.
And this is supra-lucine again.
Now let's talk about unpaired.
The paired gun, right?
In the paired image translation, you have one from one mapping.
But in red here...
Paired training data is a bit time consuming.
Of course you can do it.
But if...
Let's say one year later you graduate and you take a job, right?
If your company asks you just every day to collect the data,
you will say, I don't want to do that.
So trust me, that you will say that.
That's why I'm always coming.
Nobody like...
Everybody like to work on something with high technology.
And keep collecting the data is not something...
Of course, sometimes we have to do that.
But we always try to find our way.
If I don't keep collecting the data, I still can't do it.
So in reality, right?
Let's say if we want to change the network,
we can turn horses to zebras, right?
It will be very difficult to have one-to-one machine
where the shape of the horse is exactly the same as the zebra.
You can easily get a lot of images of horses
and get a lot of images of zebras.
If you want these two animals to be exactly paired,
it will be very difficult.
But we still want zebras.
So although each image will not have a mapping,
one-to-one mapping, but these two domains could be mapped.
For example, I may take an image of the horses
where the size of the horse is comparable to the image of zebras.
To the size of the zebras in the image of zebras.
If this side is...
So we call this...
...pair.
And here comes the idea of a cycle gun.
So inclusion is very simple, right?
So if y have two domain x and y,
I want to have a generator or a gun generator to convert x to y.
But we also hope this y can come back to x.
So x can go to y, y can come back to x.
Then we have two generators.
Y is called g, y is called f.
So g is converted x to y.
f is converted y to x.
This forms a cycle, right?
So I can fly from Singapore to China,
but I should also be flying back, right?
And this process, right?
You can consider.
You can consider, right?
And if we compare...
...to the same thing for the y.
So we try to minimize this cycle consistency.
Then we can change the...
Let's say I do a translator, right?
...translator, right?
...from Chinese to the English.
I hope that English...
During the translation, all the information should be saved.
If there's some information being lost, just come back.
Just give it to the translation.
Give it an English sentence.
Let's try to translate to Chinese,
and then translate it back to see whether it's the same or not.
I believe it won't be identical,
but a good network should be close to each other.
So with a side gun, right?
We can do...
...transfer for different weather from zebra to horse to zebra,
and from summer to winter and winter to summer, right?
So if we want to use a paired gun, right?
The paired image...
We need to collect the data from the summer and the same data,
same place in the winter, right?
So if I want to turn Singapore Street View,
become a winter view, there's no way.
Because we don't have paired winter...
...here, there, and take a picture in the summer
and half a year later, right?
The texture of the winter, then...
Of course, you can get some data, right?
But with a side gun, we do not use it, right?
With a side gun, we can do...
...we can...
...the same city, maybe,
and then we can turn to the buildings to be completely different.
But at winter time, we do not require the camera to be at the same location,
or exact same location, just similar location will be fine.
And then we can change from winter to summer.
And...
...for side gun, right?
So actually even for normal gun, right?
So there's one potential challenge is sometimes...
...the training, the model will be collapsed.
So with the one-to-one mapping, right?
We hope every item here have a unique mapping on the right side.
But when the model collapsed, everything will be mapped to one thing.
And this is the issue.
Now just now we show some images.
Effect...
...the real image, I ask you to...
...which one is the effect, right?
I can see from the details, right?
It's one of the weakness of the gun network.
And this few years, there's another type of generation technology being popular,
which we call diffusion.
So I only want to introduce the concept of...
...input...
...turn this input one step into many, many steps.
And in each step, I add some noise.
So here is an image driver.
I'll add some noise.
Make this...
...like completely random, right?
From X0 to X1, there's a network.
Normally they use a unit structure.
So if you haven't learned a unit, I think in my part, I will cover that.
And from X2 to X1 to X2, there will be another unit.
So let's say N is 1000.
It's like true 1000 units.
And each unit, you add some noise.
You will get this random.
And if we change this one, right?
If we make use of ideal cycle gun, we should come back.
So when we have that unit, we add noise.
We also hope to have a unit that can remove noise.
From X1, I want to go back to Xn minus one.
I want to go back to Xn minus two.
And cheer go back to X0.
This...
From left to right, we add noise, right?
From right side to left side, we are removing noise.
Or we can solve this noise.
So...
You can think of what...
We may have some task to do noise removal, right?
This place is to remove the noise, right?
So this diffusion has an application that can be used for removal noise.
But one of the big advantage of diffusion is that this process...
...
So this you can try if you have some access of the GPUs.
There are many public...
...
Now, so...
Just now we are talking about using image as an example.
So come back to video.
So how the game can be used to generate a video.
Of course, the video may have images and...
...
So video is a sequence of images.
Just now we learn how to generate images.
Now, to generate video, right?
We actually generate a sequence of images.
...
but I also make sure this a series image...
So, how the way is...
...
How we generate a video is take care of making sure the...
And of course, you can use...
...
So let's come to some other approach
where they convert a text for video.
So when we generate a single image, right?
So we just make sure this image is a similar distribution
compared with the training images.
When we generate a video, right?
So besides to make the image looks real,
we also make sure the image sequence looks real.
And when we have a text input,
this is like a condition, right?
Text, let's say,
this image should be
between the text and the video.
Okay.
Although this just looks quite complicated,
but the main concept here is
we want this network to generate something
where the image look real.
And of course this comes with,
we should have some training data
that can tell stories.
So the images is,
this one frame two to three,
it should follow the similar appearance
in existing video data,
or the data you are used to change the video generation.
So besides the image itself, right?
So this case maybe
is more easier to understand.
So for video, right?
So we know the video actually can be
an image plus a motion, right?
So if a video, am I working here?
Then you can say this is
an image of me, and from one frame to another frame,
I'm working, right?
There's a motion.
So we may have asked,
so if we can generate the image in a real disk way,
and also make sure the motion is realistic.
So if I'm working at speed,
like example, five kilo per hour, for example, right?
And this is my training data.
I will generate a video.
I shouldn't be running very, very fast,
like a car is driving, right?
Because in another video, I can go in that speed.
So I'm not sure how many of you are taking the course
of the video signal processing.
You know, video compression, right?
So we basically compress the image into
i-frame, b-frame, p-frame, and p-frame.
The i-frame is the independent recording frame,
and the rest may be based on the prediction
from the previous frames.
So you can say that one frame is the image frame.
The rest of the motion frame.
So we'll be generating the motions, motion vectors.
So if the motion vectors are realistic,
then my video will be real.
So this solar, right?
So it's, we can try in our website.
And it is based on, I'm not sure
whether you have learned about the future mode
I mentioned just now, right?
And the transformer is a new architecture
that previously may learn about convolutional network, right?
Transformer is based on attention,
convolutional network.
And this solar is purely based on transformer
and diffusion models.
And it's going to be a generous, realistic videos.
How is this?
So in summary, today we,
we choose the guns,
generation networks.
And it includes the generator and also discriminator.
Of course, the very one has best one generator
and one discriminator.
But nowadays there are a lot of approaches
where they may have multiple generator
and multiple discriminator.
So if you see, if you go do some research in the area,
you will be able to see that.
The generators try to generate
as input random noise is gonna go there.
And discriminator is t dismiss,
ser-
blockchain.
And per function.
That is function of the speculative type,
not set up to receive.
So it's being identified.
The other, right.
It's like, left hand fight with your right hand.
And eventually both hands can fight very well.
And,
by,
and the model will become better.
At the end of the network when the network is converged,
both components are good as they are.
Right?
And because the generator is doing very good,
you can generate data that's for the simulator.
Disminator.
And when the output of the samples from the generator
and the samples from the real world distribution
are given to the simulator,
what does the simulator do?
It will not be able to tear, right?
Because you can fool me.
That's why just now I say the simulator will get it.
Right?
But because the generator is very, very well,
so you will get 0.5.
But of course, if you go try, train your own approach,
you want to get, ideally, ideally get 0.5,
but you won't get that.
An example is just now you see the fact data
and the details are missing, right?
Okay, so in the second part,
we do have one assignment.
And this assignment will be,
what's called?
Yeah, this is the first one I should have, right?
Have keys, right?
And then you have a,
and then you have a,
yeah, final score?
Here.
Finish.
Suppose you receive a task, and the task,
let's say you're a company, right?
Fake images of Donald Trump, right?
And this is just the task to give it to you.
I hope you can describe how you are doing.
Put this into the system,
and in the day or tomorrow, maybe,
and you will be able to upload your solution to this.
Yeah, so I will let you,
I will just look at your final one as your solution.
So I will keep the system open until November.
So I want you to describe
how you should use to change it, right?
So second is what is the network architecture you are using?
And besides the data and the network,
so what other resource you want?
So you have some, think carefully of this task
and give me your explanation and how you think,
your thoughts in this task.
Yeah, I can remind you it's not as simple as you may think.
So, but,
and I think in the last two years
when I teach video signals,
I want to go for PhD because my,
let's say this A or B has a lot of map.
They don't really look at your scores.
Of course, your all is all C compared with another
with all A is matters.
B plus or B minus one structure itself is one.
Some students,
you'll look at your record as groups and never look at it.
For,
part of paper before,
I see you here from your seniors,
how competitive we are in the future.
I'm curious how competitive we are now
if we want to get that scholarship to do PhD
in previous computer science,
and I'll call it CCDS, right?
The why?
A subject,
but doing PhD is,
it's not for you to learn something, right?
So, at time you think you want to learn something,
you are already, PhD is for you to invent something,
to discover something.
Much helpful.
So, this is also why I hope you to explain your design
and your course.
You just spend time on it.
And also,
based on my experience, right?
So, the criteria for your information is,
we actually,
only 100 score, right?
There's no way, so they will adjust.
You try to think of this,
by no effort.
Okay, I think that's,
most of, that's almost everything today.
And, I also like to share
my opinion on the,
what you should learn from this course.
Or,
what are the opinions when I'm,
from bachelor to come here to for PhD study?
I actually know very little about the potential research topics.
And therefore, I just choose one topic I hear about.
But from this course,
I hope you know more about the research topic
that's currently hot,
or you may be able to work on it.
So, I'm not going to examine your,
so,
but I will test you on how you understand the things,
understand the concept.
So, I can do that.
Technology.
Or existing.
If we,
to say whether it's novel or not,
we may say it's not really novel.
But what it dissolves is,
how to do,
how to,
the network can generate the data
as long as you wish.
So, it is one of the potential ways
to solve the data.
So, you may hear about the AI have three main components.
Why is the data?
Right.
So, data is one with the generate the AI.
Or mix them or
say in this lecture, I shared again.
So, and from the general,
difference.
Conceal is a little different.
It's just different dimensionality of the data.
Images are here, right?
We also have a 3D.
Pretty much.
And the image plus become video is,
is, is other go is another kind of it is just to
the time.
Of course, you may have 4D, right?
So, I have MRI data plus time.
So, that's, that's the single way you
data of the fact of the video, right?
So, you look at the talk, I believe there are some
things that are not,
but the fact of the video,
the fact of the video that looks really quite high quality.
This assignment and the, the score,
the assignment, it won't be, don't worry about that.
So, if you're fair, either you didn't submit the assignment.
You also didn't attend the quiz.
It's two parts, right?
So, I think it's about 40% of the issue.
And until I see you, as long as you got 50,
I'll score, I'll score your pass already.
The, the, the, the, the result is already become zero.
Score 70, right?
Point six times 70, you still can pass, right?
42.
So it's actually quite easy to pass, get something.
And if you go for a job,
the top,
I don't need a company,
I don't look at the transfer rate.
I just talk to each of you,
ask what you have done,
whether you can...
Some students can answer.
I think you don't know the details.
So...
I can tell.
Yeah, and the score for this wanna be very...
I think as long as it submits your solution,
you shouldn't be a...
You should get at least a pass within this part.
Yeah, but on average,
these are...