you
are
.
Last week we studied the
traditional neural network, the
M.A.R.P.
and how powerful is the neural
network and what is the problem of
the traditional neural network.
And how the
C.A.N.
solve the problem of the
M.A.R.P.
basically it is
the overfitting
problem of the M.A.R.P.
.
So maybe just use a few words to
summarize the property of the
C.A.N.
and just one most
significant property of the C.A.N.
.
So the C.A.N.
is a
kind of a field or
convolution.
So the convolution
if the field is small
then the output
only depends on
the few input
no-coning.
Because if the field window is
small, output only depends on a few
inputs.
So the C.A.N.
is the
two determining the output
in one layer of the C.A.N.
.
So people always understand C.A.N.
in such a way.
This is a very
straightforward understanding
of the C.A.N.
.
So people always think C.A.N.
is some kind of the local feature.
So C.A.N.
is a very good property.
But in my
opinion this is not
the most important features
of the C.A.N.
The most important feature
of the C.A.N. is
one output
depends on a few inputs.
This is not very important.
The important sense is
the
relation between output and input
goes through a few weights.
The two weights
are used
for all output.
You see in that
field time process
the field
coefficient, the field window
we are sliding to all positions.
So that means
all output pictures
come from
same field coefficient.
So I think
this is the most important.
The most important feature
of the C.A.N.
is the
output.
So in the prediction process
or in the traditional
field image to get the output
this is not important
but in the machine learning
if we introduce this one
in the machine learning
then in the training phase
that means a same parameter
goes through all pictures
and the value
of the parameter is very reliable
robust because
it is determined
by all pictures
in the input.
So I think this is
the most significant
feature of the C.A.N.
Of course I haven't read this
statement from any paper
or any literature. This is what
my thought, my understanding
of the C.A.N.
because
I mean
particular parameter will go through
every position so all
pictures are used to determine
the value of the parameter.
So this is
most significant.
That means the same parameter
are applied to all
output of a layer
of the C.A.N.
Okay later we will further
utilize this one to study
how the
transformer works.
Okay.
Now before we
come to the transformer
we first
take some time
to study some extension
of the C.A.N.
because C.A.N. is very powerful
so it must be trained
by a large dataset.
So usually if
we want to solve the problem
we use a powerful C.A.N.
trained by a huge dataset.
Okay.
But the C.A.N. in nature
it is a general feature extractor.
Right? It extracts the feature
from the image. This is
a very general
extractor feature from the input.
If we use a huge dataset
to train it then
the extract feature will be
a general feature on
the huge dataset.
But how to utilize this powerful C.A.N.
to solve some
specific application problem?
Then
for specific application problem
we need to put some additional
components on top
of the C.A.N. so that
together the network
can perform a specific
task. Okay.
So for specific tasks we also
have a training dataset
but this dataset could be small
compared to such as
the image needs this huge dataset.
Right? But we need to adapt
the general C.A.N.
into specific tasks.
So here we
first introduce some examples
how to utilize the C.A.N. to solve
specific tasks.
Now the first one is
we utilize the C.A.N.
for the image segmentation.
Okay. Here we show an image
this one. Right? Then this is
a segmentation result.
Here with different C.A.N.
represent different object.
Sorry.
Okay.
Okay. This one.
This picture shows the segmentation result.
We use different color
indicate different
object be segmented
by the image.
So we have a segmentation result
which is the image
such as a person, the car,
the road, the side road,
the building, the sky.
And so on. Right?
So this shows the segmentation result.
From this segmentation result
we see that the so-called
semantic segmentation need
classify every picture
into different class.
Okay. Not classify
every picture into different class.
So for such
segmentation problem it will be
much
complicated than just
an image classification
problem. Image classification
given one image the output
of the network just one class.
But for the segmentation we need
classify this picture
into the person, this picture
into the road, this picture
into the building, and the other
part of the segmentation is
much more complex
than the image classification
or object recognition because
it need classify every
picture in the input image.
Now then how
to use the print trend
powerful thing to
solve this segmentation
task. Now
first of all we use one thing
and this blue color one
is a wrist
net 101.
It's a wrist net has
101 layers.
Okay. You such a very
powerful CNN. This CNN
is print trend by the image
net. Okay. So the
performance of this CNN for
the image classification is
very excellent.
It's already print trend.
Now after
we use this powerful
CNN as a backbone. If we
want it to do the
image segmentation
so what additional
sense we need to do?
Okay. So first
of all we
study the structure of this
print trend and wrist net 101.
So the input image
is 500 by
500.
3 channel RGB. And then
after many convolutional layer
and pooling layer at the last
convolution layer the output
that becomes to 16 by
16 with
2,000 channels.
Okay. So this is the
output of the CNN and of course
last convolution layer
of the wrist net
101.
Now the wrist
net is
all
parameter is trend by image
net. The image net
is classifying every image
into different class.
Okay. So after
this last layer of the
CNN and then all this
value are used as the feature
to do the classification.
Then to classify the whole
input into one of the
into one of the class.
Right. So here we see
that the final classification
still utilize some
spatial information of the input
image because the last
layer the feature map is
16 by 16.
So we have
similar to image size
of the 16 by 16.
We still utilize this 16
by 16 features
together to perform
the classification.
Now because of this training
in case that means the
16 by 16
metrics
each element in this
metrics will be different
because they are trained
together to make a
decision to do the classification.
Right. Okay.
But for the segmentation
we need to classify
every pixel even
in this last
even in this
sorry.
Okay.
Sorry.
Yes.
Okay. Even in
this last layer
we need to classify every pixel
into different class.
So but the output
is trained
not
for each individual one
to determine its class
but together to determine its
class. Okay.
Now we understand that if we
want to we are classify
a pixel for example we
cannot just look at this pixel
we should look at its
surroundings so that
this is some kind of the context
of this pixel.
So because of that if we
utilize this in the print transition
directly to do the
segmentation that means to
classify every element in
this special map
16 by 16 it will perform
poorly because the print
training is not such
a purpose. Okay.
Well in this
application we need to classify
every pixel independently
into different class. So
every pixel one pixel
unknown may not
contain sufficient information
to determine this what
is this pixel reliably.
So we need to build up
so called context that means
to classify each of this
16 by 16 pixel we need
to look at more information
its context or its
surroundings. So
to apply this print
transition into the segmentation
we need to build up another
a few layers
here CCA context
to further to do the
convolution
based on this 16 by 16
further
a few layers in this convolution
so that we can connect
the information of one
position not just from this position
also it is surroundings.
And this connection of these
surroundings to train its weights
is used our segmentation
data set.
The ground truth is
the segmentation is different from
the previous the
segmentation data set.
The ground truth is just
the whole image is one class.
Now here we
we are training this CCA
this context is
we are utilizing our segmentation
data set. The ground truth are
different in the segmentation
training data set we have the ground
truth different pixel is
different class.
So here we need to build
up our context
to look at this pixel
not just look at this pixel
look at more surroundings
okay we need
to classify one pixel
we need to look at more
surrounding information to determine
which is a class of one pixel.
So we need a so-called context information
to get a better, renewable classification
for individual pixels.
Now, this is one site.
Another site is the image.
Object could have a large scale, could have a small scale.
For example, for this image, this person is large scale
because it's closer to the camera,
whereas the car is very small
because it is far away from the camera.
Some class, it can be small scale.
Some class, it can be large scale.
So for the classification, we cannot just
utilize the final feature to do the classification.
We also need some small-scale features.
That means the output of the convolution layer
in the earlier stage, in the earlier layers,
to do the classification.
Because we could have a very small scale of the object.
And also, along the edge, we need to look at a small scale
closely to do the classification.
If we use a large area, somehow it will average the information.
So it cannot specify to determine accurately the edge
location.
So to do the segmentation, we need to classify,
apply the classifier, not just in the last layer of the feature.
We also need to utilize the feature in the previous layers.
So all these features will come to a classification classifier.
Of course, the classifier is a very simple classifier,
just a linear classifier.
Then the classification result should merge together
to make a decision.
What is the class?
So this layer is called skip layer,
because it's from the earlier stage, skip to the last result
with a classification.
So this classification layer is called skip layers.
So we need to combine the classification of multiple
scale of the features, then merge them together
to make a decision.
So this is so-called skip layers to do that classification.
And also, even we use lower layer of the feature
to directly do the classification,
and then merge them together.
So usually, we cannot use the very known layer,
because it is very noisy.
So we usually use the higher layer and the middle layer
feature to do the classification, then merge them together.
So the lower layer is very noisy.
If we use it to the classification,
it may cause some problem.
So the context information, built up context information
by these additional layers of the convolution,
and the merge of the classification
of multiple different layers to get the segmentation result.
This is already proposed before this work.
But then in one of my work, what is our contribution?
This work published in 3VPR 2018 as an aura paper,
and then later further published in a transaction
and image processing.
Now our contribution here is we make this context layer.
Context construction is not a simple convolution.
We try to build up our context as a contrast context.
Later I will elaborate that.
And the second contribution is we don't just simply sum
all classification score together.
We build up a gate to actively combine them together.
Because for some positions, we should mainly
use large scale of the feature.
For some other pictures, we may put more weightage
on a small scale of the feature.
Depends on the position is in the large scale of the object
or small scale of the object.
So here we built up the gate to control the fusion
of the classification score.
Now the third contribution of this work
is we utilize a very known layer of the feature.
But we only utilize it around the age,
around the boundary of the different object.
So we try to identify a position is close to the boundary
or far away to the boundary.
Then we utilize a very lower layer of the information
to work close to the boundary so that we
can very specific to determine the position of the boundary
more accurately.
OK, so this is the three contributions in this work.
Now I will go through the ideas of these three.
The first one is so-called we have the context,
but we call it the contrasted local feature.
Now how to build up the context?
For example, the last layer of the ResNet 101
is the 16 by 16 map.
So we want to connect information of larger area
as the context of the center pictures.
Before our work, others work is also
apply the convolution then to next layer,
then convolution to next layer.
Because convolution will connect information
in a window to the output.
So we were further to apply the convolution, of course,
trained by the segmentation data set
and not the imaginary data set.
But what in my opinion is if we further do the convolution,
although the output will connect the larger area of the information
as the output, but if the area is too large,
it will blur the information.
Because convolution anyway is a weighted average.
So if we weighted average of the picture of a larger area,
then as one output, then the output
is just some kind of the blurred information.
So this may cause some negative effect.
Now then how to connect the information of the context?
We do the contrast.
Given the input feature map, to produce the output feature map,
we apply two convolution.
One convolution is with a very small window.
For this 3 by 3, contains just a focus on the local area.
Get a convolution result.
And then we use a dynamic convolution, also nine pictures,
but it cover large area.
Then this is a convolution result.
Then the final result will be the difference between these two.
So here I show the difference between these two convolution.
So what is the purpose of this difference?
This difference means that the output
is focused on the information of this specific position.
But we compile this information with its surroundings
to see what is the difference.
OK, this is a contrast.
It's a difference.
So this is also simulating our human.
If our human want to identify what is it at one position,
we cannot just look at this one.
We must also look at some surrounding areas.
But the information at this one and the surrounding
are different.
We use the surrounding information
is just to do the comparison, compile,
what is the difference between this central information
and its surroundings.
This difference will help us to determine what is it
at the center point.
OK, so we build up this module, this block,
to call this context contrast local feature.
Because basically it is a local feature,
but it compiles with the surroundings
of these local positions.
So basically we also build up a few layers of this one.
And then all these features are used for the classification,
go to the fusion or classification scores.
OK, so this is one idea of this contribution.
Another contribution is so-called gauge sum.
As I mentioned that to do the segmentation,
we need to classify the feature of the convolution feature,
not just from one layer.
We need to classify the convolution feature
in many different layers.
Earlier layer is a small scale of the feature.
The high layer of the convolution has a larger scale.
Because after many convolutions, it
will connect a large area of the information.
So the feature is a larger scale.
Now here, this blue one is the backbone,
is the same as recently when 0.1.
So we utilize the feature map of different layers
to go to the classifier, then get the classification score
based on the different layer of the feature.
And then after that, at the end, is
a sum merge of all this classification
score to produce a final classification score.
But here, we don't just simply sum them together.
We produce a weight, so-called in the gauge fusion.
We produce a weight.
Then to make all this different, this classification score
from different layer, weight sum together
to produce a final classification score.
Now, mathematically, basically, it is just the weight sum.
This is a classification score.
This G is this weight.
OK.
Now, this is just a weight sum.
So why I call it a gauge sum?
Because in traditional way, how to determine the weights
in the weight sum?
Some approach, some application, we
may pre-define what is the weights.
Then to do the weight sum, some other approach
also try to determine this weights by the training data set.
That means the weight can be learned from the training data.
Right?
OK, so it will adapt to the training data.
So then to do the weight sum.
But here, this weight in this network is not pre-defined,
is also not determined by the training data.
It is generated by the test data.
OK, so because we have a network in the prediction process,
in the inference process, the input, the test image comes.
Then this test image comes, generates this convolution
and their output, then goes through this network
to generate what is the weights.
So the weights come from the test data,
not determined by the training data.
But this network, the permit of this network
is trained by the training data.
OK, but the real weights is generated by the test data.
So because of that, we call this is a gate to sum.
Now, how is this network?
OK, now, we have seen and has many layers.
Each layer will produce multiple feature maps.
And all these feature maps will come together
to do the classification.
Right?
Now, because one layer, each layer will produce
many feature maps, then we just use a convolution layer,
one by one convolution, to merge all map into one map.
OK, then one layer has only one map.
One map, we call this map as information map.
It contains information of this layer.
We convert multiple layers into just a single map
into just one single map.
This map is information map.
Now, from this information map, then we
use this information map of different layer
to generate the weights of this layer.
Now, but this information map, the information is unbalanced
because in the convolution network, in any network,
the information is from input to the output.
So the higher layer information is
generated by lower layer information.
So that means the higher layer information
contains a summary of the information of the lower layers.
But the lower layer has no information.
How is the higher layer summarize its information?
Become information in the higher layer.
So anyway, the information is transferred from one direction,
from no layer to higher layer.
To balance this information, then we
utilize a simple R to make the information of the higher
layer information map go to the no-neighborhood algorithm
to produce the final feature information map.
So this information will be more balanced
because the information now, this information,
is the two direction, or have two direction transfer
of the information.
So the information of a different layer,
the information will be balanced after we go through R.
Now then after that, of course, we
need some kind of the normalization.
And then we produce the weights based on this map.
OK, the weights is also a map because every pixel,
we have different cospheres.
We have different cospheres score.
Then we need to merge them together.
So why these weights cannot be generated by the training data?
Because for the segmentation, the object
for different test data are totally different.
Even a same person, for this test image,
it can be this position.
For other test images, it can be totally other position.
So the weights cannot be determined by the training data.
Must be generated by the specific training data
then used in the classification of pixels of this test data.
Now this is our second contribution.
Another one is so-called boundary reframing.
From here, we can see that in this network structure,
we see that from this classification score,
we merge them together.
We already have some roughly segmentation result.
And then from the roughly segmentation result,
we can generate a boundary of this test image.
Now this generated boundary, then
we can utilize it to guide how to utilize the lower neighbor
feature.
We can put the lower neighbor feature higher weight
for the position close to the boundary
and the small weights for the feature far away from the boundary.
This is an idea.
The idea is also not difficult to understand.
So basically, given an image from the higher neighbor feature
and a middle neighbor feature classification,
we can roughly get a rough segmentation result.
Then based on the rough segmentation result,
we can produce a boundary.
This boundary, of course, is just one pixel line
to form this boundary.
Now from this boundary, we can always
go through a smooth field to convert this hard boundary
into a soft boundary.
This one is a hard boundary because the boundary
pixel is 1.
Not a boundary is 0.
It's a hard boundary.
So we convert this into a soft boundary.
That means the pixel value is directly from 0, increased to 1,
and then decreased to 0.
The soft boundary.
We easily understand.
Go through a smooth field such as Gaussian field,
then we can blur this boundary into a soft boundary.
Here, we use a Gaussian field to produce a soft boundary.
But if we utilize the Gaussian field, the Gaussian field,
if we choose a Gaussian field, we choose a Gaussian PDF
as the impulse response of the field.
Then if we choose this small standard deviation,
then the Gaussian function is still like that.
If we choose a large standard deviation,
then it is more flat.
Now if we look at a line closer to the boundary,
if we take a line closer to the boundary,
then the hard boundary is just one impulse.
Only at the pixel of the boundary, it is one.
All other peaks are not on the boundary, all are 0.
So it is an impulse.
Now if we apply a Gaussian field to smooth it,
then one impulse will become to this Gaussian function.
Because we know an impulse can walk with any function,
it's this function.
Now if we take different standard deviation of the Gaussian
filter, then we can produce different output.
Now from this different output, we
can see that for a position close to this impulse,
close to a boundary, this function has a large value.
Well, this filter has an output way of small.
But for the position far away from the boundary,
it could be this function has a larger value,
but this function has a very small value.
So from here, we can see we can use
these three different outputs to weight
different layer of the very known level of the features.
So we can see close to the boundary,
the small scale has a large weight.
Far away from the boundary, the small scale
has very small weights.
Well, from this output, we can see far away from the boundary,
the weights will be higher than other weights.
So this smooth output with different Gaussian
filter, different standard deviation
are used to weight the classification score
from different layer, then merge them together
to produce the final classification score.
So this is so with that, it can improve the boundary.
I just introduced the idea, not show the result.
So basically, this paper in the CVPR aura paper,
2018 now it received more than 300 of the citations.
OK, next example, we will show how
to change the convolution from the fixed kernel
into a variable kernel and why it is necessary.
Now here, we show an image here.
This is the ground truth of the segmentation.
We have the train, we have the lake, we have the sky,
we have the mountain, we have the land,
the different cars, we classify every pixel
into different cars.
So this is the segmentation result or the ground truth.
Now from here, we can see, for example,
for pixel A and the pixel B, one pixel,
the segmentation network should be very reliable,
classify it as the lake pixel.
Well, this pixel, we should classify it
a pixel of a train.
How can make the pixel A and the pixel B different?
Obviously, we need to produce the feature vector
that the feature vector at the pixel A and the pixel B,
it will be very different.
So that this is a pixel of the lake,
this is a pixel of a train.
Then how to reliably classify this pixel as a train?
We cannot just use the information at this point.
We should use information of a large area together
to determine this pixel is a train pixel.
If you just use one local information,
it is hardly to decide it is a belong to a train.
We should look at a larger area.
OK, now if we use a convolution, maybe
layers of the convolution to produce the effective color
size is larger, for example, this example.
We should show this large convolution kernel
to get the output of the pixel A and output of the pixel B.
What happened?
We will see that the information in this pink color window
and the yellow color window, the information
are almost the same because you use a large area.
We have a large area of these two windows are overlapped.
So this will affect the discrimination
between pixel A and pixel B. But if we
use a small area to connect information,
then we cannot reliably make sure this pixel B is a train.
We need to use a large area.
But to use a large area, it could average the information
so that the different class, the convolution result,
are almost the same because we have much common pixels
as the input to produce the output.
So this is the problem.
Now how to solve this problem?
We should try to do a convolution
to produce a feature vector of the pixel A,
use the information of the neck and surround the neck.
Now the final feature vector to represent this as a pixel
of the train.
We should use the information of the pixels
or pixels of the train and the surroundings of the train.
It is meant.
So if it's possible, we do the convolution,
the effective convolution kernel of the pixel A
is this red color.
And if we do the convolution to produce the output feature
vector of the pixel B is this yellow color,
then the output of the pixel A and the pixel B
were significantly different.
OK, different from this case.
And also we connect a large number of the pixel information.
We can reliably determine this point
is a point of the train, not a neck.
Now then how to make our convolution
use the kernel with different size and different shape?
Then we need to produce a so-called filter mask
to mask to put different weightage at different pixels
for the convolution of a single pixel.
So how to produce that?
I will skip the ideas.
But basically it is a pired convolution.
So given a print train to get an output feature map,
we further go through a large size of the convolution.
So we can connect information of the large area.
But this convolution result will be multiplied by a mask.
This mask is where we determine the filter convolution
kernel shape and size.
But how to produce this mask?
To produce a mask of one pixel, we
try to do a pired convolution.
The pired convolution is the difference
of the convolution of this center
pixel with all possible other pixels in the surroundings.
Now after the pired convolution, we
can get the information, correlation information.
That means for one pixel, we want to have a mask.
We try to get the information how
this pixel is correlated with other pixels.
For other pixels, it has strong correlation to this one.
Then the weight will be larger.
For some pixels, it is a weakly correlated
with this center pixel.
Then the weight will be small.
So we will produce a mask.
Then we use this mask to multiply to the convolution.
Then we will effectively to shape the convolution kernel
size and shape.
OK.
Here we use the pired convolution.
Every time we only use two small convolution,
one is a center position, another is a different position.
Then we compile these two convolution results
to get the correlation between different pixels.
Now next one, we will show a result.
What is this so-called shape mask?
OK.
This is an input image.
And this is a generated shape mask of a pixel in this area.
Because the shape mask is just weighted, right?
So we reduce the size.
So in fact, this image is the size
is similar to the whole image.
OK.
Now from here, we can see if this pired convolution
correctly generates a shape mask.
Because to do the convolution to extract the feature of the pixel
around here, we do the convolution
to collect all the information of all the pixels
in the large area.
But we put the weightage.
The pixels in this area is this car
where it has very high weightage because it's bright.
And the pixel on the road is also relatively high weightage.
Where the pixel of the grass and the cow, the weightage
is very small.
So this is a generated shape mask for convolution
of these pixels within this window.
OK.
This shape mask, in fact, represents the whole image size.
Now another shape mask shows that this is a shape mask
of to do the convolution, gets the output of the pixels
in this small window.
This is a pixel from the cow.
So we then connect the information of the cow
and other cows where it gets the high venues.
And even grass has high venues.
OK.
Where the road and the car is not correlated with the cow,
then in the shape mask, the venue is very small.
OK.
Similarly for other examples, I will not go through this example.
Just use this example to elaborate
what is the meaning of this shape mask.
Now from this shape mask, we can say
that if you have some experience in deep learning,
you should know this map is very similar to the so-called
attention map.
And attention map, in fact, the transformer
is fully utilized the attention.
OK.
So before the transformer, people walk on the scene
already notice that we need some kind of attention.
Well, this attention, we produce this attention
using the PyRWise convolution.
OK.
Use two pixels at two different positions.
What is the compare the convolution result
to get the attention result?
This is quite similar to the attention
module in the transformer.
So later I will elaborate that.
OK.
Now another contribution of this work
is called neighboring denoising.
In the segmentation, somehow we have
two different kinds of the arrow.
One arrow is somehow is the so-called high level
of the arrow.
It is a classifying arrow uses the feature
of the higher level of the convolution.
So because the higher level of the convolution,
the feature map corrects a large scale of the features.
So that most likely the classification class is correct.
We can identify what is different class in this input image.
But we can only identify the class center
where on the boundary of the class, it may make some arrow.
So this is one kind of the classification arrow.
Another kind of the arrow is called
the known level of the arrow.
Known level of the arrow is the classification result
may introduce many different class
never appear in your input image.
It comes from the very noise input.
OK.
So how is this two types of the classification arrow?
For example, here we show examples.
In usually in one input image, we want to segment it.
It may contain a few different objects.
So the number of the class could be just five or seven,
a few different objects.
OK.
This is for one single input image.
We want to do the segmentation.
We have only a few particular class.
But your network is trained by a data set.
A data set may contain many images.
Then together we may have 500 different class inside
of your class training data set.
But for one single particular input image
to do the segmentation, it contains only a few class.
Then we do an experiment.
Show that if we use the feature map of the convolution
as the feature to do the classification,
if we use a higher layer of the convolution map
then the final classification result
will produce just five class.
This five class is the two class in the input image.
All together, it only produce five different class.
But the class may be run at the edge, at the boundary,
between two different objects.
But it will not produce a very noise class.
Now, the class pigeon result of the middle layer
or lower layer of the convolution map
as the classification feature, then
will produce a large number of the class.
Many class is never shown in this input image.
OK.
So then how to solve this problem?
We somehow utilize the so-called enabling denoising.
That means in this network, in the convolution network,
we use different layer of the feature map as the classification
feature to do the classification.
The result of the classification score of the different layer
will be different.
Right?
OK.
The last layer, the classification result,
will be mostly correct within the two class level.
But for some pictures, it could be wrong.
But it will not introduce the class
never appear in the input image.
OK.
So we can utilize the classification score of the higher
layer after some conversion to remove some class
or reduce the classification score of the lower
layer classification result.
For such class, it will not appear in the higher layer.
So for the class not appear in this result,
the classification score will be reduced.
Well, for class appear at the same layer,
we increase the weightage.
So that means we use the high level of the classification
score to de-depress the classification score of the
lower layer that the class is not
appear in the higher layer.
So we can do such way from the higher layer
to lower layer at the end to produce a final classification
score.
So this one, the basic idea is use the higher layer of the
feature classification score to somehow remove the noise
of the class key result generated from the lower
layer of the classification result.
OK.
So this is another example to show how to use print
and C&N general C&N for some specific application.
OK.
Now, in fact, here, as I mentioned that, in the work
of the C&N, we already generate some idea to produce
the attention map.
The attention map, what means attention map, for example,
this part is highly correlated.
So the attention will be high.
Well, the grass is not correlated to the car, so the
attention in the grass is very low.
So the correlation is also some kind of the attention.
Just use different name.
OK.
Now, we will study the so-called transformer.
So why people study the transformer?
OK.
Transformer is invented by a group of the young researchers
in Google.
Publish a paper in CWPR called is a transformer.
OK.
So first, we understand what is a transformer.
Transformer is a neural network architecture that will
transform an input sequence into an output sequence.
OK.
Such a sequence can be a speech, can be text, or a time
series.
OK.
So originally, the transformer is to handle a
sequence of the information.
OK.
So this is basically the original basic structure of
the transformer.
Now, we know to handle a sequence of the information.
We can use the so-called recurrent neural network, or
RNN.
The further development of the RNN is the AROHTM.
This is somehow enhanced structure of the RNN.
So we have AROHTM.
But the transformer outperforms them because RNN and
AROHTM, the information processing is one by one.
OK.
So it's from the beginning to the end to process this
information.
But in the transformer, we take all sequence information
parallel together into the network to produce the
output.
OK.
So this is the difference between the transformer and the
previous RNN and AROHTM.
Now, it is developed originally for NARP, natural
language processing to process the text information.
Now, the chat GPD is very powerful.
The basic element of the chat GPD is transformer, or
come from the transformer.
OK.
So originally, it comes from the NARP.
But now, it also becomes a very powerful structure, even
for the computation problem.
OK.
So much powerful as CNN.
Now, transformer gets its powers because it's used a
tension module.
OK.
It captures a relation between different parts of the
input.
OK.
So then, how to understand the transformer?
So after the transformer shows such a very excellent
performance, much better than CNN.
Then people try to understand what is the transformer, what
is the difference between transformer and the CNN.
Then people think about CNN is somehow has no quality.
CNN output is only captured at local information.
But the transformer is global information.
OK.
Because the output of the transformer is captured
from all input.
So because the transformer is global, so it will outperform
much better than the local information
shown in the CNN.
But in my personal opinion, this understanding is not
correct.
It's somehow problem.
Now, if we want to capture the global information, the
traditional NARP is really connect the whole global
information.
In the traditional neural network, each output is
determined by all input.
It is fully connected.
So the traditional NARP is really get a global
information.
But why is this traditional NARP perform so poorly?
It has a very severe problem.
And the problem is solved by CNN.
We come from the global information to a local
information.
The CNN field size is small.
It capture a local information.
So the local information in the CNN perform much, much,
much better than NARP global information.
But why we come back to the global information in the
transformer?
OK.
So this superficially understanding is not
strictly correct.
So this is why here I show this global and the local is
the transformer will capture the relationship not global
in relationship.
But it capture the relationship of each token with
every other tokens.
It's not all tokens.
OK.
So here we understand what is the difference between the
CNN and the transformer.
First, CNN field size is small.
When they are of the convolution, really the output
only capture a small local information.
But the CNN has several times hundreds or
thousands of the NARPs.
Then after we do many convolution, the effective
kernel size is very large.
Because the first layer, 3 by 3 convolution, then the output
of the 3 by 3 convolution come to next convolution of the
3 by 3 window.
Then the output of the second layer, it capture the
information of the 5 by 5 window in the input.
Now if we increase the size of the convolution layer, then
the output of the convolution, in fact, capture a very large
area could be the whole image.
Because we have hundreds of the NARPs.
So the CNN only capture the local information is not
strictly correct.
Because the higher layer of the output of the CNN can
capture information of a very large area.
But if the CNN, we only use the high
level of the feature.
For example, in the segmentation, we cannot just
use the higher level feature.
We must use the earlier layer of the feature together to do
the classification.
If we only use the high level of the feature, it capture a
large area of the information, but it capture all the
pictures in this large area, then the output will somehow
blur the information.
So it has some kind of the average effect.
Because all convolution is just weight
the average of input.
So it will blur the information and somehow average the
information into not so discriminative.
Now, in the transformer, it is not used or large area to
produce the output.
It compute one picture with each of other point, not all
together.
So this is the difference.
So the transformer here is to capture the relation of each
word or token with every other.
Not all other.
So this is a difference.
Now, another sense is the original paper, the first
paper of the transformer.
There also are a group of the young researchers in Google.
The title of this paper is Attention Is All You Need.
This is the title of this paper.
Attention is all you need.
Here I will discuss.
Really, attention is all we need.
It appears to be this paper present this transformer
first time, try to make the transformer totally different
from the thing.
Nothing to do with the thing.
OK.
But after I study the transformer, I will say the
transformer is also very closely to the CNN.
OK.
Later, I will show you how it close to the CNN.
Now, the rest part we will study how this transformer
works.
And the attention is really everything.
And the transformer has any relation to CNN.
So can we simply understand that the transformer is
global and CNN is just the local so that the transformer
out of the CNN is not such a simple reason.
OK.
So we will study these issues.
Now, before we further study, I would like to mention one
very interesting sense.
So you know, just last week I read the newspaper,
Hinton received the Nobel Prize.
Right?
Now, Hinton received the Nobel Prize
because of the two contributions.
One is Hinton invented the back propagation in 1980s.
OK.
This back propagation greatly brings neural network research
into a very high peak.
Just the back propagation.
Although back propagation is just a simple gradient
decent method.
We use the chance to compute the gradient.
That's all.
This is the back propagation.
OK.
The second most significant contribution of the Hinton
is CNN.
Hinton is the first person together with his student
to build up the CNN then to achieve the image recognition
of very high performance.
Significantly higher than the performance before that.
Use a CNN.
OK.
So this is the two contribution of the Hinton.
Now, Hinton received the Nobel Prize.
Now, because in fact, the Hinton,
after invented the CNN, then many big companies
show that CNN performs so powerful.
Right?
So try to get Hinton join the company.
So many companies, big companies,
try to ask Hinton to join the company.
So at the end, Hinton joined Google
as the vice president of Google.
Of course, the salary is 10 times
as a professor in University of Toronto.
Now, he worked in Google several years or more than 10 years.
I don't know what is the exact years
as the VP vice president.
Now, two years ago or one years ago,
I cannot remember.
Hinton left Google, come back to the University of Toronto,
somehow left Google.
But what is the reason that Hinton left Google?
I'm not quite sure.
Can you guess why Hinton left Google?
Hinton himself claims that he's very somehow disappointed.
He thinks about the AI can do very bad things.
OK?
Now, the AI is so powerful, right?
Can be cheaper than our human.
So in future, AI could do a very bad thing.
So he don't want further work on the AI.
This is a reason given by Hinton himself.
So he don't want to do the AI anymore.
So he left Google, come back to the University of Toronto.
But I have doubt this is a real reason.
Because it does not make sense that AI
can be cheaper than the human.
In my opinion, AI can never exceed our human's brain.
OK?
I doubt this is a real reason of Hinton left Google.
But there's one sense in Google.
Because before the transformer, the thing
is the most powerful network structure.
But then a group of the young researchers also in Google
invent the transformer.
And then people see that transformer
is much more powerful than CNN.
Now, all this larger model of the AI, large model,
is built up by transformer, not the CNN.
OK?
So you can think about what is the reason this Hinton
left Google.
But Hinton received the Nobel Prize.
OK?
OK, now we will study what is a transformer.
It is so powerful, right?
Now, this is the basic component of the transformer.
Basically, transformer has encoders and decoders.
OK, encoders and decoders are two fundamental components
in the transformer.
OK, input, sequence, input into that decoder.
Sorry.
Then after the encoders process the input information,
the output of the encoder come to decoder.
Then the decoder output the final features.
Then we just use a simple classifier, linear classifier,
to get the output.
So this is the basic structure of the transformer.
Because the transformer first proposed
to solve the problem of the NLP.
So the input is a sequence of the word.
It could be a sentence or a whole paragraph.
Anyway, it consists of many different words, right?
OK, it's a sequence.
OK.
Now, in this sequence we can define each word as a token.
OK, so we have a number of the tokens
parallel input into the encoder of the transformer.
And then the decoder will output a larger sequence.
This sequence could be the translation of the input
sequence into different language.
It could be answer the question.
The input is a question.
The output is the answer.
OK, depends on how you train these transformers.
OK.
So this is the basic structure of the transformer.
Now, then what is encoders and decoders?
Here is encoders is ace, right?
So this encoders and decoders contains a stack of the encoder.
And here a stack of the decoder.
So we have many encoders linked together.
We have many decoders.
OK.
This number of the encoder could be 6, 10, or several times,
or even 100.
OK, many encoders.
Here also many decoders.
And each encoder, the network structure
are identical, exactly same.
No difference.
For the decoder, it's also all these decoders.
The structure are exactly same.
OK.
So we can study the transformer, just study one encoder
and one decoder, right?
Because all structures are identical same.
So we have encoders and decoders.
Well, we have multiple encoders.
It's the last encoder output where input into each decoder.
OK.
Then together this decoder produce
the final feature vector and then
to do the classification to produce output sequence.
The final one is also a class field.
For example, in the NLP, if it's a class field,
then each word is one class.
If a language has one million different words,
then we have one million different class, right?
So to determine what is the word, it's just to classify.
This input should be not which class, right?
OK.
Now, first then from here we can see, right?
This is encoders and decoders meaning, but all are identical.
So here we only study the structure of one encoder
and one decoder.
OK.
Now, this is show a structure of encoder.
Here show a structure of the decoder.
So here we can see what is the component of the encoder
in the transformer.
First input come, we need to convert the words
into a feature vector of each word, a different vector
to represent the input.
This is called embedding, embedding the natural words
into a numeric value, right?
This is common sense.
But here the transformer utilize the so-called position
encoding to sum together with this one.
This is not important.
We first ignore that.
But anyway, the input in terms of the numeric representation
of the input, we are input into encoder.
So what's the component of the encoder?
The component encoder has first self-attention.
It performs the attention.
Then after that, just do some kind of normalization
and then go through a feed forward network
and then go through a normalization.
That's all.
We can see from here.
An encoder, the key part is two component, attention
and feed forward network.
This feed forward network could be two-nayer, three-nayer,
just a few-nayer of the neural network.
OK?
Now then what is a decoder?
In the structure of the decoder, we
see that the input come to also to do an attention.
This attention is exactly same as the attention in the encoder
because both call self-attention because it's just
to pay attention of the same input.
And then same as the encoder, decoder, go through after
attention, go through a normalization.
Then after normalization, now this is a neural for decoder.
It has a so-called cross-attention or encoder,
decoder, attention because if you receive the input from
decoder and the output from the encoder to do the cross
attention, OK?
But basically it is attention.
Only the input are different from the self-attention.
Now after this attention, go through a normalization,
then go through a feed forward network similar to same as
the encoder.
Then get the linear cross-fee, get the output.
Now from here we can see even we have the encoder and the
decoder, they are very similar.
The key part of this encoder and the decoder are attention
and a feed forward network.
OK.
As the cross-attention, encoder, decoder,
attention, and the self-attention, it's only
input of the attention are different.
The structure or the method to do the attention are exactly
same.
OK, so this is structure of the transformer of one encoder
and one decoder in the transformer.
We know the transformer just now we mentioned that it's
multiple encoder and a multiple decoder.
Now for one encoder, before we go to study specifically one
encoder and one decoder, we first
want to see how the transformer works.
Now here I show an example.
This transformer is utilized to do the translation.
One sentence in one language, I believe this Spanish language,
goes to the transformer to get the output in the English.
So it transfer, translate the Spanish into English.
OK, so how the transformer works?
First, if we want to do the translation,
we put a whole sentence input encoder.
OK.
Each in a sentence, each word is a token.
It's a different word, a different token.
OK, then this word go to encoder.
Of course, we can have many, many encoder.
Then get the output of the master encoder.
Then we get this is output of the encoder.
Now then the output of the encoder,
we are input into the decoder, all different decoders.
But all words, all word token in the input go to the encoder
and then go to the decoder, only produce one word
of the output, or one token in the output.
OK.
And then what is the next word?
The next word is the first output of the word
come back as the input of the decoder together
with this encode output, same as before.
OK, then go to the decoder, produce a second word.
Then the second word come here.
The first word and the second word together
with the encoder output go to the encoder
to output the third word.
So anyway, this is a process to generate a sentence word
by word.
Each output word determined by all input words
and the previous output word in this decoder.
OK, so this is the working process of the transformer.
Then after break, we will first study the insight of the encoder
and the decoder, the how attention works, OK?
What is this feed forward network?
OK, so we can have 20 minutes of break now.
Maybe 180.
Then
that is the feed source of the encoder.
How many different times across hook or a block problem
five.
Ah, yes, yes, yes.
So, what do you think is a combination?
Ah, so there's no fusion.
Yes, there's no fusion.
So, it's like,
Oh, that means that the way it is,
it's a combination.
But it's just,
it's a kind of a combination.
The use keeps in the way.
But attention seems to have some correlation in way
to find their correlation or not.
But why we say the clouds,
clouds and clouds are correlations.
The correlation is some kind of a stocky thing.
It is a terming by the trend.
Because in the trend,
many image,
as an image,
the case of the cloud,
although some image may not be accurate,
but most image,
the cloud and the cloud always are accurate.
So, in the trend process,
things are established.
Ah,
ah,
take training data.
It's a mistake.
So, the question we have from the last question,
is the first one is here.
Here is the question about the surrounding context.
Why is it taking its place?
Or is it going to return to a place?
It's okay to return to a place.
This is not just a good one.
This is also a good one.
Right?
It's just that it's just a small point
that it's going to put on the spot.
Right.
It's just that we want to make it a larger size area.
We still want to just use the 90s.
So, these 9 points,
do you find the effect better in time?
No, no, no.
It's not going to use more effects.
But if there are more,
it's different from the other calculations.
We want to make each calculation
the same as the other.
So, these are the 9 points of the calculation.
Let's get it.
This is to make the last question
the information we are going to talk about.
Okay, this is not the information.
The reason why we are talking about the information
is because the information is coming from this side
and from this side to this side.
So, this information is generated
by these information.
But this information has nothing to do with this information.
This information doesn't know what this side is.
What is this?
But this information is generated from this side.
So, if we need to create a different position,
then we need to make different layers.
We need to do comparison.
If we want to do comparison,
then their information is comparable
and has a more coherent effect.
But if they create this information
from one point to another,
then the comparison is not so balanced.
So, we use a network
to make this layer of information
more consistent.
The next question is about the other one.
I don't understand how to
explain the information of these two groups
in this video.
Okay, this is the part
where we create this mask.
When we make a comparison,
each pixel has a mask.
The common one is the mask.
The next one is the mask.
The other one is the mask.
The second one is the mask.
Each pixel has a mask.
This mask is equivalent to
the image of all the images.
Okay?
This is the output of this pixel.
The resolution is the image of all the images.
But this picture is equivalent to the image of the year.
I don't use this picture.
I only use this icon.
How do I make this mask?
I have already made a comparison.
This is the image of the year.
This is the special image.
How do we make these two things
into the same image?
This picture is equivalent to
the image of this picture.
I need a mask to make this video.
Of course, the next one is the image of the year.
The next one is the image of the year.
This is another mask.
This one is the image of the year.
The other one is the image of the year.
This part is where the masks are placed together.
What about the other part?
We don't have enough time to talk about this part.
What about the other two masks?
What?
There are many masks here.
This is the mask that is shown.
H times W is the size of this mask.
So each one has a mask.
This is the mask.
What do you think is the best way to bring the masks?
What is the best way to bring the masks?
I think it's the best way to bring the masks.
You should choose the first one.
This is the best way to bring the masks.
I haven't chosen the right one.
But normally, the best way to bring the masks is to bring the masks.
I think it's the best way to bring the masks.
I haven't chosen the right one.
I don't know what to do next.
I want to hear from my parents.
I want to see if I can bring the next one.
I don't have any other choice.
I'll talk about it next time.
It is closely each other
for similar words,
and far,
and the distance of the
embitting vector is larger
for the words that
are totally different.
Or quite different.
Somehow, we can have
a better
embedding to present
a word by
numeric vector.
So, usually
So this embedding of the word we need 212 dimensional vector.
Okay, just different words.
This vector are different.
Okay, so this is the embedding, right?
Now in the transformer,
it is particularly have a so-called position encoding,
because the different words show
at a different position in the input, right?
So we will encode the position into a vector.
And then this position vector, for example,
position one, position two, position three,
they are different vector.
Then this vector will sum into each word
to get the final vector.
Now this position embedding is very specific
for the transformer, okay?
Then I may ask the question,
why we need the position embedding?
In the input, different word,
we have a vector, numeric vector,
they already at a different position.
Their position is always unique in all process.
The first order, always in the first place,
the second order is always in the second place.
So the information of the position of different words
is very clear show at the position, right?
So why we need to code the one, two, three, four,
sum into this numeric vector?
Why?
Try to find it,
because I cannot find the reason why.
I also think this problem by myself
of why we need this position
and the sum that this information of a position
into this word.
Because the position of this word is clearly show
the word appear at a different position, right?
Okay, but in the transformer,
somehow use this position embedding, okay?
I haven't found the reason in the literature,
in the paper, in the information, right?
But I figure out some reasons by myself, okay?
I don't want to illustrate what is this reason
you can think about by yourself, okay?
Why we need this position embedding?
But anyway, after position embedding,
we still have one vector for one word,
or one token, right?
And then in the transformer,
it is different from traditionally,
one input vector is always, we use a column vector, okay?
Here, in the transformer, one word is a vector,
it's a 512 dimensional vector.
We put this vector into a row vector.
One row vector represent one word, or one token.
Then all token together, a sentence or a paragraph
of the text will form together a matrix, okay?
So keep this in your mind.
In this matrix, the input to the transformer is a matrix.
In this matrix, one row is one token,
is a numeric value of a vector of one token.
Different row is different token, okay?
Then we have the matrix.
This is input to the encoder and also decoder.
Now, after we have this embedding, right?
Anyway, the input data is a matrix.
Then we can make this matrix go to encoder.
And this is the structure of the encoder.
From this structure, we can see this matrix
come to the attention module.
Then the output of the attention will be,
also a matrix has same size as the input,
exactly same size.
Then each module have the residue connection.
Residue connection, we know if you study
what is the wrist net, right?
If you have some experience in deep learning,
you must know what is a wrist net.
wrist net is also a very significant advance
in the development of the thing.
Okay, wrist net has some kind of the residue connection.
So all module has the residue connection,
includes the decoder here, we ignore it.
This just show the residue connection, okay?
Now, this residue connection
or basically borrow from the same wrist net, right?
Okay.
Now, and then in this module,
the layer normalization is nothing to elaborate.
It's just do some kind of the normalization.
We know after some process, we need some normalization, right?
So the two key components in the encoder
and also decoder is attention and feed forward network.
Feed forward network is just a few layers of the network.
But in the paper, it mentioned that
this feed forward network is point wise network.
Okay, so you can think about what means this point wise.
Okay, so it's a point wise feed forward network.
It's just a couple of the million layers
separated by a new function, that's all.
But try to find out what means the point wise.
Okay, later I will elaborate that
because many people somehow ignore this one.
Even some paper, published paper,
just simply change the point wise feed forward
and this feed forward network, change it into MRP.
This is totally wrong, it is not MRP.
Okay, even the VIT vision transformer
is the first paper published in CELIPR
to utilize the transformer into computer vision
called VIT vision transformer.
In this paper, it's running show that this module is MRP.
It's totally wrong.
Okay, later I will show that.
What means the point wise feed forward network.
Now, next we will focus on what is this attention?
Because attention, the first paper of the transformer
claims that attention is all you need.
Right, so what is this attention?
Now, the attention is a module of the attention
has three input, okay, it's called
query key and the value or QKV, okay.
All these three input come from a same input.
That means input is a matrix, right?
These metrics will produce three different copy
and these three different copy we call
is a query key and the value.
How to produce three copy from one matrix?
Produce three metrics, very simple.
We just multiply this matrix by another winning matrix,
then produce one matrix, multiply different metrics,
produce another matrix, not all.
Okay, for example, if here show this matrix,
we have four tokens, each token has three dimensional
vector, right, of course in practice,
it is hundreds of the dimension.
This is just for illustration, right.
So we have this matrix, data matrix, four by three.
Now, if this four by three matrix multiplied
by three by three matrix, what you result?
It's a lot of four by three matrix, right.
Now, if this weakening matrix W are different,
then of course this multiplication
will produce different metrics.
Okay, so one input matrix, we multiply by a projection
matrix, three by three matrix, then we'll produce
three different copy.
These three by three matrix is,
all element in this weakening matrix
is learned from the training data.
Okay, we learn from the training data
to get this weakening matrix, three by three matrix,
then to learn three different weakening matrix,
then multiply by two the input data,
then produce three copies.
Okay, now these three copies will perform
the so-called attention.
It is called self-attention because these three copies
come from a same input matrix, right.
So it is called self-attention.
Now, anyway, after this attention,
and then go to the feed-forward network,
and then the output of the master encoder,
where output come here, where produce two copies.
Okay, save us key and the value.
And the output of the previous self-attention
from the decoder is take us the query.
Then these three perform attention exactly same
as the self-attention, but it's called cross-attention
or encoder-decoder-attention because this come
from the two different input matrix, right.
Okay, and the decoder input to the decoder
also perform the self-attention exactly same
as the encoder, no difference.
Okay, so now after we understand that,
we will see how this attention performs.
But this attention will show in one encoder,
we have attention at feed-forward, right.
We have multiple attention or multiple encoder
or a stack of the encoders, right.
But one encoder in fact is multiple attention.
It's called multiple attention heads.
What is multiple attention heads?
So as I mentioned that one to perform one attention,
we need three metrics to perform attention.
But in one attention unit, in fact in the transformer,
we have mainly these attention,
but all these attention comes from a same metrics,
data metrics.
As I mentioned that a data metrics can multiply
by weighting metrics produced three different copy.
Of course, we can produce 30 different copy.
Then this 30 different copy,
every three of them to perform the attention,
a lot of three of them to perform attention and so on.
We can perform many, many attention.
You can design how many attention you want to perform.
Then each attention unit will produce a same four by three
metrics, same as the input, original input.
Then all this output of the attention will merge together
to form just a three by four metrics,
a four by three metrics, right, same as the input, okay.
So this is a process of one attention.
It is called multiple attention heads
because it's parallel to perform many attention.
The difference of this different attention
is just the different projection metrics
to project the input data into different copies.
The each attention, the working in each attention
is exactly same.
Then we will see how this attention comes.
Okay, as I mentioned that here I need to repeat again, okay.
The input words, right, this example show
we have four tokens, okay.
This four tokens after the embedding
becomes to four numeric vector.
Then the four words, each word is a vector
with each word four metrics.
So in this example, the metrics are four by three metrics
indicated we have four words or four tokens.
Each token is a three dimensional vector.
Again, this is just for illustration.
The vector is hundreds of the dimension, okay.
Okay, so anyway, it is a matrix, right.
Now, these metrics we can project
to three different subspace.
So called subspace is just multiplied by three by three
metrics then produce, this modification
we'll produce as four by three metrics,
different three by three metrics multiplied to the input
then produce different copy.
Now, then this three copy is called
query, key and the value.
Now, how these three metrics perform
the so-called attention?
Now, the three metrics first,
the three metrics here, first the shield
because this is very important in fact.
Now, if, although the input is a metrics
but we can use one, x one to indicate
one row vector, right.
Because one row is one word.
So if we have four words, then we have four rows.
So we use x one to indicate the first row,
x two indicates the second row.
So anyway, the x is the input metrics.
This input metrics multiplied by three different
projection metrics will produce three different output.
QKV come from the same x, just different
this waiting metrics to get QKV, three different metrics.
Okay, this show here, right.
This data metrics multiplied by this three projection metrics
produce three copy of the metrics.
Okay.
Now, then from these three metrics,
we perform the attention.
What is attention?
The attention is just one metrics Q
multiplied by metrics K transpose.
Of course, it must transpose.
Otherwise it cannot multiply together
because number of the column in Q
must be equals to number of the,
number of the column in Q
must equals to number of the rows in this,
in this second metrics.
So we need to transpose K.
Then we multiply them together to produce the R.
Now, the dimension of the R must be four by four,
not four by three, right.
Three is a number of the element in one word.
Four is number of the words we have.
Okay, so we get a four by four metrics R.
Now, of course this is just a metrics multiplication.
No more than that, but we can still look into
what is the element in this four by four metrics.
Okay, so from the element of this R metrics,
we can see each element is the product of the two words
or two token, okay.
Q one multiplied by all key,
then Q two multiplied by all key,
Q three multiplied by all key, right.
Okay, so we have such metrics as R.
Now, each element in this R is a multiplication
of the two words, multiplication of the two vectors.
The result will show the similarity of this two vector
or the correlation of this two vector.
You see, you can recall what is the definition
of the correlation, what is the definition
of a covariance matrix.
It's just a multiplication of one element
multiplied each of other elements
to get the element in our covariance matrix.
Covariance matrix will show the correlation
between different components, right.
So this attention is not very novel,
it's just very similar to the concept
of the covariance matrix or correlation matrix
because we should understand this thought product
of the two vector or one vector in row
multiply another vector in column, produce one number.
This number will show how these two vector are related
or correlated or the attention is larger or no.
This more, the same meaning, okay.
Just to take the correlation between different words.
Okay, so after we have this matrix,
we call it some kind of the attention matrix, right.
R is a Q times K transpose.
Then we need to do some kind of the normalization, okay.
Or I will skip this normalization,
but anyway it's just divided by D,
KD is the number of the dimension of the feature
of this data vector.
So this is just a normalization.
Then go to a softer matrix is also kind of the normalization.
Anyway, after we multiply two vector,
two matrix to produce a similar as a covariance matrix, right.
We need to do some kind of the normalization.
Then this normalized matrix show the correlation
between Q and K, then multiply to the third matrix,
way to produce a matrix Z.
Now a four by four matrix multiplied by four by three
matrix produce a four by three matrix Z.
So this Z is the output of the attention unit.
Okay, the input is the X produce three copies Q, K, V,
then produce a Z as the output.
This Z and the input X has identical size,
same shape four by three matrix.
Now that's all, this is the attention.
Okay, so now if you try to figure out
what is the meaning of this attention,
how this attention performs,
we will take one examples, what is the output Z?
Now as I mentioned that output Z matrix is a matrix,
is also four by three matrix.
It is same one row is one token.
Different row is different token.
Okay, different column is different feature for this token.
Okay, same as the input.
Okay, now in this matrix if we pick one row,
one token for example Z four is the fourth word for example.
This fourth word, how to produce the output of the fourth word?
This fourth word by mathematical expression is shown here.
From the matrix multiplication,
you can very easily figure out,
I will not, I will skip how this one multiplied this one,
then produce this expression, right?
This is just an enlium algebra matrix multiplication.
Now, but from this expression what we can get,
an output word or token Z four is a combination
of all input words,
V one, V two, V three and V four.
Is a,
weight combination.
Why is the weight combination of the V one, V three,
V one, V two, V three, V four,
not Q one, Q, not K one, K two, K three, K four.
Because I believe for this is the wrong,
it should be transposed, right?
Here K should be transposed.
So somehow I'm lazy, I just copy this from some,
some information this should be transposed, right?
Okay, now because this Q times K already produce,
somehow the meaning are different, it's a transpose.
After the transpose, we have one vector multiplied
the vector produce just one value.
The value in this Q times K here,
in fact it shows a correlation between Q and K, right?
This is one vector multiplied by one, it's just one value.
So this is just the weight of the V.
Okay, so now we can see the output,
the first word of the output is a linear combination
of all words in terms of the V.
But how to weight, this is a different way together
to produce the new, the new word.
Because it's a fourth word,
where to indicate it is related to the four.
We have Q four, Q four, Q four, Q four, right?
Okay, the query is the four,
is the fourth word of the query, okay?
Well, the key and the value we use from one up to four.
But the usage of the K and the V are different, okay?
We call this V is the value, it's really the word, okay?
Where K is the key, it's a key of the V,
it's somehow representation of the V.
So we want to use the Q to retrieve the information
from the V.
We don't know which of the four V four should be used
to produce the output Z four.
Then we combine all this V together
but put different weightage.
Well, if the V is represented by K, right?
If this K and Q four is highly coordinated,
then the weight will be high.
If, for example, the V four,
the representation of the V four is K four,
it is not very well related to this query,
the fourth word of the query,
then this weight value will be very low.
Okay, so we can see the first multiplication K and V
will establish the correlation between different words
and then use this correlation as the weight to each word
to produce a new representation of a word.
Okay, so this is the meaning of this attention, okay?
So the meaning of this attention is output,
each word of the output is a linear weight combination
of all input, but the weights is determined
by how other words are coordinated to the fourth word.
Okay, for example, if the fourth word is closely
coordinated to the fourth word,
then of course this weight is high,
after normalization is one,
but the fourth word can also coordinate it
by some other word.
Then we also use the information of some other word
to get some into the fourth word.
So after one attention, one word, for example here,
is a fourth word contains information of all other words,
but based on how other words are coordinated
to the fourth word.
Okay, so this is based on my understanding,
the role of this so-called attention.
Now it's pretty clear, right?
The fourth word is a linear combination of all words.
If we take weight as the word, okay?
Different way are different words,
but the different word has different weightage.
The weights is determined by how the other words
are coordinated to this fourth word,
because we have k and the correlation between k1
and k4, k2 and k4, k3 and k4, k4 and k4.
All are coordination of all other words to the fourth word.
This correlation are used as the weight to other words,
then combine them together to produce
new representation of the fourth word.
Right?
Now this is the role of the attention.
This attention is used in the self-attention,
cross-attention, and used in the encoder and decoder.
Exactly identical use this formula.
No difference.
Okay, now here, of course this is a self-attention, right?
The cross-attention, as I mentioned,
that the mathematical formula are exact same.
The only difference is for the cross-attention,
the key come from the decoder,
the previous stage of the decoder,
our self-attention of the input of the decoder.
Then the cross-connection is keys come from here,
but value of key come from the output of the encoder.
Okay, so then in the decoder,
why it is working in this way?
We want to produce the output.
It is generated from the input, right?
So the input, final decoder output is take us the value,
the basis of the information.
Based on this information, we produce the output.
But this information is come from different words.
Each word we have a representation as the word,
so we have the key.
Then what output we want to have?
We use the previous output as the query to see,
we have this query, we want to retrieve some information
from the input to produce new output.
Okay, so this is a rule of the query, key and the value.
Okay.
Now this is the attention,
cross-attention in the decoder.
Okay, but the mathematical formula is exactly same as here.
After we produce, we determine what is the key,
key and the way, these three metrics.
Then the operation inside of this one
identical to the self-attention,
also identical to the attention in the encoder.
They are all identical.
Okay, now if we further see that for the decoder,
we have two attention, right?
Self-attention and cross-attention.
Okay, somehow you can also study each element,
what is each element to try to find out
the meaning of this attention,
what we try to get.
For example, this cross-attention is a final output, right?
Of course, we have much stages, right?
Okay, so here the input is this one,
output is this one, right?
So here one word of the output come from the,
all words of the input because it's a V1, V2, V3, V4.
Okay, this is, V1, V2, V3, V4 come from this different words.
So we use this, the first word as the key,
as the query to see how this word
coordinated to the first word, second word, third word,
and fourth word as the weight.
Use their coordination as the weight
to weight this four words to produce one word here.
This query word is this one.
Anyway, before that here,
I can clearly show how to produce one output of the attention, right?
It's the same applied to the cross-attention.
So you can also see the difference
between the self-attention and the cross-attention,
just if I forget input is here,
here is input, here is output, right?
If this one, then one output word come
is one, come from one column, okay?
Then, no.
I somehow get confused to elaborate this matrix.
But anyway, you better use this one
to understand the meaning of what is output of the attention,
okay?
Now, we summarize this transformer
and also to figure out what is the unique feature
of this transformer.
Now, this shows how this transformer works, right?
Okay, so here is the input.
This is your application of the answer, the question.
The input is a question, hey, how are you?
We have four words or four tokens, okay?
These four words and all words of the input
apparently come to the input into the transformer.
Then transformer after encoder and then decoder
will produce one word in the output.
Then this word come to the input of the decoder
together with the output of the encoder
produce a second word, then come to the input,
produce the third word and so on.
So this is a working procedure of the transformer, okay?
Now, this is a diagram of the transformer.
I just capture this one from the first paper
of the transformer, okay?
In the CVPR published, the author is a group
of the young researcher of the Google.
Okay, now this is a diagram shown in this paper.
Okay, show the whole diagram of the transformer.
Here, show the transformer contains encoder and decoder.
Right?
But the encoder is times n.
So that means we can have many encoder linked together.
A stack of encoders.
Here is just show one encoder, okay?
The real transformer can have many encoder.
How many depends on your design, right?
You want to put how many elements
but all module are identical, structure are identical.
Now, in one encoder, it's called multi-hate attention.
Okay, so the attention is we will produce
many, many attentions, then produce many output,
then after that we merge them together into one output.
Okay, this is a multi-hate attention.
Now, for each attention, to perform each attention
is one input go to a projection to project
to three different subspace or three different space.
Okay, use three different projection metrics.
So one metrics generate three copies
of the same size of the metrics.
Then this three metrics is called query key value.
And then this three perform attention.
The output of the attention is a metrics same as input.
Okay, for example, four by three metrics.
Then of course go to some kind of the normalization.
Okay, I skip this normalization,
it does not make much role.
Anyway, we need this normalization, right?
Then after that we go to a feed forward network.
Then normalization, that's all.
Output of one multi-hate attention.
This is one encoder, right?
Now, for the decoder, okay, we have two attention.
One is a self attention, it is output of the previous
output as an input.
In the training phase, it is target output.
It is a ground source, okay?
But in the prediction process,
we use the previous output as input here.
But in the training, for example, in the translation,
this is an input sentence, then this is the output sentence.
We know the output sentence in the training, right?
So we have the input in the encoder in the training.
Then in the prediction, this one is unknown
because this is the output, the true output, right?
So we use the previous output link come to here.
But anyway, the decoder has also a self attention.
The module exactly same as the encoder.
The decoder has one self attention
and then come to cross attention.
The structure or the procedure of the cross attention
is same as the self attention only,
that three copy of the input are different.
It come from, one is come from the output
of the previous self attention,
the two come from the output of encoder.
Okay, then after that is one feed forward network.
Then produce the final feature vector.
Then we go to a very simple linear classifier
to get the final output.
Now this is a whole structure of the transformer.
This is what this picture I just copied from the paper.
Attention is all you need, the title of the paper.
Now from here we can see the paper
represent the structure of the transformer.
It's really all attention, right?
Besides the attention, we also have a feed forward network.
Feed forward layers here, show here.
Okay, now here attention is, we must admit,
attention is a core component in the transformer.
But attention is people already use this attention
in the same to put some attention
after the same and so on, right?
But the transformer is systematically use the attention
and repeatedly use attention many many times.
This is only difference between the attention
in the transformer and the attention of some other works
in the same structure before the transformer.
Transformer, I already emphasize this,
it use attention many times.
It systematically use the attention, okay?
But the attention itself is not a new one, right?
The attention in many other application will already
use the idea or similar concept of this attention.
Attention is just to try to capture the similarity
or correlation, right?
Okay, so of course in the transformer,
the attention is core component.
But although it's a core component in the transformer,
the attention itself is three metrics
in the input multiplied together.
This is attention basically
process of the attention, right?
So attention itself is not a learnable module.
Attention there's no machine learning
inside of that, compute the attention, right?
So then what are the machine learnable parameter
in the transformer?
And then how are this learned parameter applied
Are transformer any connection to the CNN?
From this presentation of the structure of the transformer,
it appears to be really nothing to do with the CNN, right?
It just computes the attention and attention again.
Many times and then of course we have the feed forward
network, but feed forward network,
you can use the name feed forward network,
never use the name CNN.
It just a feed forward.
It just put one another word,
it's a point wise feed forward network.
Now, if we really study where is a learnable part,
is learn from the training where we see
the learnable part is this read corner,
is this weakening matrix,
is learned from the training data, okay?
And this read corner matrix,
one is used in this feed forward network,
another is used to from one input produce three copies.
In fact, it could produce 30 copies
because it's a much hate attention.
It's not just a producer three copies
to perform one attention,
it's to perform many, many attention,
but after that it merge them together.
Okay, so anyway, the basic process
of how to use the learnable parameter is here.
W, Q, W, K, W, V and W, one, two, three.
All these metrics are learned from the training data.
Then how these metrics are utilized
to process the information,
the input information is X, right?
Okay, from this metrics matrix,
what we can observe,
X is a matrix, okay?
One row is one word, different row is different word, okay?
So this metrics X produce a metrics Q,
this is the same size of the X,
so it is just a copy of the X.
Of course, different, we have different copies.
Then this Q is also metrics,
is also a word one, word two, word three, word four, right?
We have Q one, Q two, Q three, Q four.
Now, if we say X is an input sentence,
the output is a Q is a sentence,
then what is a word one?
From this metrics multiplication,
we see the word one Q one is the X one multiplied by WQ.
Right?
So you understand how the metrics multiplication
to perform the first row of the Q.
The first row of the Q is only determined
by first row of the X and all parameter in this W, right?
Then the second row of the Q only depends
on the second input X, second row of the X.
Nothing to do with the other row of the X.
Now, this operation, what is this operation?
If we say the different words in the image
is different pixel, okay, or a map, right?
If we say the vector X one is a different channel,
different column in one word is different channel
in a feature map,
then how use this X to produce Q?
We use the same metrics applied to all different eggs.
Now, in terms of the different word,
this is a convolution,
it's just a single point of the convolution
because the same parameter,
learned parameter are going through all positions
to produce different output.
In my opinion, this is a convolution.
The effect is the same as the convolution.
That means the W is determined,
is learned from all X one, X two, X three, X four,
not just from one X something.
All words are used to determine this W
and the same W, same learned parameter
are applied to all different words.
If you try to understand what is this metrics
of operation, you know that, right?
So, all this linear projection,
this is has same effect of the convolution.
As I mentioned that in the beginning,
the most significant feature of the convolution
use the convolution in the machine learning
is the parameter is go through all input.
All input are used to determine a same parameter.
This is also true in the transformer.
How to learn this parameter W, KW, KW, W.
Okay, so this is strongly linked with the convolution.
Convolution does not mean it's just a local window.
The convolution, the most important thing
is the convolution is this window is moving
to all positions in the training phase.
Okay.
Now, the next known parameter is W1, W2, W3, and so on,
used in this feed forward network.
The feed forward network, we here show an example
of the three layers of the feed forward network.
Now, in the transformer, it is just X multiply W1,
go to a renew function, then multiply W2,
go to a renew function, then multiply W3,
go to a renew function.
From here, we can see this X multiply by W1
or the output multiply W2, same as this structure, right?
We can see from here is also same parameter W1
goes through all different words.
And the same as this Q, one output words only depends
on this input words, nothing to do with other input words.
Right?
So this is why there are some literature called
this network as the point wise feed forward network.
So in fact, this network is equivalent
to convolutional network.
Well, the convolution is the theater goes
through all different words.
The convolution in the different words dimension,
it is just one point.
Similar to image recognition, it's a one by one convolution.
It's just one point.
The size window is not three by three,
it's just one by one, just one pixel, okay?
But this one point goes through all positions of the pixels.
But one point is we have many multiple channel, right?
So this one point is just for the theater,
it's not just one width, we have a weighting vector.
But weighting vector is weight different channel, okay?
Not a different spatial position.
So here, this W, different W is just,
the value of the W matrix is just weight different,
compliant of a word, but all words use the same W, okay?
So I believe this is also very strongly related
to convolution CNN.
All parameter learned from the training data
is in a way same as the CNN.
We move the parameter in all different positions.
Here, we move this learned parameter
in all different token.
We are running through all different token
to produce one parameter.
And the learned one parameter are used in all input token.
Now, from this matrix multiplication,
it is not difficult to figure out that, right?
So I don't believe in the transformer attention
is everything, it's all you need.
All learned parameter is learned in a way similar to CNN.
Okay.
Now, because the transformer is first used in the NARP,
the text processing.
So the transformer show very powerful.
Before the transformer, the NARP is much behind
the computation.
The performance of the NARP is very poor.
Compared to computation, computation you see
and the performance is already very good.
The NARP performance is very bad.
So not widely used in the practice.
But because of this transformer,
the performance of the NARP jumped
to very highly performed.
So now the NARP, I believe, outperform computation.
For example, chat GPT, right?
It's so powerful that the computation
because of this transformer.
Now, because the transformer is so powerful,
so excellent to perform in the process, the text data,
then people try to convert this transformer
into the computer vision.
Okay, so we have the VIT, the vision transformer.
So the first person that converts it
call this structure as the VIT vision transformer.
So how to do this conversion?
So it is very simple, right?
We have given an image, we partition the image
into different patch.
Okay, then for example, we partition an image
into three by three patch.
Then we have nine patches, right?
Then this nine patches, each patch will serve as one token.
Where different picture in one patch is different component
as the numeric vector description of this patch.
Okay, so the picture within a patch is a vector
of this token, different patch is different token.
So after such a conversion, we can input this image
into a transformer, right?
Now, the first application to apply this transformer
into the computer vision problem is VIT,
is applied to do the image classification,
to classify the image into different class.
For example, the image is an image of the bird
or image of the bar, image of the car and so on.
Okay, so in this application, we only need the encoder.
We don't need the decoder because it's a discriminative
network, not the generative network.
Only the generative network, we need some decoder.
Okay, now this is a VIT.
This paper of course is very important
because it's the first work to use the transformer
in the computer vision, right?
But this paper although is very famous,
it shows this transformer structure here.
Okay, show this network, feed forward network
to name it as MRP.
This of course is incorrect.
As I mentioned that this feed forward
is point wise feed forward, okay?
Output of this network of one token is only determined
by one token of the input, not all token.
Okay, obviously this is not the MRP, right?
Okay, in the encoder module of the transformer.
It should be a point wise feed forward network.
As I mentioned, explained just now,
in fact this network is a convolution network.
We can treat it as a convolutional network.
Treat each word, each token are similar as peaks.
Okay, different components to describe a word
is different channel in the feature map.
Then it is just a convolution, a one by one convolution, right?
Okay, so this is of course the VIT is a first work
to apply the transformer in the computer vision.
It may not be very optimum, but anyway,
it already shows that the performance could be
much better than CNN.
So the vision transformer outperforms the state of the art
of CNN in multiple benchmark data set in the computation.
So this shows how powerful is this transformer.
So while the CNN has already approved track record
in various computation problem to handle a large scale
of the data set efficiently, but the vision transformer
offers the advantage in the scenario that
somehow we need global dependency information.
Now I put a question mark in this so-called global.
Now from the transformer, we say that it capture
the relation between each pair of the word.
That means it can capture of the correlation
of the two parts even far away, right?
But it only
generates the attention between one part
and each of other part.
It never connects all information together, right?
So we cannot say it's a global information.
It's a pile-wise correlation, but all possible pile
is computed by the transformer.
Okay, so this is very important because in the computation
maybe one part of the information could be closely
correlated to some other part, but not correlated
to all globally, right?
But it can be closely correlated to other part,
could be far away from this part.
So the thing really is difficult to capture
this kind of information, but the transformer
will compute the attention between each pile of the token
to solve the problem to get the relation
between the two parts in the image.
It could be far away, not closely together.
So I believe this is a very significant feature
in the transformer.
Not just simply say transformer is global,
Cn is just a local.
Okay, now, lastly, I will show some of my work
use the transformer, okay?
In the earlier stage, of course, all this segmentation work
I use the Cn, but now because the transformer
is so powerful, then I also utilize the transformer
in the image segmentation.
We use this one in the so-called referring image segmentation.
We build up a similar as a transformer,
we call it the Weihung language transformer, VLT,
because this network structure will handle
the two information, image and text,
or a language information and image information.
Now, this network will perform referring segmentation
that means given an image and given instruction
in the language to segment the part of the image
following the instruction of this language.
For example, given this image, right?
But the language instruct us to segment
the small elephant on the left.
Then the final result is owning segment out this elephant
where other elephant is not segment out
because the language instruction is small elephant
on the left.
Okay, this is so-called the referring segmentation.
Okay, so this network meet handle two types
of the information, image and the text.
So it is called Weihung language transformer.
Now, basically the structure we show here,
we have image encoder to extract the feature of the image.
This one we can use the CNN, right?
Then we, from the text information,
we need to get a feature vector, okay, by the embedding.
Then after that, we go through some few process,
then take a transformer, the encoder and the decoder
of the transformer where the input of the encoder
is the image feature.
We take the feature of the language feature as the query
to query the image feature and then at the end
to produce the segmentation result.
And here from original tokens from the language,
we need somehow convert this token into a token
closely related to the image.
So we have the so-called query generation.
We generate the query different from the original
language tokens by compiler,
compiler this different language token with the image token
to generate a new queries.
So here I show this module.
I will not go through the details,
but anyway, after that, we take the query
from the language information,
but convert it into related to the image
as a query to query the image feature as a venue
and key and as a key and a venue.
The language as a query, then go to the decoder,
then to produce the response to each query.
And then all this response to each query
we are figure out the segmented result
where satisfy the instruction of this query.
Okay.
So this work is published in ICC way in 2021
and also published in Parmi in last year.
So these two papers, the ICC one already have two,
more than 200 of citation this Parmi just published
in last year, the citation is over 100,
more than 100 of citation is in this one.
Okay.
So here I show example of how to apply the transformer
in the computation problem.
Okay.
At the end, we will get the conclusion
of all this deep learning part.
So first AI now is very hot, right?
It's booming.
So we know this industry and the great impact
of the artificial intelligence to us.
But AI is booming because of the deep learning.
Without deep learning, there's no AI.
If there's no deep learning,
then the standard of the AI is the same as 30 years ago.
Okay.
Now this whole AI is boost by the deep learning.
Now the deep learning is becomes too very powerful
because of the convolutional neural network.
Convolutional neural network bring the deep learning.
Okay.
That's the CNN.
Now CNN in last week we already studied the CNN.
What is CNN?
CNN solves the problem of the traditional neural network,
M-A-R-P because CNN is a strongly recognized neural network.
It has no co-attention,
but the most important sense is CNN.
It overcomes the overfitting problem.
The parameter is learned from every single part of the image.
Not just one part of the image determine one parameter.
Other part of the image are used to determine other parameter.
Each single parameter is determined
by all part of the input image.
Go by the convolution process in the learning phase.
All right.
So this is a key revolution of the CNN.
But of course CNN has a limitation
because it captures attention or similarity
in terms of the filter window.
Okay.
So it will capture somehow how a window,
this window small, then it can just capture local information.
If the convolution window is larger,
then we have too much of the information average together.
It will also cause some problem.
But this limitation is solved by the transformer
because transformer captures attention pile wise.
Okay.
So it can capture attention between two parts
is very far away,
but it just captures the attention of the two small part.
Okay.
So this transformer,
this property of the transformer
overcome the limitation of the CNN.
So the most critical machine learning part
is not just simply make the machine learn from the data.
We must use our human knowledge to guide the machine
how to learn from the data,
to design the network structure,
to design different component,
then apply this one in the machine learning from the data.
So this guy,
use human knowledge to guide the machine learning
is also called some kind of the regularization.
So this is why I, in my opinion,
the regularization is utilize the human knowledge
to guide the machine to learn from the data.
This is the most critical part in the machine learning.
So machine learning is just simply make machine to learn.
This use our human knowledge to design the way
the machine to learn from the data.
This is really the center part
of the machine learning and the computation.
Now, if we take this opinion,
the real good machine learning
is not because the machine very powerful learn from data
because our human can design architecture,
design structure to make the machine
where learn from the data.
If in this perspective,
many people scare the AI,
future AI can outperform our human,
then we cannot control the AI.
Human cannot control the AI.
In my opinion, this is nonsense.
AI can never outperform our human
because AI is always controlled by our human.
Okay, so this is my opinion from artificial intelligence.
Okay, then with this way,
I complete my part of this course.
Okay, so next week,
we will have the new lecture come here
to introduce the 3D and the video part of the computation.
Okay, thank you very much.
Thank you.