________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
meet
.
We are studying our topic 8 and tonight we will also study part of the topic 9.
So next week we will just use one hour to complete the topic 9.
So we will have the quiz next week.
So the next week for the quiz in fact you don't need to specifically prepare for it.
So if you understand the concept then you should be able to work out to solve the quiz
things.
So no need to take a lot of time to prepare your quiz.
Just keep your normal study pace should be no problem.
So don't worry about the quiz, right?
Because we must have some assessment so we must have the quiz.
The quiz is just two simple questions.
I will give you one hard copy, one page, you write your answer in both sides of the page.
One side for one quiz.
No worry about the quiz.
Mainly based on your understanding.
If you understand the concept you should somehow work out what is the solution.
So I haven't given the examples about the quiz thing or the final exam quiz or quiz
quiz things.
Because so anyway the quiz quiz or final exam quiz must be somehow different from what we
have seen in the past year, right?
So basically you should have based on your understanding and your knowledge to work out
the solution of the quiz.
Not just to memorize something to solve the quiz or the final exam quiz thing.
So we are not testing your memory, mainly testing your understanding.
So no need to take time to memorize a formula and many things.
Just try to focus on your understanding of the concept.
Okay, now this topic is about the handcraft feature generation and feature selection.
So far for the image recognition for the computer vision problem we have studies of decision
or prediction or classification, right?
So this is based on the data then design a classifier to do the classification.
But the input of the classifier may not be original image.
If we take the original image directly go to the classification then it will cause the
trouble because the original image has many pictures, it's high dimensional data.
Okay, so many information is ear-read-mounted to the class membership.
So we need pre-processing the image.
Then after that goes through the classification, the final decision module, right?
So the pre-processing also includes the so-called feature extraction.
Okay, to do the feature extraction we can also separate the feature extraction into two
steps.
First is a feature generation and then the feature selection.
This is one way to do the feature extraction.
So this topic we will study how to generate the feature based on some of our intuitive
knowledge to generate the feature and then to select the feature use the machine learning,
use the training data to select the feature.
So this is even important as classification, how to classify it.
In fact now it could be more important because for example all this deep learning in fact
is some kind of the feature extraction.
Even the transformer is also to processing the data into different form.
Now if we have very strong feature extraction or selection then after we process the feature
into a very good shape then we can just use a very simple classifier to do the classification.
For example now it is the big model or this transformer and the last classification is
just a linear classification.
Because before the classification we have go through many layers to process the data
already create a very good feature.
So this feature generation and selection or extraction is a very important component in
the whole computation system.
So this topic is about the handcraft feature generation and selection.
So we first study why we need this feature generation and the selection.
Here give an example of the face detection.
So face detection is just one example of the visual object detection.
So to detect the object from an image because the object is only a small part of the image.
And then in one image we may have some multiple objects and the objects can have different
position and different size.
So then how to detect it?
Then we need some kind of a sliding window.
We just first use one window to detect the object around this size to move this window
to all possible positions.
And for each position try to classify the image within the window or image patch.
It is a face or non-face.
So basically here the step is show here we use a window of size for example m by n size.
And then place this window at a different position so at the i and j position and then
to capture one patch of the image then we do the classification because it is a detection,
face detection then the classification is just a binary classification.
This window is a face or non-face.
But we to classify each this patch we need to move this window to all possible positions.
For example here we will first take this position and then after that to oh sorry.
So I think it is.
I have one sense to show this process.
Okay for example this window in this position we need to do a binary classification and
then after that we need to move the window to different positions.
So this window will move to all possible positions and for each position we need to do a binary
classification.
Now here we detect a face then further move the window into different position here we
detect a face and then we need to scale all the remaining positions.
Now after one round of this scaling we just detect the possible face of this size.
Then we need to scale the image or scale the window into a larger size and then to do the
scaling again and then somehow we can detect a larger face.
Okay so this just illustrates that to do this detection in traditional way we need to do
a lot of classification for each window we need to classify it is a face or non-face.
So if we want to make this face detection work in the video then it must be able to
detect a face at each frame before the next frame comes.
So to achieve this speed we need somehow a fast classification then we need to generate
the feature fast and select a small number of the features.
So here we see that the detection needs numerous times of the binary classification.
So then how to generate the feature then we have three challenges how to generate the
feature.
First generate the feature is to compute some value from the image.
So how can we compute the feature quickly and how can we refine from the repeated computation
from the image into the feature.
Okay then how to we obtain a good representation of the features.
Okay so this issue here we have studied one solution to solve these issues.
This solution is called Adaboost use the Harleck features.
This is a very famous method to firstly apply to the face detection invented by two researchers
I think it's the same new researchers.
So this is somehow before the deep learning or detection somehow utilize this method especially
for the face detection.
So we will take this example to see how we can generate the idea to solve these challenges.
Okay so basically this is the so-called Weiner-Jones approach.
This approach is called Weiner-Jones is the name of these two authors.
Okay basically this approach utilize the so-called Harleck features extracted from the image
and then use the Adaboost to connect the useful feature and remove the somehow not so good
features.
Okay so the Harleck feature is somehow the feature is just a difference between the sum
of the pictures of two rectangles.
Okay for example given this patch of the window of the image.
Okay we can generate the feature use a rectangle and then to sum all pictures in this shaded
area then minus or summation of all feature of another part.
So it is a difference of the sum of all pictures within two rectangles.
So this feature is called the rectangle feature.
Now for the face detection we can see that this is a rectangle feature can capture some
information about the human face.
For example in the human eyes right so the difference includes the eye and not includes
the eye the difference will be significant.
Well for other parts the difference will be small.
For this kind of the feature we can use the summation of all pixel value in the center
minus the summation of the pixel value at this two part.
And this two rectangle so if it goes through the nose position then it will produce a large
response.
So this is some kind of the rectangle feature.
Now the rectangle feature can also be regarded as some output of the filter.
Of course here we use a very simple filter right.
So for example the difference of the summation can be say as the output of the filter the
filter has the coefficient 1 all is 1 for this pictures of this rectangle and minus
one of another rectangle.
Then the filter output will be the summation of all this pixel minus the pixel in another
rectangle.
Right so this is also an output of the filter.
And of course we see the CNN convolution layer is always used the filter to get the output
as the input of the next layer always repeat this process.
Of course in the CNN the filter coefficient is learned from the training data.
But here we just use very simple filters which is 1 and minus 1 within this window and 0
outside of this window.
Okay to generate the feature.
Now if we use this rectangle to difference of the two rectangle to generate the feature
then we can compute the feature very fast.
So this is why or a reason why we use this rectangle feature.
Because the sum of all pixels within a rectangle can be computed very fast.
Because we need to compute a lot of different rectangle features.
For example we can design our this rectangle differently and place this two rectangle at
a different position, different shape then we can produce a lot of different features.
But we use this rectangle because we can compute this summation of the pixels within a rectangle
very fast.
Here give examples how to fastly compute this rectangle feature.
To compute this rectangle feature we first to create an integral image.
So given an image we can give an image Ixy.
We can somehow create or generate an integral image Ixy.
It is the integration of the Ixy from one corner to this position.
Of course in terms of the discrete image we use the summation instead of the integration.
So this formula can show what is the Ixy for example.
Given this white rectangle is a whole image or a window of the image.
The integral image value of the Iy at this Ixy position is the sum of the pixels of
all this blue area.
Then if this Ixy at a different position then the summation will be different.
Anyway summation is from if we put the coordinate here it is 0, 0.
Then it is the sum of all the rectangles up to the position x and y.
So we know two positions were specified a rectangle.
We use one position is the left upper corner another position is xy.
These two positions were formed a rectangle.
Then sum of all the pixels is the value of this Iy at the position xy.
So mathematically for continuous images this Ixy is the integration of the Ixy from 0,
0 to the position x and y.
So discretely we use the summation.
Now in fact to compute this integral image we can also use another way to very fastly
to compute it to avoid the repetition of the computation.
This is very clear because if we directly use this formula to compute the integral image
we have a lot of repeated computation.
We have a lot of repeated computation for example.
To compute the Ixy here we need sum of all these pixels.
Then to compute the Ixy at the next position we need to repeat the sum of all these pixels.
So many pixels are repeatedly used in the summation.
So to avoid repeated computation we can use this so-called iterative method to compute
the integral image Ixy.
So the idea in fact is quite simple because it's iteratively computed the Ixy come from
the previous pixel Ix minus 1y.
Suppose we have already the Ix minus 1y then to produce this x and y it's just x increment
1 pixel.
So we only need to use the previous result plus one column up to here pixels.
Then get the x increase 1.
Then x increment further 1 we just need to use the previous one plus another column,
the sum of another column.
Then this Ixy is the sum of one column from this one to all pixels from this position
to here.
And Ixy can also compute it from this iterative method.
Suppose we have already x, x, xy minus 1 then to compute the y increment 1 is just some
1 pixel.
So we can see from one iteration x and y we need only use one summation and here another
summation two summations.
Then we start from x and y from zero then apply this one to increase this xy from zero
to this for example m by n position.
Then each time we only use two summations at the end we can produce this Ixy.
So this is pretty clear we use a small rectangle to generate the larger rectangle is just some
of the additional pixels in the previous result.
Okay so from here we already marginally speed up the computation of the integral image.
Now this integral image only need compute 1's so given an image we can get an integral
image only compute 1's.
Then after that we can use this integral image to produce the summation of a pixel
with an arbitrary rectangle very fast.
Here give examples.
For example if we want to get a summation of the pixels with this rectangle d.
So obviously this summation within the d is a summation with this large rectangle it
is ii4 at this position.
The integral image at this position is a sum of all pixels in this large rectangle.
Then minus the ii1, ii1, so minus ii2.
For example this is a 2 the xy at here is represented by 2.
Then the integral result is the area or the sum of pixels within this rectangle.
So this rectangle minus this rectangle then minus this rectangle but this a is minus twice
then plus this ii1 this rectangle.
Then we get the area of this d or the sum of the pixels within this small rectangle d.
So from here we can see to produce the sum of any rectangle we can just use the integral
image use 3 summations.
We just use 3 summations to produce or generate any rectangle feature.
Then this rectangle feature minus another rectangle feature is this hard like features.
So because we need to generate many rectangle features but the integral image we only need
to compute once.
Then use this integral feature iixy.
We can generate arbitrary rectangle very fast just use 3 or 4 summations.
So basically here I show that we can generate 2, 3 or 4 rectangle features just use 6, 8
or 9 summations.
Of course we need to reference the integral image to get the value from the integral image
then just use 6, 8 or 9 summations we can compute 2, 3 or 4 rectangle features.
So this is one way how to very fastly compute this rectangle feature.
So here basically we first use integral image enable us to compute the features of all possible
rectangle size and different shape.
You can design the 2 rectangle or 3 rectangle in different size, different shape at a different
position to compute all these different rectangle features.
So we also don't need scaling the image smaller or larger because we can use different size
of the rectangle to represent all different size of the features.
Then after that we can produce a lot of the rectangle features.
For example here given image detection window right we can this is just a few examples to
see how to produce a feature means that this shaded area minus another area.
We can also use this pattern to extract the rectangle features.
But anyway all this rectangle features each of them is just a few summations we can get
what is the result.
So now if we design this so many different kind of the pattern to extract these features
then we can produce numerous different features.
For example here give examples show that even given a 24 by 24 pixel detection window the
number of possible this rectangle feature could be almost 200,000 different features.
Now in all these features some features could be very discriminated, discriminate the face
and the non-face.
Some features may be useful but we don't know it is very difficult to check which feature
is useful, which feature is not useful among this 200,000 different kind of the pattern,
different kind of the features.
But we cannot utilize all these features to do the classification because we have too
many features.
We know most of them is year read run feature only some of them is useful for the face detection.
Then how to select the useful feature and only after we select we can only use the useful
feature and we don't need to compute the useless features.
So to do this selection because our human knowledge is very difficult to apply to this
selection then we can use the training data to select the feature.
So we need the feature selection.
So basically for feature selection we need to use the training data then this is some
kind of the machine learning.
We use the machine to learn the useful features.
So this diagram shows the process of this feature selection.
First we need to connect training data.
So training data for all detection problem we have two class, one is a positive sample
another is a negative sample.
Positive sample means all this image is a face for the face detection.
Of course negative sample is a non-face.
We need to connect a huge number of this training data.
Then we utilize this training data to train different classifier or different feature and
then to select the good feature or good classifier.
Then after that this is a training process.
It's offline.
So after we determine what feature is a good feature, what feature is a useless feature
then in the real face detection process we only need compute this good feature selected
in the training process.
So in the classification real detection process it will be very fast.
For example originally use this tank feature we produce 200,000 different features and
go through this training process we can select just 200 features.
Then after that we know which 200 features among 200,000 is a good feature.
Then in the detection process we only need to compute 200 features and use it to do the
classification.
Now then here the learning process is to train a classifier and see how is the performance
of the classifier to select the feature.
So we can design a very simple classifier.
Each classifier we just use one feature.
So and then if the classifier use one feature the performance is good.
Then this feature will be selected.
So here if one classifier only use one feature a classifier and a feature is the same meaning
right?
We select this classifier means we select this feature.
So if we use a classifier just use one features then it is a weak classifier and all this
classifier will combine together to form a strong classifier.
Now here I show an example for the feature selection in the training process we need
first to connect training data right?
It's not to connect the whole image we just connect a window a patch of the image it contains
all face.
Here is an example we connect the we crop the face image with many different expression
different lighting different pose.
Okay?
All these are positive samples.
One image face image is one sample.
Okay?
Here is just show we connect around 5000 face images as the training data and we can also
connect meaning non-face image.
Non-face image is very easy to connect it right?
Any image we crop it without the face then is non-face image so we can connect a large
number of the negative training samples.
Okay?
Here I show we connect 10,000 of the negative training samples.
Now this work is more than 10 years ago in that year it is not very easy to compute the
large volume of the training data.
So this number of the training data in this currently deep learning is too small but in
10 years ago or 20 years ago this is already somehow relative good size of the training
data.
Okay?
This is just to show an example we can connect a positive samples and also negative samples.
Now after we have such a kind of the training data we can utilize it to train a classifier
and each classifier use only one feature to find the good classifier that means to
find the good features.
So based on that to connect the different feature.
Okay?
Now the method in this learning is called boosting method.
It is a machine learning with the meta-archism to perform supervised learning because the
training data we know it is a face or non-face.
Okay?
To do this binary classification problem the two class membership we already know so it
is some kind of supervised learning.
So the boosting method basically utilize a weak classifier.
We can first use numerous different weak classifier and to connect a good weak classifier.
First we connect a number of the good weak classifier then we merge this classifier to
build a strong classifier.
Okay?
Now for the feature selection each weak classifier we only use one feature.
And use this one feature to classify the training sample into two different class.
Then if the error rate is just smaller than 0.5 then it is a better than random guess.
Right?
If you for two class classification problem if you random guess it then the error is around
50% or 0.5.
Okay?
So we only require this classifier is smaller than the error rate is smaller than 0.5 then
it can be a candidate for us to connect.
Okay?
So now here we keep this in your mind one classifier only use one feature.
Because it is very easy just use one feature to do the classification because one feature
is each training sample has only one value.
Now if we sort this feature from smallest to largest of all training data then we can
always find a trisor to separate all training data into two class.
Right?
This one feature single feature the value larger than trisor is the class one smaller
than the trisor is the class two.
The trisor is just one value we can always utilize many different trisor to see which
trisor will get the highest accuracy or lowest error rate.
Okay?
This is very easy to implement it.
Right?
Okay.
So this other boost we are aggressively used for the feature selection.
Okay?
So the training set have the positive sample and the negative samples.
So we use a simple classifier use only a single feature to try to find a good classifier and
then to select a good classifier is same meaning to select the feature because different classifier
use different feature one classifier is just use one features.
Right?
Okay.
Now basically this is idea of the classifier selection or feature selection.
Now how to select the feature use this feature try to use just one feature to classify all
training data.
Of course we can always try each feature one by one and then find one feature it produces
the lowest error rate.
Right?
Okay.
But if we try every feature and find the feature that has the lowest error rate is just a little
one feature.
Right?
Then what is the second feature?
Second good best feature.
If we just select the remaining feature to also get the best accuracy or the lowest error
rate does not mean each individual or though it is the best has lowest error rate does
not mean we put this two feature together we perform the best than any other two features.
Right?
Now suppose you have you because one select one feature is very simple right we just try
every feature to find the feature that has the lowest error rate.
But the second feature if you're if it's a signal lowest error rate but you put together
may not improve the accuracy.
Because for example if the first feature and the signal feature classify same samples correctly
and same sample incorrectly then if we combine them to the classification accuracy are same
no difference.
Right?
So this is why here to do the selection the variety is very important we should select
the make the select feature has has larger variation so that the different feature can
compensate each other can complement each other.
Okay?
Just now I mentioned that if one feature and the other feature two features the rule is
are exactly same to classify the sample correct or incorrect exactly same then you combine
these two features together does not improve the accuracy.
Right?
So the running classified feature sample if you use two still running classified.
Okay?
So this is why the selection is not just simply select the best feature the signal best feature
then third best feature one by one this is not a proper way to do the feature selection.
So how to solve this problem to really send that set of best feature this is the we la
Jones approach utilize this so-called other boost to solve this problem.
Okay?
So the idea to solve this problem is try to wait the sample differently.
Now for example if we want to send it the first best feature okay we just use this feature
to one feature to classify all training data and then to find the lowest error rate.
Okay?
But to send it the second based feature we should make try to find the second feature
can correctly classify the samples the first feature running classified.
Okay?
If the first feature already classified correct classified samples we don't need the second
feature also correctly classified.
We want the second best feature can classify some samples the first feature running classified.
Right?
So that means to select the second feature we should wait the samples running classified
by the first one higher weightage.
Well the samples classified the correct classified by first feature we are put a lower weightage.
Okay?
So this is idea of this selection process.
Okay now here as I mentioned that we have a large pool of the different features for
example to around 200,000 features.
Now among all these features we need to send next them one by one.
Okay?
So for then we can design a filter or not filter a classifier a very simple classifier.
This classifier just use one features X. Okay?
Then we can we can design a classifier very easily to find a choice to classify all the
training data.
If this classifier the result of this feature is larger than this choice is one smaller than
choice is minus one.
So use this very simple classifier we can classify all training data into two different
class one is one class minus one is the other class.
So here this HG is a classifier utilize feature FG and the theta G is we try to find use this
feature best classify all training data so we need to find an optimal choice.
Okay?
To use this optimal choice to classify this data with minimum error rate.
So we have this very simple classifier utilize only a single features here.
So then this is a selection process is show here.
Suppose we have aim example image in our training data or we have aim training samples or training
image.
Okay?
We have aim.
So then image we have the feature X1.
This is for each feature we have for image for sample one we have for X1 and it's label
Y is either minus one or one.
Right?
Then this we have sample one, sample two, sample two, up to sample aim.
This is cross all training sample training data for one features.
Okay?
So here we have the index here it's index all different training samples different training
samples the class label will be different but we have only two possible class.
So this Y is class label can be only two different value either minus one or one.
Now for example if we have one sample is X1 minus one so this minus one means it's a
negative training sample.
Okay?
This feature is X1.
So we have another training sample is for the ninth training sample we have the feature
value and it is label is one so this training sample is a positive training sample.
Okay?
And ninth image or ninth training sample is a face image or a positive training sample.
This is just an example.
So here show a training data set for one feature for example is X, value of X.
Okay now if we only use one feature to do the classification we can very easily to try
to classify all this training data into two different class.
Now to do so we first initialize a so-called waiting function dI.
I is for different training samples.
We first make this waiting function is a constant one over aim.
Aim is number of the training image or training samples.
So it is one over aim means in fact it's a constant we suppose this waiting function
is uniform distributed over all training samples.
So this is the first initialize it and then we will need to try the feature one by one.
So we will iterate this classification process from iteration one up to t if we store by
to the t then we will select g features.
So each iteration we try to select one feature.
Okay so this t is the index of different features.
So for each iteration in this process we select one features.
Okay now given a feature for example given a feature then we find a class of a ht that
minimize the error rate.
Here we say the expect to the distribution d here this is the distribution d but at the
beginning it is just a uniform distributed.
All training samples have same weightage.
The weights are same it's just one over aim.
So here we find the class of ht.
If we find the class of ht for example then we can use ht we find the class of ht to minimize
the error rate because given a feature we still need to find what is the tri-show to minimize
the classification error.
So suppose different tri-show is indicated by hg this hg is for different tri-show for
one tri-show of g then we can classify all training sample xi into two class into either
one or minus one.
I is index of different training samples because I is here from one to aim obviously I indicate
different training sample where j indicates different class field use the same feature
then the different class field means different tri-show because the class field is only depends
on this tri-show because it is only use one feature right one value we just use one tri-show
can separate all training data into two region.
So here given one single feature we take it out then we can design our class field hg
different hg is different class field because the tri-show will be different right then
given a tri-show given of on this feature single feature we can have a class field then
we can classify all training data xi i from one to aim all training data of the x training
samples.
Now this classification can be correct can be wrong right if the classification result
is same as yi then it is correct if it is not equals to yi is incorrect because yi for
sample i is either minus one or one for different training sample the label is either minus
one or one where the classification result h is also either one or minus one okay because
we can find a tri-show to find this feature smaller than tri-show is minus one larger
than tri-show is one right okay.
So here basically it's just given one feature we can design the class field this class field
is just determined by the choice okay then use this class field to classify all training
data it can be correct or incorrect okay if it's incorrect that means the classification
result is not same as the class label the training data okay so this is not equal right
now if it is not equal then it's di here at first all training sample are same value
one over aim this di were summed together then this submission is the arrow rate and the
tri-show g or this hg use the tri-show g or this class field hg so this is arrow rate
why is arrow rate for example at the beginning all this di is one over aim right so aim is
a total number of the training sample right here this is just one over aim where the submission
is a sum of the training sample it is a it is a false classified so this is a non this
submission web is a number of the training sample incorrect classified divided by the total
number of the training sample right so of course it's an arrow rate right the number of the sample
incorrect divided by the total number of the training sample so this is an arrow rate now this arrow
rate is just arrow rate we try to use one tri-show okay so use different tri-show web produce different
arrow rate then we can try we can test all different arrow tri-show to find a tri-show that were
minimize this arrow rate then we find the ht ht is just one of this hg it is its arrow rate is
minimized okay different hg is use different tri-show so anyway this process is because we
just use one feature we can use try to use different tri-show to separate the training data into two
cars then we find which tri-show is produce the minimum arrow rate that's all okay is the meaning of
this this expression okay now here we understand that if the classification result under this
tri-show is not equals to the ground truth neighbor then it is this this sample is running classified
right then it will contribute to one to sum together over all 20 samples then divided by
aim this d is one over a right now here we understand this is an arrow rate right because the number
of the incorrect classified divided by the total number of the samples this is the arrow rate but
in general this is the arrow rate just we treat all training sample equally okay all training
sample correct in quite classified we are contribute one to this summation okay in general we can put
this this d not equal to all training sample we can make this d different value for different i so
this is why in general we can we can make this d is a function of the i for d i is the index of
the training sample for different training sample we can put different weightage in compute this
arrow rate right of course at the beginning to send next the first feature this all sample has the
same weightage so it's a one over a okay now later we were we were we were changing this
weight on the different the training samples so here show e this e j is a sum of this one for all
mismatched x and h mismatches means miss class fear is run running classified because this one is not
equals to this one so the sample the class key result and this training sample are mismatch it
okay the for for a connected smallest this a rate we can fix the class fear for for one
feature okay now after we find this class fear for these features we have the arrow rate right
all the performance of this class fear then use this result we can update our weight in the
on the training samples so we first put compute a weight of this class fear because for for different
class fear or different feature because we utilize it for the feature selection right for different
features this arrow rate this arrow rate may be different so for some feature the error it could be
very small for some features the error it can be very large right so after we compute the arrow
rate then we can utilize this error rate to compute a weight for small error rate the weight for this
class fear will be higher for large error rate this alpha t will be smaller okay because we have 1
minus e t over e t right if e is smaller this is larger this denominator is smaller the fraction is
also larger so anyway we just convert small error rate to larger weight this weight is a weight for
this class fear t or the feature t now why this is a t previously we have a e j right e j is all
post a different trisor so we find the minimum error rate corresponding to the trisor is the
class fear t or the feature t right we get the feature t then we can compute the weightage
weight of the class fear t or feature t okay then after we have this feature t we can compute this
weight on different training samples okay the weight is computed in this expression the weight for
next feature is computed by the weight of the current feature after we either increase the weight
of for some training sample or decrease the weight for some other training samples okay now if we for
for feature t we have this weightage at the beginning of course is an evenly weighted right so after
we have the classification result then we can use the classification result to weight it to have to
update this weight on different training samples now this update will put the sample running
classified a high weights where correct classified by this class fear the weight becomes too small
so here we can see that the the change of the weight is the exposure function the exposure
function is the index is a minus alpha t is always positive because if g is smaller than 0.5 we can
see this is always positive right now multiplied by why I multiply by the classification result of
the current feature so if the for sample I if the class fear is correct then why I equals to
why I and the HT has same sign either both are one or both are minus one because it is a correct
classified right so the if y is a one this is also one if y is minus one this classification
result also minus one so it is a correct classified right so that this product will be positive
because one matter by one so why minus one matter by minus one is also one right so it's a positive
then we have e to power of negative index so this is a positive then is the index becomes
to negative so e to power of negative value will be will be somehow smaller than one so this factor
is a smaller okay now for the training sample x 20 sample x i if it is a running classified then
the sign of this y and the H will be different so for whatever class because they are different
this multiplication is a negative value so negative value this minus negative value becomes to a
positive value so it how positive value the value will be larger so it will not just on one so it
will increase this weight for this training samples okay now this that is just a normalization to make
this D is the sum of this D overall 20 sample is one just normalize into the weight is always smaller
than one the sum of all weight overall 20 sample is one okay this that is just a normalization factor
okay so then somehow we update the weight of different 20 sample then we try to find the next
feature so to find the next feature because the training sample of the previous feature
running classified has higher weights then the next feature to get a small error rate we are
trying to focus on the training sample it has higher weights so that the next feature we are
trying to classify the training sample the previous feature running classified okay because
otherwise this otherwise this value this this value will be larger because it is a the
running classified is weighted by this value this value for running classified by previous feature is
has higher weight okay so after this process it originally go from a T from one to this small
T from one to T we can select the T features so after that we can combine all these features to
form the strong classifier so before we further explain that we first further to understand this
process use this graph to understand it now here suppose all training sample has only two
three two dimensional training samples okay first each training sample has same weightage right
same weightage 1 over m m is the number of the training samples okay now in in the first iteration
we will try to find a feature it based classify just one feature based classify all this training
sample with minimum error rate okay so suppose we find the feature is this feature then we use
this feature to find a choice so then use this choice so to separate all training data into two
class positive class and the negative class right okay just use one feature okay now this
classification if we use this feature we can find that for some training sample this one two three
four five are correct classified this three is also correct classified well this training sample
this training sample because it's a negative training sample but classified as a positive one so this
three is running classified right then we use this result to weight the training sample so that the
correct classified training sample whereas we are decrease the weight whereas the running classified
training sample will increase the rate so that the these three will increase the value so next
for next iteration one training sample quality classified where for example reduced to half
becomes only half of training sample two training sample together is just take a rule of one training
sample where the running classified training sample increase to three that means once sample
we are contributed to error rate as same as three training samples okay so the weight increase means
this training sample we would the number of the Chinese equivalently it's a number of this
training sample increase so then use this training samples we have tried to find another feature to
correct it to minimize the error rate then we will try to call a friend of the feature that can
correctly classify this three 20 samples because this three 20 sample has higher weightage because
it is a running classified by the previous features right so the next one we we we repeat it then
we are find this trisor to separate use this feature then the trisor will be here because it
was separate this three training sample correcting into positive class and the negative class oh
this two are correct classified this one is still incorrect classified but all this one is correct
classified right okay now then after that we further update the weight okay then somehow in in the
first two features this tool is correct classified but this year incorrect classified if we further
update it then the weight we have become we increase this three and the others were decreased so the
next one the feature become to this one is the largest okay so at the end we were found the feature it
will correctly classify all training samples to form this decision boundary okay so this is a somehow
the idea how to use the weight on the training sample to increase the weight of the running
classified and decrease the weight of the for the correct classified to find samples so that we
can find the the different feature together can form a strong class fear okay just now I
indicated this increase the weight and decrease the weight basically come from from from this from
from this formula right because the next weight of the training sample is from the previous weight
weight of the training sample factor by this one this factor can be much than one smaller than
one depends on for this training sample it is a correct classified or running classified okay
now if we iterate this process t times then we can find the t features so joining these t
features we are performed the best because we said next feature try to find this feature can work
together to classify more training sample correct right okay so this is a basic ideas in this
so-called other boost method okay now after we send next to the features then each feature is a
class fear right so then we can combine all t class fear together to form a strong class fear so
the formula given is still here okay if the the feature one feature two and the feature n the
classification result result weighted by the way alpha then some together is much than this
try so then is one otherwise is zero this is a strong class fear how to understand this one this
one is in fact if you we move we move this sum of this all alpha to the left side we can see this is
just a normalization of all alpha one to alpha n so that alpha one plus alpha n after divided by
this one is one so all weight of the class fear the summation is one okay so this is just a weight I
believe this class fear the result will not be one or minus one it is for each class fear fear
after we send a feature for each single class fear the output should be one or zero right now
for example if all class fear has same weight one okay now this is a some then is a n if you divide
by n then all are is a sum of the n class fear result divide by n divide by n right so if for
some they need to get a divided by n if each h value could be one or zero then this summation
divided by n if larger than half then that means more than half of the class fear is the class
king result is one then we the final result is one if each the next half class fear classify it
as a one then the result will be zero right so here is just combine multiple class fear together
to form a strong class fear okay so this is the idea of this other boost to select the feature
now this selection of the feature after this training process we already know which t feature is
important to do a classification so in the really detection process we only need to compute this t
features we don't need to compute this 200,000 features we just compute this t number of the
features in if we select t features okay we need to compute all features only in the training phase
we need to compute a large number of feature and then to do the selection after selection in the
training process in the really big detection process we only need to compute the t feature so it
can be very fast right now from here we train a class fear of weak class fear to form a strong
class fear so then we can design our strong class fear very accurate as accurate as possible even
close to 100% correct or the error rate is zero because we can always increase the number of the
class fear or increase number of the feature okay so on the training data we can always in this way
increase the number of feature to classify all training data correct okay so that means the error
rate is zero but it could be generate a large number of the feature to achieve the error zero of
the error rate or 100% of the accuracy okay so this where although we increase the detection
accuracy but we decrease the detection speed because it could be we need several thousand
or hundred thousand of the features to get the error free classification okay but this we can
increase the accuracy always increase accuracy by increase the number of the features in this
training process we roughly understand that but the increased accuracy is the accuracy on your
training data okay if we even we increase the number of the features a huge number of the features
can 100% correct classify all training data does not mean it is 100% accurate for the test data so
the increased number of the feature may not be always increase the accuracy for the test data
right so we should not try to find the accuracy is 100% for the training data because it could be
overfit your training data well for the test data the accuracy could be very low okay so but anyway
from the experiment it shows that around this 200,000 features we can select just 200 features it is
sufficient for a very good face detection okay this is go through some experiment we find that we
can select only around 200 features from 200,000 features okay to get a very good result now if
we utilize these 200 features to do the classification it is still take around 0.7 seconds to scan an
image of this size pixels to complete the detection this 0.7 second is still larger than
the time between two frame in the video so in the video it can it still cannot achieve the real-time
face detection but of course this is more than 10 years could be 15 or 20 years ago the computer is
not as fast as now much slower right but this is a result okay so here because our our class
sphere is built up the strong class from each week class here okay although we utilize this 200
features that means we use 200 the class fear to do the classification we need this 0.7 second it
cannot be real-time but we can further speed up the detection because we use this feature or
class fear one by one individually and then based on our knowledge in the face detection or object
detection right in all scanning window only a few of this scanning window is a positive class the
vast majority of the window is a negative class right okay so we can utilize this property to further
speed up the detection process okay so we can build up the so-called attentional cascade class
fear not use all the next feature to do the classification for each input okay because for
99% of the input is a negative only 1% of the input could be the positive right so we can
use the feature to select the trisor to make the input sample go through each class fail one by
one in cascade case well for each class fail we only use one feature okay we can take the trisor
to make the classification into two class positive class or negative class we can make this trisor
to make the positive class always correct cannot be wrong okay oh the negative class is always
correct where the classification of the positive class could be correct or could be wrong okay in
such a case for most negative class it will go through here we just use one feature very fast to
get the result well for the one for some sample it is a positive one it will go to this one but we
cannot make sure it is a positive then we refer we further use the second feature to check it if
it's a negative then we stop it if it's a positive then we further check it because most input is
negative so in most window it we can very fastly stop it complete it only a few of this window
we are go through a non-process so overall in the whole image it will take a very small time because
only a few window where go through a non-process to finally determine it is a positive class right
so this is not difficult to understand it I believe I have one
to show that no this one cannot
because this is based on our knowledge right the almost all most the much portion of the input
will be negative only small portion is a positive so that fear we can see that the input window
okay if it's a face it will go to this or positive we further use the second feature further use the
third feature at the end that if it conforms a positive then it must be positive right the most
input is non-phase even it is the same not to face it just go through two feature it classify into
the non-phase then the classification were complete at this stage for other non-phase even it is a
very different from the face even from the first stage it will stop okay so in such a way we can
further increase the detection speed okay so this is so-called a tensioner cascade class fear
okay we utilize the feature one by one okay very fastly to fill it out the overall three non-phase
well the for some image it can be face and can be non-phase we use more features to determine it is the
face okay so this is detection structure where further speed up the detection process okay the
whole process is called the Villa Jones approach it is a very famous approach widely used in the
face detection before the deep learning area okay so because it's a very very famous approach
achieve a good real-time result so in the in the end meaning company implement this this approach in
real product okay so here the key point in this issue is the for many detection process it is
general need a large amount of the classification we need to numeric numerous times of the classification
so because of that we need to very fastly to generate the feature and the send it and they use a
small number of the feature to do the classification okay to achieve the real-time detection process
well this rectangle feature together with this other boost gave us a very good idea to very
efficiently come generate the feature and the select the feature and only use a small number of the
feature to do the detection where this the cascade connection further speed up the detection process
okay so here I show examples this Villa Jones approach implement by by inter and then this is
demonstrated in the inter given an image it can very fastly to detect all face this is an
actually output of one implementation of Villa Jones approach by the inter okay now here we
complete how to select the feature right but this action is based on we use the handcraft
to measure to generate the rectangle feature so we don't know it is a good feature or not good
feature so we can generate a huge amount of the features then we try to use this other boost
makes the use the machine learning to learn good feature from the training data okay so next topic
we will study a lot of way to to reduce the number of the features to use the dimension only to
reduction to reduce the dimension of the features so because all feature together will form a high
dimensional data right so we can use the dimension only to reduction further reduce the dimension
of the features so this is another way to use the data to to reduce the dimension of the feature to
have efficient classification so after the break we were studying another topic is dimension only
reduction for feature extraction so this is also a topic of our assignment okay so after you understand
this approach then you can use this PCA or ARDA to navigate a program to reduce a high dimensional
data into no dimension and then to do the classification and try to use a program to get
what is the classification accuracy we can use this method to reduce the data into different
amount of the dimension and so how is the classification accuracy you can also compile the
PCA and ARDA which one will perform better than the other or combine them together okay so now we
have a break after that we will study part of the next topic okay
you
money
What is the actual meaning of this D?
Okay, at the beginning,
this D is not 1 over m.
If every one is 1 over m,
then this D is equal to 1 over m.
So the meaning is that every running class,
the class 5 sample is either 1 or 0, sum together.
Now this summation is the number of the sample incorrect.
The number of the sample incorrect divided by m,
m is the total number of the sample.
Then this is a percentage, this is the error rate.
This is like a average.
Yes, if we have 100 training samples,
then this is not equal to the running class,
this is 20.
If this is not equal to the running class,
then this is 1.
Now this sum together is 20.
20 is equal to m,
20 is equal to 100,
that is 20% of the error rate.
Okay, 20% of the error rate is divided by the total number of the training sample.
If you come inside of this 1,
that means every training sample is multiplied by 1 over 100.
If you have x1 plus x100 divided by 100,
that means every value is divided by 100.
So this is what we can generate.
Every sample is divided by this number of training samples.
In general, different samples can be put in different weights.
We can make this 1 over 100 larger or smaller.
Okay.
How does this part make the error rate smaller?
This alpha is a positive value.
If the classification is correct,
then it is 1.
If it is incorrect, it is minus 1.
If it is minus 1,
then it becomes a positive value.
If it is positive value,
then it is larger.
But if it is correct,
then this is a negative.
If it is negative value,
then it becomes a little bit smaller.
Isn't this yi a positive value?
Yes, this yi is either 1 or minus 1.
If it is correct,
then these two are either 1 or minus 1.
They are the same.
Then their multiplication is a positive.
I just said that the positive and negative are the same.
This multiplication of these two is positive or negative.
This yi?
Isn't yi either minus 1 or yi?
Is yi the correct foundation?
No.
yi is the sample i.
It is a negative class or positive class.
If it is negative,
if it is a negative,
then it is 1.
If it is a negative,
then it is minus 1.
Okay.
This is a Chinese sample.
Do you know that every Chinese sample is a negative?
It is a negative or a negative.
If it is a negative,
then I will put yi.
then I will put yi minus 1.
Isn't this h also 1 or minus 1?
Yes, it is after the division.
Yes, if the division is correct,
then they are the same.
The same thing is a positive.
If the division is wrong,
then these two are different.
Then it is a negative.
Yes, I understand.
What does this part mean?
This is x.
x is the value of this.
Okay.
Let's first understand this.
Let's first make this position equal to the same value.
It is 1.
If this is 1,
what is this sum?
It is t, right?
Yes.
If this is 1,
then this is t,
the classification result.
If I add this,
then it is t, right?
Yes.
What does it mean?
If this is 1,
then this is t, right?
Yes.
If every one is 1,
then this is t, right?
This is t, right?
If this is t,
then it is t, right?
Yes.
Then I will put t,
then I will put t, right?
Yes.
If every one of the cosfals
is right,
then it is 1.
Then the sum of this is t,
t is 1.
1 is not 1 over 2.
It should be 1.
Because every cosfal is 1, right?
If half of the cosfals is 1,
half of the cosfals is 0,
then this sum is 0.5.
So at this time,
it is just 0.
If half of the cosfals is 1,
then this cosfals is 1.
then this is 0, right?
This is in the same weight situation.
The same weight situation is like this.
But I can make this alpha not equal to you.
It is not the same.
For different cosfals,
I can put different weights.
I still don't understand.
Half of the cosfals is 1 over 1.
Is this division just divided into...
The result of this division is 1 over 0.
Every cosfal is 1 over 0, right?
Then we have 7 cosfals.
If the cosfals are 1,
then this division is T, right?
Then the second T should be bigger.
If this T is bigger,
then every cosfals is 1.
If every cosfals is 0,
then this cosfals is 0.
If half of the cosfals is 1,
and half of the cosfals is 0,
then this cosfals is 0.5.
I understand.
But how did this become the strong cosfals?
Because the last one is 1 or 0
is based on the majority of the cosfals.
If half of the cosfals is 1,
then the result is 1.
then it is 0.
If half of the cosfals is 1,
This division is a majority vote.
I have 100 cosfals.
Based on the 100 cosfals,
I take the majority of the cosfals.
The majority of the cosfals is 1,
and the majority of the cosfals is 1.
If the majority of the cosfals is 1,
then the majority of the cosfals is 0.
H is...
Result is either 1 or 0.
I know.
This is the same as the other one.
Which one?
This one.
Which one is the same?
Yes, these two are the same.
This is the same as this one.
This is used during the selection process.
The line in the picture just now,
what does it mean?
It's just a demonstration.
If we connect all the cards,
then we can put all the samples together.
This is the concept of the cosfals.
Yes, this is the concept.
You can see the whole thing in real life.
Thank you.
We are the top of the class.
What?
Our class is the...
No, it's just the top of the class.
The top of the class?
Yes, yes.
It's the top of the class.
The top of the class?
Yes, the top of the class.
Thank you.
We just talked about the wrong answer.
If the negative is 1,
then we think the answer is wrong.
No, no, no.
If the negative is 1,
then the negative class is 2.
then it is 1 class,
which is the top of the class.
It doesn't represent the result of the prediction, right?
It is the result of the prediction.
The result of the prediction is that the prediction is 1 or 0.
Is it 1 or 0?
Then we are talking about the positive and the negative.
Yes, it is 1 class,
another class is minus 1.
It's just divided into two.
Yes.
What does zt mean?
zt is a norm.
zt is sum of all y.
So, in this case,
we can change the rule.
The normalization is the rule.
So, we can change all the i's?
No, no, no.
All the i's.
After we get rid of this,
we can make all the i's sum together equal to y.
So, all the i's sum is equal to y.
So, this sum is not equal to y.
I will get rid of some of the i's sum.
Now, I will get rid of all the i's sum,
and this is the sum.
Yes, yes.
Thank you.
Mr. Wang.
I think this is something that...
Mr. Wang, you are not...
This is not...
This is a concept.
I don't know what it is.
But it is a concept.
Because we are waiting for our English pronunciation.
If you want to understand your concept,
you need to use the word,
not writing.
Not writing.
This is not saying that you don't need to memorize.
You don't need to memorize.
Yes, you don't need to memorize.
So, this thing is...
It is almost necessary to remember.
It won't be tested.
I won't be tested.
I will remember this thing.
It is a concept.
So, I won't be tested if I remember this thing.
It won't be tested.
For example, this is a concept.
Yes, yes.
I won't let you explain it.
Because this is something to be remembered.
OK.
The real concept is the most basic concept.
And then it can be pushed out from the math.
OK.
The push of this math is something you can push out
after you understand it.
OK.
Mr. Wang, you wrote down the history.
And then we will remember it.
OK.
This is not it.
It is not it.
For example, I want you to design a decision rule.
It will minimize the error rate.
OK.
Then you should understand that I want to minimize error rate.
Just like I maximize the probability of the class.
You can...
You can push out your decision
by the way you want to do it.
Just like you said,
the last name is...
No, it's not it.
I said this concept won't be tested.
This concept is not a very strict concept.
This is just something to be remembered.
This concept won't be tested.
OK.
The last one is...
For example, in this place,
I will write down every t is an i to t.
Every t?
Yes.
Every t is an i to t.
There is a branch, it is a value.
It is i to i to x i.
This 2 is a t to t, right?
Yes.
It will have a result.
I will use different numbers to get a result.
Yes.
OK.
So now we can resume our lecture to the Topic 9.
So Topic 8, we are not including the final exam or quiz.
OK.
So don't worry about it because although Topic 8,
this other boost and the Villa Jones approach is very effective
before the deep learning.
But basically this approach is a very bright idea.
It is a very good idea, a skill to do that.
There is no theoretical mathematical support,
strongly support or prove it, right?
So basically the Topic 8 is a very bright idea
of Villa Jones to solve the problem.
So this topic we are not including the final exam or the quiz.
OK.
So now compared to Topic 8 is more intuitive
or somehow a very good idea or skill to solve the problem.
Compared to that, this Topic 9, we have very rigorous
mathematical support, very strong mathematical support to that,
especially PCA and ARDA.
So this is more important.
OK.
Now the Topic 9, we need to study the so-called dimensionality reduction.
So because in many applications such as the visual object detection,
recognition, some bioinformatics and data mailing,
we have a very high dimension of the data.
Given an image, every pixel is one dimension
because if we convert the image into all data utilized for the classification,
then if the image is 1,000 by 1,000, then we have one million pixels.
Each pixel is one dimension because for different image,
every pixel, the value will be different, right?
So in most application, we will face the problem of very high dimension of the data.
So the high dimension of the data will cause the problem
or generate some burdens on the robust and accurate recognition or classification.
OK.
So it will cause a big problem.
So because of that, the feature extraction and dimensionality reduction
becomes to a very critical module in the whole computation problem
or the pattern recognition problem.
So in the feature extraction, we always try to find a reliable feature
and a discriminative feature to utilize in the system
to differentiate the object into different class.
Now this feature extraction is most very critical one.
It also comes from the, we can see this from the deep learning.
All deep learning, all modules are some kind of the feature extraction
or feature generation extraction.
So owning the last layer is to do the classification.
OK.
Where the last layer is very simple, we can just use a very simple linear classifier.
Because we already generate or extract a very reliable features,
then the classification is very simple.
So later, if we study the CIN and the transformer,
we will know that, for example, in this transformer,
the last layer is owning a very simple linear classifier.
But before that, we have very complicated steps,
try to convert the feature into different form,
try to extract good features.
OK.
Now the feature extraction basically can be done by many different approaches,
such as use human knowledge to identify what is a good feature.
For example, for the fingerprint recognition,
we can use the point of the ridge and all ridge bifurcation as a point.
Then a distribution of this point can serve as a feature.
Right.
We can also use some kind of the corner of the image as a feature,
because different objects in the corner will be at different positions.
Right.
But given a green level image, what is the corner?
It is unclear.
If it's a binary image, of course, it is very clear where is the corner of the object.
Right.
If it's a green level image, even within the object,
it may also form some kind of the corner.
Right.
But basically, the local structure can use some local property,
such as a corner or blob of the image,
to take the position as a feature to do the classification.
We can also use some global structure of the image, such as transform,
for example, the Fourier transform and other transforms.
After this transform, for example, after the Fourier transform,
the magnitude of the Fourier transform is the translation invariant.
Then we can take it as a feature.
This is just an example.
But now here, we will study using machine learning to learn the feature,
use the training data set to determine what is the good features
or to reduce the dimension of the feature.
So in this topic, we'll give a wide examples.
For example, for the face recognition,
before deep learning, the subspace approach or dimensionality reduction approach
is the most famous approach to do the face recognition.
Later, it goes to a sparse coding.
But in that year, the so-called dimensionality reduction
is one of the very good approaches to do the face recognition.
Now, in this dimension reduction, what is the feature extraction?
We give an image.
Image is a matrix, right?
It's a two-dimensional one.
For example, this image is 300 by 200.
Then all together, we have 60,000 pixels.
Then all these pixels, we will arrange it into very long vectors.
Each element in this vector is one pixel.
So all together, one image will form a 60,000 dimensional column vector.
This is a very high-dimensional vector.
Now, then we try to reduce the dimension of this non-vector into, for example, just 60.
Then the feature vector is just the sixth dimension.
So from x to f, it starts from 60,000 dimensional vector becomes to a 60 vector.
Then this one can be complete by the x-multiply matrix.
For example, if this matrix is 60,000 by 60, then it's transposed
multiplied by this 60,000 vectors becomes to only 60 dimensional vector.
Okay, so this is one example.
We can reduce the high-dimensional vector x into no-dimensional x.
Now, of course, if we do such kind of dimension reduction, this transform is a linear transform
because the vector x, high-dimensional vector x, is just multiplied by a matrix
to generate a no-dimensional vector f.
So this is a linear transform.
But don't underestimate the role of the linear transform.
It is a very important role.
Just give an example.
All Fourier transform is some kind of a linear transform.
For discrete single or image, all Fourier transform is some kind of vector multiplied by a matrix.
Whereas the element of this matrix is just e to the power of j minus omega and so on.
Okay, so it's a matrix.
It's just one specific matrix.
And in the neural network, a multi-linear perceptron, it is also some kind of a multiply by a matrix.
Only the neural network is input multiply by a matrix, then goes through a nonlinear function.
But the nonlinear function is not a non-nullable.
So the non-nullable parameter for all neural networks is some kind of a linear operation.
And convolution is also some kind of a matrix multiplication.
Later, I will further show that after this week.
And the transformer also utilizes this matrix multiplication to generate many multiple copies from one copy of the input.
And it's also utilized in the transformer.
So this is a very important transform, although it's a linear.
Then from this kind of a matrix multiplication, what we can understand is the role of this matrix multiplication.
First, it will take a feature scaling.
Because the original feature x in this x1 to x60,000, right?
Multiply by a matrix, that means a different feature will multiply by different weight in this matrix.
So we have the feature scaling.
We can use this value of this matrix to put important feature element in this x, higher value, where unimportant is very low value.
So it will form a feature scaling.
Now, if this matrix is not a square matrix, for example, it is a 60,000 by 60,
then this multiplication of the matrix will perform the dimension and true reduction.
It is some kind of a feature extraction.
So this is the role of this matrix multiply by a vector, right?
Okay, now, as I mentioned that all Fourier transform is just a specific matrix.
But here, to determine the matrix, to do this transform, we use our training data to learn or to estimate or to compute.
Use the training data to compute.
What is the optimal matrix here?
To perform this linear transform.
Okay.
Now, we will introduce the very famous PCA algorithm.
This algorithm is called principle component analysis.
Okay, this is the most important method in all data analysis, high dimensional data analysis.
Okay.
Not only used in computation or classification or recognition, also utilized in many other areas.
So I hope you should really understand the principle and the physical meaning of this principle component analysis.
Because it is very useful.
It is widely used in many areas.
Include this recognition.
Okay.
So what is a principle component analysis?
Principle component analysis is to determine this transform matrix, fine, based on the training data.
Okay, so suppose we have a set of the training data.
We have Q samples.
Okay, so X1, X2 are up to XQ.
Each XI has n dimensional vector.
All vector by default is a column vector.
Okay, so we have this represent a set of the data in the training set.
Okay.
Now, here each 20 sample is n dimensional vector.
So it is a point in n dimensional space.
Right?
For example, two dimensional vector is a point in a plane.
Three dimensional vector is a point of the three dimensional space.
Okay.
So here high dimensional vector is also a point in a high dimensional space.
Now, first we will study how given a training samples, Q training samples, how to use just one point, one samples to best represent all training data.
Okay.
So in fact, this is very simple, very clear.
We should know the average of all training samples should be this one.
But mathematically, we can prove it.
Okay.
Suppose we have XI, I from one to Q.
We have Q different samples, but we want to use just one sample, one vector to represent all this one.
Then we, how to find this one?
We need to find this one to make the difference of this one to all training samples, the sum of this distance smallest.
Or this arrow, we can say that this difference is arrow.
The arrow between this vector to all training samples, this difference, the sum of this difference will be minimized.
Okay.
Now, this is a vector difference.
Then to convert this into one single value, we use the arrow to norm.
So arrow to norm is just this vector transpose, multiply by this vector.
So produce one value.
So this is arrow to norm.
So we have minimized this expression to find the X0.
Now, to find this X0, it's very easy if we take the differentiation of this E square against the X0 to make this differentiation equals to zero.
We can very easily to get the solution of this X0 is the average of all training samples.
So the mean vector of all 20, of all vectors is the best single vector to represent all training samples.
Because the distance between each of all training sample to this vector, the sum of the distance square is minimized.
This is also definition of average or mean, right?
So we minimize this arrow.
Now, after we have this mean to compute the average of all training samples, we can subtract all training samples by its mean.
Okay.
To produce this training sample, this training sample is called centralized training sample.
Because all this X curve, it's mean will be zero, right?
Because it is original X i minus it's mean.
So all this X curve is centralized.
Now, the centralized vector is also a vector.
If we put all this training sample together, then we have a matrix.
Okay.
This we will utilize this matrix to simplify our computation.
So here, because as I mentioned that all vector by before is a quantum vector, right?
One sample, one image is a quantum vector.
Then we put all training image together.
Then it will form a matrix.
This is big X, right?
This is all training samples.
Now, we utilize this centralized training sample.
Now, next one, we will try to find one dimension to use one dimension to reduce the high dimensional data into just one dimension.
So to determine one dimension is just to determine a direction.
Along this direction, we can project all high dimensional data into this axis, into this vector.
So it becomes to one dimension, right?
So basically, we need to find a vector phi.
The length of this vector is a unit.
So we have unit length of the vector phi.
Okay.
So if we try to use this phi to best represent all training sample, then if we can use this phi to produce one dimensional data.
So that means this high dimensional data multiplied by this vector,
all this vector transpose multiplied by this data, then produce just one value.
This value is the value project this undimensional data on this vector, right?
This is a projection.
Okay.
So we need to find one dimension X.
If we project all data onto this dimension, then produce just one dimensional data, AI.
Now, we know an undimensional vector transpose multiplied by another undimensional vector,
a common vector, the result is just one value, right?
This value, physical meaning is project this vector to this vector.
Well, this vector is one training sample.
All training samples project to the same vectors.
So different training sample, we have different single value, different value.
This is just one dimensional value, right?
Okay.
Now, if we see this dimension, one dimension, one vector best represent all training sample,
that means this, we use this vector to project a high dimensional data into just one dimension.
Then this one dimensional data AI, I from one to Q, we are best represent AXI, high dimensional.
This is the undimensional.
Okay.
This is just one dimension, right?
This one dimensional data AI best represent all AXI.
How to say it is the best represent AXI.
Okay.
AI is just one dimension, right?
But this one dimension is the value along this vector, right?
So if this AI multiplied by this vector, then becomes to undimensional vector.
So this one is, we use just one value to construct an undimensional data,
because AI multiplied by undimensional vector becomes to undimensional vector.
So this is use one dimension to reconstruct the undimensional.
So we use just one dimension to get an undimensional data, make this difference minimum,
to make this one dimensional data reconstruct to undimensional close to the original data, right?
So to make this difference minimum.
Of course, this difference is the difference then take the error to long.
Then it should be minimum overall training data, then sum overall training data, right?
So we need minimize this one to compute what is the best five, best vector.
It can minimize this reconstruction error.
Okay.
So we understand this is a reconstruction error,
because we use one dimension to construct the undimensional,
and then make this undimensional data close to all training data to make this difference minimized.
Okay.
So this is a square is a reconstruction error square, right?
Use one dimension to reconstruct the undimensional to minimize this error.
So we need to find what is this five to make this error minimize minimum value.
Okay.
Then to compute it, this mathematical direction is very straightforward.
First, this error to norm is just this vector transpose times itself, right?
This is very clear.
Okay.
So this, the error to square is just the vector transpose multiplied by itself.
So get one value, right?
Then sum overall training data to get one value.
So we need to minimize this one, right?
Now to minimize this one, if we do the cross multiplication, then you will generate the four items.
Now in these four items, we can check out, for example, this one multiplied by this one is just a i square,
because this item multiplied by this a i phi x curve, where phi transpose x curve by dilation is just one dimension of the a i, right?
So this multiplication is just a i square.
This one multiplied by this one is also a i square.
We can very easily say that, show that, because phi transpose times phi is one, which is a unit length.
The length of this vector is one, right?
So from here, we can very easily to get the result.
Okay.
Because this one multiplied by this one is a square.
This one multiplied by this one is also a square.
So we get only the first one multiplied by the first item is here.
So we have the difference of these two.
This is very good for just to multiply them together.
We get this expression, right?
Now from this expression, what is the a i square?
A i is just one value, right?
A i square.
A i is here.
If we replace this a i by this expression,
we replace a i by what it comes from, then we get this expression, right?
So a i is this one, so the transpose, this a i multiplied by a i,
then we can put this transpose because the a i is just one value,
the transpose is itself.
So anyway, we can get this expression, right?
It's this one, a i square.
Now this expression, if we put this file outside of this summation,
then we get this one, right?
Now from this one, we see what is the value,
what is this amount within this bracket?
We have a column vector multiplied by a row vectors.
This is a training data, minus its mean because it's x-curve, right?
Then sum over all training data.
This one is a covariance matrix, right?
By definition, it's a covariance matrix.
So here, we can very easily show that this multiplication is a covariance matrix.
Of course, we need to divide by this constant, but this is not very important.
So anyway, then the second term is just a q multiplied by this phi transpose times ST.
ST is this covariance matrix.
So because the x-curve is x-minus its mean, right?
So we get this expression.
Now this is a data covariance matrix or total scatter matrix, right?
We already mentioned that in the previous lectures.
So to minimize this one, it's just to maximize this one
because the first term, the value is fixed for whatever value of the phi
because it is nothing, the value of the first term is nothing to do with the phi, okay?
So to maximize this, it's just to minimize the second term.
So, sorry, minimize this e square is just to maximize this one.
So this minimization becomes to maximize this term
and the condition that phi should be unit length, okay?
Phi should be a unit length vector.
So if we don't have this constraint, then the length of this phi larger than this value will be larger, right?
So we cannot find an optimal result because anyway, if we always take the phi, the length is very long.
All this is, if we not constraint this is a unit length.
So we, from here, we have to minimize the reconstruction error is to maximize this term
and the condition of this unit length of the phi.
So we have the so-called conditional optimization.
Well, for this conditional optimization in the mathematics, we have a very common method.
We can convert the conditional optimization into unconditional optimization by using this term minus this phi transpose phi minus 1,
use lambda minus these terms to maximize this one.
This is so-called Nagaranger optimization method.
We can convert conditional optimization into unconditional optimization.
Now, I will not go through this mathematics.
You just accept this so-called Nagaranger optimization.
This is also very fundamental in mathematical books, right?
But I will not go through the directly derivation how we get this unconditional optimization from this conditional optimization,
but conceptually, we should be able to understand that.
For example, what we need is maximize this one, right?
Maximize this one, but under this condition.
Now, this condition is the same as phi transpose times phi minus 1 equals to 0.
If we move this one into the left side, then the right side is 0.
So is this 1 equals to 0?
Now, if we need to constraint this one equals to 0, but we can convert this one into optimization to minimize this one.
So to minimize this one, it will close to 0.
So we maximize the original one and minimize this one is make the solution close to this condition.
Because if we maximize the whole sense, it will maximize the first term and minimize the second term, because the second term is minus.
So we understand this term equals to 0 is the condition.
Well, we not take this one equals to 0 to minimize this term.
So it is somehow equivalent.
So from here, we just try to concept it to understand the reason why it is possible we can convert a conditional optimization into unconditional optimization.
Because this unconditional optimization already tried to achieve this condition to make this one close to 1 or to minimize this difference.
Now, after that, we should be able to accept anyway, this is strictly rigorous mathematics, a Nagaranger optimization method to convert conditional optimization into unconditional optimization.
So if we accept that, then this optimization is very standard for solution, right?
So to get the solution, we just take the differentiation of this function against the file we want to have, then let this differentiation equals to 0.
Then the solution of this equation is the file that maximizes this term or maximizes this reconstruction error.
No, maximize this term, then it's a minimize this reconstruction error.
Okay, so to solve this equation, we can very easily to find this equation is this form.
This two cancels because x to the 0, move this one to the right side, then we have this formula.
So what we need is to find a vector phi, satisfy this equation.
Now, this is very familiar, we're very familiar to this one, right?
So what is this equation and what is the solution?
So this is a very standard problem in the linear algebra that the vector phi satisfies this equation is called eigenvector of the matrix ST, right?
So this is the very standard linear algebra problem, okay?
So here we understand that given training data, we can compute the covariance matrix or total scatter matrix, okay?
Then in this matrix, we find the eigenvector and the eigenvalue, then this eigenvector is the vector that will produce the minimum reconstruction error, okay?
Now, then we convert our problem to the problem to solve the eigenvalue and the eigenvector because this is a very common problem in the linear algebra.
Okay, so we see that if phi, this vector, is an eigenvector of the covariance matrix, then this one will be maximized.
This one will be maximized, so the reconstruction error will be minimized, right?
If it's an eigenvector, then this one will be maximized, this term and reconstruction error will be minimized.
Now, what is this term? Okay, what is the value of this term?
This is just a single value, right? Because a row vector multiplies matrix and then a multiply by a common vector is just one value.
So this one will be maximized if phi is an eigenvector. Then what is this one? We can very easily see what is this one.
Okay, so this term, in fact, if we replace this s-key back into its definition, okay, is the training data multiplied by its transpose, right?
If we make this phi inside of this summation, then we have this expression, very straightforward.
Now, from this expression, we can see this term and this term are same, okay? This vector multiplied by this vector.
But what is this one? This is project the centralized training data onto this phi.
So this one is the AI. This is AI. So this multiplication is AI square.
So AI square sum over all training data, what is this?
AI is the project of the data, high-dimension data into one dimension phi.
And then minus its mean, then square sum average over all training data. What is it?
It is a variance of this one-dimensional data AI, right?
Okay, so that means it will maximize the variance of this one-dimensional data.
Whereas this one-dimensional data is project the original high-dimension into this phi or onto this vector phi, become to one-dimensional data.
Then this one-dimensional data, overall training data, the variation will be the maximum value.
It is pretty clear because the eigenvector maximizes this one, right?
Now here we understand the physical meaning of the eigenvector.
Given a high-dimensional data, if we find a vector to project high-dimension data into this vector, it becomes to one-dimensional data.
Then this one-dimensional data, we can compute the variance.
Variance indicates the variation of the data, right?
Then eigenvector will make the variance on this dimension maximum value.
It will larger than other phi value.
If phi is eigenvector, the variance along this eigenvector will be larger than other vectors or other vectors.
So the eigenvector will produce the data in this one-dimension has largest variance because this is the largest produced by the eigenvector phi.
Okay, so here this is the definition of variance, right?
Because AI is already minus its mean, the one-dimensional data minus its mean.
Okay, so this is the definition of the variance.
Now we understand the physical meaning of the eigenvector.
Now what is the meaning of the eigenvalue?
Okay, now in the linear algebra, this is a common definition.
What is the eigenvector and eigenvalue, right?
Given any matrix, okay, here is a covariance matrix.
If satisfy this equation phi is eigenvector, lambda is eigenvalue.
Now from here, if we multiply phi, I suppose, at the both sides, we can very easily get this one.
This one equals to this one, multiplied by phi, right?
Then this one, because phi is a unit length, then it is a lambda.
So we can see this amount is the eigenvalue.
So here we understand the physical meaning of the eigenvalue.
The eigenvalue is the data, oh no, the eigenvalue of the covariance matrix of the data
is the variance of the high-dimensional data projected to the corresponding eigenvector.
So the eigenvalue is this variance of the data along the eigenvector.
Well, this variance will be maximum value compared to other non-eigenvectors.
Okay, so these two findings, we find the meaning of the eigenvector and eigenvalue,
is very important because the variance is useful for the classification, right?
Okay, so now, because we try to find this phi to maximize this one, then this one is the eigenvalue.
So we need to find the maximum eigenvalue, right?
So because of that, we have the PCA, the principal component analysis, is to try to reduce the n-dimensional data into m-dimension.
Then we need to find, you use the m eigenvectors corresponding to m, not just the eigenvalue.
Because eigenvalue is the variance, okay?
So eigenvalue is the value of this one.
So to minimize the reconstruction error, we need to maximize this one.
So we need to maximize the eigenvalue so that we need to find the eigenvector corresponding to the largest eigenvalue, right?
eigenvalue is a variation, variance.
So if the eigenvector is the vector project high-dimension data into this dimension, then the variance of the data in this dimension is the eigenvalue.
So to minimize the reconstruction error from high-dimensional and reduce to no-dimensional m, we need to find m eigenvector corresponding to m, not just the eigenvalue.
Okay, now one eigenvector is n-dimensional vector, column vector for n-dimensional data x, right?
If we put a m column vector, eigenvector together to form a matrix, then this matrix is m by m.
Now this m by m matrix transpose multiplied by n-dimensional vector becomes to n-a-m dimension.
So the n-dimension will reduce to a-m dimension by this multiplication, by this matrix.
So we reduce the n-dimensional data into a-m dimension if we choose a-m eigenvectors to form this matrix, okay?
And this dimension reduction will minimize the reconstruction error, okay?
So this is pretty clear, right?
Now, again, what is the reconstruction error?
Now, given n-dimensional data x, use this m eigenvector to reduce the n-dimensional data into a-m dimension.
Then what is the reconstruction error?
That means we use this a-m dimension of y to reconstruct the n-dimensional x.
So this reconstruction is the phi multiplied by yi.
yi is a-m dimension multiplied by n by a-m dimension.
Then this multiplication will produce n-dimensional vector.
This n-dimensional vector, of course, plus the mean, because we discussed this one already minus its mean y, plus this mean vector.
Then this one is the reconstructed x, n-dimensional x, x hat.
Use the no-dimensional data to reconstruct the high-dimensional data, okay?
Then this high-dimensional data, compared with the original high-dimensional data, this error will be minimized, okay?
So this is the famous principle component analysis, okay?
So this is why we have principle components, right?
So the principle component 1, component 2, component 8 is a principle component because it uses each each way best to represent the high-dimensional data x, okay?
So we choose the principle component.
Each dimension is one component. It's called one component.
So the famous principle component is just find the eigenvector corresponding to largest eigenvalue to form a matrix.
Then these matrix will be used to reduce the high-dimensional data, n-dimensional data, into no-a-m dimension.
Then the reconstruction error, of course, we can reconstruct this x by y, this x hat, is just this phi multiplied by y, it becomes n-dimension, right?
This is reconstruction error.
Now this reconstruction error, we can very easily prove that it is a sum of the eigenvalue not used in this eigenvector, okay?
If we only use m eigenvector, then we have remaining eigenvector not used, then not used eigenvalue corresponding to this not used eigenvector sum together is this reconstruction error, okay?
So from here, we can also see we should choose the eigenvector corresponding to largest eigenvalue so that the eigenvalue not used, the summation will be minimized, okay?
Right? This is reconstruction error.
So this is a pretty clear, right? This principle component analysis.
From here, we can see this mathematical derivation in fact is not complicated. In fact, it is pretty clear, very straightforward.
Now here, as I mentioned that this, we need to find the eigenvector and eigenvalue of the so-called covariance matrix or the total scatter matrix.
The definition of the covariance matrix show here.
Now if we put all training data, centralize the training data into a matrix, we can very easily to show the covariance matrix is just the multiplication of these two data matrix, right?
Because we utilize it to simplify our derivation.
We can utilize this one to simplify our derivation.
Now from this matrix, we know a matrix can have the rank.
For m by m matrix, the rank of the matrix can be n or less than n or smaller than n, okay?
So a matrix may not be always full-ranked matrix, right?
This is also from the linear algebra, okay?
Now of course for m by m matrix, the largest rank is n, right?
But it can be smaller than n if all column, all element is not independent, then it can be smaller than n.
Now because the covariance matrix is computed by the training data, so if we have the q training data, if q minus 1 is smaller than n, then this matrix, the rank is only q minus 1.
Because we have only q independent sample to compute this matrix, okay?
So we can very clearly see that why it's q minus 1?
Because the 1 is utilized to compute the mean, okay?
Because all vector minus is mean, so the rank will reduce 1, so it's q minus 1, okay?
So how to understand this rank is q minus 1 can be less than n.
Now we understand that the rank somehow related to the variance because the eigenvector...
or moment here with all the...
If the rank, the matrix has the rank is k, then this matrix will only have k.
So we can see nonzero eigenvalues, okay?
Because the number of the nonzero values is equals to the rank of this matrix, okay?
This is also come from the linear algebra, but we can understand that why?
Because the eigenvalue is the variance, right?
Now if the data, the variation is 0, then it will cause the rank will reduce.
For example, I just use one example to try to explain why this high dimensional data, the rank, could be very small.
Now for example, we have very high dimensional data, but this high dimensional data, we have only two samples.
If we have two samples, then we can always find a line to link these two samples together, okay?
Then what is the variation of this high dimensional data?
This high dimensional data has only nonzero variance and nonzero this line.
All other directions also go to the line, link these two samples, the variation is 0.
So the rank is only 1, right?
Only a non-1 dimension, it is nonzero variation.
All other dimensions also go to this one, the variation is 0, okay?
That means, for example, if we have multiple training data, if all this training data is high dimension, but all this training data is a non-straight line.
So all this training data, in fact, is just one dimensional data, because it's only a non-1 dimension, it has difference.
All other dimensions also go to this one dimension, the difference is 0.
All other dimensions, all training data are exactly same value.
In other dimensions also go to this line.
If all this point in high dimensional space is a non-align, right?
So here we understand that.
Anyway, roughly understand this concept of the rank.
Now, basically for the PCA, if the number of the training data is smaller than the dimension,
if we have only the q minus 1 dimension, it's smaller than n, then we can reduce the dimension of x to y into this q minus 1.
Then the reconstruction error will be 0, because the remaining, all remaining eigenvalues is 0, so the reconstruction could be 0.
Right?
So this is shown here, because the reconstruction error is a sum of the eigenvalue not used.
If we utilize all non-zero eigenvalues in this dimension reduction, then not used eigenvalues all are 0, then summation is 0.
So the reconstruction could be 0.
Now, the scatter matrix based on the definition of the scatter matrix or covariance matrix or Boyer's, it is a symmetry matrix, right?
The transpose is itself.
Okay, this is pretty clear based on this one.
You do the transpose, then it will be identical to without the transpose, right?
So the transpose is itself.
It is a symmetry matrix.
So for the symmetry matrix, we can vary, of the covariance matrix, we can very easily to show that the eigenvector corresponding to different eigenvalues are also going on.
Also going on means the different eigenvalues, the modification is 0.
The same eigenvalue, if i equals to j, the same eigenvalue, it is a unit length, then the modification this is 1.
So this is called also normal.
All eigenvectors is also going on.
If the eigenvector will take the unit length, then it is also normal.
It's a unit length vector, and the different vector is the product, modification is 0.
So they are also going on.
Now we know this also going on is very important because we know axis, if we represent a data, all axis there must be also going on, right?
X and Y, there must be also going on.
So here, this is a proof how the different eigenvector corresponding to different eigenvalues are also going on.
This I will skip that.
If you are interested, you can see that it is not difficult.
Okay, this is purely mathematical proof, also not difficult.
Now, we, from the linear algebra, the definition of the eigenvector and eigenvalue is shown here, right?
But this definition is only for one eigenvector and one eigenvalue.
Of course, it is held for each of the eigenvector and eigenvalue, right?
To simplify this definition, we can have a definition to contain all eigenvector and eigenvalue.
By doing so, we can put all eigenvector, quantum vector into a matrix so that we have an eigenvector matrix.
Okay, now for full-ranked matrix, we have n eigenvectors for n-dimensional, for n-by-n matrix, right?
We can find n eigenvectors corresponding to n non-zero eigenvalue, right?
So we have a matrix, this five contains all eigenvectors.
This is an eigenvector matrix. It's also an n-by-n matrix.
Okay, now, because all different eigenvectors are also going on.
So, also going on means the transpose multiplied by them is an identity matrix.
So that means for such an also-gonnawn matrix, the transpose is inverse.
We can very easily to compute what is the inverse. We just transpose this one, this matrix, then we get the inverse.
Or phi transpose phi is i. Also phi times phi transpose is also i.
Okay, this is pretty clear from the property different eigenvector is also going on, right?
Now, from here, if we put all eigenvalues into a matrix as a diagonal matrix,
where the diagonal element is the eigenvalue, all of the diagonal elements are zero.
Then we have an eigenvalue matrix, also n-by-n eigenvalue matrix.
Then we can simplify the definition for each of the eigenvector eigenvalue into a matrix format.
We put all eigenvector into a matrix and put all eigenvalue into a matrix, but it's a diagonal matrix.
Then we have the definition of here for eigenvalue vector and eigenvalue matrix and eigenvector matrix.
This is very directly come from the definition of the eigenvalue and the eigenvector for each of them.
Then we can put them together to have this definition.
We need to use this one to put all eigenvector and eigenvector into one formula to do our mathematical derivation.
These two are equivalent, right?
Now, from this one, if we multiply phi transpose at both sides, we can very easily get another more useful definition.
It's a sigma.
This covariance matrix is equal to eigenvector matrix multiplied by this diagonal matrix.
Or the given any covariance matrix, if we multiply by eigenvector matrix, we produce a diagonal matrix.
Okay, by the definition of the eigenvector and the eigenvalue.
Now, this is very useful because somehow the diagonal matrix, the inverse is very easy, right?
Just inverse each diagonal element.
Then we get the inverse of this diagonal matrix, right?
So from the definition of the eigenvalue, eigenvector, we have this formula, right?
Later, we will utilize this one.
But before that, we will try to summarize this result to visualize the result to see what is the meaning of the covariance matrix.
The covariance matrix, what is the meaning of eigenvector and eigenvalue?
The physical meanings.
Now, suppose we have a two-dimensional data.
We can visualize it.
Each training sample is just one point, right?
The training sample of two-dimensional data has two components, X1 and X2.
So each point is X coordinate, X1 coordinate and X2 coordinate is the two components of a two-dimensional vector.
Okay?
One vector is one point.
This meaning, this point is all of this training data.
Suppose this training data is distributed in this shape because all point is one training sample, right?
Now, if this training data, we utilize this training data to compute this covariance matrix, sigma, then it is a two-by-two matrix, right?
Because it's a two-dimensional data.
Then what is the meaning of this element in this two-by-two matrix?
We have v11, v12, v21 and v22.
Of course, v12 and v21 they are same because it's a symmetry, right?
So what is the meaning of v11 and v22?
In fact, it is pretty clear.
v11 is the variance of the data of the first component, right?
From the definition, it is pretty clear.
So v11 is the variance of all this data, the X1 value.
What is the variance of this data along this horizontal axis?
Right?
This is v11.
Where v22 is the variance of this two-dimensional data, it's second component.
What is the variation along this axis?
So these variants indicate the first component.
How much is the variation?
It is v11.
v22 is the variance along this axis, right?
Now, of course, then v12 and v21 is a covariance matrix.
What is the role of this covariance matrix?
It will determine this shape.
Now, later I will further explain that if we do the eigen decomposition to compute the two-icon vector and two-icon values,
then we can get this covariance matrix is this phi multiplied by this eigenvalue matrix multiplied by phi transpose.
So anyway, you have this one, this expression, right?
Now, from this expression, or we can also make this covariance matrix multiplied by these two eigenvector matrix,
this covariance matrix then produce the eigenvalue matrix because previous slides clearly show this two formula, right?
This just directly comes from the definition of the eigenvector and eigenvalue.
Now, from this one, we can see what is the meaning of the eigenvalue and eigenvector because here,
the covariance matrix is x multiplied by its transpose.
This x is a data matrix, contains all training data, right?
Okay, now, from here we can see it is this one multiplied by this one.
So, here, what is this one?
This one is the project the original data into two eigenvectors, okay?
If we define it as y, then this one is the same as this one.
So, we have y times y transpose.
So, by definition, this is also a covariance matrix of the y, right?
The covariance matrix of the y.
Well, this covariance matrix of the y is a diagonal matrix, right?
So, that we see if we project the two dimensional data into the two eigenvectors,
then we have transformed the two dimensional data into another two dimension.
Then, in this new dimension, this y is covariance matrix, will be a diagonal matrix.
What means a diagonal matrix?
So, diagonal matrix means the two components of this y are uncorrelated.
Okay, so because this correlation is zero.
And this lambda one and lambda two is the variance of the two components of the y.
Right?
We already show that the eigenvalue is the variance of the data along the eigenvector, right?
Okay, so, here, the two eigenvectors is also gone.
Then, given such a visualized example, what is the two eigenvector?
What is the two eigenvalue?
It is a pretty clear if we say this shape of the data distribution, then this must be the two eigenvector,
because along this direction, the data has largest variation, right?
Okay, and along this direction, it is a minimum of variation.
So, this is the two eigenvector.
And then the two eigenvalues is two variants.
One is another eigenvector one, and the other lambda two is the variance of the data along the eigenvector two.
Well, this two dimension is uncorrelated because from the value of the one axis,
we cannot say it is related to the value of the other axis.
Okay, it's different from x1 and x2.
For example, from x1 and x2, right?
If we know that x1 has a larger value, most likely the x2 was also larger.
But in terms of phi1 and phi2, for all different phi1 values, the phi2 is independent.
We cannot predict what is possible phi2.
So here, we understand the geometric meaning of eigenvector and eigenvalue
and corresponding to this mathematical expression.
So, the eigenvector, along that, the data has the extremely variation.
And the different eigenvectors are also going on.
So, if we project the data x into data y, it's just we rotate the axis.
The data structure has no change.
Exactly same.
If we made all training data use x1 and x2, or made all training data use phi1 and phi2,
there's no difference.
The data structure has no change.
But if we use phi1 and phi2, we have nice property.
The covariance matrix is a diagonal matrix.
Each component is uncorrelated.
And the covariance matrix, we have extremely extreme variance,
either maximum variance or minimum variance.
So, this is a nice property of eigenvector and eigenvalue.
So, we have a nice property of eigenvector and eigenvalue.
Okay, so I believe I will stop here.
So, in the remaining part, we will complete next week before the quiz.
Okay, thank you for your attention.
Okay.
This one, this one, this one.
They come from martyacht Mon.
So, this one has been errors, partners former!
This one is...isn't it here?
Is it here?
Is it this one?
It's this one.
There are four of them, right?
We have the first one, the second one, and the other two are under the box.
There are two boxes under the box, right?
The box is not this one.
What's the box?
This is the A1 and the A3.
Because this time-stake is not the BIDET thing, it's the AI.
It's not this one.
It's this one.
It's the AI.
These two turns are the same thing.
Because...
Isn't this the turn?
This is the ETCL, because this is one-vane.
This...this is the ETCL.
Oh, because it's an X.
Yes, one-vane.
Teacher, is it...
For example, after I calculate this,
how do I calculate these two values?
This value is...
In the linear number,
how to calculate a matrix,
its eigenvector and eigenvalue.
This is purely a mathematics problem.
You can solve it in two ways,
depending on the linear algebra.
I'm happy to see that.
Actually, this is the most basic thing in the linear number.
If you know the definition of eigenvector and eigenvalue,
then there must be a way to calculate eigenvector and eigenvalue.
Right?
Yes.
Go ahead.
Okay.