Let's test this.
Looks good.
After several weeks of fighting with CITS, finally they replaced these two document cameras.
Looks good because it's more convenient.
Sometimes you can do some writing, which helps.
Let's finish the lecture of Part 1 first.
I think we should be able to finish it because your assignment is already given, which also
covers two questions from Part 1.
After today, you still have two weeks to do the assignment, which, as I already informed
you earlier, it will contribute to 20% of the overall marks for this 7402.
You have two more weeks to complete, so I think it should be a good time.
As usual, I will try to give a summary of what we learned last week first.
This is from what I taught last year.
Now it's already Week 6.
What we did last week was fine, but if you look at the old summary, now a little bit
of one week delay because, as I said, this year we have many more students.
Usually when you have more students, the students' backgrounds and abilities have a wider range,
so I try to slow down.
Also based on questions asked me, either during the break or after the class or by email,
I know some students told me they did not have a background in this area, particularly
probability and random processes, so I hope by doing the assignment you can learn more.
Try to do it independently and, as I said, do it giving the detailed step.
It's okay if for a certain part you cannot do it, just write whatever you can.
Of course, being an assignment, you do it at home, homework.
Nowadays you can search on some tutorial and so on.
There may not be direct solutions, but you can learn from what you can find.
I don't know, the chat GPT may also have some way, but if you do yours, it's okay, but you
can indicate which questions you use chat GPT to at least provide some partial solutions.
Anyway, that's a learning process.
You will have a quiz to come here, which is like exams, so it's a closed book and you
will be given some simple questions similar to exams.
Also if you look at Assignment 1, the first seven questions are very similar to past year
exam questions, so by doing that you can also learn something.
But the last question, question A, is more like the open-ended.
Later, I hope I have time to cover some basics or some tips about doing the assignment.
As I said, we did go through, learned the two chapters, maybe let's switch back to PC
first.
I already said maximum likelihood estimation is also a very important topic.
Also we did not spend a great amount of time like CILB, because some of the concepts you
can borrow, some of the computation you can learn from.
For example, CILB, there are certain steps that are similar.
You take the first order derivative from this log function, which we call likelihood functions
with respect to theta.
Right now, you also have built up some knowledge about how to handle random variables, how
to differentiate random, which are deterministic among the given functions, and so on.
Let's just summarize what we did for MLE.
For the scalar case, you form this, either using this P, which if you view the theta
X as random, then it will be PDA.
In applying MLE, we will consider that given the fixed X, which could be usually is a vector
of the measure data just put together, and typically we assume they are independent so
that to get PDA, you just multiply each of the data, you have a corresponding PDA together.
After that, you fix this X, consider there's no random, that means it's a realization.
This one you have to get used conceptually in the computation, how to switch from random
to no random, and that's like the learning process.
In the subsequent one, perhaps part two, we will consider some cases where the data are
not really independent of all the measure data.
Usually, you have no problem if you have the Gaussian distribution, because Gaussian
random variables, you can easily cater for the different variables, they have some correlation.
If you look at covariant matrix, they are just in the off-diagonal element, there are
no zeros, so they will be not independent, but you can get the PDA easily.
But for more general random variables, they will be much more difficult, which will not
be covered in this course.
Then as I say, you can either use P, and you can also take a log, because this likely function
is always at least greater or equal to zero, so taking a log or leaving it by itself, give
you the same result.
Very often, we are handling exponential functions such as Gaussian, so taking log will simplify
the derivation.
That's how you get the maximum, and then look at the corresponding argument.
In the scalar case, it will be quite easy.
In case you see several maximum values, among the local maximums, you look at the global
maximum, but in case some of them are the same, you need to verify probably by going
through the result you obtained.
Typically, you may just get one maximum, and sometimes you get two solutions you can also
show, and then as I say, verify.
Here you need to have some regularity conditions, which are not exactly the same as the CLLB,
but somewhat related.
For example, the first one is the existence of the first and second derivative of this.
That will be simpler compared to the CLLB.
CLLB will require that, but also plus, I hope you remember, you take the first derivative,
you need to require the expectation of that equal to zero, but here we don't need that.
Also, again this is related to CLLB, we need to have existence of no zero feature information,
which you already know the CLLB.
In the scalar case, you will just take the inverse being a scalar number, and then in
that case, asymptotically, when you have a large number of samples, or asymptotically
CLLB approaches infinity, because this is any estimate, since you're based on the major
data, it will be a random variable, but it will distribute according to this Gaussian.
In that case, we have the unbiased, because the mean will be equal to the true one, and
then you have a no zero feature information, so this is proper.
You can take the inverse, which gives you the value, so it will be a Gaussian, see this
n is normal, and also the meaning is Gaussian.
In the vector case, the theta becomes a vector, but this log function is still a scalar, you
have to combine all the data together, and then similarly, you will have to follow the
Gaussian distribution, but then this becomes the feature information matrix, and you take
the inverse asymptotically, if you have a large number of major data.
If not, then you may not follow this, you will have to look at the case by case, what
you get based on the derived result.
For example, we get the example last week, and that one, you also see, we require only
when asymptotically you assume n is large enough, then we can simplify the result.
Otherwise, you will have to use the non-linear function of the data to be more accurate.
Then, for linear models, you may notice in the case of linear models, several methods
we have learned so far, they will have very similar forms, for example, blues and least
squares, so they all have these forms, because for linear models, we assume the noise follows
the Gaussian distribution.
In that case, using MLE, for linear models, we don't require data to have a very large
data sample, you can have a finite number of data samples, so we get a result like this.
We also cover least squares.
Least squares, if you look at even the textbooks, I don't know whether you're going to an
interview library, because nowadays students usually do not buy books, very expensive and
bulky, so if you can get the online version,
probably not this book, you can go to the library and then you can see, I asked them
to reserve the book there, so if you go there, you will see they have a lot of discussion
in least squares, particularly if this leads to the adaptive filters, usually adaptive
filter, you start with least squares and then gradually evolve into data, because we
do not really cover too much adaptive signal processing in this course, so we don't go
into much detail, but as I say, towards the end, after conducting, we have a quiz, for
this course, it will be 11, because some student taking my 6401, it will be 12, so
after that, we have some time, I will go through some little bit common filter, which is quite
related to this one, okay?
So least squares, you assume some signal model, but we don't assume the noise here, so it's
quite different from the previous models, and then of course, we will need to measure
data in the scalar case, we use this simple least squares, you sum the error square, and
then after that, you minimize to get so-called optimal solution in this sense, so what you
have is this, you're saying a little bit similar to the MLE, but the criteria is different
here, we directly measure the data, we don't assume the PDF, actually we don't know PDFs
here, and then again, the vector parameter case, we only look at the linear least squares,
so we have this linear model, and then with this restriction, we get similar results again
like the proof, because once you're linear, but the difference here is that we don't need
to assume Gaussian, we just need this linear model, and then you can follow and derive
this result here, and then once you get this, you can substitute and get the corresponding
least squares errors in this form, and you can also extend the weighted least squares,
you minimize by adding this weight, and you'll get very similar one, except you add this
weighting matrix, so here you can assume w equal to i, you will get this result, no weighting
means every sample will have equal importance. Okay, so any questions regarding the
last two chapters for the classical estimation methods before we switch on to the Bayesian
approach, which is more difficult. So last week, we already started with some discussion,
and then I will just continue from, so this is the assignment, not the lecture note,
so this is the Bayesian estimation approach, so here I will assume you're already familiar
with the classical or traditional estimation theory, if not, then really take your time to do
like this, those assignment questions get familiar before you switch on this, because
as you expect, it's getting more difficult, assuming the major data contain some noise as
before, but at the same time, the random variables, the parameters we are going to estimate are also
random, so you must handle these multiple random variables. So with that, the most important
approach, one of the basic foundation here is the Bayesian theory, because now you all know
the data, major data, and the unknown parameter, both are random, so we need to consider,
try to manipulate, making good use of the relationship by using this Bayesian theory,
which relate these two parameters, here we are assuming we have a PDF of either the
prior PDF of the unknown parameter, but that's before you measure the data, and then this is the
conditional PDF, it's the conditional PDF of the major data condition of this data,
assume theta is given, then we have this conditional PDF, or alternatively,
you can write in this form, which is, you have the prior PDF of the data,
collectively, usually more than one data sample, so you need to combine them together, and then
once the data are given, the major data, we try to get this posterior PDF, so this usually
is different from the prior PDF, so you can interpret this prior PDF, we have some general
knowledge of this data, maybe follow the Gaussian distribution or uniform distribution and so on,
but we know very limited, once we have the major data, we can, we have more information,
so we can try to improve our knowledge of this posterior PDF, so that's the basic assumptions
or the relationship we should know, and then we go through some very typical race functions
in order to measure how good the Bayesian estimator is, because depending on the different
race function we are using, you will end up with different estimators,
so in this part, given the limit time, we will cover only two, one is based on this
quadratic error we briefly discussed last week, and then later we will go for this one,
this one is useful, but it's a bit more difficult to divide, so we don't go into that one.
So if you based on the, this is the, again, the very basic assumption for this Bayesian
estimation, if you think about what's mean by random variable or the PDF, it will be easier,
you can think about the distribution is more like you are doing the weighting, because being
random, we need to try to measure, you see, like given the measured data,
cover wide range, so we need to consider all the possible measured data, and then since they are
random, we need to take into account the distribution of this measured data, and
similarly in the case of now, since our unknown parameters are also random variables, so similarly
in order to being random variable, you follow certain distribution, so when you are trying to
minimize the so-called average cost, we want to reduce the cost in the estimation, you have to
integrate, and this condition is kind of weighting, because we don't want to take,
unless of course it's uniform distribution, then that's all the possible value, it will give the
same importance, but in general, for example, Gaussian, we know those data points or those
random variable value near the means will be more important and best reflect in the
in the PDF or in the condition of PDF, so based on that, we can derive, we can have the general
formula, but when you come to more specific, for example, we already discussed by in the
scatter case, and we go by using this quadratic cost function, and you can derive
our Bayesian estimator, in this case, it will be just the posterior PDF of the
theta, and then given the measurement, then we have taken the expectation or the means,
so this looks quite, turns out to be quite simple and useful, and we also try to
give the general discussion on that, and that also highlight the importance of this
Gaussian posterior, you know, PDF, because in this Gaussian case, all these three different
cost function, it end up to be the same, again, the mode, the mean, and the median all give you
the same results, and as we mentioned, one of the importance is to make good use of the
prior knowledge in doing the estimation, so we just went through this example, so this is
somewhat the starting point for you to get familiar how to handle, you know, to
now bring them available, bring the measured data, as well as the unknown parameter, also
bring them, so here I explain a little bit more, because here I want to get the means of the
unknown, here is the PC condition on the X, so by right, if you go back to the,
so this is a good application of the Bayes theory, so what you have is,
maybe now I can make good use of the, I hope this is work, so let's see what we have here.
Okay, if you look at the other side, so if you have a choice,
choice period, if we have two random variables, then if you integrate over one,
one of the variables, D1, so what do I have? Then we get the marginal period of the remaining
remaining random variables, so this is again a little bit difficult, but it's a basic knowledge
in probability, if you are handling two random variables, and that's also agree what I say early,
if you have only one random variable, then you integrate, they will become no longer
random, but in the case we have two or more random variables, you integrate one,
the randomness of Y is gone, because you're taking the so-called mean value, you're averaging out,
so it becomes no random, but however your integration is only with respect to X, you see,
to Y, then X still random, you see, so what you have left here, we call it marginal
period with respect to X, and that's how you're applying here, because if you go back to the
to the Bayesian approach, the denominator here should be the, what do I have here? We integrate
with respect to A, so what I have here, it will be P of X, okay, yeah, so following that,
it's P of X, but then since in this example, we don't have the joy PDF of both X and A,
but based on the given condition, we do have this P of A, given P X of A, given A,
the conditional PDF of X, given A, and then if you go back to our fundamental,
you know, Bayesian Bayes Theorem, you see, we go back to the beginning, you will see here,
so you see here, roughly, if you know two of them, you can get the other two,
ah, okay, because if you get these two of them, when you
multiply together, it will give you the joy PDF, and the joy PDF, you see,
it will be a product of these two, okay, so and, you know, the P X, as I say, you can also
see or integrate this with respect to Y, and the joy PDF, you will be just a product of that,
so therefore, making good use of this relationship and the Bayes Theorem, you see,
we end up with this. Remember, E here is your integrating expectation, you see here,
given X here, now we integrate here with respect to A, because, yeah, okay, so
condition PDF here is already assuming we are given the measure data, so what random is our
A here, and the denominator here is, we are just, you know, we need this P of X, okay, so that's how
what the lab is doing, so our integration with respect to A here, and then in the derivation,
there are some steps which is, you know, like what you need to learn by doing, for example,
assignments, you try to figure out what steps you need to simplify, and similarly, if you're
looking at some of the past year exam paper questions, you will need to do some of the
simplification in the derivation. For example, here, let me explain briefly how we
how we end up with that. So I think this one is not much other than in the previous Bayes,
we are already given the, you know, the PA and also P X given the A here, and then
the only difference between these two is, you see here, you have the A there, and this one,
you don't have the A, and the rest will be the same. So the idea here is we are trying to,
because when you have a summation, you see, you can think about that, where our integration,
our A here is a scalar. So if you have the exponential function of being here,
since you have A raised to the power of two, so it will be a quadratic function, you see, of A.
But then it's causing a problem, because A is inside a summation, so it's not an easier,
simple exponential function, if you look at that. Say, for example, if we have E, say, to the power
of, say, x minus A power of two dx, this is what we are hoping to derive, because
in math, we are doing, when you integrate with respect to this, of course, this one is a typical
example where you don't have the analytic solution, which is the corresponding to the
to the denominator. But however, if you have x here, so that tells you the difference,
the numerator, our A here is A there, since our integration with respect to A is corresponding to
the x here. So if you, in math formula, you can check if you have x, and then this is quadratic,
there is an analytic solution you can integrate, so this one is okay. But if you don't have the
x, you will have a problem. At least there is no analytic solution. Okay, so that's the
number one thing you need to learn. And then, however, here, as I mentioned,
we are not in that form yet, because the A is coupled inside this summation. So what you do
here is you can manipulate by rewriting this into this form. You can verify,
because all these are based on the beta sample, and A appears in a rather special way.
Here you treat A as, at least A is independent of the of the index, so you can verify here.
Somehow we remove the sum, or we still need to sum the data, or sum the, you see, sum the
power of two, each sample, raise the power of two, then you take the average. But then, at least,
our A now is outside this sum. Actually, our A can only appear in this proper quadratic form.
It doesn't matter the data except your sum, because we are treating, you see, remember,
our integration is with respect to A, not with X, so you can treat that just
another number. Similarly, for this part, all these are independent of A. Okay,
so this is a very important way to handle. We somehow remove this.
Therefore, once you may see here why this sum here, you have one term and two term,
because exponential signal, I think this is, again, a very basic property
teaching the undergraduate second year signaling system. I keep emphasizing here some of the
very basic math property you need to learn and remember. I think all of you are now in the master
or PhD level, so you shouldn't have problem. Say, for example, E of A plus B, because they're
very fundamental property, you can make it as a product of E raise the power of A multiplied by E
raise the power of B. So the sum here become a product and vice versa.
That's why we already use, if you start with multiplication, for example, PDF of each data,
then you can combine them into one exponential function by summing that. That's how we already
use. Actually, there was a sum student asked me how you remove the sum, remove the product
become sum, and that's using this property. So that's how, if you go back to here, you see,
so now we have two term here, you see? You have one term, this one become exponential of this term,
exponential of that one. And then you can think about there are two exponential function
multiplied together. And then, so you have to be careful, because one of them like this term,
it's independent of A. So once it's independent of A, you can pull out this E of this whole thing
outside this integration. And similarly, this one is exactly the same as this one.
You pull out that one, you pull out that one, then you cancel out. So what your left is,
E exponential function of this one. This one you cannot pull out, because A is still there.
And similarly for this one. And of course, some students say this constant term you can also pull
out. But we keep it here, because later we're going to see this as like still
related to the PDA functions of like Gaussian, for example. So this is step one, making Google's
use of that, you move down to here. And then what next? If you may wonder now how this numerator
integrate out, you see. And then why we create this sample mean of X here. So again, you
observe the difference between here and here. And then, remember what I say early,
you want to integrate this out. It is possible, because you have the A here, quadratic,
and you have A here. So what you do is, you make this the same here. You subtract
X, this is the sample mean. You minor this, and then plus, of course, you minor something,
you must add the same thing back. And then once you create this A minor X sample mean,
you can integrate this by changing variable. But what happened to the plus sample mean?
So that plus X sample mean, you know the sample mean there, you break it into two terms. And
that term happened to be the same as the denominator. So you don't need to integrate,
you are just putting it out. Because what you have here, now add this to the right.
So you can refer back, A minus plus X. Then this one will be equal to A plus this example mean.
So then you think about this one. You keep this one there, and then what you have is,
because this is independent of A, so you pull this one out. And so what we have is,
because we already combined this A minus here. So what you have is, once you pull out this,
this phi is exactly the same as the denominator. Then you don't need to integrate,
because numerator and denominator are the same. So what you have is this X sample mean plus
whatever left, it will be A minus this. So that explains how we derived this.
And also, after that, the numerator you can integrate. So you remove the integration,
become exponential, and then upper limit, lower limit, and so on. But the denominator,
there's nowhere. As I say, this function, no one has already been approved, no analytic solution
for that. So from here, we can see, if you look at the expression here,
if the number of observation become large, I mean the data sample, the A become large,
the estimate here is largely determined by the sample mean of the data that we have here.
So that means this phi is almost become zero, asymptotically. Mainly because if data become
large, this n will become very big. And then you'll see here, both are minus,
the e to the power of minus, a very big negative number, it will become almost zero.
So that's one observation. And then another thing is, if the prior density becomes
broad. So that means, you see, remember our prior density here is a uniform distribution.
That's what I say here, is you can apply this Bayesian approach to even
the no random unknown parameter by treating that as a very broad, uniform distribution
over all the possible range. Of course, you cannot go to infinity, then the period becomes
zero. So this makes the interval become very large. So that means there is not much information
about this random variable. So that means in this case, the estimate is dominated by the sample mean
also. Again, the meaning of here is, you see, the prior density becomes broad. That means our
A0 here. A0 measure the uniform distribution of the interval. It becomes very large. And you have
the similar implication of the n here. Because if you're a fixed order, this one is a fixed
because we're taking the sample mean. We're not adding the sample. That's why it's very important.
Sample mean is, even if you have very large number of data samples, you take the mean, you'll still
get the finite value. But if you keep adding on the sample without dividing the A, the number
may become very large. So that's the conclusion. I thank you so much for the
previous talk. And then from here, we want to get the posterior PDA is very similar to what we
discussed, except we don't do the integration. So from here, you can also see the relationship
between the posterior PDA and our conditional mean. Because what you do is just take the
expectation of this with respect to A. So without taking the E, then you don't integrate there.
Then the rest is similar. And you still make good use of our derivation early.
So now we move on to the case where it's similar to the previous example, except our prior PDA.
Previously, we used the uniform distribution. Now we make it as like the Gaussian also. But
the mean and variance, we add this capital A to differentiate from the other.
What are we going to do here? You can see here we have the prior PDA, which is Gaussian.
The conditional PDA of the data. The prior PDA is for the mean, the DC value, the DC level.
And this is the conditional PDA of the data, conditional A. So let me assume you give A,
we will have this. So both are Gaussian. And then again, based on the Bayes theorem,
you can see the posterior PDA is proportional to this. Actually, if I write here, you can say
it's equal to, you divide by the P of X. But then
here we are looking at, looking here is a random variable of A. So therefore P of X is
independent of A in something. When we are looking at it as a variable of A, we can just treat P of X
as like a number. So therefore it will be just proportional, like being a scalar in this thing.
Therefore, what we need to see is how we combine these two PDA. Treating that as a random variable
of A here. So again, you look at these two. They are having the same form, exponential signal, but
the A is the same, A is both. Now we treat A as a random variable of A. But the means are
different. This is based on the prior PDA, the mean here, and the value is here. This one, the
means is the data, you measure the data based on the sample mean, while the variance is also
different from here in general. But other than that, they look of the same form, a quadratic
function of A. So that's how we can combine them together. So again, what we use here is
a bit similar to what we did earlier. Actually this is one of the very common techniques you
learn in probably high school. You have a quadratic function, in general it's not perfect.
Perfect squared. Here we treat the quadratic, the variable is A. So how to make it
perfect squared? First, then whenever you combine, you create this quadratic. Then the remaining one
is what's left, the residue. Later we even extend this into the metric form, but it becomes
very difficult, a bit more tricky. But at least in the scalar case, it should be
very easy. At least what you can reverse doing that is, if you're not sure, you'll explain this
and then to see whether this turns out to be the same as here. So again here, you need to combine
this exponent first. It will be the exponential function of, remember what I said, small a,
exponential of small b. You're making an exponential function of a plus b, small a plus
small b. Then starting from small a plus small b, you can verify the argument of the exponent
just equal to that. So once you confirm this is right, then again you can make it like
add this to term here as what I say, because here both of them are second-order quadratic functions
of this a, but we want to combine them into one, and that's what I said earlier. You can
try to combine those coefficients here, because the coefficients are different, so you need to
add these together. So once you fix this, the coefficient of the a squared, what you need to
do is you make good use of the other first-order term, and then usually it may not give you the
perfect square, but you just do the perfect square first, then what left is those are independent of
a, so it will be just constant. So assume you can verify this is correct, then once you get this
done, what your lab, it will be going back to the exponential function. So again this is again like
the small a plus small b, so we take e to the power small a, you get this, and e to the power of
small b, because being a constant, again you treat that as a coefficient, because here
proportional means you are okay with the scalar, which is as long as independent of a,
you see, which a is available here, so you ignore this term. Now once we get this, you can see this
is already Gaussian again, and you have the proper exponential function of this
of this Gaussian period. However, here you get the new mean, this is conditional mean,
you see, so this gives you the a conditional x, the mean, and this one, you have the inverse
step, because our variance should be in the denominator, here is in the numerator, so you
take the inverse, you will give you this, okay, so that's perfectly right, and then we all know for
once you're handling this Gaussian, once you know the means and the variance, you can,
you don't need the right proposal, we can, so the coefficient, we are worrying early,
you don't care, because for Gaussian period, you must, the coefficient must be equal to that,
as long as you know, treat this part independent of the mean, you only need, you only need the
variance, so you can get the result here. Okay, so any questions for this?
So let's see what we have here, yeah, that's what the result we have, so you can, again here,
you can take a look at the simulation, so here we are looking at a is random variable, and then we
make the mean of a is equal to zero, so the one should be zero here, and then we also assume,
in this case, if you treat that as a prime period, the sigma A equal to one,
and then this is the other sigma, the conditional period, you have a larger one, so if you,
now we derive using two prime, one is the uniform, uniform prime, where n equal to 10,
and this is the Gaussian one, so you see here, with Gaussian prime, we get a little bit better
estimate of that, because we have some property about the A is closer to this mean, you see,
where uniform prime, because we will see this is over that interval, but then given some data,
we still have some estimate about this, the A is somewhere more likely to be near zero,
and then now if you increase n, then we get a better estimate, so you see here,
if you have more data, then the prime is less important, because the data give you more
information, so we get a better estimate, so that also illustrates that, and then now if you
change the, this sigma becomes smaller, then you get a better estimate, and then you will see,
because the data is now better quality, so you see now these two are very close,
and when you have more data sample, then the estimate also become much better, very near this.
Okay, so that s how we came here. We continue into the more general case, the Gaussian model,
by extending that into multivariate Gaussian, so as I say, for Gaussian, there is basically
not much difficulty, just a little bit more complicated to extend it from the scalar case to
the higher dimension, such as Gaussian vector, so here, our x and y, we are assuming that as two
random vectors, and they are not even of the same dimension, they can be same dimension of course,
but can be different. So here, let s see how we are handling such a case. This is, we start with
a very general property of the conditional period of multivariate Gaussian first, before we apply
into our estimate problem. So in that case, we can take a mean or expectation of each, you see,
from that as vector, and these are the covariant matrix, so you see from the index, this is x and
x, and then this is y and y, but these are the cross terms, that means there s a cross
covariant x and y, or this is y and x, so depending on which one first,
and then there is a very useful result, this is not what we are going to do, we are making
good use of that, these are well known. Condition of PDA, x condition y is also Gaussian, and then,
because Gaussian, you see, remember, for Gaussian, we only need to know the expectation or mean,
and the value, so we need to, we want to get this PDA, we need to have the expectation of
y, condition of x, and then, assuming we have this to start with, then you can see,
these are related to E of y, which we already have, and then plus, what do we have, E of x,
we already have, and then we also already have this, so this, based on this, we have that,
and then similarly, you can also get C of condition covariant, based on this, get the proof,
so, again, you can use some random variable property and magic manipulation to handle,
I put that in the appendix, which you can go through that, probably by yourself, to
save the time, and that may not be our emphasis in this course. So,
that we want to make good use of that result into our more Bayesian, general linear models here,
so again, this is what we are familiar with, this is linear models, except now to add another,
another condition or difference to what we learned before is, you know, so far in the
early discussion, chapter, always assume this is deterministic, but now this is a random vector
with prime PDA, which is mean of theta and covariant of theta, and the rest, the w is
noise vector, dependent of theta, then with this, and here is not necessarily white, you see,
to tell whether it is white or IID, you look at covariant matrix, so this is CW can be general,
can be, you see, proper, not diagonal
matrix. So, of course, edge here is no random, it's a known matrix relating the parameter to
the data, it just give you some deterministic coefficients here, magic. So, in this case,
because this theta now is random, and then our major data also, because w is random,
so it's also random, so we consider there is a draw it to the Gaussian. So then, remember what we
have here, you can, based on the model, you can derive E of X, because E is a linear operation,
so therefore it doesn't matter, you can just see there is two random variables added together, so
E of this two random variables, you can put in, you can equal to E of this and plus E of w,
but our E of w is zero, so you only keep this one, and then edge is not random, you take it out,
you don't need to apply the E to edge, so what your lab, here is E of theta, then we already know
this is equal to, so we get one of this, similarly Ey is already, Y is this, so you can really get
there, and then for the XX, you see, here, so you substitute this model inside, then you will see
the covariant of XX, your nth order is related to both C of theta and this, you see, so one common
mistake is some students, this is in the past, I hope it's not among the new class here, so we have
more students here, you see our w is zero mean, but the value is not zero, because if you have
zero value for random variables, that means this is no longer a random variable, a random variable
must have no zero value, so therefore, when you are handling this, because this is your product,
again think about you are measuring the variance or covariant in the metric case, so nth order is
C of w, so this is not zero, also E of w is zero, so therefore you have this extra term here,
and how about Y and X, so you have to be careful, you are doing the cross-pollination,
so for Y, since we are measuring C, you use E, you have to subtract the expectation or the mean of
Y and X respectively, so this is after removing the mean, you get this Y here,
multiply X similarly, you remove that, but you need to take the transfer of this one,
like the outer product, so therefore you end up with C of theta and H, because in that case,
the one related to the noise W here, because when you apply the X there, you still have one W,
but since we only have one W here, you will be manipulating of E, W, so don't get this,
if you have W and then outer product of W, you will get the covariant matching,
but if only one W, it will be similar to this E, W, you will have zero, so you only have part
of this, but not this one, so therefore once you get this, you can already get the result,
because we know you have the conditional multi-Gaussian given the posterior, because
both of them are Gaussian, so you end up with also Gaussian, so that's very useful, and since we
already know this expectation, you substitute in using our, remember the previous formula for the
general Gaussian, and then similarly we can get the conditional covariant based on this formula,
and the result we derived, so basically what you do is you apply this formula, but you need to get
all those E of X, E of Y, and also C of Y X first, so once you get, then you use this formula to find,
so finally this is what you get, and yeah,
okay, maybe, yeah, we'll take a break, then we should be able to finish the remaining part.
This posterior estimate, or maximum of the posterior estimation, we call it MAP, which is
another equally important one, which is quite often easier to handle, so we'll take a break
here, come back to resume at 8 pm, okay, I'll see you later.
Thank you.
Let's find this one, see how it goes.
This is a special case for this.
Okay, so I think both of them work.
I think we can continue the lectures, so I hope I finish.
Let's continue with another equally important Bayesian estimation method, which is what
they call maximum A posterior estimation.
Remember the early estimate, we are using the quadratic, the conditional mean, where
this one we use another one, where key or miss calls function.
You can see this is a very simple cost function and the definition is also very easy to understand.
The basic idea here is if the estimate one and the true one is very small, we think this
interval, assume here our delta is small, then we will consider the cost is zero, so
that means just treating that as no error.
But once you are beyond that interval, we will treat them also equally, all being one,
so it's one or zero.
So with this, let's look at the conditional cost function, again based on the given data,
and we try to measure this cost function using this formula, and then our integration is
with respect to this theta, because theta now is a random variable.
So the integration here, again we start with the scalar parameter, so by right it should
be minor infinity to infinity, over this whole interval, we are assuming this theta being
real.
Then what we have here is, so if you plug in this cost function, because when you substitute
this, it's all equal to one except this going through this interval, from minus delta to
delta.
So therefore in this part it's equal to zero, so we have to skip this interval, but remember
this is with respect to theta hat minus theta, and our integration is with theta only, so
you have to do a little bit of change of variable, so it will become theta hat minus delta, and
this is theta hat plus delta, so basically you are just adding this theta hat into that.
And then weapon, because we know the property, if any, even the conditional PDF with respect
to, we integrate over this theta, from all the way from minor infinity to infinity, it
will become one, that's what we already know before, very fundamental result.
So the idea here is we are adding up this gap, remember this is similar to what our
example earlier, we want to create this minus sample being of X, so your subtract, you have
to add in.
Similarly here, we have a gap in between here, assume we add this from delta hat minus delta
up to, sorry, theta hat plus delta, integrate from this conditional PDF with respect to
this theta, then it will become one since you integrate from minor infinity to infinity,
but since initially we don't have this part, you add this one, then you have to subtract,
so therefore it will become one, because now you integrate after filling up the gap,
you get one, but you have to subtract this what you are adding here, so remember this
is the result if you are able to add this one into that, so this is what we have.
So now let's look at this more closely.
Remember we assume our delta is a small one, otherwise your arrows will be, so here means
is assuming we allow the very small delta in this case, so therefore we all know from
what you have learned in the higher math, the calculus, that's a very basic idea about
integration.
If you are integrating, unless the function is very special like impulse, then you are
no longer, this is no longer work for a normal function, which is continuous, so you will
see over small interval, then you can treat that as almost like a constant, so therefore
in a constant, typically we take the value in the middle of this interval, and of course
in this case the interval of this function is when theta equal to theta hat, since we
don't have the knowledge of the true theta, but we can estimate this as theta hat.
Therefore we approximate this integration over this small interval as just take this
value, evaluate theta hat, because it's still a conditional period at this value, conditional
x, and then the interval is two delta.
So therefore we want to maximize this, because you see if you look at this, we want to minimize
this, minimize this, but this is a constant, and one minus this, so to minimize this means
you maximize this, because this is a minus, so therefore to maximize this, see this delta
is a given one, it's a constant, so therefore we will just maximize this conditional period.
Look at the conditional period as a function of theta, then get the very similar to the
MLE, you can see here is MAP, maximum A posterior is relative version, comparing to the MLE,
so you maximize this, get the function value, and looking down at the corresponding argument,
the argument is what we are interested in is not at this function value, but at the
corresponding argument, so it's the argument of maximum this.
So therefore what we have is the MLE, because you look at the location of the maximum, that's
how you define the MODE, rather than means or the median, there are three in statistics,
you can define three different mean values, mode and median.
So therefore here, since we have maximized this, we call this estimate as maximum A posterior,
or in short, you take the first capital letter, it's MAP, max.
So that's how you get this.
And then again, we refer back to the Bayes' Theorem, you see, if you all explain this,
this one is, you see, it will be a product, and then if you multiply P of X, it will give
you the relationship, but since we are interested in maximizing the value with respect to the
theta, so we can treat this P of X as independent of theta.
Anyway, that's a prior PDF of the data, so we don't look into that.
But on the other hand, the product of these two, they're all function of theta, so you
need to multiply together as a product to maximize.
Or again, you can take a look, because this is a product, and typically they may be exponential
functions, so easier you take a look, it will be the look of this, plus, once you take
a look, product becomes summation.
So you can do that also.
And for the case of vector or parameter, you do it similarly, except you may have several,
you see, like the unknown parameter, and then you need to look at each of the, it will become
a bit more complicated.
In the case, for example, you have two variables, you will be looking at the plane rather than
one D curve, and so on.
But remember here, if you have vector-parameter, our condition PDF here is still a scalar,
we're not treating that as a vector.
And then, as I mentioned earlier, this map is very much related to our MLP, and the formula
also looks similar, except we're in the prior PDF, and of course this is also different
from the previous one.
Previously, theta is a deterministic parameter, it's not a random variable, and it's not a
conditional PDF, but the form looks similar.
And then, of course, you also need to add this prior PDF.
So let's look at the example, and you will see this, some of this easier, this comparing
to the conditional means.
So let's look at this example, exponential PDF.
Here our condition of the data, now you always need to be careful, because you have to check
whether it's data condition on theta or theta condition on the data.
So assume this is given, our data sample condition on theta.
So this is a typical exponential PDF.
And then, you see here, theta is the random variable, we'll be cheating.
But if you fix that, there's no random here.
So that will be, if you look at the PDF of this, it will be a lambda, you see?
And then the data itself, we treat it as conditional IID.
So you have to be careful by, you see, this is a conditional PDF, I mean, this is each
data sample you have, n is the index, you have first sample, n equal to zero, n equal
to one, and so on.
So in total, you can have, say, typical n.
And then, all these are each of the measured data, we treat them as conditionally PDF,
IID.
So that means we can simply multiply this conditional PDF as a product, since IID.
And then after that, we also have another condition, which is the prior PDF is given
by that.
This is quite similar to what we just discussed, except this one is a prior PDF, so we don't
involve data.
Our theta here, this is, again, exponential PDF.
And then, when theta is smaller or equal to zero, it will become zero.
You only take the non-negative theta, you have no zero value.
So therefore, based on our, we are using log, because most of them are exponential.
So we take a log, and this is, again, one common mistake, you see, for theta, there
will be capital N of them multiplied together.
So you have the sum of this N, also theta N here.
But however, for prior PDF, it's independent of data, so you don't have the N here.
Quite often, I see, either forget the N here, or add N here, capital N here.
So to be careful, I emphasize this again.
These are involving the data, if you have capital N sample, you have this as a function
of N.
On the other hand, if you're looking at the prior PDF, this is only one term here, no N here.
So once we get this correctly done, then taking log, there is not much problem, it will be,
you know, become a function of this.
This part, you see, you have three days of product.
So this first element, you take log, since there is no exponential here, you take log
theta, and the exponent, you can become a product.
This one is easy, you already know how to do it.
And finally, this one is the same, you treat this log of lambda, and then the other one.
So now, next, here is a scalar change.
So take first derivative with respect to theta, you are just looking at each of them,
so you end up with, this is constant, so this one, theta, this is also a function of theta,
this is function of theta.
So you end up with three terms, where this one, these are all linear, so you end up with
coefficient here.
Now this is not n yet, a big similar to MLE, you let this equal to zero, you want to get
the maximum value, let this equal to zero, and then solve it, it's very easy, we only
have one theta here, so this is what our theta hat equal to that.
So that's not difficult to solve.
And then you can see here, if n goes to infinity, then the distance will become zero.
Or on the other hand, if lambda becomes very small, or close to zero, so you will have
one over the sample mean.
So this is, in that special case, depends only on the sample means of the theta.
So that's how you get it.
Any problem before we continue in this?
So now let's look at another one, an example.
This is DC level in white Gaussian noise with uniform flight period.
Now let's see if we use a MEC approach, it will become very easy, we don't actually need
to even do any calculations, because this is, let's go back to our assumption where
this flight period hat of A is, take uniform distribution from minor A-G load to A-G load.
And then we have our posterior PDA, assume give the data.
So this is a Gaussian, we already know it's a Gaussian distribution.
So there are only three cases we fixed this interval, from minor A-G load to A-G load,
that's how this is given.
So now we draw this posterior PDA being Gaussian.
So for Gaussian we all know the shape is a bell curve, that's how sometimes we say
or we make the exam mark, follow this bell curve distribution if possible.
So there are three situations, if the sample mean, which of course you can always calculate
once you get the data, you can get the sample mean.
And then you look at this, sample mean is just in the PDA it will be the peak with respect
to A. If the sample mean happens to be right within this interval, minor A-G load to A-G
load, then looking at this function, the maximum value of course will be at this peak, which
is sample mean.
So you see here, this is the first condition, and of course the sample mean could be outside.
Outside this interval there will be two situations, either very big, which is larger than A-G
load, because here is A-G load, here, so you see here, if outside, A-G load.
Then of course this bell curve, what we get, the condition of it is only this, this region.
Then you all know from this shape the maximum value is at this edge, so our A hat, we just
use this edge value, because that's the maximum value within this interval.
So you see, if the peak is too small on the left-hand side of this minor A-G load here,
then you get the maximum value at this edge, minus A-G load.
So here we don't need even to do any calculation by just getting the sample mean and then draw
the curve, and then just see where it is.
Sometimes you will see some method, if you know the property of PDF, and then you can
get easy solutions out of this.
Any questions?
No?
I think I will skip this appendix, condition on Gaussian test.
The basic idea is very similar to what we did for the second-order quadratic.
So this is a magic case, so you will be trying to completing the square, but in terms of
the magic manipulation, you can try to work out by yourself.
Anyway, this part, we will leave it not for exams for the appendix.
So in general, unless I specifically require some, I will add the requirement later when
I give the scope for exams.
So let's move on to the final chapter, which you can think about, it will be the extension
of the proof.
So this Bayesian approach, we are talking two methods.
One is MMSE, minimum mean square estimator, which is based on the quadratic function,
and the other one is MAP, which we just discussed.
These two, you either require multi-dimensional integration, MMSE, remember the formula, the
example is a simple one, but in general, you are naming data, you have to integrate, it's
not easy, and the MAP, again, if you are involving vector parameters, it may not be
as simple as what we did just now.
You need to do multi-dimensional optimization, and sometimes often it may end up with a non-linear
one.
Based on that, we will try to see whether we can get some sub-optimal one, and then
it will be easier to derive.
Of course, you know what we learned before, it's easy to do and easy to derive, but in
general, limiting it into a linear, so you have some restriction, so you have pros and
cons.
Anyway, so you see here, we are limiting the linear Bayesian estimator, so this is more
manageable, and it provides another alternative, probably sub-optimal solution to this problem.
Let's see what we can do here.
As usual, we start from the scalar parameter, which ends up to be relatively easy in this
case, so look at the data, it's similar before, but the main difference here is the bias,
so you see here, you compare to the blue, there we are assuming no bias, so we don't
have here, so here, we try to make it more general, so that's the main difference.
Another difference is our Bayesian MSE is given by this, so remember here, we try to
minimize the difference between the estimate and the Jua, but since this is random, we
use the expectation of this.
Then here, we have both theta and the theta, they are all random, so we need to, the expectation
is with respect to the Jua PDP of this.
So therefore, once we minimize this, and since we are limiting it into linear form, we add
this special name linear minimum mean squared error, so it's LMMSE for this.
In order to do that, I think the scale case is relatively easy, so what we do is, in terms
of optimization, it's almost the same, similar to before, except, of course, you see here
our coefficient is, we need a and b, and also this a, there will be a coefficient,
so these are the deterministic coefficients.
First look at the derivative with respect to b, because it's quite easy quadratic, and
b is here, so what you do, just take the two off, and the coefficient here is one.
But then, remember, you have to keep the expectation here, so to make that equal to zero, you can
solve b, which is equal to that, and then remember our theta now is also random, so
you have to take expectation of theta not equal to theta, and then once you get this
b, you substitute back, you will get theta a minus theta equal to that, and then you
can write that as a vector case, as an inner product of this, and then now put it back,
we still need to get the expectation of this, and because this is quadratic, you can expand
that into four terms, and the cross term here, because in, also theta is a scalar, because
our theta sample is a vector, so you will see this cross term here, c x theta, and c
theta x, there will be, at least the dimension will be different, one is column vector, one
is the row vector, but however they are related by just taking the transform, you see, so
in the end, you end up with c x x, this is for theta, c theta theta, that's for the unknown
scalar parameter, and then finally the cross quadratic one, okay, so therefore now, since
we already get the so-called optimised b, now we need to do, again, take the derivative,
but in terms of vector, which respect this coefficient vector of a, and again, you use
the matrix derivative formula, you will see here, you can simplify to get this, so this
is similar to the scalar quadratic function, because this is second order of a, then once
you take, and this is symmetry, you will have two coefficients a, reduce one order, and
for this one, you make good use of this relationship, you will end up with, you take first derivative,
and a is gone, what you have is this coefficient here, so make this equal to zero, then you
will solve it, and in general, we assume the theta, your measure are independent, so the
matrix here is invertible, so we get this, so finally, once you get a and b, you put
it back, we will get this, okay, so this is what our optimal one, in terms of the linear
estimator in the patients, okay, and what about this minimum patient mean square error
here, which is equal to that, you can substitute these two values, putting back, you get this,
so you can see here, the result end up to be the same as we are having this MMSE, we
did that earlier, following this, so you see the result we get, except of course, here,
we actually, we, since we assume the estimator is linear, we don't need to assume the Gaussian,
so far, we are only having the, we need the expectation of theta h, ah, theta and theta
x, and the covariance, okay, so, yeah, so let's look at some example, DC level in white
Gaussian noise, uniform price, which, ah, now we will put the theta into this form,
so you can see here, this is linear, and then our a is uniformly distributed in this interval,
okay, we don't require Gaussian, see, so a is not Gaussian, and then the w here is a
white Gaussian noise, which is valid, and then also a and w are independent, so you
can see this e of x equal to zero, because, so here, don't get confused, you know, previously,
we always say e of a is a DC value, usually we assume it's not equal to zero, a is not
zero constant, but here, our a is uniformly distributed in this interval, so e of a here
is also zero, okay, so you see here, and then you can also verify c x s equal to that, it's
a outer product, you will see it here, and then the cross correlation is equal to that,
and therefore, based on what we already had put into the formula, you get this, and then
you substitute this inside, you will get this, so here, we use a very useful matrix inversion
formula, which, yeah, which you see here, I will give you the, or you can check the
formula by yourself also, by internet, or later on, I can, yeah, there will be a matrix
inversion formula, probably in the part two, you will see, you will have to remove the
inverse, usually it's not easy, it will require some condition, but in this case, since the
matrix involved, quite simple, you can invert that into this, and then, further than that,
you observe this is scalar, and all those are very simple vector or matrix, you see,
one, this means all the elements equal to one, and similarly, this is diagonal element, identity
matrix, so you can simplify that into, finally, a very simple form, which is the sample mean,
plus the scalar, yeah, okay, and a, the value of a is equal to this, that's a well-known
formula, and then in this case, you can see, we get the closed form for this estimate,
seeing this is closed form, but this is only suboptimal, because you know the optimal one,
we got last time, is, there is no analytic solution, one is optimal, because here,
we constrain it to be linear, so what you get is not optimal, but close to the optimal one.
Any questions before we move on to the matrix case, vector parameter case? This one is a little
bit more involved, but if you have a good understanding of the proof, then a little
bit of, you know, the probability and matrix operations should be not too difficult.
Okay, so what we do here is, let's go through that, is the model is the same, you see, we,
actually here, we do not assume the model, we are assuming the estimator to be the linear form,
so don't get confused. At least, for now, we are assuming, you see, it's a linear estimator,
so it's linearly depends on the given data, A of X. Again, we add this so-called bias term,
like, for example, all those of you who are knowing neural networks, you can add a bias
term or without bias term. Usually, having this term is better, at least, if you make it equal
to zero, you reduce to the non-constant term. So, therefore, assume we have this, similar to the
scale case, we can get the errors between the true one and the estimate one here, go to that,
and then the Bayesian mean square errors, to be careful here, this part is a little
bit of matrix manipulation. We, well, now, this is a vector, so we are, this one is an
inner product, so it will be a scalar, you see here, so you substitute this inside, and then
you just explain it, you will get this quadratic form and so on. Now, if we take this with respect
to P, which is here, is also a vector, then it's not an issue here, because our P only appears in
here, this is second order, but there is no data involved here, it's very easy. And this one,
this one is independent of P, so it becomes zero, so what do we have here? It's also easy,
because this is the P transfer, the row vector P is separate, so very easy. And then, to minimize,
of course, this equals zero, we solve, get this, and then, like before, we substitute this, what
we get here, putting back this, and then this, after getting this P, we end up with that. So,
so far, so good, I think there's not much difficulty here, but the subsequent one is a
little bit more difficult. We need to borrow this, you see our idea here, we want to minimize this
inner product at a scalar, as before, because when we talk about arrows, it will become reducing
into a scalar. But, however, if we directly manipulate day one, it will be difficult,
because, yeah, I don't go into the detail here, but you can try to, try to write, A will be
somehow mixed in the middle, so, okay. So, therefore, what we do here is following this
BMAC covariant matrix, we get the outer product, because, you see here, the difference, this is
inner product, it will be a scalar, okay, and then this is a big matrix, outer product, you have
a vector, inner product, I mentioned this several times. So, let's look at outer product, it will
be this vector, multiply by this vector, and then when you explain, it will become the, all these
term matrix, it will be a square matrix, okay. And then what, we want to minimize the inner
product, but if you directly minimize day one using the inner product formula, you have difficulty
to get the derivative, so I tried that myself. So now, how are we going to solve the problem?
We know this outer product, but then how are we going to, eventually we want to minimize this
scalar, and then there is a very useful property, you see, scalar, of course, scalar, you take
trace, you know the meaning, let me see whether I define here, trace, trace, the meaning of TR is
trace, T-R-C-E, trace of a square matrix, you just sum the diagonal element, yeah, yeah, diagonal
element, A-1-1, A-2-2, A, again, again. And then, being a scalar, now I have this form to write,
so I, in the past few weeks we have a problem with this, so now, let's see, okay, you can see the
other side, yeah. So, being a scalar, of course, you know, trace of that is equal to A, since the
matrix has only one element, but if you have a proper n-by-n, n-by-n matrix, you see, and then
the diagonal is not necessarily equal to zero, you can get other values, but we don't care, so the
trace of this is just equal to the sum of this A-i-i, from i equal to 1 to n, okay, so I hope you
can see that clearly. And then there is a very useful property, you know, in general, A multiplied
by B is not equal to B multiplied by A. So here, I'm not taking the chance for, I just say the two
matrix A first, multiplied by B is different, but surprisingly, if you take the trace, yeah, it's
equal to trace of B and A, and it always works, even if the products are different, and then even
these products, they are of different dimensions, okay, for example, in our case here, where one is
a scalar, the other is a big matrix, totally, yeah, they are different dimensions, but for the trace,
they are the same, yeah, okay. So therefore, let's go back to look at this trace. So you see here,
in the product, remember this is, if I call this vector as A, this is B, so this is just B multiplied
by A, we are not talking about the chance for Z3, that is the new matrix, vector is a special
case of matrix, okay. So therefore, you see, we make good use of the property, you see. I repeat
again, a scalar, except it's a trace of this, okay, and then trace, you can swap these two,
then it's also equal to trace of this one, outer product, vector first, followed by row, yeah, and
E and trace is a linear operator, so you can, E is a linear operator, you can swap these, trace
also linear, you are summing up the diagonal term, so you swap these two operators, then you
become to the E of this first, followed by trace, and E of this, we already know, you see, this is
derivation, it's equal to matrix, big matrix of M. So therefore, we end up with putting all these
in, but yeah, actually these two, you can, these two are different, but once you take the trace,
they will become the same, you combine these two, you end up with this, okay. So yeah, therefore,
we end up with our BMSE is equal to trace of that. So the reason of having trace is very useful,
because for trace, there is a property you can take the derivative even with respect to a matrix,
okay, the matrix of A. So again, you have a formula which take the derivative with A and
that was equal to that, because this is independent of A, so what you have is, again, very similar to
the quadratic, because you have quadratic reduced to the linear of A, then this becomes constant,
and then make it zero, equal to zero, you get A, go to that, or that one. So where do we,
which formula we are using? This is the one here. Again, you can look at the matchbook trace of
this, it will be in general, will be equal to this, this, this two term, but if B is symmetry,
which is in our case here, then you can combine, because A, we have A, 2AB, and similarly,
if you have this, A and B, this is, you have A and A transfer on left and right side, this is only
one, so like this. So once I get this result, we put in the theta hat equal to that, and then
our m equal to that. So therefore, our B and AC here, the minimum one, you will be just taking
the diagonal element of this. So this is, the difficulty here is you are following the metric
in the product transfer to the outer, then we take the trace. And also, here we are getting the
linear MMAC, but you can extend to higher order, because so far, we will assume the linear
estimator, but you can extend it at least one, the quadratic one. And that's why the assignment,
you see, assignment question is quadratic, so that means you need to think about how to add
second order term, and then our assignment will be based only on one sample data. So you have,
typically in this course, actually the same as next, part two, we can get one major data sample,
this one, or sometimes we are having two, or in general, either one or two, or eight, so you need
to look at the given question carefully, depending on which. So although, of course, you have more
data, you can get better results in general, but having just one sample, you can also do something
particularly when you involve this randomness. So here I give you the hint for this.
Finally, we again extend this case into the general linear model, because what we have been
discussing is a linear estimator, but you can apply to non-linear model, but in the case of,
you have the linear model case, and then we also need to make some assumption. Both are random,
but they are uncollinearity. Then we also assume the estimator of this linear form,
so what we can derive here is quite similar to what we discussed previously using the
Cauchy Gaussian, but except here we don't really assume Gaussian, but we assume the linear form.
So what we get here is this expression based on what we discussed earlier, but now we can
specifically work out the E of X, go to that, see the covariance of the data based on this model,
get further, and cross covariance matrix, then theta and X is equal to that, and so on.
Then we substitute back, and then after some algebraic manipulation, we finally get this
theta hat equal to this form, M equal to that. Or, if you are making Googles, this M matrix is
just what this inverse, you get a simpler form of that. So therefore, comparing back, you see this
is what we tried to get easier solution for this MMSE, but in general, this is non-linear form,
but if this is non-linear, it's similar to what I have proved here, so this is what we are getting,
it's very similar to our proof. It will not be optimal unless this is, at the MMSE, happens to
be linear, then of course you get the best among the linear estimators, it will be optimal.
But however, this estimator is practically useful, because it has a closed form expression,
because in general, you may not get a closed form, you may need to do it numerically, and also it
only depends on the means and the covariance of the theta and W. So in a sense, it's easier to get
these requiring second-order statistics only, and our derivation is based on some simple
derivatives. I think that's more or less finished all the part one, which took like six weeks
previously, I repeat that in about five weeks, so I hope it will help you.
Any questions before I add in some additional explanation of previous lecture notes,
and also briefly talk about assignments, because some of you asked me about that.
So let's first try to look at the MLE, because that part involves quite some useful derivation,
which I was not sure whether this works, so I did a little bit of hand calculation previously.
So let's look at how this is done. First, I think this part, to get the CLB,
is under regularity condition. Here I refer back to the MLE example. First,
we're going to take the first derivative with respect to A. As I already mentioned,
we have three terms here, so you need to take derivative with respect to each,
and then you see here, you explain this. See, this is quadratic, this is first-order,
and last one, you involve A. I make the same denominator, because if A is not zero,
you can ignore, because we are making it equal to zero, so we look only at the numerator.
So therefore, it happens to be this one, this term is the same, so you cancel out this term,
and so therefore, you think that is, you see here, quadratic, and then this A square constant,
and similarly, you have the two A here, so you have the minus A, so when you sum this,
this A is, you're summing up, capital A sample of this constant, and finally, you have this.
Therefore, you can, you see, multiply all of them with minus one over n. Yeah,
because we, let's see, yeah, we want to make it as quadratic function of this A, so yeah,
so yeah, actually, there is no need to minus sign, but yeah, let's see, it doesn't, yeah,
we have the minus sign, where these two combine, you will have minus n, this n, this, so I got,
I forgot this term. Therefore, your n double is second order quadratic function of A, and then
you need to solve this, so everyone know how to do that, and that's why in the lecture note,
so that I gave you the derivation for that. So this, this one is the, another one is,
you see, remember, we have the term inside the square root, we want to see, work out how E of
that n double is, and then your E is a linear operator, you're putting this in, and this is
constant, so, but this is random, so we have this, and at this point, I want to highlight the very
important relationship, and that one, if you need that, they will not give you this relationship,
this, this equation, so any random variable, you can call it simple, just call x power two,
x is random variable, then there is always, you know, you are evolving this second moment,
we call that second moment, it will be, I already mentioned before, it will be E of this raised
power of two, the mean raised power of two, plus the value of this, okay, so remember this is
random variable raised power of two, but this is E of x, not, not power of two yet, then power of
two of this, plus value of this, okay, so that's, since we already know E of x equal to a, and then
your raised power of two, a squared, the value of x in this example happened to be equal to a,
you see, don't have a squared here, it's sigma power of two, but in our case here, it happened
to be equal to a, so you think that was there, and then plus this, and your, this is constant,
your sum n of that, then we become n multiplied by that, and cancel out this a, your, this part
equal to that, and then this is constant, so this happened to be equal to a perfect square with
respect to a, plus this, so that's, that's explained the other derivation, and then we now
come into this, this is the one here, okay, so you see here, this is the E of, zero is the one we
fixed at the E of, you know, the x power of two plus the random variable squared, and then sum,
then divide by n, so, so that's the one here, and then, you see, you see, if u is a function,
you will not have the zero, but u is a fixed point here, then we already derive u zero equal to that,
so you substitute, so therefore, this is n w is equal to a, so how are we going to handle the,
other, you know, using the Taylor expansion, d of g is a function of u, your n w state,
it will be, yeah, so that's, that's very easy, so therefore, you can simplify that into,
into this form, so therefore, you get, putting in into the lecture note, you will get intermediate,
intermediate step, so now the little bit more difficult part is, we want to evaluate the
value of this, okay, so be careful here, our estimate of variance, so by definition,
value being, you see, you need to subtract the E of this, you see, then our A hat minus expectation,
then take, raise the power of two, then take the expectation, so therefore, here,
let's see, what do we have here, so you see here, if you go back to, maybe, let's see,
okay, let's look at the lecture note, lecture note again, you see, if you go back to the MLE
part, let's see, where do we have here, yeah, okay, so you see here, you see our AMLE is equal
to the, to the whole thing here, you see, and then we already know it by, we approximate using this
one, E of this whole thing is equal to A, because this part will cancel out, okay, so, and then now,
E of this whole thing equal to A, and then our A hat subtract the expectation of this,
so that means you are removing this A, so what you have is this, you see, the remaining term,
and that's how we continue back here, you see, so this whole thing here, what, let me repeat again,
what inside after removing that happened to be the one without A, you see, because we already
removed A, and then now, if you look this carefully here, you see, E of, this is a constant, you see,
I can take this one out, but remember, if you take the constant out, you have to, sorry, this is
inside the, inside the square root, you see, okay, so this, you have to square it first, so the negative
one become, become positive, and power two, and out of that, you can, this E is the linear operator
after you take this outside, outside the square root, so you can take this out with, with the square,
so what let here is E of, you know, this whole thing again, raise the power of two, so, so you
can reconsider that as another variable, you see, I call this as random variable, so this is a
random variable, yeah, then this random variable, the expectation happened to be equal to A plus A,
A squared, as we already, already derived earlier, so therefore, you can see, let me see, so, so this
inside one, you see, you treat that as a random variable, so what we have is, we are, we are
interpreting that as a variant of this, okay, the definition of variant of this is E of this
random variable, subtract the E of this, and we already know E of this, because A plus A squared,
so that's become the derivation much easier, because now we are evaluating the variant of this,
and then, since we know the data sample, the IID, then we can bring in the variant, this is a
constant, you, you take this out, it will become power two, one over N squared, and then, since
the data IID, you can take each of the variant independently, so finally, how are we going to
evaluate this variant, this is a random variable raised to power two, so, again, I didn't see this,
we are not defining it, so, so how to, how to do that, because,
in general, it may be quite difficult, but in our case here, we are dealing with Gaussian,
so if you go back to the Gaussian one, you can have this, you can use this, okay, so this is
how you will be, you will be using two, you see, sorry, actually, yeah, we are, let me, let me
explain this into some writing here, so, so we want to, we want to evaluate this, you know,
variant of, okay, we are looking at, yeah, this is from the project, so this is, okay, so let's see
what, a bit strange here, a bit slow, never mind, ah, you see here, if you are treating that as
variant, I call this x squared as y, okay, then, ah, variant of y is equal to E of y squared plus
E of y power 2, alright, so this is the relationship we always, you see, if you take E of this,
then it will be variant minus that, so remember, in general, the, let's see, no, this one, this one
should be, should be minor, alright, because, ah, because, ah, variant is smaller than in general,
then the same random variable raise power of 2, because we already removed the mean, okay, ah, so
therefore you treat that as, as y squared is y, so, so, so we want to get this variant, it will be
something like that, variant of x squared, you will end up with E, you see, y, y is equal to x
power 2, then you'll become x power 4, so force moment, then minus E of this, we already know x
squared, power of 2, okay, so, so you'll reduce the variant of this x power 2, which we need to
evaluate into the force moment and the second moment of power of 2, and that one is for, for
Gaussian, you already have the formula there, you see, second order, it will be the variant plus sigma
squared plus m power 2, and the fourth one, you, it also depends on, because Gaussian, you only need
to know the variant and the mean, so, so you yield this formula, and then there is some simplification,
you can try to do that, because this is Gaussian, then we know the mean and variance, and that was
equal to that, and after that, you'll cancel out, you'll get, you'll get the result, because this is
summing up all these constants, now, you can end, you can sort out, end. Okay, so I think that was
the additional one, I think this is quite useful, it summarises all the ones here, so let me finally
just mention briefly about the assignment, so I, yeah, well, I give you three weeks, I get last
Wednesday, then you have three weeks up to the Wednesday of the recess week, which is 2nd of
October, so yeah, also remember, you don't try to sum it every time, you get until you're almost
ready, so you, so you try to attend, usually, once you're ready, you'll get, in case you make
mistake, you'll sum it another one, so that's, typically, we're doing that, so, as I say, try to
do it independently, and then, if you yield creativity, it's okay, but you'll indicate how much
you're using, so, so I think the, most of the assignment is quite clear from the question,
this one, question two is, I will say, this one is a crying ball, so you'll try to,
try to get the step, this is easier, and you want to, I want to compare the computational
log between these two, okay, and then this is not much blue, and you, where this is a
sub, you use the submatrix, very, each other identical, so that's not difficult, this one,
yeah, MLE, but you have two, two unknowns, so you try to solve it, this is linear, so it shouldn't
be a problem, discuss, what happens if this, yeah, if she don't go to G law, and so on, and find,
yeah, this question is, what I say is, your, I have only one single data sample, but you
extend it to the quadratic case, quadratic, so, previously, we discussed linear, so you now,
add this, then you try to figure out how to derive this, and, and this is,
crazy MAP, very similar to the example, and finally, this question eight, I have three
sub-questions, so depending on, usually this, this second one everyone can do, so I will assume
it's, you implement some, I don't, you can do one or two, or so on, you use, maybe, or use
pythons, and nowadays, okay, but make your results more, you know, at least clear, give some figures,
and so on, and then this one, if you have some, do some research related to that, you can,
you can describe all, if not, then at least you can read the research paper, which I don't expect
you to understand the whole paper in detail, but you try to see how much you understand,
in particular, there are some part related to the, to this course, like parameter estimation,
then at least you can, yeah, but don't do, I mean, of course, you can do three, but I will only
give credit to two of them, the last question, probably I give your, your better component,
so, but okay, you just try to select to which you feel you're more comfortable.
Okay, I think that's all for today, it's, yeah, finish at the right time, I hope you,
you, the past few now, not, not very long, I hope, so see you next week,
before the research week, next week, week seven, okay, all the best, thank you.
Thank you.