Okay. It looks like that works.
Okay.
Okay. Look, it finally works.
I don't know what happened.
It seems very strange.
Anyway, let's start the class now.
I need some writing.
Before going, let's start with the summary of the past two weeks.
Prepare the summary.
Week three and four, we are focusing on either linear models or linear estimators.
I think these two are somewhat quite similar and related.
For linear models, we know the given data because we are only dealing with a finite number of major data.
You put that as a vector.
Always keep this in mind, what we will be doing.
And then linear model means these linear functions of the true but unknown parameter vector.
We also assume zeta.
So both are not necessarily of the same dimension.
Typically, dimension is h and zeta is reflected in the coefficient matrix, which is this h.
And as I say, the number of samples, capital N, is normally larger than or at least equal to p.
That's the number of the unknown parameter zeta and this zeta vector.
Sometimes you call it n, so it's not that consistent, but you just base on the given one.
In this case, it's reflecting the size of h.
We normally assume this h is full-range.
Full-range means t is smaller or at most equal to n.
Then it would mean equal to the smaller one, which last week has spent quite some time going through the algebraic.
And then there is an interesting result.
If rank of h equal to p, you can prove this product of h transform.
We are assuming this coefficient is also of full-range.
But if the two matrix are different, say A transform multiplied by h,
even if both of them are full-range, the product may not necessarily be full-range.
So we pay attention to that.
And after that, we switch to linear unbiased estimator.
The equation will be later.
So I give you this illustration about under what condition,
blue means the best linear unbiased estimator is the shortfall for this.
And if we are putting all the unbiased estimators in this,
then of course you only have two classes, either linear or non-linear.
So for those linear, of course you may say non-linear includes linear.
So what we say non-linear is those that are non-linear.
And then what we are doing here is looking at this among all the linear, the best.
We always assume dealing with a high sum.
And if the MDUE is the one we always hope to get,
if it happens to be linear, among the linear subset,
then what do we get?
We are looking for the best linear unbiased estimator.
So it will be the optimal one.
But however, if the MDUE happens to be non-linear,
so what do we get?
Well, of course, the most suboptimal.
And then how good it is will depend on how far away this blue from this MDUE.
So this gives you the conceptual understanding about why the good size of getting the blue.
Sometimes we still can get the optimal one,
but the limitation is in the case of the blue is very far away from the non-linear and MDUE,
then we may need to be more careful.
So how to measure that?
As I say, if you are able to get the CRMP, that's to be of the best benchmark.
If not, then you try out the more practical way.
And then how to do that?
We start from scale case,
where this is only theta hat, the one where estimate is scaled.
So we assume the expectation of this data sample is equal to a vector
multiplied by this scale.
And we need to know the second order statistic, which is the covariance of the data.
And then after that, we get the optimal coefficient vector in this way.
And the variance, this coefficient vector, then of course, this is being linear.
So our estimate would be just equal to the interval type of this, based on this,
and just simply multiply this with x.
And the value is even simpler.
So you only take the denominator.
You can substitute and put in and then somewhat cancel out and get this.
In this course, quite often we end up with a simpler solution.
So you should always try your best to see how to simplify.
And similarly for the vector case, the result is similar, the derivation is also similar,
but a little bit more involved because we need to use the matrix notation and so on.
So going through this unit vector and so on.
So I won't go into detail.
So this is what we had so far for the first four weeks.
And today I plan to finish the analysis with five.
We have two more chapters among the classical estimation series,
which is MLE and the least square approach.
And these are finished.
I think you should be able to, because part of the least square is sequential one,
which is later combined into the Kalman filters, which is not for examination,
it's for your better understanding of the subject.
So it's easier because I already uploaded the assignment at NTU.
And by now you know the classical estimation theory.
And the patient one, we try to finish next week because that's a little bit more difficult.
But once you have a good understanding of the classical one,
I hope you can at least understand the basics
and can also do the two assignment questions when I take the basic one.
Yes?
The Kalman robot is if you are given the PDF or the likelihood function of the given data.
So that's an assumption for both scale case or yes.
But the CLB, CLB you can be right, but not the MBUE.
So CLB is, actually CLB is independent of the data.
So it's more based on the PDF of the data of the assumption.
This is a good question.
So today the MBUE is quite important because there are more or less summarized what you have learned up to now.
So including CLB, MBUE, and then of course naturally the MBUE makes you more likely.
So maybe you can wait for whatever.
I have another question.
If we don't have the CLB and we find the best linear estimation,
we don't know if the minimum various approximation is linear or non-linear,
how can we judge if we found the optimal solution?
Yeah, that's a good question.
That's why very often if you are given the limitation,
say for example, after MBUE, today we also discussed least square problems.
Least square is another one similar to the group.
You make some assumptions, but it doesn't require PDF.
So this is what you need to compromise for those methods.
Your requirement is less.
They only require the second-order statistics.
So you can try your best to get whatever you can, like suboptimal.
But how good it is?
Very often depending on, you know, for practical problem,
you will very much based on some kind of how to measure the performance
that you made based on the actual application you require.
And also based on the data, sometimes you can also try to estimate from the data,
estimate the distribution from the noise and so on.
And that's typically in image processing, how to get the noise,
you look at those in the image.
Those part doesn't contain much useful object and so on, like the background.
It's not the same from there, your model noise.
So noise typically will give you all the distribution of the noise that we have here.
And similarly for data, you know, like for example, we are talking about rho eta,
so now you measure the data.
And you know certain part you have contained maybe echo,
but the other part is very much noise.
So from there you can estimate.
So that's a more practical case.
Because typically we are dealing with signal plus noise.
So once you know the noise distribution, then you may be able to get better understanding.
And the true parameter and so on, sometimes you may not directly get from the measure data.
You may from other source, like nowadays data fusion is very common
and it's very helpful, such as if you are using Wi-Fi data to do some estimation.
One of the projects we are doing currently is you get some estimation,
but the result may not be good.
I'm also not sure how the grandchildren then agrees in the experiment.
You can use camera, video to take and then from there you know roughly the grandchildren
because video camera, if you have the object there, it will give you better information.
So from there you can judge, I mean, talking about the practical application.
From there you know roughly how good your algorithm is.
And then the real implementation in practice, you don't get the camera
because we are looking at the enemies inside the door.
Those you can't get camera.
Then at least you know how good your algorithm is, even in the practical setting.
So quite often you can verify your ground truth
or how good the algorithm is using another method, another modality and so on,
which may not be the final implementation of the algorithm you will be doing.
So it involves a lot of common sense and other approaches.
So our discussion here can cover all those other topics.
So we typically like to make some assumptions and assume PDA is known
and that's the best we can get.
But if PDA is not available, you still can try with limited information from the main major data.
Very good question.
I know sometimes you do a practical project and you have some constraints and limitations.
And that's why I work on some practical projects related to that.
I get the sense of what you are asking.
Good question.
So I think today we will be doing something related to the...
Although still it's through a toy example, you know, like the example where we have some assumptions.
So let's start with the MLE.
Yeah.
And let me see.
Okay.
So again here, let me switch to this one first.
But I will need to keep this on going otherwise it will not.
And then it cannot restart.
Yeah.
So MLE here is...
We are still trying to get the MLE, but if we can't get it using other method or at least not satisfactory,
such as blue will only give you the sub-optimal one.
We will see whether there are other methods where you may be able to work.
And in this sense, the method is what we call like the turned crank.
You all know that nowadays in Singapore a lot of construction sites.
So you will see a lot of crank, you know.
So turned crank, the operator will just follow the simple instructions, doing one by one, step by step.
And in MLEs, very often I always want to compare.
It's just like you are doing the derivation, you see.
If you are given an expression, you want to take a derivative, first order or second order, and so on.
Again, it's like off.
So anyway, let's fix it later.
So that's why we come to discuss this MLE, maximum likelihood approach,
which is I will always say in the estimation theory part, this part one,
the two chapters, CIOB and MLE, are the most important ones,
which is true if you look at other lecture notes or books and so on.
They may not discuss certain topics, but they always need to cover the CIOB and MLE.
And both of them happen to be required PDF or in another way is likelihood function.
These two are related.
And one very important practical implication is for MLE, if you have large data records,
so your major data, the number of major sample is large, then you can also show that it will be optimal.
Or also quite often you can approximate using the Gaussian distribution.
And that's it.
Let's see what we have here.
So we start with scalar case, which you only have just one unknown parameter.
And then we assume we have a PDF of this random sample, random variable X.
But our X here is we typically measure more than one sample, even if the unknown parameter, you have just one unknown parameter.
And the relationship between PDF or likelihood function is,
usually if you look at the function itself, it will be the same, but just two interpretation.
I'm trying to work this one, but keep turning it off.
Power saving.
Enter power saving mode.
Let me see if I need to start.
Just don't know how this system works.
We say enter power saving mode, but I do not do anything here.
Anyway, that's a big step.
So let me try to explain from the figures here.
Let's look at the case where I have Gaussian distribution.
So you know Gaussian distribution, maybe I refer to another thing, because later I need to use it.
Anyway, so let's see what we have here.
Pentax Gaussian.
Okay, Pentax.
This is the Gaussian.
If you look at the Gaussian distribution, you see, the random variable is Y.
And then you all know Gaussian distribution, I will require you to memorize this, because it's very simple.
Exponential signal, and then the random variable, subject to mean and variance.
And say, for example, in the exams, I say the Gaussian distribution mean goes to M, variance equals to sigma power 2.
This sigma is a standard distribution.
They should be able to write this for R.
And now if you consider if M is our unknown parameter, you see, and then if the mean is fixed, this is a function of Y.
And the Y is the random variable.
It will take the value over the lower axis, it can cover from minus infinity to positive infinity, something similar to this shape.
And that's how you interpret and base on this PDF to see how the random variable will behave.
And also from here, you all know that most likely the Y being a random variable, theoretically it can take even minus infinity.
But the challenge is very small, because it's very unlikely.
Most of the time, the value, even if you do realizations, it will be near the mean.
How near? Then that depends on the variance.
If the variance is very large, this random is quite random.
So it's more chance to take up value quite far away from the mean.
But still, most likely the highest chance of the value is near the mean.
But it may not exactly be the mean.
For example, that's why we had earlier the simulation.
If the mean goes to 5, then actually it's very unlikely every time you will get exactly 5.
But it could be very near 5, it could be 4.9, or the next round is 5.1, and so on.
So that gives you the sense of how the random variable will behave.
Now, on the other hand, we already take the sample, because our measured data is collected in the capital N sample.
And then we want to, based on this sample, try to see what's the mean value based on the sample.
So assume, actually our PDF is, we borrow this PDF concept.
And in the actual implementation, we don't really need to go through the PDF.
We use this PDF as an intermediate step to derive the MLE.
So later you will see.
So you already know, since given this measured data, and from the measured data we already know based on the PDF,
we are most likely saying here, here, here.
It's more concentrating near the mean value where this is what we call the data MLE.
So based on this sample, we say for example you plot, and that's how in practical application.
You don't really need to, actually you may not really know the, know the PDF.
You may say, oh, given the PDF, given the PDF, we already know the, if you look at the expression,
the mean is if you are taking the maximum value of X, there will be a coincide.
As I already mentioned, also it's high chance to appear the random sample realization near this peak,
but you may not really get that peak.
So what you do is fix this measured data, and then try to derive from the likely function.
The likely function is the one when you fix the X.
You don't treat X as random variable, but substitute is a fixed value,
and that's the case where you measure the data.
Each measured sample, you only measure one value, and then the next moment you measure another one.
So from there you do the histogram, you see, based on histogram.
From there you get the peak, and this peak value of this likely function will give you the corresponding variable,
because now I plot this as a function of theta.
From there, we get the maximum value, and the corresponding argument will give us our best estimated value,
because this value is corresponding to where the samples are most likely to happen.
Just now we looked at the PDF of the Gaussian distribution.
So that's the easiest to understand, but of course you can extend it to, you want to get the variance,
it will also be the same.
Given this likely function, you maximize, you get the maximum value, get the corresponding argument.
So that's how this is derived.
So that's the idea of the maximum likelihood.
And then because, as I say, we derive this likely function from the corresponding PDF,
by fixing the random variable as some fixed value, and looking that as a function of theta.
But as you can also see from the Gaussian distribution of the PDF, coming from the PDF, it will be positive functions.
PDF cannot take negative value.
And quite often PDFs happen to be exponential for, say, Gaussian or the Rayleigh distribution and so on.
So it's mostly related to exponential.
So it's easier if we take a log.
But of course you don't take log, later with example you can directly get maximum.
It also gives you the same result, because log function and not taking log is one-to-one corresponding.
So that's how you can get either directly get the maximum or take the log.
It's the same.
So let's look at how we apply to examples.
So this example, I don't include some detail.
So I hope that you are able to try to think and maybe do it as exciting.
I'll give you some idea, but I will skip the step.
So perhaps going back you can try to do it and then maybe next week I will show you the details.
So this one is a very good example.
You can combine CLB, combine those variants and how to derive expectation and so on.
So let's see how it works.
So this is, the example looks the same as what we discussed before.
DC level and then white Gaussian noise.
But however, if you pay attention here, you see our A here is a DC.
But this maybe, as I say, is a toy example, just to illustrate the concept.
In practice you may argue, will this ever happen or not.
But let's look at the case if our noise, white Gaussian noise, should be assuming zero noise.
Because we don't state the mean.
But the variance is unknown and equal to A also.
So this A is the same A.
So A here is the unknown mean and then being a variant must be positive.
So we assume this A is greater than zero.
So this is unknown variant A.
So then now you look at the PDF.
The PDF here, you see.
So PDF is we interpret, we have a total number of N samples.
So they are white.
So you can just multiply them together because all of them have the same mean, which is A.
And then also here, you see.
So this A here is the, it will be the variant.
So typically you have sigma power of two.
So here is sigma power of two equal to A.
And the same here, you see.
We have sigma power of two.
So you replace by A.
So that's the PDF.
But if you interpret now, we want to get using MLE by deriving the maximum likelihood value for A.
So how are we going to do, you see.
So that's the basic, because now we have the PDF or the likelihood function.
We're assuming if we already measure the sample fixed.
So we want to consider that as a function of A.
So now you can, if you go back to this, you have A appear at three places.
Again, this is the basic calculus.
You don't need to turn the crank.
You do it step by step.
You should be able to do it.
And then you can see after some little bit of simulation, derivation, you end up with these terms added together.
But the question here is, so here you show the example where you can get the CLB, but you cannot get the efficient estimator.
And also at least you cannot get the MUE from the CLB approach.
So you can get the CLB because the first order derivative, you can verify it satisfies the regularity condition, attacking the mean.
The expectation will happen to be equal to zero.
So then from here, because we cannot factorize this one.
I mean, it's very hard to prove, but on the other hand, how to prove by, if you say yes, you can do it for me.
But you can see from here it's almost very difficult or impossible because it's very hard to write into this way.
And then remember this A must be depending on the data only, where this I of A is independent of data and this must be A.
So anyway, this one cannot do, but we can still derive the CLB.
So again, this is how to get the CLB is another routine exercise.
Sometimes in some past year paper I make this as part of the question.
So anyway, the CLB turned out to be quite simple.
Also you have the complicated first order derivative.
Now you can imagine the second order derivative, you can take more terms.
But surprisingly after take expectation, because CLB is not everything depends on data.
You're depending on the expectation, which it turned out to be quite often you can simplify.
And that's why I want to ask you to do some of the assignment questions.
It's quite easy, but you will see that turned out to be very simple in this form.
So now let's see where this MLE to work.
So MLE sometimes you may confuse CLB or even confuse with regularity condition.
The main difference is here, you see, both of them you get the first order, first derivative.
And then the CLB approach, you try to factorize.
If you cannot, then you will stop here.
You can continue to do the, you need to verify the regularity condition by packing the expectation
to make sure expectation is equal to zero.
And the other day you continue to take the second derivative and so on.
But MLE is different.
MLE is you get the first derivative.
And then remember when to get the maximum value out of that and solve for A.
So you don't take expectation here.
I emphasize, you don't take expectation.
You directly lay this first order derivative equal to zero.
And then solve the, in this case you only have to scale it.
So you lay equal to zero, they will become a function of the unknown parameter A and also the data.
So usually in practice it may become a non-linear function.
They only need to solve it numerically.
So in some simple case, like in this case, it will turn out to be, this is second order polynomial of the A, you see.
So second order polynomial of A.
And of course you all know there's very famous rules that you can, that you're learning the secondary school.
A X squared plus B X plus C.
So you can get a standard way, the quadratic equation and solve this A.
Because typically second order, you will have two rules.
One is positive, one may be negative.
One is larger, one is smaller.
Unless these two rules are the same.
But in our case here, it turns out to be one of them is positive, the other is negative.
So we keep the, based on the assumption A should be positive, we keep this A greater than zero.
So it will turn out to be, this is what we can solve.
So how to solve?
Again, as I say, you can solve the second order quadratic equation of A.
It should be not an issue.
And now we want to see whether it's biased or not.
So this is, again, it's not a direct answer to, let me see.
Okay, so now it works out.
It's very interesting.
Very interesting.
Let me see.
So I hope I keep this ongoing later.
So now it will not suddenly go to, maybe I will call this problem.
So now how to show this is biased.
Because when you take expectation, if you are dealing with linear or even polynomial,
in terms of the random variable, where our random variable here is the data here.
So you can, there are certain ways to break E into even second orders and so on.
But however, in this highly nonlinear case, square roots, the square roots of operation,
which I don't think there is an easy way.
You can say we know E of this x theta power of two.
But E of taking a square root of some random variable is basically probably no analytic solution you can apply.
Because E is a linear operator.
So now the counter proof here is if we are not allowed to bring the E inside this nonlinear operation, the square root.
But on the other hand, we purposely apply this E inside.
And then after that, it turns out to be if you apply this E inside this, and you take the square root,
then our E or not really E of this, then it turns out to be this whole thing becomes A.
So since this is not working initially, I tried to use it.
But anyway, good guys said derivation in a short copy.
Yeah, that's how the derivation you want to try out yourself.
So now this is inside the square root.
If you say E of this inside, then because this is constant, I can bring the E inside this.
So this one is no problem.
And then each of them we can use the very useful and famous formula.
If your tree is X of n, because each of them they are i.i.d.
So they are basically the same.
So each of them you use the formula E of the random variable power of two.
It would be equal to E of the same random variable, as you remember, I mentioned a few times.
These two are different.
One is X power of two first, and take E.
This is E of this X n power of two.
But you must add the value of the same X of n.
So I replace this into that.
And then still waiting for something, because each of them are the same.
So now we know our random variable here.
Assume the W is zero mean.
So the expectation of X n is equal to A.
So your power, making A power of two here, A squared.
And then for this example, the value of that is equal to A.
So waiting inside, we will have this.
And then now you sum all of them together.
There will be a total of A divided by A.
You will end up with this.
And then now there is no summation, because this is all the same.
So we end up with A squared plus A plus one plus four.
And which is equal to A plus half raised to the power of two.
So this is the derivation.
Inside this, you see.
So remember, what we just do is assume I take E of this.
It will no longer become random.
It will be just equal to A plus one over two raised to the power of two.
Then you take the square root, because what's inside is positive.
So you can become minus one over two plus one over two plus A.
And you cancel out the minus one over two and one over two.
So therefore, if we are allowed to take the expectation breaking inside this,
then you get the unbiased estimate.
But since this operation is not allowed,
then what you do is wrong.
So using this counter-prove approach, you show E of this is not equal to A.
Because to be equal to A, you need to do an illegal operation,
which is not allowed.
So something like you are not allowed to go into someone, your neighbors,
unless he or she allows you to.
If you know his permission, you go in.
If there is something wrong, you take out something which shouldn't be yours.
So the argument is in this way.
So in this way, except this is the way to show.
Usually this one later, we also need this operation.
So now, because this is non-linear,
then we have difficulty to see how good this MLE is.
Because you can say, okay, I just yield this one,
since we are based on the major data.
Whatever your end sample, we use this.
But because this is highly non-linear,
we can see whether we can do something more meaningful.
Say, for example, analyze the variant.
This is a very hard thing.
Even with the difficulty to get the expectation, to get the variant,
it's almost impossible directly.
So now, that's why for MLE, we are assuming you have a large number of data samples.
The following discussion is,
assume now we want to see if our samples increase or in the same,
go to infinity last.
Are we able to get an approximation of this MLE,
which gives you some better expression?
So that's how we are going to do it.
We use this Taylor series expansion by expanding,
because this is a function of, you see here,
the only non-linear or depending on data is this.
Here we go to this.
And this is random, you see,
where I'm summing up the square, the major value raised to the power 2,
and then take the mean value out of this.
So, assume we let u equal to that,
and then now this will be a function of this GU is non-linear.
So our discussion here is,
we try to explain it around this EUG load,
EUG load value,
which is, you see, EU is random,
but we take the expectation,
you see, they become non-random.
And the idea here is,
if you are averaging many random variables,
particularly i.i.d.,
then eventually when the sample to take average becomes larger and larger,
then eventually the random variable gradually reduces the value,
it will become no longer random.
So that's a very typical famous large sample,
large data sample theory,
your approach to the mean value index.
Then you can also see from the simulation,
I showed you the sample is increased,
then eventually you will see it's very centralized around the true value index.
That's what we are doing here, you see,
because this EUG load is the angle to infinity large,
it will approach to this,
it will become E,
and then EU, which is equal to this A plus A squared.
You can try to divide that, like I said.
And then from there,
we can explain it because this is non-linear function,
using Taylor expansion at this EUG load,
and then that's a standard way.
And after some derivation,
you will show this approximately using this,
you see, it's non-linear,
but approximately at the first order derivative,
then you end up with this.
So that's more management, you see.
So now we reduce non-linear one into,
it's a linear function of,
not the random variable itself, but the power of two.
But we all know we can handle random variables with the power of two much easier,
particularly for Gaussian, you see.
For Gaussian, as I already showed you,
there is not a normal problem.
So this is what we approximate.
Finally, we can see this ANOE by using another way.
And it works well if n is very large
because our derivation is assumed, n is infinitely large.
But if we do not have infinitely large, if n is large enough,
so the error would be not that much.
So that's why I call it approximate.
And then now, again here, we can show from here,
if we are talking about this part,
then e of this part is just equal to a.
But since we had approximate here,
so we say approximately equal to a.
And the value, so this looks very complicated.
Value of this one is equal to that.
So that part is not easy.
So perhaps I will leave this part for you.
Maybe you go back and see how you can derive a.
This is not part of the assignment.
At least that's a very good derivation.
And it turns out to be now this one is equal to our CLB.
You can see.
So therefore, the MLE here is asymptotically unbiased,
asymptotically unique, n to be very large,
and also asymptotically efficient.
In this case, we achieved the CLB.
So this is the example, although it's like a tall example,
but quite a few concepts and quite some techniques together.
So I hope you are okay with that.
Take your time to digest.
And as I say, try to derive it by yourself if possible.
So now we can extend it to, oh yeah,
before going to the vector parameter case,
we can also discuss the regularity conditions here.
It's quite similar to the case we are dealing with,
the CLB, feature information,
but here it's a little bit relaxed.
We only require the existence of the first order
and second order derivative of this log-like function.
And also, no zero feature information
because these two conditions, if you do this CLB,
you also need that.
But then, yeah.
So if that's the case, we will also see,
but we are not going to prove here,
it's just called the result here.
Then in this case, in the case of the data sample is large,
asymptotic mean you have infinity of the angle to very large,
you can see this will follow the Gaussian distribution, you see.
So that means that the mean, the Gaussian distribution,
the mean is just equal to our unknown parameter, theta, the true one.
And the value is just equal to our feature information,
and take the inverse, that's the same as our CLB.
So in this case, you can see it will be an efficient one
because it will approach the CLB.
And then you can see the asymptotic behavior.
This is what I say here.
You will see here, if A is equal to one,
depending on how much sample you have to see.
So you see here, if you have the theoretical asymptotic period
of the data in the store game.
So you see here, the more data you have,
then you will be approximating the theoretical period.
But in the actual implementation, we don't need to refer to the period.
As long as you have enough data sample,
you can see it will follow the Gaussian distribution.
And then we maybe finish this part and take a break.
We take the, extend it to the vector parameter case,
then you'll still get the period or view X is fixed.
You'll get the likelihood function.
Remember, even though theta now is a vector,
our period is still a scalar function of the X and theta.
But when you take the derivative with respect to the theta vector,
you will get the derivative become a vector.
So you need to make the whole vector equal to zero
and then solve the maximum value, corresponding value.
And again, you'll satisfy the regularity condition
and then also now you'll need Fisher information magic.
Then you can show, you will also follow this asymptotic distribution,
become like a Gaussian, which is unbiased and also meet the CRP.
So let's take a look at the example where we have two unknowns here.
So this is a typical example here,
where we have unknown of A, which is the mean, a PC value, N.
Our WN is a zero mean, but the barrier is also unknown.
Now this sigma power two, it's not the same example.
It's an independent one, A and PC.
So we put the two of them into an unknown parameter vector.
To do that, we apply the derivative to each of A and sigma power two.
Sometimes you may confuse this sigma power two as sigma and then raise the power two.
It's not. You treat that as just one unknown parameter.
So that's why in the assignments, I always suggest you put that as a new,
maybe call it M1, M2 and so on.
Not to leave the power two here.
If you keep power two, you always need to remember
where our derivative is to the whole sigma power two.
So you don't give the sigma power three here.
You will never have either sigma power two or sigma power four,
which is twice of sigma power two.
Now the important one here on the input side,
because it's always the case if you are doing the assignment or the finding exam paper.
You want to solve two equations with two unknowns.
Then typically you try to solve one first and then you solve the second one.
But you need to make sure when you solve the first one here,
you put the, for example, you already get one solution of A here.
Because the first equation, you want to make it equal to zero.
You don't need to involve this sigma power two.
But to solve the second one, you must put the solution of A,
which is A hat, into this second equation.
This is always, every year I have a student probably,
I hope those are attending the class since you will gain more attention.
Other than those watching the video, they may not see my emphasis, my face here.
So I emphasize here, when you solve, so let me, let me highlight here, you see.
When you solve the first one, that's very easy.
I, yeah, I will get the A estimate based on, yeah, just based on the sum of B.
Because you want to make this equal to zero, we can ignore this one.
So what you solve is here.
And that's why the A hat is equal to just the sum for B.
And then now to put this into the second one, you don't leave the A there.
You must use the solution of this A, which is the sum for B inside.
You have to get the second one, which is the, so this part is the,
this part is the estimate of the sigma power of two.
Again, it's not sigma, it's sigma power of two, the value.
And then, so again finally we want to link this with assuming
we're dealing with, again, the general linear models, which we discussed earlier.
But here we extend it a little bit by allowing the W.
It's not necessarily Y.
It has zero mean, but the variance can be a covariant matrix,
which is, of course, must be invertible and also positive definite.
But it can have the off-diagonal element not being zero.
So in this case, you can also show the MLE.
In this case, it values Gaussian, so you will see it's equal to this expression.
So that's, because being Gaussian, sorry, this one is noise,
but our solution here will be this one.
This is the MLE for the unknown parameter vector here,
so if this is linear, then we can see this time the CLB and also the MLE.
And then therefore our PTF of this will be equal to this.
So this is very similar to what we did earlier.
So we finished this MLE.
Thanks.
But you need to take time to digest and think about some of the derivations.
I give you some time to go back.
We are doing the assignment.
You can try this, but if not, then it will be very difficult.
I will show you because this document camera is not very stable here.
So any questions before we take a break and then move?
Yes?
Can we go to slide 19 and 19, 19, 19?
9-0.
So we have the input X, and it's kind of a sequence, right?
We can consider it as a sequence of inputs, right?
n is equal to 0, and n is equal to n minus 1.
Yes, yes, yes.
So for this distribution, shouldn't it be the multiplication of all of those ones?
Oh, yes, yes. That's why you know the very famous result.
Exponential function.
When you multiply two exponential functions of the same base, you are adding the exponent together.
So that's why you end up with your multiplication becomes the summation of the exponent.
Because all the other parts are the same.
Right?
So that's why we already dig early.
That's how we directly, directly apply.
It will become the, yeah, adding up the exponent.
So each of the, because here is a Gaussian, so each is exponential of, say, A.
Then you multiply exponential B, then you multiply together, your B exponent is A plus B.
So in total, you have n.
You are summing up those, because all the exponents, they differ only by Xn and 0, 1, 2, 3.
So that's why you turn this into, yeah.
Okay?
So I hope that this is something you always need to remember.
And that's why, quite often, we use log.
Because once you make it become exponential, you take log, you will bring this exponent down to become,
yeah, it will be easier to enter.
Okay, good question.
Any other thing?
Yes?
In this class 97, so just how about your alpha size?
After you calculate all the estimators of the first item of the parameter,
Yes.
What do you mean by that?
For example, if I get A hat,
Yes.
Why calculate the second norm?
Why let A equal to A hat?
Yeah, you just put whatever the solution to solve.
This is a very common problem in math.
You are solving two equations with two unknowns.
So remember, even with the normal linear equation, you solve one.
Because in this case, it happened to be the first equation.
You can see here, you make it equal to zero.
You will be basically just let this whole thing.
Because this one is a no-zero coefficient.
So you will be letting, summing up a total of A,
they become NA, and equal to summing up this equal to zero.
Then you get the solution already for this.
Then to solve the second one, you must put this one.
Because you see the two solutions must be, you solve two equations simultaneously.
This is a very common technique in EBO.
Just think about two equations, x plus y equal to 2,
then the second one is 3x plus 2y equal to 5.
Then to solve that, there must be only two fixed values for linear equations.
Usually you just have a unique solution.
So you get one solving from the first equation,
then you substitute into the second one to solve the other variable.
That's the same here, although this looks a little bit more complicated
because those coefficients are summation of the data sample.
Sometime later you will see it can become a nonlinear function
or polynomial of the data.
But the idea is the same.
You must solve both of them simultaneously.
You solve one, then you use the solution you put into the second one to solve the other.
Because in this case, the second one, you involve both A and sigma power 2.
I hope this is the case.
Later I deliver probably one of the assignment questions either here
or here.
Normally we will not involve more than two unknown parameters,
but you will need to know how to solve two equations for two unknowns.
So you do it simultaneously.
We take a break here, then we can continue after that.
So now we come back at 8 p.m.
Now it's 7.44.
Now we come back at 8 p.m.
Can you tell us a little bit more about this experiment?
Yes.
The experiment was done in the late 19th century.
The experiment was done in the early 19th century.
This experiment was conducted in the early 17th century.
This experiment was done in the early 19th century.
So I say settled in this
the experiment was done here.
I think it was a very interesting experiment.
And keep in mind that this experiment has numerous characteristics.
news
just think about it I didn't see anything
So you, please.
You can take this.
I would like to thank all of the undergraduates for their support.
Before going to the lecture notes, let me explain briefly the assignment.
As I already announced early, for this course we have two CA.
The first one is the estimation theory.
I already uploaded this at NTU.
You go inside 7402, go to the assignment.
It's not in the contact, but you click the assignment one.
You should be able to download this PDF.
I give all the explanation here.
You have three weeks.
Now it's week five, which is up to recess week, the same Wednesday, quite a long time.
You will be by 12, midnight.
It's typically the case.
Nowadays you can use chat GPT, but try to do it by yourself.
Because mostly here you're solving equations.
So I guess chat GPT may not have that much.
Except, of course, the last question, A, you will have more math.
You can do the three options.
You can choose two of them which will be more comfortable.
Show all the steps involved in detail.
The first seven questions are quite similar to the final exam paper questions.
They cover most of the containing power, including rules, MLEs and so on.
And later these square linear models.
The last two questions are more related to the Bayesian one, which you can leave until next week.
I will go through the final chapter of this part.
Question A is, I give three sub-questions, so you can choose two.
You don't need to choose three.
Just choose any two of them.
Make it clear.
So again, describe if you have some research problem, even now or previously,
or being in your undergraduate projects or whatever.
Should be related to parameter estimation problem.
Like a small project.
And then you can also do some implementation using Python or whatever.
I think most of the students can work out this one.
And the last option is I attach a research paper where some parts are related to parameter estimation.
So this one is also open-ended.
You read it and then try your best to figure out what this paper is doing and what's related to.
It's not totally within the contents of the part.
Being a research paper, usually you cover some related topics.
So you maybe look to get some understanding if you are interested in exploring more.
And that also shows how you can relate the way you learn here to some machine learning areas.
Because signal processing and machine learning are some parts closely related.
Any questions, you can let me know.
Maybe I'll make an announcement again for you to learn.
Because some students are not here.
But before we move on to the next chapter, which is the least squares.
Any questions you would like to raise for the previous chapter?
Because this is supposed to be the last one in this conventional parameter estimation.
And I think this square is also a relatively easy concept.
Particularly what we are doing here is mostly also assume linear models.
No linear one, you will use a similar approach.
But typically one may need to do by computer implementations.
So let's start here.
And the method of least squares here is again another way of doing parameter estimation.
So you will see the different methods.
In the end we are still trying to see what we can do.
So remember the assumption here is we have a finite number of typically capital N major data.
And we want to see how to make good use of these given finite number of data samples.
It's based on certain assumptions, either PDF or some second order statistic or some models.
We are going to estimate the parameter hidden in this data.
And moving on to part two, detection, signal detection.
It's also similar.
We are doing the signal detection.
And also based on finite number of data samples.
And so you see here all these methods in the end are non-parameter.
Our estimate is a function of the major data.
Except the CILB, where for CILB we are taking the expectation.
So in the end the end-out is not a function of data.
And that also varies.
The CILB is a benchmark for any estimator.
So it's independent of the data.
Other than that, all the other estimates in the end we also express it as a function of how to combine the data in a simple way.
So again here, the least square here is we do not make any probabilistic assumption on the data.
But we assume some signal models.
And then based on that and the major data, we try to derive the best from using the criteria of least square.
So here we cannot have the results showing any statistical best performance and so on.
Because we are not having the PDA assumption or even not deriving it from the statistical point of view.
We are more based on the major data itself.
So it's simple, easier to do.
But then again there is some limitation.
It's always pros and cons.
But this one, least square, as I said, is very popular.
Quite often you do it in practice because you can also handle no linear least square.
But you may not be able to solve it analytically as we will be doing here for the linear models.
So actually the model itself here is not necessarily linear.
But it should be as a function of describing the data sample index and the unknown parameter.
Say for example you put it as a side way function or exponential function.
And then based on that you can try to apply the least square approach to do the optimization.
So how to do that?
We had a sample of data which is in this way.
And then now we are measuring this major data as certain models.
Here our model is different from the early model.
For example we have the linear models and so on where we need to assume certain noise inside.
Even if you do not appear there, we still say we are using the second order statistic of the noise.
Same mean, value, or value. Even so we may not know the whole period.
But here it differs in the case of our model here.
It's just describing the so-called signal.
So we do not directly embed the noise here.
What happens to the noise? Noise is somehow inside the major data.
And then using the model and the major data we want to see how good this model fits into the major data.
So we take a difference for each intake.
The n goes to zero with one major data.
This model is also depending on the intake as you will see.
It's both a function of the zeta.
Otherwise you will not be able to estimate the unknown parameter.
And then typically they are not the same.
But we want to see how to minimize the least square.
This is the square sum of the square because we increase the power of two.
And here it's quite useful because we do not assume the Gaussian.
It could be Gaussian or it could be no Gaussian noise.
Then the performance of this is depending on the property of this noise into this major data.
And also the modeling errors.
As I said, here you have to somehow guess what this major data are more likely following certain signal model.
Linear or sideways or exponential and so on.
So we start with, again, the simple case.
Scalar parameter and also the signal model here as you can see is similar to what we described earlier.
It's a linear model.
But the difference here is our model doesn't include the noise.
So assuming there's no noise here.
And then the coefficient here is assumed to be a known sequence.
Not necessarily constant.
It's a function of A.
But it's deterministic.
It's not random here.
So our model here is deterministic.
What being random or statistically it would be this major data.
So using this least square error criterion, we already do is take each of the difference and then we start to sum them together.
And then to minimize, as we already know, you just take this function of the data.
You take first of the derivative and then make it equal to zero.
Which is similar to the MLE.
So you can see here.
Very easy.
This one is second order polynomial of theta.
You take derivative.
You will be two of this.
And then, of course, you treat this h of n as a coefficient of theta.
So you end up with putting h of n here.
Then you're likely equal to zero.
So you're bringing it into two terms.
Of course, the summation is still there.
So one common mistake, for example, you take the derivative of h of n here.
Then, Cloud Fung students will try to move this one outside and get a simpler solution.
Which is wrong.
Because the summation, whatever inside this summation, depending on the index, you cannot take out.
So that's a very so-called golden rule.
And that happens in solving assignment questions.
So I want to just remind you of this.
And that's why you end up with h of n here.
So you multiply x of n.
You end up with this one of the terms here.
And the other, h of n.
Multiply h of n, become h of n power two.
But for the theta, you can take out.
Because theta is independent of h.
But inside the power of two, you cannot take it out.
Because it's a second order.
But once you take the derivative, you will become a linear function of theta.
So you can take out.
Therefore, this is the solution.
Make it equal to zero.
That's what we call minimize the error.
You get this.
And then, once you get the solution, you want to get the corresponding error.
So you pay attention here.
This theta is before we do the optimization.
It's a function of theta.
It's general.
Depending on which theta you are going to take.
Now once you get the optimal theta hat here.
Or at least optimal in terms of least square.
Minimal least square error.
So we need to put this one in.
Then you substitute this whole thing inside here.
You will see the hat here.
But then, you either keep this formula here.
It's okay.
Or you explain it.
I think it's better in this way.
Because from here, you can see this term is always positive.
So you will see this least square error.
After you get the optimal one, it's always smaller.
Like most equal to this.
So this is our measured data's energy.
Any data sample will raise out to add together.
So therefore you can see here.
The relationship is always greater or equal to zero.
Because you are taking the square of the difference.
So it's always at least equal to zero.
But smaller than this.
Or at most equal to this part.
Which is the original energy of the data.
So that looks quite easy for the scale case.
So let's look at the simple example again.
Here, easy level.
So here you see the difference from the previous chapter.
The other measure is our signal model is just purely trying to guess.
What if no noise, how the signal looks like.
Because easy level signal is a constant.
And that's how we do not take noise into the clouds here.
In the signal model.
But the noise is part of the observations or measured data.
So then we know this error.
Even by this.
And then again just based on all you can derive here.
Or use the result we just showed.
You will see the solution is the sample being here.
And then once you get the sample being you're trying to get this.
So it's quite easy for the scale case.
Particularly if you are dealing with assuming linear model.
Then we are getting back to what we learned earlier.
It's just from another angle.
Then we can move on to linear least square for vector parameter case.
As I say the approach can be extended to non-linear.
Solving non-linear equation.
Particularly if you have a set of equations.
Typically you may not get analytic solution.
You may do it by numerical approach.
Or sometimes some of the polynomial.
If it's a polynomial equation.
Then there is some quite powerful next tools.
You call it global basis.
Which is quite good idea.
I used that for research for some years.
I always encourage students to try it.
If you are solving a system of polynomial equations.
For those who really need that.
You can approach me individually.
But not in this course.
So let's look at how we are solving this.
Vector parameter.
We are using the linear models.
Again the model here we don't take noise into consideration.
Just saying the model is a linear function of the unknown parameter vector.
So we need to...
Where this coefficient is a known one.
Again here is N by P observation.
So you see here it's of full length P.
As we assume P is greater or at least equal to P.
And then LSE is obtained by...
Very similar to what we did earlier for the linear model.
So here you also see how to solve your explaining to several terms.
Then use the vector derivation to get this.
And then make it equal to zero.
So you get this solution equal to this.
So that's the same as what we obtained earlier.
From another angle.
Because we are not assuming Gaussian.
So turn out these equations.
Normal equation.
So that's identical to what we did earlier using the rule approach.
But in the rules, if you recall, we are assuming this assumption here.
Then also the covariance of the data equal to IID here.
But for LSE, so far we do not assume this conditional noise.
And also the minimum error is given by that.
So now once we get this theta hat, theta hat is here, you can put it in.
So this is the one without simplification.
Then there are two ways you can somehow simplify into either this.
So that means the theta hat here we already obtained as a function of h and theta.
So either this or even another way simpler one.
Because if you compare this one with this one, part of it is gone.
How to do that?
You make good use of the orthogonality property by making good use of theta hat.
Our theta hat is special. Theta hat must satisfy this.
This one works only for the theta hat.
If you put the general theta, of course you will not be able to show from here to here.
This is, as you can observe, this is only part of that.
In general, they are not the same.
Just imagine you put the transpose into each of the term here.
The first one, h transpose, it will give you this.
The other one is, remember you take transpose of the product of two matrix, you have to swap this.
Theta hat transpose, and then h transpose, and then multiply by that.
So it turns out to be that one is equal to zero because of the special property of theta hat.
Again, this involves a little bit of matrix operation.
I hope you maybe try to do it.
If not, I will explain next time.
Then we can extend the weighted least square.
The weighting here is, this one is the weighting matrix.
It's positive, definite.
The idea here is we are handling noises where certain data samples are more important.
We are doing the weighting.
It turns out to be quite useful in some practical applications.
That's how we call it, weighted least squares.
You're adding in this W in the middle.
The LAS error criteria is the same as before.
You make W equal to, I think, identity matrix.
Again, you use some algebraic.
You can divide the solution, as you see, with the weighting just equal to this.
You're adding this W in the middle.
From here, you can also see, in terms of the data, you will be weighting all the data.
Then, once you get this, you get the minimum LAS error by substituting inside.
You can explain it.
Probably, we may no longer be able to show it into that simple form.
Like this, I don't see the simple form like that.
Maybe I can try.
I try myself since I'm not able to do it.
Any questions before we move on to the other one?
I think I will skip this sequential least squares until the end of part 1 and part 2.
For this course, our second assignment is a quiz.
It will be weight 11, not weight 12.
After weight 11, we still have time to do some additional lectures,
which is the Kalman filter plus sequential least squares.
I will skip this part first because that's quite related.
I think now start this Bayesian estimation because this chapter...
Actually, there are two chapters on that.
Probably, it may take more than one week to learn.
Now to start this, at least you have some basic concept.
Maybe go back, you can try to digest.
Any questions before we move on to that?
Some previous chapters also.
Because I think this chapter 8 and 9 dealing with Bayesian approach,
which at least in theory will be much more difficult
because we are now moving away from the assumption
where the unknown parameters are deterministic.
You can imagine here at least we need to deal with at least two unknown random variables.
One is unknown parameter, the other is the random noise.
So you need to try to get used to how to handle this thing.
One very important tool, which is what we call the Bayesian Theorem.
That's very powerful.
You can see, even in the machine learning area,
some of the benchmark methods always compare with that.
Don't I call it naive, Bayesian approach, but I think it's still quite powerful.
Some researchers argue that you ought to learn machine learning,
you must be learning this Bayesian Theorem.
That's the fundamentals of whatever machine learning methods, topics need to learn.
As I say, we try to now move to the new area
where we are also dealing with parameters which are random variables.
And then see how much we can do here.
And sometimes you can, even by learning this approach,
you can even apply it to the case where the unknown parameters are deterministic
because deterministic parameters are the same.
You can consider that as a special case of the random unknown parameter
by making the distribution to be a uniform distribution.
But the area for this uniform distribution, you need to assume you have the finite interval
where the probability within this interval will be equal, one over the interval.
But if you're assuming the interval is getting bigger and bigger,
that's the case where you have a deterministic, because it's no longer random.
Just imagine if the random variable takes all the possible values equally,
they become no random variable.
That's how those people arguing this Bayesian estimation is more general.
But we'll see how we can apply it here.
So, to start with, we are now looking at the observation and the unknown parameters.
We see here both are random.
And then we still try to estimate the unknown parameters based on the major data.
And then here we start by assuming we have the joy distribution
of the PDF of two random variables, X, which could be a vector,
theta here could be also a vector.
And then, for this, you should know the Bayes' Theorem, which is very useful.
It says this joy PDF, you can consider that as a product by...
Put it here as a conditional PDF.
This is a PDF of X, if you build this X conditioning on the given theta.
So, as you see here, now what I always argue early,
when we say we take the expectation of a random variable,
you become deterministic.
It is no longer very here, because if you have two random variables,
you may take the expectation of one of them, then you still have some randomness.
So, here is the case of conditional PDF.
In this case, we are given theta.
Theta now is a random, so you have different realizations.
You can take, say, you throw a coin, it can be, say, 0 or 1,
or you throw a dice, six face, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and so on.
So, this condition is assumed this theta has some realizations,
some random, but then we measure how the X is a random variable,
still random.
So, we can use the conditional PDF to measure this X, given theta.
Or, alternatively, as we do other rounds, given the measured theta,
you do some realizations, like what we learned earlier,
like a little function.
Your X is random, but we take some fixed value, some realizations.
There is no random.
But then, now our theta is still random, you see.
So, we still need to describe, assume, the conditional PDF,
the PDF of theta, given that.
So, that's how this is going.
What happens to both P of theta or P of X?
So, this is what we call prime PDF of theta,
because our theta now is a random variable.
So, before we measure the data, we may have some knowledge of this,
you know, the random variable.
For example, it could be a Gaussian distribution,
or it's a uniform distribution, or some other form.
But that knowledge is broader.
So, some students keep asking, or ask, need a question.
If we already have the PDF of theta, then why do we still need to use
the measured data to do the posterior PDF?
So, this is what we call posterior PDF, because this is the one
after your measured data.
Then, you can interpret it this way.
Before we measure the data, we may have a lot of broad knowledge
about the distribution of this random variable.
But we're not going to measure it.
Once we measure the data, we can measure the data.
At least we assume it contains some useful information.
They can narrow down our knowledge about this data.
That will give you a better, more accurate representation
of the unknown parameter, just like machine learning.
You see, even before you measure data, quite often you may have
some broad idea about maybe the class we're looking at
and belonging to what.
But that's not enough.
Once you have the training data, or you learn from what your knowledge is,
then you'll get a better understanding.
Maybe you can improve what your previous knowledge is,
get it more accurate.
So, similar here, this is the prior PDF before we even have the data.
Then this is the posterior.
So our idea is how to make good use of the data
and using this Bayes Theorem to improve, to get the posterior PDF,
having the measured data.
So that's the main idea here.
Because now we are dealing with the unknown parameter,
except random variables.
So we need to define some risk functions
to see how much different from...
Yeah, both of them are random.
We make it easier to look at the scale case.
So these measures, the estimate and the true one,
how much different.
But then, of course, you may argue again here,
because being random is not a fixed value.
So our criteria here, the risk function,
is just think about in terms of the random variable,
how you see the difference.
Later, when you put this into the expectation, for example,
or the integration.
So that's how we try to define the difference
from the true one and the estimate one.
But later you will see these risk functions,
not the deterministic comparison by itself.
Later we need to interpret that in the statistical sense.
So for the moment, we look at the difference
by using three very popular risk functions.
One is quadratic errors, which is co-open errors,
which means the difference with power of two.
And the second one is absolute error,
which is here graphically,
which is take the absolute error.
So all these risk functions must be positive,
or at least greater or equal to zero, to make sense.
So the difference itself may be positive, negative,
but we take absolute value.
And this one is also interesting,
because if the error is small enough,
so within the given delta, then we consider just zero.
So we consider no error.
But greater than that, then we give the same,
all of them equal to one.
So these are the three popular criteria.
But it turns out this one is not easy to apply.
So our validation, our estimation method
was based on either this one or this one,
to get some useful estimate.
Okay, so yeah.
So quadratic cost function, this is commonly used
because it's easy, it's just like the least square.
You have analytic function,
so it's easier to derive analytic, basically.
So therefore, here, as I say,
we are dealing with random variables.
So whenever given the observation,
then we need to take the average cost associated
with the selection of a set of estimates.
This is one, based on the major data you estimate.
And then you need to see how good this is.
So now this is random,
so you need to take the average mean here,
assuming continuous random variables,
so you take the integration.
And you see here, given the observation,
so we're looking at this condition period,
it's more like the weighting, you see.
We want to see in total how much different,
but by putting the weighting here,
given things, now we have the observation.
So we add this as a weighting to see,
we integrate theta over, say,
the scale case over a certain weight.
So we'll see which one is more important,
so we see it's more likely to be near the means,
then it's more likely to enter,
where the other one will be a smaller value.
And then, now we can also measure the total average
of the various rates by averaging the cost function
of all the possible X and theta.
Here, we are thinking about we put the observation first,
then we only need to deal with theta.
But now, if we are taking for all the possible major data,
say, in the X space, and also for theta,
then, of course, your integration will be double integration
of both theta and the unknown random parameter.
So this is, you see, needed to take,
except this is more comprehensive.
You cover all the possible X also.
Then, so this is where the Bayesian can be in the prior, see.
This is the joy period, because you have both of them.
So we substitute this into this formula.
And then, after that, you can put the total integration,
that each integration, if X, you can get many,
depending on how many data you have,
and in theory, in practice, you need to integrate n times
at each of the random variables over a certain range.
So we put all of them just into one, both ways.
Similarly, for theta, if it's more than one parameter,
you have to integrate several times.
So in any case, you will see here,
the Bayesian theorem allows us to, you know,
group those, depending on both theta and X,
within this interior integration, theta.
And then, once you integrate with respect to over theta,
it will no longer be a function of theta.
So that's a very basic idea.
You integrate over one variable, then you take the average.
So this variable is a common.
You still have the theta, sorry.
The first integration with respect to theta.
You integrate with theta, then you will no longer see the theta,
but you still have X there.
So it will still be a function of X.
That's why you integrate there.
So you see here, you no longer see the theta.
The theta hat is different.
Theta hat is the one depending on the observation of the X,
but not depending on theta anymore, because theta,
we estimate the theta based on the data.
So you will become a function.
Theta hat is a function of the data,
but no function of the theta without hat, except.
And this insight is precisely what we have here.
You see?
The one, the so-called average cost,
given the observation data.
So we put what's inside here.
So now this is, the other way is you can consider first,
so it's a two-step approach.
First, we assume we measure certain observation data.
Then we treat this measured data as not printed,
so we integrate this data.
And then after that, because our actual observation also
is a random variable, then you can, again,
you see here, assume the data at a certain period it's used.
Again, because this is a total of all the X,
we integrate it again over all the possible X.
So that's how this links together as a joint distribution.
So therefore, the estimate here, coming back,
if we minimize the Bayes' risk, the one we defined early,
it will be called Bayes' estimator, based on that.
And then, so again here, the Bayes' risk,
it will depend on how you select the error,
you know, the risk function we defined early.
By choosing a different one, you will get a different estimator.
So one of them, as I mentioned, as I said earlier,
is this quadratic one.
It's the one easier to do, and this is very popular.
So this is what we call a minimum mean square error,
or ensure it's MMSE estimator.
What I do here is we try to minimize this.
Then you put, now we have the risk cost function.
But as I say, this function you need
to integrate over the possible zeta,
because it's not a fixed value.
You take a possible distribution.
And then, given the measured data,
we put this condition, you know, PDF into that.
And this is, again, similar to what we did early
in the CIOB derivation.
That's why I say the several part,
you study the early part well.
You have good understanding.
It's easier to apply it to this one here.
So therefore, you want to get minimized.
And one difficult approach is you take a derivation.
But you have to be careful.
Our derivation is with respect to this zeta hat, as you see here.
It's not the zeta here.
Because as you see here, you integrate over zeta.
After integration, it will no longer be a function of zeta.
It will be a function of zeta hat, condition of x.
So we take the derivative with this.
So you put the first order derivative inside, you see.
Now we take the derivative, assume we can exchange
the derivation integration.
You put it inside.
So this is a quadratic function of the zeta hat.
You take the derivative, bring these two down here.
And then for this zeta hat, you don't have a negative sign.
And make it equal to zero.
So again, this is, you have two term here.
You see your brain, one and then the other.
And then you also have to be careful.
We want to solve zeta hat.
And then you observe zeta hat is independent of zeta.
You can, in this integration, you can take it out.
So this zeta hat, multiply this.
Within integration, you can take it out.
But not this zeta, you see.
This zeta is no hat.
It's part of the integration.
So you have to keep this one in.
So finally, we solve this zeta hat.
So that's how this is done here.
And then PDF, even conditional PDF,
you can see with respect to this zeta.
You integrate all over all the possible range.
It's equal to one.
That's what we already know.
So therefore, our various estimate here
is just equal to the so-called condition expectation.
So based on the data here,
we estimated zeta conditioning on the major data.
So this is the expectation, also we call it means,
the posterior period of the zeta
given a set of the measurement x.
And the result right here is we do not assume, say,
any underlying period.
Just assume it has a period,
but it can be Gaussian, can be other form.
So this is very, very general.
So early on, we define quite a few, you know, cost function.
And then usually different function, cost function,
you put in your angle with different various estimator,
except the Gaussian.
Gaussian, that's why Gaussian is very special
if you're looking at Gaussian distribution.
So they all become the same.
You can see, here it all means you're corresponding to the,
in statistics we call it as a mode.
I mean, it's more like the,
later you will see this is very similar to our MLE.
We call here MAP.
You get the optimal, the so-called value
using these criteria is you're getting the mode.
Mode mean you get the maximum peak,
then the corresponding value.
But quadratic, you get the mean value, which is right here.
And if you use absolute, then you get the median,
absolute, using the absolute cost function.
So median is for those who learn image processing before
and at the same time you will see median filter.
You define the, the median is not average,
not like the mean, not the mode.
All depending on the, you're ranking those values
and then pick the one in the middle.
But for Gaussian, for stereo video,
it happened to be that all of them are the same.
So you just, you only need to get,
using one of the criteria, whatever is easiest.
Once you get one, you get the other.
So that's why Gaussian become very, very special.
So here, you should know here in the estimation theory.
So the way why we need to use the Bayesian
or want to use this approach is if you recall early,
all the other traditional estimation theory,
you cannot make good use of the prior information.
We may just assume, say, A is positive and so on,
but that's the constraint rather than you make good use of that.
But then if you are using this Bayesian approach,
you can incorporate those prime information.
Say you know the prior PDF,
so you can incorporate into the estimator.
So that's the main advantage using this Bayesian estimation.
Even if you are dealing with more deterministic unknown parameters.
So that's the main difference or, say, motivation.
Okay, so let's go through this example quickly.
We will end this part.
At least give you some head start for this topic.
So this is very similar to what we did before.
It's a simple model.
DC level in white Gaussian noise with variance sigma times 2.
But now the main difference is our DC level A here
is not deterministic, not a fixed value as we did before.
Now it's also a random variable.
And then the prior PDF here is, you see, prime.
Before we measure data, we know it's a uniform distribution
over this range from minor A0 to A0.
So therefore, from here, conditional PDF of the data,
you see here.
So conditional PDF, you need to see whether data conditional A
or A conditional on the data.
So it's easier if you know, because we know this distribution
like what we did before.
So except now if the A is random, then you have two random variables.
But assuming we fix A, you see, the A is random,
but A takes some realization within that.
For example, you take one of the value of A,
then you can treat this measure data now as a standard way
of DC in white Gaussian noise.
So in this case, the conditional PDF here is the same
as what we did before.
You see the mean equal to A, and then everything else,
like our, you know, our PDF.
Particularly if A is, you know, you take one realization,
take some fixed value.
So it will just be the PDF of the data.
So that's how this is done here.
And then the Bayes MME estimate, based on what we learned before,
is we are taking this E of expectation of the A conditional on X.
So now you have to be careful.
We are doing the other one, so this is X conditional on A.
So this is, you know, based on what we learned is A conditional on X.
But then you use the Bayesian approach.
You can see here, because we don't have the PDF of A conditional on X
based on what we have here.
But on the other hand, we have P of A here, and also a PX conditional on A.
Now you can see this can be related in this way,
so that we have already everything we need here.
And now the topic is a little bit complicated,
because we substitute something here,
then because it's a uniform distribution of a minor A0 to A0.
So we don't need to integrate from minor,
because here it's only one random variable, from minor infinity to infinity.
So because of the prior PDF of A, we can integrate over this way.
And you can see the difference between numerator and denominator is
only this A in the numerator, the rest is the same here.
So here is A, here is BA.
You cannot take this A out.
If you take A out, then you will be set, you can cancel out.
So how to handle that?
Again, you need a little bit trick to rewrite this.
So this is one summation, this is quadratic term.
You can show this.
This one you can write in the sum of this.
Why we want to write in this way?
Because for data, the data, you know,
eventually our estimator need to depend on the data only.
So we want to separate the A into the data,
because our A here is mixed.
Usually inside the power of two terms it's very hard to enter.
But if you all write into the standard way here,
this is A becomes this one fixed value.
Right here, you have the different values.
So this one you can do all this time.
You can prove, you can show out of today.
And after that, you will be simplified.
You see, we rewrite this.
And this term is a constant, you see.
In terms of A constant, you can take out,
because it's the same for both numerator and denominator.
You pull out.
Then what you let is this.
You have A here, A here, cannot.
So that's a simple way.
And out of that, you can apply some tricks
to take out this X sample mean.
And then what let is the numerator again integrate.
But the denominator, there's no way,
because this is our very standard error function.
Integrate from zero to X using this term.
Because there's no way, there's no analytic solution.
But you can do it numerically.
So therefore, this is what you can get, our A heads here.
And then you can also get the posterior period,
which is the one numerator you don't integrate.
So the denominator is still the same.
And therefore, this one is you can use similar approach
based on what you did.
Except I don't need to integrate.
You end up with this.
I think we will stop here, because there
are a lot of materials to establish.
And I just give you some idea of how this Bayesian approach
looks like.
So it means we pay you for the next week.
And you can download the assignment,
and then take a look and see how difficult or how easy
you can do it.
OK, I think I will stop here and see you next week.
Any questions?
Then you can stay back or you can email me.
Thank you.
Any questions?
Yes?
I have one more question.
Sure.
You know this.
It's estimated.
So how can we from this to this?
OK.
So first, you know how to rewrite this.
Assume this one.
This is not a negative integration.
So this one, you break this summation to this one.
You can verify.
So once you put this on, you see the both of them.
You basically substitute this term
into the sum of this term and that term.
Because this is irrelevant?
Yes, yes, yes.
So what that is, you see, so you only leave this term here.
So from here to here, there will be no problem.
So now from here to the next one is really difficult because.
So what you do here is you know for exponential integration.
If you only have the exponential raise power 2,
you cannot integrate this denominator.
But the numerator, if I subtract this x hat.
So they create, you have the same term.
Except this is power 2.
Then you also you need a in x hat.
Minus sample mean of x plus.
Now that one of them you can integrate.
So that's why you end up integrate.
Then the other one, you add the x hat.
Then you can accept x bar.
It's a constant.
Pull out.
Well, then you give you this.
So how do you get the other one is?
You add the one minus x, you get this one first.
Then what the other term is, you become the integrator.
You see x.
You change the variable.
You can integrate.
X and exponential minus x power 2.
That's how you can change the variable.
You can integrate that one.
So that's why the numerator, you can integrate into the energy one.
But the denominator cannot do that.
You don't get A here.
So you can only write this error function to do it automatically.
I will try the other one.
In your end, could I email you?
Sure, sure, sure.
Thank you.
How long does it take?
It takes a long time.
Okay.
We saw it.
Where is it?
Write clearly.
Type reform.
Let's talk please.
Okay.
Thank you, thank you.
I'm sure you thought...
S overall,
yes, of course we are technology
and the energy sources.
That's it.
And what if we add cup?
We have to add.
Then he just means that energy sources.
You need to add Roger or disagreed with it
to a robot.
I can't remember what happened.
I think it's a good idea to expand.
Can you tell us a little bit more about your experience?
Yes, I think it's a good idea to expand.
I think it's a good idea to expand.
Yes.
How much time is in the slide?
21.
I want to ask why the right-hand side is not different from in the CIRLE.
Why the right-hand side here?
CIRLE.
Yeah.
So in the CIRLE example.
This is a different topic because our...
In this last two chapters, we are dealing with random variables.
X and Y is also random variable.
So A is also random variable.
So now we have to take up...
We have the boost field of property, right?
Yes.
Okay, sure.
That's why you need to look into the concept.
So in the first chapter, I just want to clarify the notation we use here.
So...
Just to take example.
In the CIRLE, what does this mean?
This notation is property density...
Okay.
This one is...
Our A here is just a deterministic parameter.
So it's like a function of the property density function?
Yes.
It's dependent on A, right?
Our A here is a different interpretation.
Our A here is just a parameter.
A take maybe a value of...
Can take different value, one or two, but it's not random.
So in this...
It's not random, but the function of A here is dependent on A, right?
A in the sense of the mean value, the A or the coefficient change.
But it's not...
You don't interpret A here as a random variable.
So the main difference is...
In the last one, our A there is...
Random variable.
It's a random variable.
But unless you are conditioner, if you are taking the condition P there,
and you assume the A there, like our first derivation,
you will be not random.
You will be treating it similar to this.
Consider A as a deterministic...
So we consider here A is a parameter, right?
Yes, yes, yes.
A is a parameter.
Later in the second part, the detection,
we are also phasing the similar 4.1,
whether it's random or it's a parameter.
So when you talk about you adding or weighting here,
I don't know, the simple expression is like this, is that okay?
But you need to see, because for the no weighting one,
you can show they are the same.
But I'm not quite sure.
It seems no weighting one.
You can try to see.
Yes, it's just like you multiply A inside, yeah?
So from here to here, it's just this?
Like a theta hat?
You see?
You see.
Not... Let me see here.
A inside?
A inside, yeah.
From here to here, it's a theta hat?
You see?
Then maybe...
Then you take W, make sure outside,
then you've got this formula?
This symbol is over here.
I don't know, I don't know.
Yeah, maybe.
Initially I thought it would be different, yeah.
Okay.
But yeah, maybe it's the same.
You can try to see whether you explain it the same.
Yeah, probably the same.
Let me verify that.
One time I thought it was not the same.
But good, good for you to point out this.
I will verify that.
Yeah.
Thanks for reaching out.
So in an example here, right here.
In example, slice 97,
I actually want to ask,
how can we satisfy this parameter here?
Why theta hat includes both A and a variance?
Why?
Because I think the W here is just a white noise, right?
It's a white noise, so we...
As in particular implementation,
we have to care about its writing.
Oh yes, yes.
Because sometimes the value, we don't know.
So you may need estimate.
This is a very common problem in strategic.
Sometimes you don't know the value.
You need to base on the data sample to estimate.
So this is the case here.
Because the noise value is sometimes also important.
You may want to use the measure data to estimate.
This is a very practical problem, common also.
You estimate the value,
because you don't know the value
based on the measure data you can do.
I ask you a question,
because I think we only have to estimate the matrix A here.
No, matrix A is a common, simple problem.
You may...
Sometimes the variance is also unknown.
You want to estimate both.
Because it may relate to the quiz,
because we may miss out something we have to estimate, right?
Oh yes, in the exam I always make it clear
which one you need to estimate.
It's a norm.
So when you try to take the expectations of the insight,
I may miss out what you have told.
We take the expectation from this side here first,
then we take the square bit,
then we first do it in one...
Yes, it happens to be equal to A.
But you're right, you cannot take the expectation.
You cannot take the expectation inside the nonlinear function.
But is there a way to do that,
or you told us to do that, because I am?
Yes, because the way is...
Actually, I don't know how to take the expectation
within the nonlinear function.
So we just do that.
If I encounter a nonlinear function,
I take it from the inside, and I follow all the others.
No, that's not the right way to do it.
So this one is the other way.
If you do that, you happen to become unbiased,
but it's not the right way.
So in this example, you said you followed what you told us,
and if it equals A,
so you conclude that if we take the expectation of the whole value here,
it's equal to A, right?
The expectation of A here will not be equal to A,
because we don't know how to take in the square root.
There is no easy way.
So we are so-called if you do a shortcut,
which is not the right way to do it.
It happens to be equal to A.
So you conclude that it shouldn't be A,
because you are doing something wrong to get the correct result.
So the result must be wrong.
Okay, I understand. Thank you.
Okay.