I'm quite familiar with these three courses and I'm teaching two of them. On Monday, 6401,
now the 7402. But this year it happened to be probably due to too many courses and we
have quite a number of courses on the same day. That's why 6401 and 7401 happened to
be on the same Monday. But anyway, this course is on a different day. Otherwise, I cannot
teach both courses at the same time. I never taught the 7401.
So just a very quick introduction. As you can see, my name is Lin Chih-ping and the
office telephone and the email is there. So I think now it's still the edge of theory.
Over the past few days, we are talking about statistical signal processing. We also monitor
the statistics of the course registration. Now it's more stable because I'm involved
in the signal processing and machine learning MSc program. I think some of you should know
me also. Because as I said, this week is still at 12 and then some students are also in the
They may fear not sure whether they can take. So I usually, we want to try to make it slower
and also not to go into too much detail. So I hope those of you who maybe already know
this topic well, perhaps can bear with me on that. Also, I want to try to use this opportunity,
as I say, being a bit slower. I want to get some feedback from you also, say what's your
expectations and how much you fear about this course and so on. In relation with other courses,
6401, which I was teaching this Monday, and also 7401, as I say, happened to be also on Monday.
Okay, so let's start. It's time to start now. Let me just have a quick show on this because from
student point of view, they always want to know, you see, like what's the exams and the CA here is a
continuous assessment. So normally, it would be either assignment or quiz or both. So yeah,
is a very, very standard percentage in terms of percentage, except a few courses, very few in the
EE. Some other school, actually I noticed the variation is quite large, you know, so from again,
from statistical point of view, variation is a very important indicator, you see. So if you take
about percentage is one thing, that's more talking about average, but variation. So let
me explain a little bit more why. Usually for final exams, EE courses mostly follow the 60%
and 40%, but I noticed some other school, the MSc course, they have sometimes final exam only 30%,
40%, or sometimes zero, so purely based on continuous CA. And in EE, we did have a course
starting from last semester, still ongoing, 6405, the NLP, Natural Language Processing. There is no
final exam. So I saw that most students maybe want to go for that, but it turned out to be the
the, currently the class size is not that large, but because that course, every week you have the
CA, you see, continuous assessment. So it's the real meaning of continuous assessment. You cannot
miss, you cannot do it online or do it at home. If you miss day one, you will reduce a certain
percentage counting towards the final exam. Okay, so that's one thing. So final exam, usually,
you go back in the past year, we had five questions, but in the past two or three years,
you can go for four questions, four or five. So most of the paper now is four questions.
And in this course, I happen to have like two parts, which I will go into that later. So we
will have four questions equal in each part. In terms of CA, because 40%, then according to the
regulation, each component cannot be more than 20. So you see, minimum number of CA will be two,
but maximum, like just now, the early one, the every week one thing could be maximum 13, but not
that likely. But it's quite common to have three or four in other MSc course. Or we say this is
7,000 series, it's more like research student course, 7,000. Okay, so yeah, but that thing,
we only have two components, but each is, must be 20%, because it cannot be smaller than 20,
and you have two components, you don't know. So it's equal. So I already follow the path,
will be just one homework assignment. So I hope now, maybe not that easy to use the CHED GPT to do.
So yeah, anyway, let's see how it goes this year in the past, seems okay. Because this course is
only offer once per year, not every semester. I think it's not likely to repeat next semester,
but we'll see how. So for those considering, say, or you may take next semester, then may,
that may not happen. But every year, it will repeat. Okay, so I plan to do it in week six,
so that after basically, after I finish the part one, I plan to do part one in about five weeks,
depending on the progress. Because this year, at least so far, we should have over 100 students,
according to the column. Actually, more than that, maybe 180 so far, but I don't know whether,
and so on. And yeah, so we have a much larger number of students. So we do this and part two
will be a quiz for this part two, and this will be week 11. So just make it very clear so that in case
you decide to take this course and you are maybe planning some overseas trips or so on,
then you at least avoid this physical, yeah, this is in class. Okay, so it should be clear.
Any question about this? We will go into more detail later. Okay, so that's at least give you
some idea. It's quite similar to the 6401, the Vance DSP, except the 6401 is taught by two lecturers.
For this course, yeah, I should say I am the only one teaching the whole course for this one. Maybe
to make it a little bit informal, I'll give you a quick quiz from you. How many years have I been
teaching this course by myself? Can you, just a quick guess? Well, very close, so you are doing
a good parameter estimation. Yeah, estimate this. So this is one of the numbers where estimate,
although this is a very simple one, I'll just guess. Yeah, so if you already want to get the
better estimation, I mean, of course, that's research. You can, for example, do an internet
search and get the CV, then I might at least when I began to teach, you know, which course. So 15
years is about the time. And that's also when this course was proposed. We start, I think some of
you may hear from you, me, during the orientations about MSc program. We started this program many,
25 years, and that changed a lot. And initially, many years ago, there was no 7,000 series.
Everything is 6401, 6402, and so on. And about 15 years ago, we arrived, we converted this course,
initially, the same name, the same title, statistical signal processing from MSc to PhD.
And for several years, it was mainly, it was only for PhD and MSc students, not open to, at the time,
the courses are separate. MSc course for MSc students, 7,000 for PhD and MSc students. But
the class size is always very small, whether it's for MSc student or research student. So,
because I taught the 6,000 series even before this 7402 for some year, but only for part of it,
for the parameter estimation. Yeah, for that one, I taught about 20 years. And the detection one is
the co-lecturer, he resigned from NTU, then took over. So, that's been teaching this one for so many
years. Okay, so I hope at least my experience maybe will help you. Because also, this is,
this course, as you can see, is more towards mathematical. So, mathematical, not like AI or those,
you know, machine learning, it change, change a lot. This one is changing a little bit slower
Okay, so let's start now. Let's see what we have.
Okay, so you can see here, we have also mainly part one and part two later, mentioned a little
bit on part three, which is just for introductory, not for the CA and exams. So, we will have part
one starting with estimation, estimation theory, followed by the detection theory. So, these two
part follow the, we should say, actually it's two books, but we call it as the same book,
all fundamental statistical signal processing, making it volume one is one book, volume two is
another book, but the same author, it's a single author. And then, this is more recent, like reference,
but I always use these two books. And our library, I don't know whether you know, I'm not there,
all those, thank you my course. In library, once you go in the level one, you have the reserved rooms.
That one, normally it keeps the textbook where students or staff cannot borrow for too long,
so to make sure everyone is there, you can go there. So, I request, I didn't check whether
it's still there or not, it's here. Hopefully it's there. So, you can go there to take a look at these two
textbooks. And talking about, just earlier on, I told this statistical signal processing doesn't
change too much. And this one is, I get a, I won't say proof, but just evidence from this
author, K. So, this professor is an author, it's very interesting, you know, I hope you don't mind,
a little bit of small story. Some authors, they keep updating books every few years,
you know, like the first version, second version every few years. It could be up to fifth version,
sixth edition, you know, the famous guy, you know, with the book Simon Haking,
he's one of the big topic, adaptive signal processing neural network. And he publishes
every few years, now the book is probably in sixth edition, at least fifth. But this,
on the other hand, some professor, some author, they say they don't need to update. A few years
ago, I wrote to him, NTU always want newer one, so they say, oh, this two book too old,
you cannot use it for textbook. So, that's why I include this one. But then I wrote to professor,
this K, and he, the first year he's very proud, being a Westerner, gentleman. The first year,
he replied me, he said, oh, sorry, I haven't got time to edit the new book. I was also patient,
I think it was a few years back. So, the second, the next year I wrote to him again, he replied
the same using similar. Then the third year, I asked him again, say, do you have time to get
a new edition? He got impatient, he replied me, say, don't ask me again, because I don't have
time to update. And there's no need, because this book is more like a mathematical, you don't,
calculus and those, you know, very basic theory. You don't need to update, every year is the same.
So, he said, oh, I will keep this book. And that's true, you know, even by now, after how many years?
30 years, I don't see a new edition. So, this is an interesting story. This is a personal one,
also. So, let's now go to the so-called business. Let's see whether, one point,
okay. Yeah, there is, but at the end, we will talk a little bit about adaptive
signal processing just for introductions. I won't make a detail comment on that.
So, let's look at what we will have for this part one. And for part one, I use about
two thirds from the book, the volume one. So, yeah, the chapter on
like methods of moments, which I taught in the early days, but it becomes a bit more difficult.
So, I try to reduce some contents and then make it a little bit slower. That's why we have more time.
So, it covers about two thirds of the book. And I try to make the lecture know in some detail.
At least, it's easier to follow. So, even if you don't read the book, I think, mostly, you should be
able to go through. Some of the proofs I purposely leave out and then in the class, I take some time
to derive. In the past, this course is always, actually, in my memory, never had more than
60 students in the class. So, this year is at least about three times. And
in some years, the number reduced to just about 10. And instead of even empty, we go into tutorial
room. And then that was very good because I taught the 10 students. So, every week, you take time
to come up to do some derivations in certain parts. And the course is almost closed because
if you have too few students, NTU doesn't allow you to open because you're not around this course.
Anyway, it's good to survive after that. And then it's a big pity if we have time, we can
talk a little bit about the Taman filter because all this is more like the batch processing. We
do have a little bit about sequential processing, which I will include. And then roughly,
among this, about two thirds of this part is more on traditional parameter estimation theory up to
least square. And then in the end, we also introduce Bayesian estimation, which is
a little bit more mass, but I think it's quite useful. It's more related to machine learning
because you all know there's always a compare with so-called naive approach, which is the Bayesian
approach. But it's not really naive. It's one of the very important fundamental theory in
statistical and also in signal processing. So, that's what we will cover in this part.
Okay, so any questions you'd like to ask before we... Yes?
Yes.
Yeah, that's a good question. Yes. So, actually, you raise a very good question. In the
very early days when I told you before I taught this course by myself, the curriculum
when this course was for... At that time, it was called 6421. Yeah, it's a 6000 series. And it was
set as detection first and then estimation. And because that's follow what you say is from the
application point of view, from the natural application point of view, you should do that
way. You'll detect first and then do estimation. But mathematically, it turned out to be
what we will be teaching here. The detection, some of the results we use, we derive is used for the
detection part, but not vice versa. And that was why when I took over, only when I took over,
because when you follow your two lecturers, the other one used the teaching first. So,
he said, okay, we keep the sequence. And after I took over, because it's myself, so I have freedom.
I said, it's better to change to do estimation first, although a little bit against the
application. But in terms of theory, later you will see what we derive in the estimation
partially can be used in the detection. And furthermore, I also argue if you look at,
if you go back to this author, he published a book in this order, you see. You see here,
estimation theory first. And then after five years, he wrote this detection. So I say that we should
follow the author, because the author must think this is more important, more fundamental. And
it turned out to be the case, because if you learn estimation, it's more diverse. There are
several different methods and so on. And once you have a good understanding of estimation theory,
it's easier to do the detection. Of course, the detection book, I only use half, because the first
half is easier. The subsequent half is getting very difficult. So, yeah. So, actually, to assure you,
because many, particularly MSc students, they always fear it's called 7,000 series, maybe
very difficult and so on. Yes, and they try to avoid. But I will say,
most is about the same level with the advanced BSP. So, yeah, that's a 6,000 series. And it's
even easier, because these two parts, you follow the same book, the principles are quite similar.
You use almost the same, later you will see, same model, except the objectives are different. Yeah.
That's a good question. Yes. So, yeah. Later, we will show the so-called connection of these two.
But anyway, I think you all agree, you know, estimations, not just in signal processing,
because we, EO signal processing is an example, because this book, the author of the books,
he happened to be an expert researcher in signal processing. So, he also explained EO's that as,
you know, it's more like the showcase. But the estimation theory, I will say,
is more primates, you can think that way.
So, in terms of application, you can see here, you see, you can almost apply everywhere,
radar, sonar, speech, and so on. And the estimation
could be in terms of, you know, software, which you design some algorithm. It could be also
incorporated into a real hardware system. For example, in radar, sonar, and sometimes even
speech, you see, you need a system to do. And that's estimation of certain parameter, or even
waveforms. It's one of the very important part in this system. So, what I do is, you take
measurements, and then measurement is like signal in noise, later you will see.
And from there, you try to extract the useful feature. So, this thing is very
related to nowadays, you know, talk about machine learning. And except here, we are not really
going to neural networks or deep learning. It's still more the models, you know, based on
analytic approach. And examples of signal, you see, yeah, then again, let's talk about
physical walls. How do you measure the signal? Of course, nowadays, you have different sensors, and
you can do all the kinds of measurements from our daily life, like acoustic,
electromagnetic, and those. Even financial data, you see, financial data like your
like the stock market, your monitoring that, and you know, those and so on. And even interestingly,
is like mechanical vibration. And that's why every year, it seems we always have some student,
PhD student coming from other school, like MAE and civil engineering. Because they say, oh,
their research, you know, really, you know, applying this estimation theory or statistical
processing into the, you know, some of the vibration data or earthquake. So, you see here,
there's more geophysics. And yeah, and of course, you know, there's poll and survey data.
Some of the data are not continued time. Also, we are used to continue time data, and we do,
we say we use sampling theory to get to compare to discrete time signal, but not necessarily.
If, for example, some of the finance data we receive is already in discrete time format,
poll and survey, you know, nowadays, the US going to the president election, so they keep conducting
those things. And yeah, and so even in the more biomedical, you see, you have the genes or,
it's more in the bioinformatics, gene expression. So there you can apply those parameter estimations.
And then, if, as you can see from the, or understand from the title of this
call, you know, we start with statistical signal processing. So it's very natural to
link into random signal or random process. And that's also the reason in the past, they always
have a very small class size because it's not easy unless they, at the same time, learn the
probability and random process. And that's true because if you're
not considering noise, you see, but your measure is more almost accurate. So if you are doing
accurate measurement, then to estimate parameter is somewhat easier. And yeah, so that's why
here our Samsung is, Samsung is always have noise. The question is, how big is the noise? How you
categorize this noise? And of course, you all know noise, you must model using
random variable because it doesn't make sense to say, oh, noise is a deterministic signal.
That was why I was a tutor. Actually, not today, today is Wednesday. Yesterday I had a class
undergraduate, because here usually we need to teach both postgraduate and undergraduate.
And the undergraduate course is also called signals and system. You know, those attending my
advanced DSP, I relate that. And year two student, then there we were talking about different
kind of signal. We say, oh, you have the random signal. And sometimes in the classification of
signal to test them about the quiz, a very simple test every week. There is a 15 minutes we call
IRAA. And then the question is a multiple choice. One question, they give a sideway or give some,
you know, like a unistep function. They ask students five choice, all function, even function,
energy or power and so on. And there is a, there is one of the answer is the random. And some
students they don't know, they select random. Then I get them a hint, I say, oh, random signal
is not at your year two undergraduate level. Basically, you can almost show there is
undergraduate level, at least year two, we don't deal with random. So don't choose
random. I give them a little bit of hint. But here is the opposite, you see? Everything is random.
Okay. So we may have deterministic signal in random noise. Or sometimes in later part,
we also consider random signal in random noise. So you need to build in this concept. We are
dealing with a ringed, noisy measurement. And so our approach here is among those,
because you have noise, then the measurement are not accurate in the sense of, you know, your
noise, you have some contamination. So you need to try a way to reduce noise. And at the same time,
try to extract the useful information. So that's how the meaning of estimation
is being applied here. So, okay. So for example, again, this is the daily
life example. You are very anxious or pay attention to very sensitive to your body weight.
So, for example, every day you take your own weight. Nowadays, very easy at home. You have a
very simple scale just in the bathroom. So your measure every day, say, it will not be exactly
the same. I'm not sure. Even, yeah, 69.9, 70.1, and so on. So this is very, you know, very common.
And then with that, you'll try to see what is your true weight. Because if you are
reporting to the doctor, you know, very recently, for new student, you have the medical check. But
there, you only do one measurement. Then you know that one. But that may not be your true weight.
Okay. So the question here is, at least over a certain time, maybe one month, we'll see
whether we can estimate our true weight based on the measurement. And the amount there is how much
committed in your estimate. For example, the very easy one is you just sum all of them together,
take the average. But so the estimate one, you'll get whether this is the true reflection of your
weight or there is some false alarm or there are some outliers there and so on. So that's why
we want to see how much is the variation, you see, to see. Not just the so-called estimate value,
the average. Typically, very often, we use the mean value. But then after getting the means,
that's not enough. How much is the variation? And then, furthermore, if we have more measure
data, whether the variation of the estimate will decrease so that give you the more reliable.
And that was right from the beginning, you see. Not just the average, but the variation is
very important. And that's more or less the basic questions or the important question.
We are going to study this in this course. Now here, there is a more
real-life example. And there's also some more link with detection also.
Yeah. And it happened to be my research also, not fully on this, but I did some research,
at least, in radar and sonar systems. So we have a good understanding of this topic.
Actually, one of the projects is really down to earth project that we work with the ministry of
defense in Singapore. And then we bought a very expensive radar, and went all the way to the
to the western side of Singapore. NTU is already in the west, but not the far west. I don't know
whether you heard of this. Tuas, Tuas is more like southwest further down. NTU is very close
to west, but if you go further down to the industry part, there you will see
some very remote place. Then we carry the radar to measure the UAV. Maybe next week I can show you
some of the radars and some of the data we take there. So this is what we have is
in the radar system, we have a transmitter. I guess most of you, if not all, most will be
in the engineering side. A few, maybe your background, maybe a primate, but the majority
engineering. So you should know the rear transmitter and the send out signal. It's a
physical one. And after that, the purpose is of course not to just play around with doing some
useful stuff. Typically, you try to detect certain targets. And then the target,
you know, like the RF, typically it's RF signal, you hit the target and that's the one you'll be
echoed, bouncing back, and that's our so-called de-zai signal. So here, again, this is a
very good justification as what I say early. If we do not have noise, you see,
a very clean signal. You see, I send out, hit the target, it comes back. Should have almost
very similar waveform. It may be reduced, but still, you know, if we send out a continuous wave
or even an impulse, what you'll get back will be a similar waveform. So that's very easy. We don't
need much detection or estimation to do. What you'll do is just, probably the signal getting lower,
then you'll be there. But however, in the real world, you know, we have all this
so-called interference and noise, which we all can see the noise, echoes from other objects,
and that's very common. You do your project facing the real world, you know, not to select,
I'm not talking about laboratory. In the lab, you can say, oh, I placed this target there,
then everything makes the room very quiet, no other interference. That way, measure that
that signal. That's okay, but you go like what I did. Yeah, as I said, next week I'll remember to
bring, actually, in my USB, I will see during the period. So what you'll see is a real signal. You
cannot avoid, as I said, let other people go away, no. So that's why you have other echoes from other
objects that are coming. And sometimes these echoes are not the one we want. It may be even
larger than that, so that causes a big challenge. And there will be other external noise here,
and then even the receiver itself. Your receiver may not be the ideal one. You will have some noise
and also. So it turns out to be you can broadly say we have the ideal signal in noise.
So after that, this is what we are trying to extract. And assuming, of course,
we will later come back to the detection part. Assuming we are doing the estimation,
we already have the feeling the signal should be there. So we can do the estimation of range,
velocities, and bearings, bearings in the direction of arrivals. And some others. So this is
one of the main purposes of using the radar and sonar. And, of course, you can also do it from
image processing or video processing point of view. That's another way. But here we are more
or less assuming the signal is more or less a 1D signal in the time series rather than
image. That's another topic. Although some of the ideas could be similar. So this gives you a
picture and also highlights why we need to consider noise because in real world,
any measured data will be a signal in noise.
And then come back to our aims of this estimation theory. Here we try to learn some techniques and
some theoretical frameworks for the estimation of either disturbance and system parameter.
Those are related to the system. Just now I mentioned in real world, we always have signal
and system. These two are related but not the same. Why? Because, for example, if those are
disturbance and system parameter, channel parameter, for example, I'm not sure. Every
year taking this class, we have students or PhD students or math students from the communication
engineering area. So there, channel parameter is very important. And channel parameter is
your link to the system. It's always there. It's not from the signal. It's from the system,
except all the channels. On the other hand, we also have signal parameter,
which is the signal may be there, the signal may disappear. So it's on and off. For example,
amplitude, you know, you've been talking about side wave amplitude, frequency, time delay,
topa, baling, and so on. All these are related to just signal and waveforms, not from image or
video point of view. We are not looking there. And then furthermore, there is going forward,
you can even estimate signal waveforms, which is one step forward. If you look at the book
in the last chapter, it's called Kalman Filter. Kalman Filter is estimate signal waveforms.
And that's how this, yeah, this, you need a little bit more advanced theory, because you can
combine like some system theory. And that's, again, there's another PhD or
7000 series offered by the control people. You have the 7204. So don't get confused with
our colleges, 7402. The other one, linear system. Currently, the size is about the same.
We are against sister courses. Yeah, I gave you a little bit of a
linear story. And that's, you know, there's one or two years ago, this course, the
exam hall, because the class size is small, then the exam hall have these two courses to do
exam together. And then I'm the examiner of 7402, and another professor is 7204.
And we, at the beginning, we're lucky we went early. And also, I'm a little bit more
careful. Usually, I check. And suddenly find out the aiming people, those aiming people,
they mix these two, you know, they only brought the 7402 paper, they forgot the other one. So I
say, okay, no, these two courses are different. The name looks very similar, 7204. Well, here,
it's 7402. So luckily, called the other people, then they deliver the exam paper. And this
finally solved the problem before the exam start. And there, you will need to learn the
state space model, because common field is, you must learn state space. And from there, you
build up this signal polarization or control theory. It's combined together. But
we are not going to go into that part in this course. Okay, just let you know for some of you,
I think in the end, it depends on the time. If I have time, I will try to give some
introduction. It should be possible. Okay, now coming to the starting point, a little bit more
technique, we need to make some assumptions and notation. I'll say mostly throughout the course,
but there may be certain part, they may use some slightly different notation, but
not to worry too much. It's mostly we are consistent. So here, our observation is we are
assuming like discrete time signal. Our measure data is not like the continuous waveform.
So we are taking finite samples. So we can put it as a vector. And as I say,
most of the time, we are dealing with one D-signal scalar. So you put all this together into a vector.
At the end, we may consider special case where one sample itself is a two by one vector.
That's not common. And then similarly, now we also have a vector of parameter.
Usually, we always start with a simple case where you have a single parameter.
Then it's easier. And then after that, we extend to two or usually it's multiple. And that's A.
For the observation of data, typically we have several N. But in some special case like the
detection, we can start from just one measure data. So you have to be careful. For example,
particularly in the exam paper, you have to read carefully whether it's a single data sample
or multiple. And also how many parameters. So these are important.
So these are the very basic assumptions. Measure data, vector of parameter, we're going to estimate.
And then now based on the measure data, you see. So our study here looks like very simple.
Based on the metadata, we try to estimate this true parameter. Because the data doesn't tell you
how this parameter looks like. It's hidden there in the data. So we use the head. The theta is the
true one. You use the head. That means we estimate that. And since we're based on the data,
you see. So it's a function of X. And yeah, that's how this is formulated. And how to do that,
then there are several ways. And which one is better or so on. That's another question. So that's
the technical detail. But in terms of the aim, it looks quite simple. So now the next question is,
once you have this estimate, how good is this? I would really say you measure your body weight and
then you simply just guess or take the average and so on. So you want to have some competence,
some so-called metrics. Nowadays in machine learning, you use one, you can have two. Accuracy
and then depending on which area you'll be dealing with. So here, the very simple
performance measure here is the estimation error here. And this is the estimate, this is the true
one. So we want to see how big it is. Just a simple subtraction. And then remember, our data
is like the random, at least contain noise. It's partially, well, we can say it's random.
If you all have a deterministic signal plus random noise, then of course we say this
combined together, it will be a random signal. Even so, you have the deterministic part because
always when you describe a signal or function, we always use the more so-called complicated one,
because deterministic part is easier compared to the random one. So that's why this is a random
quantity. As I say, in the first several weeks, maybe four weeks, we will consider
the parameter here as deterministic. They are not random. So even so, this vector is deterministic.
We have this one is random. Your estimate is based on random vectors, so it will be not
deterministic. So therefore, the error itself is a random quantity. So you need to keep this in mind.
You will need to study further. And then another very useful one, so this basically measures the
variation. So this is just to tell you how big will be the error. So now since we are, later you
will see we need to take the expectation because this is a random quantity. So this is,
you also need to be very clear about dimension. And that's why I introduced maybe today or
some other time. I will talk about linear algebra because that's very important. Vector and matrix
is unavoidable in this course. So you can see here this is a column vector. This is a row vector.
So this is an inner product. So inner product except before you take the expectation,
it will still be a random variable, but it will be a scalar. However, once you take expectation,
anything random after taking the so-called average or expectation, the mean, it will become
a no random anymore. It will be a deterministic number, and that's why it becomes a single number.
So it's very important, this E here, denote the expectation value, or we say this is you are doing
the expectation operation. So don't overlook that. We'll go through that later. Actually, in this
course, both part one and part two, you will see everywhere we apply this E. So expectation,
just simply you are taking the mean value. Okay, then how are we going to characterize?
As I say, how good is estimate? The first one is bias, and then the second one is consistency.
Consistency, then the third one is efficiency. So don't get confused. The efficiency is here.
It's not the computational efficiency. We'll talk about this later. Although it's the same
in English, but different meaning. Bias is very easy. It looks like some student initially confused
with this estimation error here. Here we take the estimator and then directly take the sum.
So it's random. Bias is different. Here, sometimes for convenience, we don't put bracket x. We just
simply use theta hat. So we do the expectation on this first, then subtract the true parameter
vector. So this is called bias. So the difference is one is this E, the other you don't have.
And now in this case, this is no longer a random signal. Remember, a random variable or random
vector. After you take expectation, become no random. And then for this first few weeks,
this is no random. Therefore, this is no random. Therefore, if it is possible,
the result here could be zero. Because you are talking about two deterministic vectors.
So there's no random. Therefore, if it happens to be zero, it means the expectation of this
random quality vector is the same as theta. So we call this unbiased. But going back, if you are
talking about this, then you can never say this is zero. You always get a no zero one. It could be
occasionally zero, but because a random variable is something that keeps changing. And then that's
why if you measure this estimator error, you have to take the expectation to reduce this randomness.
But here, it makes sense. So that's the starting point. Bias, whether it's biased or unbiased,
you take the expectation of this estimate first. For estimation, you do it one time,
you get one estimate. You do it again next time, you will get another one. They are not exactly
the same. They can never be exactly the same. It may look similar. Remember, it's a signal plus noise.
Signal plus noise. So the noise keeps changing. You don't expect the noise will behave
sideways. Not possible. So that's one thing. So for this one, it's a measure of how close
the estimate is to its true value in the sense of the average.
So the bias estimate usually depends on the number of observations. I'm talking about if
your estimate is not unbiased, if it's biased, then we have to consider it will be a function of the
number of observations. So it depends on how much you estimate. And in the case of
web files, but the files may go to zero if your observation number increases. So you keep
estimating more and more. That's why here we have another measurement, the performance measure,
called asymptotically unbiased. That means it's biased if you have a finite number of data. But
when the number of measured data increases to infinity, then this bias approaches zero.
That's asymptotically unbiased. Ideally, we hope we have unbiased ones. Just use finite number of
data samples. But if that cannot be achieved in some cases, it's okay. We can go by asymptotically.
Average of many unbiased estimates will be close to the actual value.
But however, the estimate is less error than the bias one. So maybe at this point I will
try to illustrate a little bit. So let me see how we go. This one is working.
Let me turn to this one.
Okay, looks like
the
X star
is working.
Seems not to work.
Early on I tested, it seems working. I don't know why.
I think I can try to explain using, yeah. So the main purpose here is, for example,
we are just talking about the simple case where the parameter, you have just one parameter,
which is more like a DC value. The DC value is a constant. Based on our measured data,
we try to estimate this DC value. But because our measured data is noise, so each time you estimate,
you may not get exactly this value. You may be, say, the DC value is five. Your first one is, say,
4.5. The next one is 5.5 and so on. Then the subsequent one is 4.8. The other one,
go to the other side, 5.2. Then you will expect in this case, you see, after you take many
measurements, you'll take the average. The average is what we call the E of this, the expectation of
this estimate. It happens to be, take the average, you will be fine. Then in that case, we get the
unbiased estimate. You will be good. However, we may have the average value, which is the same as
unbiased, meaning it will be the same as the true value. But the variation can be quite big in the
case. For example, it can be minus 10, 10. The next value will go down to, say, minus five and five
or so on. Sorry. This is what I'm trying to say. If the DC value is zero, we estimate the zero
means. Or in the early example, five, then you see minus four, for example, and minus four. Then
you'll be low. How much is below five? You'll need nine. Then you can go to the other one. Five plus
nine will be 14. So you add together, divide by two, you'll get five. But the fluctuation is very big.
So you may have the mean value is unbiased, but if the variation is very, very big,
in this case, maybe I will get the biased one, which is very close to five, say 4.9, for example,
very consistent, very close. Then at least we have some commitment is very close to the true one,
although there is a small bias, but the variation is very small. So it depends on how you measure
that. In any case, what we'll be dealing with is we need both to be, ideally, it will be unbiased
and then small variation. That's how we will be talking in this course.
Let's quickly go through other measures before we take a break. Consistent is
the mean square estimation error, 10 to 0, and when the number of observations becomes large.
So remember, we define this. Because as I mentioned here, if you don't take the expectation,
this inner product is always greater or equal to zero, although it's a random. A random signal,
it can be always on one side. Random, it can be 0.1, 0.5, and 10, and so on. It will never go
down to negative. However, if the expectation of this, when the number gets bigger and bigger,
the number of observations, then it is possible it becomes 0. So in that case, we say this is a
consistent estimator. That means in the same group. What we need to do is just keep the
data getting bigger and bigger, then we will have more and more competence. That's one very
important measure. Therefore, it means accuracy increases. As I was saying, the estimate is also
asymptotically unbiased. On the other hand, if you have an inconsistent estimate, then
it's not very certain. Because if you have not enough data, then we are not quite sure
how good is this estimate. In this case, you may also have problems. Even if you have more
observations, it doesn't help to reduce the value. So that's very important. Finally,
we come to efficiency. Here, it's not computational efficiency. We are comparing with the benchmark
quantity, which we call Cramarov's lower bound, or CILB. In some other books or papers,
we just simply call it CRB. Because the CRLRB is always the lower bound. Some people argue,
no need to lower. The bound means lower bound. This is one of the very useful benchmarks. We
will explain one chapter just focusing on CRLRB. Why? If you assume you have an efficient estimate,
then in that case, the CRLRB is the greatest lower bound. Therefore, that means no other estimate
has a smaller mean square error. That means it's already the best. It's a benchmark.
Whether you can estimate, you can achieve that or not. If you can achieve, you're done. Remember,
I said there may be several different methods to do it. If you already get the best one, then
you don't need to do it. However, if you cannot achieve that, then you may want to try
find a better one, or you may stop after the errors are reduced to a certain percentage.
You are satisfied. We will go into that later because this is a very important one.
However, for many practical problems, we don't have an efficient estimate.
Wherever you try, you will never achieve this theoretically optimal one. He thinks the CRLRB
is the ideal case. In practice, we often don't have the ideal situation, so you need to see
where you're going to stop. Nevertheless, CRLRB is very useful benchmark. That's why
research papers typically, if possible, you can get CRLRB. You always use that as a benchmark.
Okay, so that's summarized what we have discussed so far. First question, how close is the estimate
to true value? Then, whether there are better estimators than the ones we've chosen.
Because what you get is if you cannot meet the CRLRB, then that means it's probably not the best,
but we are not quite sure. We want to see how to get a better one, or if possible.
Then, we're dealing with random variable. Therefore, the performance here,
it can at best, you can completely describe it statistically. In that case,
random variable, the best description is if you know the probability density function,
that's the best you can describe. You can't describe it as using a deterministic number,
because it's random. You need to take this in mind. Then, also, even many years ago,
this is mainly from the books. If you can't get the theoretical result, you may say,
nowadays it's common, particularly deep learning. You always say, oh, I do simulations. Sometimes,
it works, but if you cannot prove it, you still don't have at least
a theoretical proof showing that's always the best, because you cannot rule out that maybe
someday another method can do better. So, in that sense, computer simulation,
at least, it can show some good justification, but you cannot 100% use it to prove. That's why
quite often my students or researchers, they write papers. They say, do experiments and prove this.
I always ask them, don't use proof, because if some reviewer like me,
I will say your statement is not correct. It's true. We have been running some simulations,
even if you run 100 times, 1,000 times, using multi-color simulations, you cannot prove.
So, what about I run 10 times more compared to you? Then, suddenly, some
bug or some problem may come up. Also, another very important trade-off is
between performance and computational complexity. Here, the complexity is what we often use,
computation efficiency. It's more common, but since, as I mentioned in this course, efficiency means
another sense, so we use computational complexity. You may have a very good
method, optimal, but it takes forever, days or months, then you cannot use it in practical
verification. This is also not very good. Sometimes you need to get suboptimal estimator,
if that's reasonably well, but easier to implement. As I said, the first week, I get
very slow, so we only take 12 pages. Then, we take a break here, maybe not a long one, and then
after that, we will go through some of the, as I say, PDF probability density function, which
some of you may already know, but some may be new. I won't go into too much detail, and then
we will continue into maybe chapter two today, but not in depth, just a very simple introduction.
Anyway, you decide on whether this course is suitable for you, but nowadays for MSc students,
there are a lot of other courses to choose from, not like the first day or two where
most students panic, but now if you look at the course registration website, you have quite a
few courses. Even the waiting list is not that long anymore. Anyway, I hope you are now in a
better situation. We have a clock at the back, so maybe now it's 7.49, we take 16 minutes.
Come back at 5 past 8 if you want to continue. I'll see you after the break.
Our course here, we usually take just one break in the middle.
Okay, so let's continue here.
Okay, as I said, today we will go slower and go through, not in detail, but just at least
I'm preparing you for some of the important PDFs, probability density functions. What we are
looking at here, there are random variables, there are two types. One is discrete, and the other one
is continued. For PDF, we will refer to those continuous random variables.
Okay, good. So this is one of the very important PDFs, or we should say the most important at
least in textbooks, because Gaussian PDF is maybe the easiest one to handle. And also
one very important feature is if you extend Gaussian random variable into a vector case,
you can steer this quite nicely. Most of the properties will be preserved, and even in the
case you have not independent Gaussian random variable, you can still use the
analytic format to describe. Otherwise, other random variables, once you have correlations
or not independent, they will become very complicated. So let's see what's the Gaussian
PDF. Sometimes we call it normal, so that's another meaning. And for scalar, you will be
a normal vector, just a scalar random variable. Then the PDF here is, we use a single scalar
variable, x, to describe. x is a real variable. And PDF here is an exponential function where
you only need two parameters. One is the mean, you see. Okay, mean is here. And the other,
so don't get confused, we use the power of two. Sigma power of two will be the variance,
so you need to write both together, not to separate. Because sometimes if you just write
sigma, it will be the standard deviation. So variance refers to sigma power of two.
And then because we call it normal, you can use this paragraph, capital N, to describe also.
Because the whole PDF, you only have two parameters. One is the mean and variance,
so it completely describes this PDF. Of course, the other one, pi, or so on,
the exponential is a function, you all know. So those are not the parameter. What we have is
only these two. And here we use this symbol, mean is distributed according to this. So try to get
familiar with some of this. And sometimes in the special case, we quite often here, we use,
we are talking about zero means. So zero mean mean is mu equal to zero. And that's similar,
quite often we talk about measure the data in circuit and so on, we say the DC value. So
mean is in a sense more like a DC value. If you have zero mean, that mean the DC is zero. So
every other signal, it will go up and down. The average is zero. And if the standard deviation,
the variance here equal to one, then it's the same. Variance and standard deviation
only equal when you both equal to one. Then we call this PDF as standard normal PDF.
Okay, so at this standard. And this is MATLAB. I think NTU still provides this free MATLAB.
So now it's less, more and more people using Python, particularly for deep learning. But
traditionally, MATLAB is still very useful, but you need to pay certain fees.
So on top of that, we have a cumulative distribution function. On Monday, some students
also asked what's the difference by adding this cumulative. So cumulative means you start
you start from minor infinity. So all the way up to one particular value. Because this upper limit
x, it can also change. You can be, you make it as two, then you integrate up to two. If x becomes
five, they integrate to a longer interval. So somehow just like,
a big similar for those who are familiar with the circuit, it's just like capacitor. It stores your
your
energies in the device. And then this is
what they call cumulative from minor infinity up to this point. And assuming in this case,
the miracle of g low and sigma, the value equal to one, you simplify into this.
And very often particularly in the detection, the second part, we have another more convenient
description. We call it the right tail probability. Right tail, of course you can get the meaning,
it's on the right side. And tail is the one towards the other side. So you see here, it's
opposite. Here is minor infinity up to x. Where this one, starting from x, then we are looking at
the tail. And of course you will see if you add these two, assuming the same x, it will be equal
to one. And therefore these two related by this. So that's very important function we need to
remember. And then assume, now assume we have this right tail
probability. And if evaluate this gamma value, then if this happens to be equal to
p, then we can of course determine if p is given, we can determine this by,
not analytically, because this integration is you can't really do it analytically,
but at least numerically you can evaluate that. So this part later in the detection
theory, we will use it very often. So therefore from here you can get the inverse, once p is
given, get this. And we call this q inverse, it will be an inverse function. But this function
analytically is not there. So now this is give you a
visualization of how this part is a CDF and the other part is the right tail. So the further
the x becomes bigger, because this part becomes smaller. So on the other hand, the cumulative
CDF, the more you go, the value gets bigger as you are accumulating both.
And then there is very useful property for Gaussian, you know,
co-economic. In the case of mu equal to zero, then it's moment, I guess, do you know how to define
moment? A random variable, you raise to certain integer order, say power of two,
power of one is just except, then it will be the expectation of mean. If you go to two, then
it's second order moment, or you can just simply call it second moment. And if n, then it will be
n's moment. And if you have the mean value case, then this becomes very easy. For even order,
it will be one multiplied by three multiplied by five and so on. Because n equal to one, sorry,
n equal to two, it will give you the variance. And we are talking about
yeah, the variance here. So you just one multiplied by this
variance here, n equal to two, and so on. Four, you have multiple of this. And n equal to all,
then it's zero. Why? Can you guess why this is zero? Any quick answer? We are talking about
Gaussian and zero mean. Yes, very good. Even symmetry. If you're even, sorry, even
symmetry and then zero mean, you see. So you are evaluated by the first order,
it will be just equal to mean. And then order three, you can do also the integration.
The variable itself is like all function. So you take the mean value, it will be zero.
Third order, second order, then second order can never be zero. It's always positive. You get some
deviation, variance, and so on. And then if in the case of not zero mean,
it's more complicated, you need to explain this, then you also get this analytic formula.
But this is a little bit more difficult to remember. This is easy. It becomes a function of both
mu and then you can make good use of this. And the moment,
yeah, so that means this is, the center is not zero. So moment, we refer to
x raise to the power of n, where here is more general.
And then the very useful one here is multivariate Gaussian. So this is why Gaussian is used so
frequently, particularly if you are looking at some papers and so on. Because nowadays for
dealing with a practical problem, you always have multiple parameters or multiple variables to
handle. So you cannot avoid like vector analysis. But however, remember here, our noise, you also
assume they will come with every entry, every element. So in double ways, you are dealing with
the noise matrix. And for Gaussian, there is no problem. You can deal with a multivariate
Gaussian PDF of n by 1 random vector by putting this nicely, the PDF of this data in this form.
But remember here, this PDF itself, you see, it's still a scalar, you know. Don't get confused,
you see. We are measuring, we are dealing with a random vector. But the PDF itself,
where our PDF is referring to try to deal with the joy, the joy behavior of this random vector.
So we consider there are so-called interactions and so on. So it still ends up with
scalar functions, you see. It's not a vector PDF, okay. P of x equal to this. Because you can see here,
determinant of matrix, you see, then becomes a scalar. And this is scalar. The exponential of this
also becomes a scalar. We have a matrix in the middle. This is column matrix, this is a row
matrix, row vector. Then it ends up with this exponent itself. It will be scalar. I think
it's a little bit problem. Next, we will begin to draw some
illustration and so on. When we come to vector matrix. Therefore, this
meal here is a mean vector. You have a random vector, you can take the mean vector by taking each of
the element. Each element is one random variable and take this one. So it can be zero, can be no
zero here. Assuming no zero in general. And then the covariant matrix is the one, you see, where
removing the means. So the mean in something, as I say, you can interpret that as a DC value.
When you measure the voltage, you can always subtract, remove the means. So in a sense,
we typically try to do that. That's why this covariant matrix is your, yeah, so this is an
outer product. This is an inner product. This is more like an outer product. Your style is
column vector first, now derived by a row vector, becomes a matrix. On the other thing, you become
a scalar. So this is always assuming to be positive definite. And that's another very
important concept. We will discuss that later. And then we'll have the inverse of this
matrix. So you can take the inverse. And in this case, we say it is a random vector for all this
distribution, this normal distribution. So very nicely, we only need the mean vector and the
covariant matrix. Remember for the scalar case, we need a value, just one value right here. It's a
matrix. And we take expectation. So this covariant matrix except it's not random. So in this course,
you always remember which variable or which quantity is random, which one is not random.
Not random means deterministic. So don't get confused. And that's also why in
assignment one, I will try to test students this very basic concept.
Okay, so let's move on. This chi-square one, chi-square or we call it centros
PDF, is the one we, again, the detection theory, we use it very often. So this is the
formula. And for chi-square PDF, we need to define the degree of freedom. So that means
how high is the degree of freedom? This is a parameter. So again, this PDF here,
depending on, it's only on one side. The positive x, you have a proper description. Looks very
complicated. You don't need to memorize it. It's for nature. But we also need this gamma
function here. But for negative x, it's zero. So you only, it only means a node zero for this
x take positive value. And we use the symbol, you know, this, so indicate the degree of freedom,
or call DOF here. Okay, so this is how you're going to do. Then we, here we're assuming this is an integer
with greater or equal to one, starting from one. And this function is a gamma function here.
And this gamma function in the case of integer, integer value here, it certifies this
formula. Starting from one over, if one over two, it will be equal to this value. And then you can
get it recursively. You see, starting from previous value, then you go to the next one.
And then for integer, if n is integer, then it becomes this formula, which is very easy to
remember. And if you do a plot, as I said, you can get the same result. So you can get
the same result. So you can get the same result. So you can get the same result.
And it becomes this formula, which is very easy to remember. And if you do a plot, as I say,
the central one, you see, so chi-square is the central one, which refers to zero means,
and the non-central one. So you only need to plot on the positive x on one side. But this side is
zero. Again, you use a mallet, you will see this. Then the degree of freedom is small,
it's very sharp. Starting from high, then all the way go down, zero. When it gets bigger and bigger,
then it becomes rather small, rather flat. And the wide way of this chi-square PDF,
this one is also very often related to the communications. It will be,
depending on the degree of freedom, as you remember, we have these parameters here. So
simply it's a sum of the independent and identical distribution, or call it IID.
So each of these variables is following this normal standard, normal Gaussian distribution.
And you are square it first, and then sum them together to generate another new random variable.
And you can verify, or just try to derive,
E of this happens to be the degree of freedom. And also nicely, the value of this
equals to twice of this. So this is a very useful property you can have.
And then, in the special case of this degree of freedom equal to two, then we have
rather simplified exponential PDF. That will be a special case where you can see here,
it simplifies a lot by, say for example, if this equal to two, then we're looking at gamma one.
So gamma one here is equal to one, if you look at this. It's all in digital.
And then if this equal to two, then one minus one becomes zero. And then any number
raise to the power of zero becomes one. So more or less this part becomes like a constant.
And you only need to look at this. So that's a very useful special case. We call that as
exponential PDF, which is equal to this.
And then, furthermore, we can also work on this right-tail PDF for this chi-square,
central one. And you follow this formula, but don't forget to indicate this.
Then right-tail means you integrate from x up to this infinity large. You will get this.
And however this becomes very complicated, if you are trying to write down,
you need to separate into this equal to one, then all, all number, or integer, or even integer. So
each looks very messy. We will not go into detail for this discussion. And next we look at the
null-sensure chi-square one. So this becomes much more complicated. Null-sensure means we still
define as sum of each of the random variables, raise to the power of two, then sum them together.
But however, each of these random variables, they're independent, but
the mean is no longer zero. So that means null-sensure means null zero.
So in this case, we have another so-called null-sensure parameter to measure. Summing all these
square means, sum together, we call it lambda here. And then in this case, the PDF itself even also
becomes very complicated. Also for if x greater than zero, you have this. And now we introduce
another function, which is modified basal function of the first chi-end, or the R.
So you see here, we involve this here. So you can see the PDF becomes very complicated. And you
are not expected to memorize this. So don't worry about that.
So only in the later detection part we will go back to it. And then the Rayleigh distribution,
this is quite useful in the communication area, quite often. And how do we get this?
So again, we start with this zero mean IID random variable. But only have two.
Square, sum together, then take the square root. So in this case, we have a PDF, which is again,
just measure the positive x here. And this is not too complicated. It's more or less like the
Gaussian exponential signal, but exponential function. But you need to multiply this x here
also. So it's a product, but still manageable. For negative x, it becomes zero. So you have this.
And finally, we look at the uniform PDF. So uniform means within that interval, the PDF
will take a constant, just like one, like the DC value, horizontal line, but only within that
segment. Outside this interval becomes zero. So far, all of these available, we are assuming is
continuous, that means x. Even so, it may take a segment, but it's thanks. It's not countable.
You cannot say number, like one, two, three, four, five. There are always thanks and continuous.
Then in this case, you can also very easily get the expectation, which is just take the middle
point between A and B. And variance is, this is the interval, the size of the interval,
squared divided by 12. You can always get this, at least for the simple one, such as Gaussian or
uniform distribution, use the formula. Of course, you also remember how to get the means and the
expectation. I hope you know this very basic definition, and you can derive this also by
yourself. Okay, so any question before we look into this chapter two? Chapter two is a basic
part of this whole estimation theory.
So far, it's all easy. Let's look at now how we are going to deal with minimum variance and unbiased
estimation. That's how this, in the part one, and this in the classical or traditional
parameter estimation theory, we're always trying to achieve this.
Doing it, making the estimation unbiased first, and now with that, we minimize the
variance of the estimate. So it looks like simple, but this is what we want to achieve. It depends on
how the data behaves. You can become very complicated or can be very simple. So this is
the way we want to try to get a good estimate. It may not be very optimal, but at least it looks
like it meets our objective from the beginning. So how good is it? On average, it will yield
the true parameter value. That's the definition of unbiased on average. Not necessarily require
infinity of very large data. We are hoping unbiased means you have a finite measure data.
And also at the same time, we are trying to achieve the same thing. So we are trying to
achieve the same thing. So we are trying to achieve the same thing.
And also at the same time, it gives the least variability. If possible, as I say,
the oscillation will be as small as possible. It cannot be zero, because if zero, totally zero,
then that's no noise. That's not our objective in this course. So it's small. Make it very small.
That's why we use this short form, MBUE, minimum variance, unbiased estimator.
That's how we are trying to do. Before that, we look at a simple example to start with.
I should say this is probably the easiest model we have in this one. Later, we will
come back to this again and again for a simple case. Let's look at what we have here. We have
the measured data. And you have the deterministic part. This is the parameter. We are going to
estimate the sum of A in noise. So what is the noise? Zero means Y Gaussian noise.
So that's how this stuff is. So don't get confused. Our measured data is a discrete sample,
because in total, typically we hear we start from zero. So if you have a capital N sample,
up to n minus 1, zero, one, two, three, and so on. But the noise except
follows Gaussian distribution. It will be a continuous random variable. So that means
zero mean. That means this Gaussian noise except the value is take any values from minus infinity
to infinity. But how high the chance of getting this random variable, the noise, to take a very
large value is very small. Because remember our Gaussian curve, you always remember it's like this.
Like a bell curve. That's right. You know, like the exams, we always ask whether the exam result,
the mark will follow Gaussian curve. Yeah, typically, yes, if the student's number is large enough,
we will see most of the students are near the mean value, where some very good one, very few,
to the other side. The other very poor one, the other side. But sometimes it doesn't appear in that
way. It could be mixed Gaussian. I mean, you have two peaks. Those are not very good. But they are
not towards the end. You're dividing to say, for example, if 60 is the mean value, from zero to 60,
maybe the average is 40. Then the other side, 60 to 100, the average may be 80. So it all depends.
But that's how Gaussian, when we talk about single Gaussian, it will be just one mean value and
follow this bell curve. So here, assuming zero means, and Gaussian noise.
So therefore, the simple guess is you have the metadata. Our A here is more like the DC value,
the constant value. Then since noise is zero mean, then the simple way to do it is just
simply take the sample mean. Sample mean mean, you see, we have capital N sample,
measure data, we just add them together, divide by n. That's very, that's the easiest
estimator you can ever think of, you know, with the measure data. I sampled that.
And that's also very, sometimes it turns out to be this is the best estimator you can have.
Look at example. In this case, in our setting here, this is a simple setting,
and satisfy this condition, you see. It turns out to be this is the one, the best you can achieve.
You know, there's no use. In this case, you'll derive more complicated estimator,
you will get the things, at most the same or worse. So sometimes, not necessarily you'll go to
very deep, say for example, you know, simple one may be already the best, then no point to go
any complicated or deeper. So let's see why. First, we verify it's unbiased. So this is,
typically this is what we will do in this estimation, and later you'll do
for the detection is always. Also, we are trying to get the means and
expectation. We set them really derived from the principle, like how to use a PDF and then do the
integration. It will be very complicated. What you'll do is you'll operate on the data, you see.
And for example, for expectation, expectation is a linear operator, you see.
Ah, linear operator, then you operate into the sums of these, you know, samples. You can
simply bring it in directly, and whatever constant you can pull out. Because expectation,
when you apply to a constant, I mean, only the constant has no effect on this. You can just
simply take it out, okay, because it's a linear operator. Then therefore, you take this out and
bring this E inside. So that means you are now summing each of the expectations, yeah. And then
each of these, you go back to here to see E of Xn equal to what? Again, this is linear, E of A,
A is a constant. So constant, the expectation of course equal to except, you see. You see,
like the DC value, you know, it's not random. And then, how about this? E of Wn, meaning you are
taking the means of this. And of course, this is zero mean. So you will be just equal to
A. And then how many of A sum together? In total you have capital N, then divide by N,
because equal to A. So that's easy, but it's the fundamental, you see. So you need to
operate using the same way. So that's unbiased. How about efficient? At the moment we don't know
CIOB yet. We're doing next chapter, next week. But then we can try to see whether we can apply
this variance. We need to get the variance, you see. Variance is equal to this. However,
variance is a second order operation, not a linear one. So you cannot take it ground by
breaking down this variance as a sum of each of the variance. Except, only in the case of this,
if this random variable, they are independent. Independent means there is no constant.
Okay? So if not independent, you will become complicated. You will have to create the constant,
because this is a square, variation is a second order operation. So we will go into that later.
Because the white Gaussian noise, they are independent, then you use this property,
bring in. But the constant here, you have to square it, because second order operator,
mean the constant, you will become square before you pull it out. Okay? Therefore,
you pull it out, then apply each. And then we know variance of each is sigma power of two.
Therefore, you sum this capital N of this together, but you divide by N square. So in the N,
the variance of this, related to the variance of the noise, you see, this is, okay, I forgot to
write this zero mean with the variance. If we don't write down, it will be always use sigma power of
two. That's the same way. That's how it's doing here, sigma power of two, divide by N.
Yeah. And then later, next week, we will show the CIOB is having to be equal to this. So
now assume we have it, we say this is efficient, since this variance equal to the CIOB. Therefore,
it's done. So that's look like very simple. Follow certain step, then you will achieve
what you, yeah. And then also we can get the PDF because let's go back again. What's our
estimator looks like? Will be summing a finite number of Gaussian random variable, right? X of
N. So each of X N, you can consider is no zero mean, Gaussian variable, because this is Gaussian,
you add a constant, you are shifting the mean. Assuming, of course, A not equal to zero. So you
make the means no longer zero, shift mean. But it's still Gaussian, you are adding a means,
adding like shift in terms of the PDF, you will be shifting it to, depending on positive, negative.
In terms of the sample accept the variable, you'll be shifting from zero mean, either up or down.
Okay. So therefore, you add finite number of Gaussian random variable together, it's still
Gaussian. That's a very important property. And that's also one of the very special case for
Gaussian. If you, for example, if you are adding two uniform distribution random variable, you
no longer get uniform distribution random variable in general. Similarly, you add any other,
exponential, you create another new random variable. It's not the same time anymore.
Only Gaussian preserve this. And that's why Gaussian random variable is so important,
and so useful in this thing. So therefore, since we know it's a Gaussian, we know the
PDF must be following the same pattern of each sample. It will be,
this is each sample equal to that. And estimate of this A will be
follow a similar distribution, except the mean equal to A, and the value is smaller than this one.
So you only need to change here into this. So that's it. Okay. So in this case, we're assuming
D is A is DC value. It can be positive, it can be negative. It can be any real value. Here we are
dealing only with real data. But sometimes the value of certain unknown parameter, it may be
restricted in terms of the physical consideration. So it could be only positive. For example, you are
estimating the variance of the PDF. It cannot be negative. The variance is always at least greater
or equal to zero. So yeah, so that's the case. You can look at the simulation, or just numerical
example. Assume A equal to five, and sigma equal to two, and n equal to five. So that means A is
n equal to five. So that means we have five samples. So that's what I say is, if you measure each,
it's not necessarily all equal to five. It could be around five. And then now, depending on, you see,
how this is. So don't get confused. This n is the number of samples you are taking the
average, your estimate each time. And this histogram is the one you are repeating, you see,
an ensemble of this one thousand realizations. So you take five, generate five random measured data,
using our formula, sample mean, to get. And then you can get the measured
values, the measured means and values. And then up there you regenerate again, another five
samples, and do it again. So therefore, statistically you can see the estimate of A sometimes is a very,
have a very big arrow. It gives you a very small value. Sometimes it gives a very big one. But
most of the time it's still reasonably near to five. So this is the histogram. Okay, you can see.
Furthermore, if we now increase the n equal to ten, so what happen? You'll see this become narrow,
you see, like better. Of course you'll see. Very, you don't, among this one thousand, you don't see,
at the smallest you'll get is three. Highest is seven. You go to the previous one, you can go down
to two and eight. So you'll expect the more sample you go, say n equal to one hundred, you'll get
much better. Yeah, so yeah. But even there you'll never get the exact, you know, numerically you
don't get exactly equal to five, you get something very close but not five. The very standard
deviation of variant reduced, but not equal to zero. You'll never get into zero. You may be
approaching zero. Okay, so yeah. Let's look at the case where you have the bios
estimate for the case of DC level. We won't go into too much detail here, but just highlight
why we always want to achieve the unbiased one. Because if you have bias, you cause some problem.
So let's follow the same example, except we purposely use the estimated by take the
summation but multiply by another parameter a not equal to one. Okay, so this is the one
we purposely do it. Then from here you can see the expect value of this, you already got the small
a times a. And since a not equal to one, we know this not equal to capital A. Okay, so therefore
it will give you a bias, unless in the case of capital A got zero, which is not very meaningful
here. So this value typically we're trying to see some no zero value. Then in this case we'll see why
at least the bias estimator is not good. So we want to measure the mean square error here.
So mean square mean, you see, our estimate subject the true one. This is different from the expectation,
so don't get confused. Mean square error mean we are defining estimate one subject to the true one.
And then after that, we remember there is a square here. So we purposely make this a little
bit more complicated, but by subtracting this expectation of a, since they are not the same,
you see. Yeah, so we subtract, but you need to add this back. Okay, so we create two terms here.
And why? Because if you explain this, it will give you the variant of this a,
that's by definition. This part give you the variant. And then the other part, it will be
bias term. Bias term raised power of two. Okay, so it's very easy to calculate this equal to that,
and this one equal to this. So we, yeah, you can try to derive by yourself. Now if you are
trying to see which a will give you the best to minimize this, then of course our tools here,
later you will always try to use. It always take derivation, you see. Derivation with respect to
small a, then making equal to zero, you can easily solve by the optimal small a, called this.
So, but this is value, optimal value of a depends on the unknown parameter. So that means it's not
not very good. We want to estimate this capital A, but we want to see how good to get this small a.
Then we rely on this unknown a, so this is not realizable. I mean you cannot achieve
this in just based on the data. So, yeah, if you look at the simulation, you also see
if your a equal to half, then our estimate value is near the 2.5, even when you have more data.
Okay, so that's, yeah, that's not a good estimate. So therefore, our motivation is always try to
motivate to get the MBRE, not the, yeah. And then here we give some illustration about
when we can have MBRE and when there is no MBRE. In the more general case, our parameter here, it could be,
you know, it could be not always a constant, like what we, we just now the simple example,
it could be, you know, certain curve, say this is one, the value of this,
so one follow this, when theta change, say assume real value, then you get this, theta 2 estimate
this, theta 3. So in this case, theta 3, assume we only have 3 estimate for all, then this is the
best because this is always lower than other, but not this case because you cannot say which one is
better, theta 2 hat or theta 3 hat, but in this part, this is better, sorry, in this segment,
this one is better, but beyond this point, then theta 3 hat is better. So, yeah, so therefore,
we show this as a uniformly MBRE, this one, you don't have.
And we can even use one example to show here, and here, you see, as I mentioned, every time you have
to be careful how many data samples or observations you are dealing with. So now we are looking at two,
one sample follow this, the other sample follow this, this is for all the theta,
M is one sample, so it's always the same mean, whereas this one, it depends on
theta is positive or negative, and you can do different way. So therefore, in this case,
let's see how we are going to get this. So we now assume we are dealing with, we are using two
estimators, one is simply sum this two sample divided by two, the other one is we give more
weight to this one, or less to this one, because this sphere, you may have larger variance here.
Now we want to see which one is better, so we need to first easy to verify, both are unbiased,
you can do it easily, but however, to go to the variance, the good thing is those are independent,
so you simply add the variance of both, but don't forget to square this, any constant you need to
square, and then the other one you also square the coefficient, the other one square, and now we can
get the variance of each, but since it involves both data, this data and that data,
we have to divide the theta into two segments, theta greater than zero,
for this one, you'll get one variance, theta smaller than zero, you have to
follow this, then you get a large one, so this is one case. Similarly, for theta two-head,
you also do the same, theta greater than zero, you get something, theta smaller than zero, you get
this value. Now we want to see which one, is it here, theta one is for negative theta value, you have
a larger variance compared to theta two-head, but however, for the positive theta, it gets a smaller
variance compared to theta, so this is the good example, auto simulation, it verified this case,
yeah, something like this case, but we only have two, you can ignore this, so that means,
yeah, you can go back and look at the value here again, so you see,
this one is smaller than that, but this one is greater than that, so we can't say which one is
better, so that means there is no minimum value, unbi-estimated in this case, okay, so therefore,
how to find the MBOE, that's our next topic we are going to do, but different from
detection theory, that's why I say the second part is somewhat easier, I will say, in a not so accurate
comparison, you know all of you, learn calculus, you know the derivation, take the differentiation
and the integration, to take the derivative, however the formula complicated, you can follow
the chain rules to do it one by one, in the end it may become very long, but you can, it's workable,
as long as you know how to take the derivative, however, so that's a big similar to the detection
theory, or at least the easier part of the detection theory, so you think about, you learn some rules,
then you just apply, and quite often you need to simplify the result, while on the other hand,
parameter estimation is a little bit like integration, you need to find some tricks to
make sense to do the integration, although it may be there, but if you cannot think about the
correct way to do it, you may be stuck, so that's why we say, no turn the crane, turn the crane,
operate on the crane, you can do it step by step, so yeah, even though the MVOE exists,
and then how to do that, there are several ways, one is you can, in the next chapter,
you can use CIOB, and then we check some estimator, whether it satisfies this, then if you meet the
CIOB, certainly you already get the MVOE, but quite often this may not be achieved, then another
way is you assume the unbiased estimator to have a linear form, so it's more like a linear function,
and from there it's easier, you can get the best linear estimator, but this is best only
for the linear form, not in general, but yeah, that's how we will go next, and there are some other
methods such as maximum likelihood and so on, we will discuss later, so as I say, we take an easier
approach to just give you a very basic idea, introduction to this parameter estimation
theory, and then also some important PDA, and then also start with this very simple instruction to
MVOE, where subsequently we will go in more detail about how to get MVOE using different
methods, so I think that's about time to finish, we will end the lecture here,
we'll see you next week, assuming you decide to take, any questions you can stay back or
write an email to me, I'll see you next week.
Thank you.