The
Interesting.
Looks very dark.
Let's see.
What we can do here.
Okay.
The class of Tangdeng Lease has finally been released.
It's very interesting to see this year this class.
We have a majority of students from the MSc Com engineering.
We have about 160 students, and then among them probably about 100 from Com.
This class was supposed to be the SP ML course, now it becomes more or less like a Com course.
Anyway, on the other side I realized, because I reviewed some new African students from Com background,
Tangdeng took similar courses before, maybe at the undergraduate level, like the detection and estimation theory, so on.
So in a sense it's perhaps easier, so that could explain the reason.
Anyway, as I said, this new challenge, this year we have many more students, and particularly this course, we have almost a triple of what we had before in early years.
Okay, so I hope this one should be working.
It's still working here, but let's see, because I want to do some writing.
Okay, let's see how.
Finally it works.
Very interesting.
Okay.
Okay, let's get started.
By now we finished three weeks, and today is week four, and my plans are based on the progress,
and because of the much larger size also from different background.
So my plan is we will finish part one, we have another three weeks to go, about by end of week six,
or perhaps we need a little bit more time, we can use half of week seven.
And then after that, next week I will give the assignment, the homework assignment, since you have learned by next week,
we find you learn most of this part one, and then we'll take another five to six weeks for the part two.
So that's, and then usually I leave the week 13 as revisions and questioning and answering and so on.
And we can also add in a little bit about additional material, like carbon filter, but it's just at the initial taxon level,
not to go by in terms, so that's about the plan.
Okay, before going, I want to clarify some of the questions last week about how to differentiate this.
Yeah, that's how some students ask me the question, and this is also a good exercise to get familiar with mainly the matrix operation.
And if you recall, I also upload, you can double check with me whether the matrix calculus already, I already from my side can see from the,
in until learn, but in case you cannot open or so, you can let me know.
That's the one, I think not in this folder, I can go up a little bit in the appendix.
Anyway, I think probably no need this, we can just take a look at this.
So there are two ways to address this, how to derive from the, with respect to a vector.
So let's do a very quick review about the, for example, your, your familiar with like scalar, you see, if I have just looked looking at a scalar, you see, a scalar function, let me try to focus.
Then everyone knows this is undergraduate year one math and so on.
So for example, if I have x square divided by x, because everyone knows, it will be two x.
So polynomial, you'll just get, you'll get down one, one degree.
In matrix, we have like similar operation, but the main difference between scalar and matrix is usually you cannot, you cannot swap for scalar.
So if you cannot say you multiply by b, you will be equal to b multiplied by u.
So this is very, very simple and very useful.
Then the derivation, you can, for example, with respect to x, assuming both are functions of x, then you're just doing either the first one,
derive the second plus, derive the first, keep the second.
I think you all know this rule.
The main difference in matrix is if you have two matrix in general, you see, you cannot just simply swap.
So this is one thing very fundamental.
You need to, you need to take note.
And that's also why I spend quite some time, you see, looking at for matrix.
Very often we, we need to make sure the dimension as you match and you do it correctly.
And that's, that's why I feel useful through this course.
I, this, I emphasize this.
For example, if you can, you can have this.
You see, you don't need to write down.
Very often you will see, you use this as a guideline to check the dimension and, and this is simple techniques that we will use very often.
You see, it will be different from you, you do the other way around.
Okay.
So you have the same, same matrix, roughly the same, but you multiply from the left first and followed by the other one.
It's different.
And that's also, also what I emphasize here, you see, a model of a b not equal to b model of a, if the dimension doesn't match.
Okay.
And then let's come back to this.
So if you look at the, at the derivation there, we, we go back to this.
You can, when you take derivation, derivation with respect to theta, as you ignore the constant, just keep, keep it there.
So what we are looking at is x minus h theta and then transpose x minus h, h theta.
So, so there are first we check the, check the dimension.
This, this one, the dimension should be the same as, as a h.
Okay.
Because h is the only vector standing out where theta is a vector, but the, our edge usually is a not square matrix.
So, so this one after multiplication, you will get the same dimension with h.
Okay.
And then if you first, if you reduce this, assume all these edge, x, h, theta, they are all scalar.
So what do we have?
You will have the very special case because in, in scalar, you, you do not difference here with transpose.
So transpose is equal to itself and everything becomes a scalar.
Then you will have the simple case of like the polynomial with respect to, respect to theta.
So, so usually you can always try to make the, make it as a special case of scalar function and then get the result.
And then you will see in the matrix case whether you will be the same or there is a different.
So, so that's how you will be derivative with this in the, in a scalar case.
I mean, you all know this is twice and then you copy this because it's polynomial.
And then you'll need to remember you have this minus, minus h.
Okay.
So this is the scalar case and we will expect we have something similar in this matrix case.
And it really turns out to be almost the same except you'll have to, for a scalar case, you can put the, either this edge being a scalar.
You see, you can put it on the, on the left or on the right.
It doesn't matter as you will all familiar.
But for matrix, you cannot do that.
You have to follow whether it's on the left or on the right.
Okay.
So this is something, you know, the first thing you need to take care.
And then the easiest way to solve that problem is as I mentioned to some students, you can expand it.
You see, you, you'll expand it or play on the transpose.
You see, you also need to be, to be careful.
You have x minus h theta.
Then you take the transpose.
The transpose operation is for one item is linear.
Just putting, if you have a plus b or take the first one, transpose, and then keep the minus side, of course.
Then here, this is something very important.
I'm not sure how many of you remember this.
Okay.
So if you are transfer, a product of two matrix, you must remember you, you take the one, if you have two, the last one,
transfer it first.
Okay.
And then after that, you'll do the transfer of the, of the, of the first one.
So, so these two must follow.
Okay.
You cannot swap.
I cannot say, or I take the edge transfer.
Then you'll get something totally wrong.
If you don't believe you use my so-called magic box, I call this box, just like the black box.
You only need to know the dynamics.
Okay.
So this is a, this is a very important that you can see one of the major difference between a scalar,
a scalar variable operation and magic.
So if you do that right, then you should get more or less you solve the problem.
Then in terms of multiplication, again, it's again similar to scalar, but you need to follow, follow the order.
For example, you, you do this X transfer multiplied by X.
So you're, so you need to keep this is left first, then you follow by the right.
You cannot say it will become edge multiplied by edge transfer.
It will totally wrong again.
So again, the next one, I do this one first, transfer X transfer, etc.
And then after that, you have minor, etc.
Yes, X.
Then finally, this is a CTA transfer edge transfer edge and then follow by CTA.
All right.
So there are, there are several useful property here before you even simplify further.
You see.
First, these two, these two terms are the same.
So you may want to get a quick answer why because you keep saying you, you cannot swap the sort of magic.
Why these are the same?
Again, to start with, you look at the so-called box measure.
You see this one is a vector.
You'll transfer become a row vector.
There is a flat one.
Then this edge must be the same as, you know, this dimension must be the same.
So it's a longer one.
Because our CTA vector usually, it will be a smaller.
I make it very thin so that, yeah.
It will be a vector.
So therefore, just, we don't care how big this intermediate dimension is.
Oh, I know it's at the end.
It will become a scalar, which is one by one.
Right.
Okay.
Same as you can see, this is also a scalar.
A scalar, you see, as I mentioned, X, transfer, it will be the same as X because being a scalar,
it's just one element.
So then, you get these rules that we are going to use later, which is more important.
So things we are going through the previous material I can explain.
So later, I will cut you, you see.
So if you look at this being a scalar, I can transfer this, you see.
So this X transfer edge, theta, it will be equal to, I take the, take the transfer.
And then when you take the transfer, again, you see, you follow the last one, theta transfer
first, edge transfer next.
And then finally, you see X transfer and then transfer again, of course, equal to, equal
to accept your transfer twice.
So reverse back, okay.
Then, you see here.
So this term is exactly the same as this one.
After you, first you observe, this is scalar.
So scalar can transfer is the same.
So after transfer, these two become the same.
So in this course, the simplification is very important, you see.
So for example, you do the assignments and do the final exam question.
You always expect you try to simplify until the simplification, or at least, yeah.
So that also at the same time, save you some trouble to, you know, to derive further because
you can compile these two.
It doesn't matter where you can use either of them, it will be the same.
So X transfer, edge, theta, then minor, theta transfer, edge, transfer, edge, theta, okay.
So this is one thing.
The second one is if you observe this, this matrix in the middle, you see.
If the same matrix multiplied by another matrix either from the left or from the right, then
this matrix must be symmetry.
Okay.
With the edge itself, it's not symmetry, but the product is a symmetry.
So because if you don't believe, you can do it easily.
Okay.
So again, remember to take the transfer, you have to do this one first.
And then this one is your transfer once, transfer again, you go to excel.
Okay.
So therefore, you see, your transfer, these metrics will be equal to accept.
So this is symmetric metric because you have the product, which is the metrics multiplied
by its own transfer.
Then either from left or the right, it will be the same.
But the dimension will be different if the matrix is not a square matrix.
Okay.
So combining these two, then you, and then apply the formula.
I gave you, gave you early.
You can see if you take with respect to this whole thing with respect to the theta.
The first one is a constant, you see.
Constant with respect to the theta.
The vector is also very important whether the variable or the metric is random or not.
You, you need to also follow the similar rules.
If independent of, of, of, of theta, then you consider that as a constant.
And then some students always argue, say, oh, your theta is hidden within the, within
the data.
You're right.
But when we are talking about the explicitly derivation, we just consider the, these two
are, you see, not related.
So you consider this x as, as a constant with respect to theta.
So therefore you only need to, you only need to take care of this term, you see.
So, so remember when you take derivative, you look at the variable, which is the theta,
the theta vector, you see.
So you'll just treat this, this whole thing being a constant minus two, you just take
that.
And then this one is a vector, you see.
And you take derivative with respect to theta, you keep this, this low vector, but you need
to transform.
So, so you just take the transform of this, transform.
All right.
So that's easy.
So you do this.
And then this one, finally, because it's very important because this metric is in between
the one A is in the appendix.
And symmetric, then we, we get the almost the same result as the scalar case, you see.
So we only need to, we only need to write down two and then this edge, transform edge,
because this is A symmetry and theta.
Then we get almost the same result in the scalar case, in the case of this A matrix in
the middle is symmetric.
If this is not symmetric, the one, then you will create one more term and it will be quite
different from the, from the scalar case.
So with this, you can see we get our results here, you see.
This is the, look at the first term, it will be the, it will be the one there first.
And then here, here again, you see, the minus two, yeah, I think the minus side cancels
out and the two cancels out.
This one, previously with minus, minus two there, okay.
Then out of that, you see, here, yeah, here, I need to do one step more because, you see,
remember, it will become edge, transform, X.
And then after that, you have this minus two, edge, transform, H, theta, you see.
Then you pull out this, then you become edge, transform.
So again here, you, to be very careful, you want to take the same common factor out.
It must on the, on the same side, the left most.
You cannot say if this edge transform in the middle or at the end, the right side cannot
pull out.
We are not doing the scalar operation.
So matrix operation must be very careful.
Okay, I remove minus two, they will become X minus, become plus.
Then since you pull out this, you become edge, do I, do I mess up?
I think there is a typo here, so that's why it's very important.
You multiply minus, you are, you are plus here.
Okay, and then eventually here, you will have a plus.
Then you take the, yeah, so you take the plus.
So therefore this become minus, and then you have H theta, you see.
So, so be careful to do the proper checking.
And that's how we come out with this, this laser.
And then as I say, we want to take out this edge.
Actually, if you can, we don't need this, we can directly walk from here, because this
is already edge, transform edge.
This is square matrix of smaller size, and assuming edge is full range, you can prove
this is invertible.
So, so maybe this is one of the potential questions I may ask you in the future, but
never know.
Okay, so that's how this is what you can do.
And another way to do is, but I won't go, I won't go through this step.
Maybe it's a good exercise for you to try out for those students who really want to get
more.
You can first consider X minus H theta.
This is a new, you can call it Y or whatever, a new vector.
Okay.
So, so then you'll become very simple.
You will have Y transpose multiplied by Y.
And Y is a linear function of theta.
So, you can apply what I say early, you see, you can apply these rules.
First, you do the derivative with respect to Y.
Okay, because they will become Y transpose Y.
And the formula you use is you consider A in the middle is identity, identity matrix.
You'll get a very easy result with respect to Y first.
But after Y, our derivation is with respect to theta.
Then you need another operation.
And it's like two steps.
But the only thing you have to be careful with this combination, you are doing using the
two formulas, whether you're putting on the lab or not.
So, it may be a little bit confused, but again, if you follow my approach here, you will solve
the problem easily because among the two, only one of them, if you are not sure, you can
think about it, put it lab and verify whether the dimension is right or not.
But if it turns out to be wrong, they must be on the right and you can verify.
So, this is a very useful technique.
Later, we will also go through again, you see.
Okay, any questions?
Before we start the new lecture, anything you'd like to ask or any questions?
No?
Okay, that's fine.
Let's start the new chapter, which will be the next one.
So, I will look at this chapter 4.
It's very short.
So, today I'm playing a supinis chapter 5 and we combine these two in a summary next week.
So, I will say this chapter 5 is relatively easy, at least in terms of concepts.
So, the rule of thumb is whatever you see linear, you know, like the now.
So, I assume chapter 4, you also consider that it's easy compared to chapter 2 and 3, which
usually involving maybe the now linear operation.
So, anything linear should be easy.
And at this point, I will emphasize this course other than some of the signal processing,
you know, backgrounds and concepts you're going to learn and so on.
The two mesh tools, the most important one is some simple property and random process.
Very little random process, more property.
And among properties, mainly is the first order moment, which is you take the mean expectation
and also the second moment.
Variant is the combination of first moment and second moment.
I mean, yeah.
So, and very often we don't need to go back to the definition of doing the integration.
The exception case is the CIOB derivation.
We do go through that.
But in the end, we do not really integrate.
We're just making good use of some property.
But later on, you will see throughout this course, mostly we will be just assuming you know the mean
and the second order moment, then you'll directly do the operation and the simplification throughout.
And this is one.
Another one is linear algebra.
Mainly is like some matrix operation and like the one where we use how to take transfer inverse and later there will be some
eigenvalue decomposition, eigenvalue, eigenvector.
And that's probably mostly what you need to do and learn.
So that's how we come back to this, you know, NBUE because as I say, our main target for estimation is try to get the NBUE.
And to make it unbiased relatively easy, some simple operations.
So it turns out to be how are we going to optimize, try to minimize the variance.
And also variance being a second order statistic usually is a little bit more difficult compared to the first moment.
First of all, it's not linear operation, second order.
And so we will spend like more time to work out that.
And we already learned the CLB.
So CLB you can think this is one of the tools to do it.
And if you are lucky, you can get the NBUE.
Furthermore, that becomes even an efficient estimator.
But quite often we may not be able to get the CLB or if we get the CLB, you cannot do it,
you cannot factorize into that spatial form.
So you may be stuck in getting what requires NBUE.
And so one way is I mean we assume most of you are engineering background.
And this you are in the EEE.
So engineers tend to be a bit more compromised.
We are more practical people.
Actually my background also engineering also I like math.
So being facing the practical situation, then we reduce our expectation.
You cannot get the optimal one, we get suboptimal if you can achieve suboptimal.
And that's also end up why the CLB is important because some students are,
oh CLB may not give you the estimator you still need to file.
And that's why if you are getting a suboptimal one, then you are also assuming you can get the CLB,
then you can compare.
It's not optimal of course, but if it's not too far off to the optimal one, then we are acceptable.
For example, 100 mark, ideally you get hit 100.
But if not then suboptimal, 90 is good enough.
NTU level 85 and above is all the same, A plus.
Actually you may be okay with A because the GPA is the same, A plus.
I mean 80, this whole range is eventually the same GPA.
So that's how it's suboptimal.
We can see how far away you're from there.
And then looking at the suboptimal one, one way to do is we lower down our requirement.
In general, you will expect the estimator is a nonlinear combination from the data.
And that's why now this deep learning and neural network is deferred from the linear model.
It contains the nonlinear operation.
So it's more powerful, but also more difficult to get in general.
So now you'll see the relationship here.
So what we're doing in this chapter is we assume we have linear unbiased estimator.
So we only lower down our requirement, we look at this subclass.
And then among all the linear unbiased estimator, we look at the best one.
So that's how we're going to do it.
But then how good it is?
You will need to either based on some common sense or based on some ideally CIOB,
or you can maybe often based on your data, you may have some practical implication and so on.
But in the course here, we will just focus on the mesh models with some assumptions.
So that's our study here.
So we start with, again, the scalar case where this is somehow easier to manipulate.
So we have capital N sample of data.
And then here we assume we have the PDF from each of the samples.
So I need to emphasize here, you see, so each metadata data sample, you consider that as a random variable.
But collectively, when we are discussing the PDF of this whole data sample, if you are assuming PDF,
but some of the methods, like later, you will see this method, we don't really require the PDF.
But assuming a CLB, you need PDF.
You need to combine them together.
And in the case of IID or independent and identical distribution, you can just simply multiply each of the PDF as a product.
So that's some very basic assumption from probability.
But if they are not independent or they are correlated, then it becomes more complicated.
And in the case of Gaussian, you can still get the analytic result.
But you will have some, basically, just like some cross term.
So it's not simple multiplication.
You have the correlation.
So now coming back to that, we have this data sample.
Then we use some constant, like the weight to compact.
Because the simplest one is just, I just add the sample together,
or in case the sample size is large, you add the sample divided by the number of samples.
That's the very common technique we call sample means.
But of course, the better way is because each of the data points may play different roles, you see,
so the difference of the hidden parameter, we are going to estimate.
Some contain more information, less noisy than the other sample.
So that's why, in general, even if it's a linear combination, we want to make the constant.
This constant, they're in general different.
How to choose this constant, what we are going to do, like optimize.
So this is the base among the linear.
But it will become an NBV.
Assume this NBV, except it's linear.
If the base is linear, then we are lucky.
We only look at the subset.
And then among the linear, we get the base.
So it turns out to be the base.
If the base is nonlinear, then it will be a little bit far off.
So far off, we have to see the performance.
So it becomes maybe very even optimal or suboptimal.
But sometimes even become very poor and not acceptable.
And that's how you will need to turn to those nonlinear models.
In the past, Neural Network now is a deep learning model and getting much larger parameters.
But it will be very hard to analyze, even having no linear and very large number of parameters.
So let's see how we can, probably, learn this so far.
I should say most of these techniques, they are more or less the same as what we did in the first few weeks.
It's just some kind of combination and some tricks to simplify.
So let's see what we are going to do.
We put that as a constant vector.
One thing you need to be very clear is you always need to differentiate whether the vector or matrix or the constant or the scalar,
they are random or deterministic.
Yeah, random, yeah, between random and deterministic.
So because that play a huge difference, particularly when we apply the expectation inside.
Not random, you can pull out.
Random, you have to keep that.
So among these two, the one we are going to do is the Ingle product.
So you know this is, usually is a column vector, but your text transform becomes low.
So this is Ingle product.
Become a scalar because we start with the scalar case to start with.
And now we need to look at the variant.
This is, as I said, one of the key requirements.
We need to minimize this variant.
So based on definition, as I said, you don't need to go to integration.
What you need is you write down the definition of variant.
I hope by now you can treat these.
Because the data contains some randomness.
So this is a random variable.
It's only a scalar.
Okay, although the data here is a random vector because we combine them together.
So become a new random variable, which is a scalar for this part.
So the data will be dealing with vector.
But there's more later.
So now based on definition, you look at this.
This is your text.
To make it easy, you'll call it either C-thigh-hack or call it Y.
And then the definition of variant is you subtract the expectation of this.
You know what this is saying.
So make sure you square this whole square the difference.
Square the difference.
And then you expand it because, yeah, then you see this E operator itself is also linear.
So let me see what we can do here.
I hope this one is still working.
Better to turn on because after some time, after this one, I don't know why then.
It takes a long time to turn on.
So I try to refresh.
So if you look at the one here, let's do it one by one.
This is a very important operation.
We have E of this.
Inside, we have E, A transpose of X.
Then this is being not random.
You can pull up.
But you need to keep the E with respect to X.
So this is what we're doing here.
But then after that, you see, because remember both of them, you are still within the branches.
So now you're talking about this term.
I pull out the A transpose.
Then you can pull it out because both of them have this A transpose.
So one of them will be X.
Then the other one, your lab is E.
E to the E of X.
And then remember our square has to include this A transpose, this A vector transpose.
So you're still within the big branches.
So be careful.
You'll be inside.
So now this is very interesting because we first write down using the so-called box method.
You see here.
So when I write this inside, this will become A transpose.
This is A transpose.
And then this is the column vector X minus E of X.
You'll be a long one.
So this is one of the factors.
You see, this is a scalar.
Scalar, then because being a scalar, you're powered too.
You can just write another one.
You see, I use this.
If I write this whole thing using the matrix operation and square it, you will have this low vector
followed by column.
And then this is low vector again, followed by the same column vector.
So this will create a problem when we apply the E with respect to this power of 2, this square term.
Why?
Because being constant vector, low vector or column vector, you see,
we don't want it to be in the middle.
You cannot pull out.
You see, our operation, as long as you are involving either column vector or low vector,
you see, I cannot pull this A transpose in the middle out either from left or right.
That will cause a problem because we don't want this one to be in the middle
because it's just a constant vector.
So how are we going to manage to pull it out?
So this is the very important trick about what I say early because if you observe this
as being a scalar, I can take the transpose of this one.
So I make this transpose only on the right factor.
So I transpose it so that it will become x minus E of x transpose.
So this is low vector because this one is a column.
Initially, we have two, we have both columns.
So I transpose this scalar.
Then after that, A transpose, transpose again, it will become just A because you transpose
twice.
Now this is very important.
Our E is still outside, you see, but now I can pull out this A transpose from the left
and this A, the lower far right side to the right.
So our E now only applies inside this, this involving x, or yeah, x is random.
And that's a trick that you must use because otherwise you are just routinely right down
here and then you cannot continue.
And that's why some of the past year exam some questions involving the step in the middle
and then only a few students who learn this technique well then simplify and test.
But usually this more difficult question, the mark is not that high.
We have to differentiate difficult questions and simple ones.
So this is one of the things I really hope those attending here.
I heard if you're doing to learn, can you see this handwriting?
Some students say you cannot see this, but can anyone try?
Yeah, can.
Once I show this, it will be okay.
Yeah, so good.
So at least it helps.
Okay, so now if you come back, it's a bit hard to pull it to the other side.
And we get what we want almost because our variance now becomes, this is something, the
coefficient, the one we want to or play on, one on the far left and the one on the far
right.
Because in the middle, you see, so again here, if you apply inside, this is exactly our definition
of covariant magic of the data, the data vector only.
So I hope this is an extension from what we learn early, the normal variance.
Variant we're referring to a scalar random variable.
And then when the random variable becomes a random vector, you'll be doing the same,
but for the left, you have to follow the order.
For variance being a random variable, a scalar, you just use product because scalar, you don't
need to differentiate left and right.
But for matrix, you have to make sure this covariant magic is a big magic, is outer product.
In the product, it will be scalar.
And we can emphasize this many, many times because outer product being your vector on
the far left, followed by the low vector, the transform.
You swap it, then it will be different.
It will be in the product.
Okay?
So this is more or less what we are going to do.
Now look at the means of the estimator.
So again, this is easy.
It's a first-order statistic, linear.
Again, again, bringing.
And actually, this is what we did early in our derivation.
But we need to have one assumption here.
Also, our linear estimator, we do not assume linear model.
That's a difference from the previous chapter.
Linear model means our data is a linear function of theta.
Linear estimator is either our...
We give the data.
Our estimator is a linear function of the data.
So these two, at least conceptually, are different.
But in terms of the data, the meaning here, we also see our requirement on the...
The data is weaker.
We don't require the data here as a linear function of the unknown parameter theta.
But in order to make it unbiased, based on this, we do require the expectation of the data
to be a linear function of theta.
That means it...
Because this is a vector.
It will be theta multiplied by a constant vector.
So again, only the means, expectation of this to be a linear function of theta,
where our chapter four is the data except it must be linear.
Linearly dependent on theta.
So this is weaker requirement.
And then assuming this is given, and we also know this, you need to know this.
So that now you apply this again here, then you substitute this inside.
We will see this.
So again, this is...
This become an inner product of two different vectors, A and S vector.
So S is constant.
Therefore, in order to make this unbiased, we require this condition.
So again, this S is given.
S is one you should know first.
Where A vector is the one we are going to work on.
We are going to find out the optimal one.
So two steps again, we make this unbiased.
Unbiased, we require A transpose, the inner product of this equal to one.
Because we are dealing with a scalar.
And after that, given this constraint, we want to minimize the value.
We already derived.
So you need to put this in the Lagrangian or it's a cost function.
So this is also now very often.
In machine learning, you also need cost functions.
And this is what we are going to optimize.
Okay?
So Lagrangian, yeah, these techniques, we also need a very simple one, as you can see here.
Then again, this is...
The loss function is a scalar.
But the A here is a vector.
Also, our unknown parameter except theta is just a scalar.
So you need to differentiate this.
Then we take your derivative and again, this is a very simple rule.
We also, because Lagrangian, we need to take derivative with respect to this parameter,
Lagrangian parameter, rho.
Then you get this.
So we set both of them equal to zero.
And from this one, you make it zero.
From that one, you combine these two, then you get the relationship.
So I hope this is a very easy A-O-G break.
You'll know how to do it.
And assume this one being a covariant matrix.
We normally assume our data independent.
Then, that means this covariant matrix would be invertible.
So we get this.
And this is the condition.
And again, here, you see, I make the use of being a scalar.
You can transfer here.
You transfer, you get this.
Even so, these two vectors are not the same, you see.
So, yeah.
And after that, because we need to remove this, you see, that our A cannot, because this lambda is unknown.
So we use it as intermediate variable.
You have to remove it.
Then, again, you make good use of the given this constraint.
And we already know A need to satisfy this.
So we put in, and then we solve this lambda, equal to that.
So these are all given, as you remember.
Our S is given, because given the data, we also need to assume we know the covariant.
Then, after that, you combine together, put this lambda in,
and you get this, our optimal coefficient vector will be equal to this form.
Then, this is the coefficient vector.
Finally, our blue is, remember, we just, like the Inger product, this is a scalar.
So we already know this, then multiply this, you will get this.
And then we can also substitute back to get the variance.
Yeah.
How are we going to get the variance if you go back the operation?
So the variance is equal to this.
We have the A optimal transport by Cx and A.
So some students say, why your variance becomes so simple?
Because you have several terms.
This is, again, a very useful property.
Once you substitute, you will see there are some terms, k-sawa.
So you end up with the denominator is the same, but the numerator becomes simpler, just one.
So how to do it?
You can try out, verify.
So here, you see, we do not need the entire PDF in this, in this method.
What we need is only the knowledge of the scale means s.
Assuming we know the data, scale into this s vector multiplied by theta, and also the
covariant matrix of the data, which typically you can measure based on the sample.
So we don't need PDF.
So it's not always we need PDF.
So this idea is more practical, at least from the major data.
You can try out something.
So let's see how we apply to our example, which is the simplest example.
You can think of in this estimation here, because we only estimate one unknown, and that's a constant throughout DC,
plus white Gaussian noise.
Yeah, and this one here, we even do not, sorry, this one is a white noise, but it can be unspecified.
It's not necessarily Gaussian.
So somehow or something is a little bit easier.
We don't even need to know the PDF.
And then now, how are we going to get the s vector, since we are given the data and the model here?
So you see here, with e of this, you need to know the way standard way of operation.
So e of this, then that means e, because e is a linear operator.
So very easy.
You just apply e to each.
And being a constant, of course, e of the constant is still equal to accept.
Even if you don't believe you're going to the integration, you are in the same way.
So that's why I say you don't need to do it again.
And then e of this, normally when we say white noise without mentioning the means,
that means you will be assumed zero means.
If not, mention the means.
But for exam paper, normally we will, I will add zero means to be sure.
But yeah, just follow the convention.
And the variant is this.
We know this.
So therefore, you will see each of the n, whatever n equal to 0, 1, so on, your mw is a.
And so therefore, we know this.
A is the one we are going to estimate.
So the coefficient vector for each of the n is just equal to 1.
So e for each.
So yeah, so it is at the one vector.
The one vector, you're right, is a pole phase one.
And in this case, the covariant matrix is also equal to this.
The noise of white.
I mean, there's no correlation, no constant.
And then you can directly substitute the blue using the formula inside as you see here.
So this is one vector.
And this is the identity matrix.
Because this is identity matrix divided by sigma power of 2.
You take the inverse.
You only inverse the coefficient.
So therefore, you can simplify by just by work out this.
I think that's quite easy.
If you are not very sure, you'll do it by writing down the one vector, low vector, column vector.
And then you will see that will become just the sum of n.
And similarly for the other one, it will become the summation of the data.
Of course, you have to pull out this.
So n dot where this sigma power of 2 can show up.
That's your 1 here, the numerator, and the denominator also over there.
So we are taking the sample mean.
And the variance, also easier.
As I said, this one, of course, you take out, become numerator.
And this is just summing up the n.
And therefore, our sample mean here, this is sample mean definition.
You take the sample, then divide by the number of samples.
It happens to be the blue, even without knowing the PDF of the data.
As long as we know the data, what?
The noise, PDF can be Gaussian, can be any other one.
Actually, we don't even need to know.
So this is useful.
So let's quickly go through some relative examples.
And then before we take a break, look at the DC level in uncorrelated noise.
But then the noise level is different.
So this is somewhat more practical case, as I said, early.
Some of the data may be more less noise, less noise,
where some other data, depending on the variance.
Of course, you all know if the variance is smaller,
the idea case, the variance reduced to zero, then there's no noise.
If the variance is very large, then it would be very noisy.
Assuming here to be practical, we assume there always some value.
Otherwise, we can take out that data.
There's no noise, so it's not our consideration.
So then, being a target of metrics, you take the inverse,
you just invert each of the elements.
And we put into the blue.
And we will get very similar results, except you have the weighting.
And the weighting is one over the noise here.
So that means here it's also meaningful.
For example, if you are weighting at the data sample,
that means if this is small, then one over this will become a large number.
So that means if the noise, the noise is very small,
the data has less noise, it's more important.
It contains more useful information.
So we give it bigger weight in getting this sound.
And for the variance, it will depend on how much different.
So that's the one here.
So yeah, that's what I already explained here.
Then having this CX inverse in an N is sometimes we call it pre-weightening.
You can also do it in a two-step approach.
Given the data, if you already know the noise distribution of each of the samples,
you'll do pre-weightening first, get the more balanced data,
and then update it, you'll apply the formula.
And this is the approach we're also going to do,
one of the approaches in the detection one, so pre-weightening, so the one here.
And then to tell you the proof here is identical to the MVVE for the Gaussian noise,
although we do not need to assume.
So in some sense, sometimes it's like this.
For some example, we don't need the more complicated one.
We can use a simple one with less assumptions.
So I think it's a good time to take a short break here before we continue into the vector parameter case,
which is extension of what we do, but a little bit more involved.
So we come back in now 7.40, maybe 7.55, 15 minutes.
But then we can finish big early.
So any questions, you can come to me during the break also.
7.48.
Yes?
Yeah, here we are taking the transport of A optimal,
but in the denominator nothing is changing when we take the transport.
So we have S transpose CX inverse S, we didn't change it.
So the denominator is not affected by the transport?
The denominator, you are talking the last line?
We are talking about A optimal.
So we have A optimal, okay?
The line before the last one, good week.
Okay, that one is a vector.
You know A optimal is a column vector?
Yeah, yeah, then if you look at denominator is a scalar.
Denominator is a scalar, must be a scalar.
Otherwise you cannot derive the biometric, right, to become inverse.
That's how the next one, the next vector case, because that one, yeah, that side,
I told you you are always verified.
If you look at this, it is a row vector first,
followed by the column vector, then you can't scalar.
You can work out this.
Yeah, I can see it now.
Yeah, you can see, yeah, that side has even consensually you can view it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Simple one, yeah.
Yeah, good.
Thank you.
I hope you'll find it useful.
Yeah, thank you.
Hi, you.
Thank you.
Yeah, hopefully we finish early, shorten the break in the middle.
Before we go into the content, I will give some quite basic but useful techniques and
I will talk about the probability which is just involving some simple relationship.
And that's why I emphasize here.
Here I'm talking only scalar, random variable, but they are mostly you can extend into matrix
in some special case.
So for example, if you have a scalar ring that's available X, sorry, actually, when
we talk about variance, we don't need to, yeah, yeah, we, so sometimes I get confused
myself.
So that's variance of X.
It's already the variance except it's a second-order operator.
So it's the same as you take the second-order moment, I mean X is a random variable, raise
a power of 2 is second moment expectation.
Subtract first expectation, E of X, raise a power of 2.
So don't get confused, this E of X power of 2 and EX raise power of 2.
So this is we are operating on the random variable power of 2, like the number polynomial,
you raise power of 2.
Well, this one is E of X, just first order the expectation, then you make power of 2
on the E of X.
And these are these very useful relationship.
We will use that again very often several times at least in the future.
Remember this.
And then this following is some very simple results also involving variable and deterministic
coefficient.
Again, I just looked at the scalar case.
So if we are, yeah, so here I have a value of this.
So this is constant multiplied by X.
And remember always you can take out the constant, but when you bring out mass-making power
of 2, this is second-order operation.
So quite often some students make mistakes by just take out B, then that will be wrong.
And the B here is deterministic where X is written.
And similarly here, if you work on the other two factors in it, anyway, so there also you
can show this, you get the same result here.
So BX, you take expectation raise the power of 2.
The same as you take out B power of 2, then take the expectation raise the power of 2.
And similarly here, your BX raise power of 2, you can take out B square.
But the X power of 2 remain inside.
This is outside, this is inside.
So don't get confused too.
Okay?
So these are very useful.
So I hope you remember this.
So yeah, just now some students asked about why this looks like the matrix.
So we put it in the denominator.
But of course this is a scalar.
A matrix will never divide a matrix.
A matrix, you divide, you have to take inverse.
So we will show that.
But how to see this is a scalar, you see?
You look at the most row vector, multiply by, this in the middle is a square matrix
because this S is column vector.
So you're just verified by using the box measure or just think about the dimension of the
multiplication is always determined at the end.
The row is determined by the number of rows of this first.
And this is a row vector.
Of course it's one.
And the last one, the number of columns of the last vector, which is one also column.
So therefore this is one by one scalar.
And some of you may wonder, yeah, the variant here, we have one here.
You already have this part.
Then another one also have this.
But somehow the numerator create one of this.
So you can show out one.
The end up is very simple.
So that's to clarify.
Then now we continue into vector parameter case based on what we learned early for the
scalar case.
So the idea is similar except we're getting more involved.
You have to handle the matrix now in this.
This is vector.
So the data is still vector.
But because this become a vector estimator, then everything become more complicated.
And that's why here we need to be more careful about those matrix operations.
So how to do that is if you look at each of the elements in the unknown parameter vector,
we were doing the linear estimation for each of them.
So we call it as use a small index m.
So one, two, three, four, five in total m.
So that means we are given the same data vector.
The data vector is also assumed as n.
But we are using it multiple times.
So think about the same data.
We use the same data to estimate each of the scalar element unknown parameter.
But of course you will be using a different combination.
So you combine different ways.
Your n times is the different estimate in the n.
So again, how are we going to choose this?
That's very similar to what we did before for the scalar case.
But you extend it to the more general case.
The first difference is now this is vector, then this x is vector.
So in order to create a vector, of course, our a must be a matrix.
So that's again, as I say, you see our theta, it's a column vector.
So the number of rows, in this case m, so our a matrix must be m in order to match this.
But for x is n, so for the a matrix dimension, the row must be equal to this.
And the column, number of columns must be equal to x.
So therefore n times m by n matrix.
And then again, similar to what we require in the scalar case, we don't require the data to be a linear model.
But the expectation should be linear in terms of theta.
So you have a constant matrix s and multiplied by theta.
So in this case, assume this is already this form then, we just work to achieve the unbiased.
You want to make this equal to theta, then this a of s, the product must be a identity matrix.
Because s is a vector, not the scalar.
And this s matrix, the dimension is the transpose of this, of the dimension of this matrix.
So if you a matrix, when you transpose, it will become n by n.
And that's how this, otherwise when you multiply, you want to make it to be identity matrix of what dimension?
This i dimension must be the same as theta.
It will be n by n.
So you can also verify.
Usually n is bigger than m.
So you can draw the figure by making Paul or making Fett.
And how are we going to do for this?
In order to try to make good use of what we just did for the scatter case, we partitioned the a and s matrix.
Be careful here.
The partition of s is easy.
It's a standard way.
You just do it by column.
Because this is a matrix.
You have encoder m number of columns.
So we just call each column as column vector.
But the a is, you have to be a bit careful.
You can think about the two ways to interpret.
Why we want to do that?
Because later you will see the result is much easier to interpret.
So the easier way, which I always tell students to remember is you transpose the a first.
You can give them an a.
Think about your transpose the a.
Because a is not square matrix in general.
So you take the transpose.
After taking, you see, because I take the transpose.
We have the transpose here.
Now with that you divide into columns in the same way as there.
But you partitioned the a transpose into a1, a2 and so on.
Alternatively, if you already want to look at how are you partitioning the original a matrix.
Then you need to apply this transpose into each of the column vector.
So how are you going to do that?
Remember this is not a product.
So I'm going to show you again here to make good use, keep this one active.
Because the system is very funny if I don't use it for 20 minutes.
Turn off and it seems I cannot recover.
Actually last week when I shut down the computer, I cannot shut down.
I have to report.
It took quite some time to, so I hope today I can shut down.
If not, I will keep ask one of you to be here to observe.
I think a few students stay back then they know the problem.
But the CITA they say, oh, the next day they came, there's no problem.
So it looks like I'm telling them something with a mistake.
Actually I did take photos.
So anyway, this is one of the problems.
I really don't know.
So let's go back to this A again.
It's also useful to know how it operates.
If I have column, so these are column vector, A and N.
Now how are we going to transfer that?
So what you do is you convert each column vector to transpose.
So become, of course, become row.
A1, then now you are putting because they become row.
So you are putting each one on top of the other.
So that's another way to do it.
So that means I, in a sense, if I directly partition the A, A matrix,
I partition it according, I think this one last one should be,
is it M or N?
Yeah, M, yeah, also.
So I'm going to call it A1, because the number of rows of A is the same as the number of columns of S.
So either way, just repeat again, you can easily transpose A first and partition according to column.
And each column we call A1, A2, A3.
So then gradually you can directly partition the A matrix into rows.
And each rows we call it as A1 transpose, because we want to keep A1 as a vector.
So it's a vector transpose to become rows.
So hope this is clear to you.
Because later on you will see this notation is easier to link to the result.
We're deriving.
So therefore, why?
Because if you're doing in that way, then you will see A as the condition equal to I,
then it will become very convenient.
And then you will be taking something like inner product of two column vector, A, I and S, J.
But of course, A, I must transpose, become a row.
Yeah, so yeah.
And why this I?
You see I is the intake of this.
J is this intake.
They are all running from 1 to M.
So this delta function, this is the conventional definition.
So I hope you know the definition.
That means I equal to J for this delta, you are equal to 1.
If I not equal to J, say for example 1 and 2, then of course it's equal to 0.
So that captures the identity matrix.
I and J basically, if you are referring to the same index, you will be in the diagonal element.
You will be equal to 1.
So this condition is the same as that.
That's important.
And then again here, this is even more important, you see, because we are involving matrix.
J is a matrix, but you can use the similar operation as I did early.
So I don't need to repeat what I mentioned earlier.
So basically, we want to relate this covariate matrix of the estimator with respect to the covariate matrix of the data.
Of course, involving now our coefficient.
And the relation of this, and if you again, of the data, of the estimator,
related to the covariate of the data by adding the A matrix we are going to obtain.
So that means from here, you see this data, the data given, covariate matrix of the data given,
but we can try to work on A to achieve, you know, minimize this.
So going back to the early one, I think this Lagrangian, the meaning of this operator I need to emphasize.
Why? We want to minimize this.
You know, this is one we are going to minimize.
But we need to add this constraint, because if not, if we don't add constraint to minimize this,
it's a very easy task if I choose A vector equal to 0.
And this becomes 0, which is a smallish one.
And it doesn't work, because if A equal to 0, then that means our estimator is also equal to 0.
So we are doing nothing.
So this constraint means A cannot be 0.
If A equal to 0, then you cannot satisfy this condition.
So that's very important.
And it's similar here.
In the vector parameter case, we cannot do an easy job by making A equal to 0.
So if we add constraint, then it's the easiest one, make this E equal to 0, and achieve.
So what we're going to do here is to rely this into breaking down into each of the elements, you see?
So now C theta hat is this relation.
Then if you use this partition of A and then A transpose, you will see here.
And then after that, using the very simple sub-matrix multiplication,
you can see each of the elements.
It will be the first one.
For example, you multiply in the center.
There's always this Cx.
This is the same.
But to get the first element, you take A1, the first low transpose of this A1 vector.
Then A1, you'll get this.
Similarly, to get this second one, two, you just take A1 transpose and A2.
So you get this and so on.
So all this by using the partition form of A.
So as I said, you need some very simple operation on sub-matrix.
Therefore, the variance of each of the estimates, you see?
Because to get the variance, we only need to look at the diagonal one.
This off-diagonal is you need there if you are later doing the inversion.
Just like our CILB, you want to invert the i-matrix.
If it's not diagonal, you need off-diagonal.
But after inversion, what you need is this.
Only the diagonal one is the one meaningful.
And it will be the same here.
In A, we want to get the variance of each of the estimates to be as small as possible.
Again, there.
So now here, we have a very similar form.
It's the scatter case.
But we need to do this collectively, not just look at each of them.
Because you may end up with they all become the same M.
We have to do it according to the given data and the constraint here.
Because this S vector may have a different value for different elements.
Again here, we make our task look at each of these M, become this term.
Minimize that subject to this condition.
The one we already know.
So again, we go back to our good friends, La-klang-je.
It's the same here.
We look at each, so it becomes more manageable.
So this term is the same looking at each element.
But this constraint, we need more constraints.
So be careful.
For 1, 6k, we need to run through the different J.
The J is basically based on this.
You are from 1 to M.
And then the La-klang-je, this coefficient, it will also be a matrix.
Because we have different J, different K.
So once you fix this, we take the vector derivative.
It's similar to what we did before.
So it should be familiar with that.
And this is linear.
This is second order.
Second order, you take derivative.
And this, oh, I also need to emphasize this C-X matrix.
It's a symmetric one.
So you only have one term.
And this one is the fourth order.
It's a linear function of A-k.
So you don't have A-k left.
You have this.
And then after that, again, you need to simplify a little bit.
And we get a similar form of this A-k here, except it's more involved.
We have this S-matrix here.
And also lambda is, now it's a vector also.
Because this is a vector.
It is okay.
And let's see, this is the constraint, you see, given.
We already know for this.
The meaning of E of k is here.
The unit vector in the k dimension.
So I hope you're familiar with this.
Let me emphasize the meaning of here.
Because this one we need to use quite often.
Say E-k here will be equal to say unit vector.
That means the other value, they are all zero.
Except this is the k-k position.
Say assume k equal to 3.
It will be the first one, zero, zero, then three.
The position of three becomes one.
And k equal to one, then it will be one, zero, zero.
So remember the definition of this.
Again, this helps me to switch back to this.
Yeah.
And yeah.
So we have this relationship based on this condition.
Then we get the similar result as what we did before.
Lambda k.
But except, this pi is similar.
Except now this is, you have to, this is a vector.
So you need to have this, have this also vector.
And there are, that your sub-student bag, you'll get the optimal 8k vector.
Our k is, we have to do it one, two, three, four up to m.
So each of them, we have a similar form.
So this part looks interesting.
This one is independent of k.
So only this, the last one.
So that means we get, for example, the first one.
We will basically taking the, you see the first number.
This is a matrix.
Then you'll be picking up the first column and so on.
So the second one, you pick the second column.
That's, now to be careful about this.
Now we have to put back this theta hat, which is equal to a multiplied by the theta x.
So remember our a is this vector transform.
You see, I told you there are two forms.
You'll get this, you'll get this a.
So here is something.
Oh yeah, okay.
So here.
Yeah, so this is one, you see, our a is either this way or this way.
So that's how the optimal is the same.
You see, we do it here, multiplied by x.
And then again, you'll do, you see, each need to transform.
So if you go back to here, you'll, this whole thing, transform, our e k transform will become the,
become the lab most and the other independent of the k.
So you see here, if you know the meaning of e1, e1 is a vector.
The first element equal to 1.
The rest equal to 0.
But after your transform, it becomes a row vector.
Then the first element is 1, 0, 0, 0.
Then the second one, 0, 1, 0, 0.
Then subsequently, you're shifting this one from lab to the right by depending on the position.
So therefore, you can verify this become an identity matrix, i.
So being identity matrix, of course, we do not need this.
So therefore, our rule for this vector case is just equal to this one.
All right.
So this looks nice because it's almost the same form as the scalar case except the s,
previously is a vector.
Now become a matrix.
And furthermore, the covariant matrix, again here, this is, you'll put in here.
And then again, our optimal one is this.
And then you put this EL here.
So this is, we are talking about covariant matrix of each element, KL, because the matrix is big.
So we just look at each element.
The element could be off-diagonal, could be diagonal, depending on the value of K and L.
K is the row, and L is the column position.
So again, I repeat here, that will be, you see, our AK here optimal is K transform.
Then this EL is the one column at the far right.
Then you multiply and then you simplify a little bit.
So again, in the middle, they cancel out one term.
So we end up with this.
And to be careful, if you observe, you'll see as I mentioned earlier, this EL, multiply at the far right.
If you pick the L column, where the AK transform row here, pick the K rows of that matrix.
So in the end, combining these two, we will be picking up this matrix from the K rows and L column at that position.
And we happen to be, for this covariant matrix, we are evaluating at this KL, looking at this KL position.
Then, of course, for all of the index run through from 1 to M.
So therefore, this matrix inside must be just equal to the matrix inside.
So finally, we get this C, C, the hat, this covariant matrix is just equal to this.
So that's why this understanding of the matrix and how to operate will be very useful and essential to,
of course, some of the basic factors about this unit vector and the meaning of that and the definition.
And in particular, how are we going to get each element through this?
Because the observation is, you can see here, our theta hat in the end, you only depend on this.
And similarly, C, C, theta, we will, once you substitute, they also make sense because we only need the so-called,
this scale matrix based on the means, the expectation of the data.
And the second order, the data covariant matrix.
And also, remember the scalar case is the spatial case of the matrix case.
So if you reduce this, the unknown parameter from multiple M into 1,
then you expect to get the same result as by making this more general expression reduced to the scalar parameter case.
And that verifies the, yeah, being the case.
So any question, any problem at this point?
Are you okay with the elevation and so on and this?
So yeah, some should ask whether this elevation requires, yeah, I think mostly you should know.
And if you are working out the Simon question, some of the Simon questions are similar to the like,
paper question. So it's one of the first assignment one.
So it will be, yeah, also let you get familiar with the requirements and get familiar with the exercises on this part.
So yeah, and yeah, after you submit, then we'll go through the solutions or at least the partial solution for that.
So any questions before we maybe move on to finish this chapter?
So do you find today's week easier compared to, okay, so mostly just metrics and some tricks, yeah, fine?
Okay, good. So we can continue.
So this is the same year.
Now this is where we go back, combine with the general linear model.
So you see here, there's a relation between linear model and linear estimator.
So depending on, you know, model is our data linearly depend on the unknown planet.
So this edge is called this.
Well, linear estimator is other, we're given the data doing linear combination.
So and then we, before coming to this part, we do not require this model, but we require the means expectation satisfy this similar condition.
So yeah, the same as something edge is data vector.
And then this is a non constant coefficient matrix.
And then I mentioned it to make sure it's not necessarily square one.
And usually not equal to n.
Usually n is much larger compared to n.
And this is data vector.
And now we also have this noise is, there must be the same dimension with x.
You are adding this noise vector with zero means and covariant metrics.
So we assume this first, we do not need Gaussian here first.
We are just looking at this linear model.
And also our noise covariant metrics is c is not necessarily diagonal.
So yeah, so from here, you see you apply this expectation into this vector,
then you follow the same linear operation, e of x, you apply this.
It will be edge theta.
And then e of w, because this is a zero mean, then become zero vector, zero.
So therefore, in this case, we know the s metrics have to be edge here.
Therefore, if we apply the proof, since here we already know the covariant metrics of the noise.
So here some students may argue because our covariant is for the noise,
but why is for the data also?
Any feedback, any comment?
Because this part is deterministic, you see?
So when you get the, maybe it's a good thing we had a little bit time left here today.
I don't want to rush into the next chapter.
If you continue into some of my discussion here, here I'm talking about constant,
the deterministic multiplied by a random variable.
But we can also extend it into the summation part.
If I have, say, again, we just look at scatter case, if x plus b, okay?
So, yeah, you can make it more general by multiply coefficient a, yeah.
But we already know how the road coefficient.
So if you look at expectation of that, we already know this is e of x plus e of b is just equal to b.
But the weapon, if I now want to get the variance of this x plus b, it got to work.
Yes, can we ignore this?
If you take the expectation, we cannot ignore b.
b is no zero.
But to get the variance, it's just equal to variance of x.
Why?
Any, you can conceptually, b is a constant, yes?
Okay, yeah, that's very good, yes.
So that's conceptually.
But here we can make it a little bit more rigorous.
We can apply, we can derive that also to be, yeah.
So let's see what we can do in this case.
Actually, this is also good, because early on I talked about this relationship.
But some students may also wonder why do we get this?
So I think I will do the two steps in one go.
So we go back to principle, you see, to the definition.
I want to get the variance of x plus b, just ignore the coefficient.
So by definition, you see, we go into very fundamental.
It will be, you see, 3D is, we don't remove the b first.
We put that, we call that, that is y, for example.
Then it will be x plus b, correctively thinking about y, minus expectation of this x plus b.
So b must be also there, okay.
Then take the difference, then you square it.
So this is how we will be doing.
Now if you explain it first, because we make it easier just looking at the scalar case.
So we make life easy, but metric case is similar, just more, more involved.
So we, because this one all being, being scalar.
I can take the first term here, square, alright.
And then subtract two times of this x plus b, then e of this x plus b.
Then finally, you have to add here.
Early on I make a mistake by making it a minor, so it should be add.
Now this is e x plus b, power of two.
Okay, so yeah, so now since we break down into each term, we can bring the e inside.
You cannot break the e inside the term within the power of two, because that's not the right way.
Now since you're explaining the sum of three terms, so I can do it now, you see.
So therefore we have this e of x plus b, power of two.
Okay, so remember it's power of two first.
And then subtract this two x plus b.
Then now we multiply, multiply inside, because we call e of x.
I just keep it there, but e of b is the same as b, you know what I mean?
Keep this.
And then now how about the last term?
You multiply inside first, e of x.
Plus b.
Okay, then you need to do it power of two.
Is it right? Anything wrong?
Expectation, yes, we still need to keep the expectation from outside.
I haven't moved in yet.
Yeah, very good, thanks for pointing out.
So that will be like this, am I right?
So let's try to simplify it a little bit now if I...
Yes?
Oh, the...
Maybe you mean?
Yeah, we would have the state b outside the state of n plus 2 minus 3.
Yeah, okay, that's another...
Yes, that's a simple way to do it.
But yeah, we can do it either way, but okay, that's good.
So what you said, yes, maybe it's also easy.
You are saying you directly operate on this first,
but I want to show how you remove the power of two.
You need to explain the power of two first,
or let's see, yeah, how are you going to take the b out if it's reading?
Maybe you'll come up sometimes,
you know in the past, smoke outside,
actually I take them for some students to come out.
It's good your volunteer to...
I want to see how you do it then,
and then I can take this from student point of view,
it's actually better to take this.
Yeah?
So this is plus b minus expectation of x plus b,
and this square is outside.
So we don't have to handle the square,
we can just do this, okay?
This is just equal to the expectation of x plus b minus...
Okay, okay.
expectation of x plus b here.
Okay, okay, there you can sort out the b.
Oh yes, yes, very smart, so we see.
Yes, very good, yeah.
That's right, very good, thank you.
There is almost done, so we...
Yeah, that's good, but if you all go to the routing way,
then you will see in the end, it can sort out.
But this is even better inside.
Inside one, but you have to be careful,
you don't touch the power of two first.
Yeah, because there is a very good operation,
because then after that, yeah, that's a property of e of x.
So I may like more clearly.
It will become minus e of x, then minus...
Because e of b is the b, so your minus b.
Then this one needs the power of two.
And you can sort this equal to e of this,
x minus e of x, power of two of this.
And that's precisely which is the variant of x.
Yeah, very good, very fast.
Okay, so for this part,
e of b is a much easier way.
So please learn from...
So let's give a applause for this.
I know your name.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Thanks.
I hope the other students can be more active, proactive.
Okay, so very good.
I give you some bonus, because you...
Yeah, so that's very good.
You never save the trouble of deriving from the principle.
Yeah, so yeah, that's a good way.
You make good use of whatever simple step you can make good use.
You do it early, then you'll get a much easier derivation.
And that's what I emphasize.
In this course, later through the assignment one,
there will be some of the questions.
There are always...
Usually they will have several approaches,
and I also want to show after the...
you'll submit the results.
Then I will go through them to let you know they are in this course,
because derivation is...
You know, sometimes very often you can get different ways.
Some are a bit more troublesome.
Some is easier, but try to find the easiest way.
So therefore this concludes the result is random variable plus a constant.
For means, you have to keep the mean, the expectation, the constant, still there.
But for barrier, you just look at the random part.
Yeah, that's also very useful,
because save a lot of trouble here
when we are looking into this one here.
So you see here, our covariance matrix of the data is the same,
because this one is just like the P, you see?
So when we get the expectation, we are taking this part.
But when we take about the covariance matrix of this,
it's the same as this random part.
And the covariance matrix of the noise already given by C.
So our C of X is the same as C here.
Okay, so therefore you'll get everything,
then you'll get the covariance matrix of the estimate here.
Yeah, that's good.
So we spend a little bit time to at least understand here better.
And you can also see here at least through this past two weeks or so.
Most of the time we need to know the expectation
and the second moment of the random variable.
It's not as the requirement of probability and random process,
rather minimum,
comparing to the 7401,
where everything is about the whole cause,
is probability and random process.
But we are here, we are combining with some signal processing
and maybe a little bit on the communication one.
Not much, but more in the...
Yeah, it's related to communication.
But in communication, you also need to do detection estimation.
Okay, so yeah.
So we still have some time, but I, as I say,
I won't go into the next chapter because the MLE is important,
but I want to make good use of this probably 20 minutes or so.
Go through this matrix again
because that part I believe is very important.
So this is one already uploaded in the interview.
So these are the one.
This part, the trace we will do later.
So we put it together.
So symmetric matrix is easy.
And this is the...
64.
64 is the early topic, it's actually the same,
but I can go through the newer one.
So let me just go through it
and then I will emphasize some of the important properties
because linear algebraic is, later you will see, is quite useful.
So first, we have dealing with no square matrix in general, including no square.
But in the special case, with M equal to N, here, they will become square one.
So they are here, I'm assuming where M is smaller than N,
or equal to N, maximum.
But we can do it otherwise.
So I partition this into low vector.
And then each is one by N matrix called low vector.
And then one of the important concepts, we call that as, assuming we have K low vector.
Among them, K of course, maximum up to a small m, but it can be smaller than N.
So at least that is going a1, a2, aK up to K.
If K equal to M, then all of them, if not, then it will be somewhere in the middle.
So we put those linearly independent.
So what's the meaning of linearly independent?
Because that's an important concept.
How to define that?
If we want to try to use any constant, b1, b2, and so on, a1 here is both phase.
So these are low vector.
But b1 and so on, they are just scalar constant coefficient.
If you try to see they add together for whatever choice of b1, b2, and so on,
you want to make it zero, then the only choice, the b1, b2, and up to pK,
all of them must be zero in order to make it zero.
Of course, you make all of them zero, you will also become a zero vector.
For linearly independent one, wherever you let even one of them not equal to zero,
your n-tabway is not equal to zero.
Of course, we're assuming our a1, a2, and so on, they are not equal to a zero vector.
Actually, if one of them happens to be a zero, then this zero vector cannot be linearly independent
of the other because I can always, for example, a1 is a zero.
Then I make b1 not equal to zero.
Then the rest equal to zero.
You satisfy the condition, but it's b1 not equal to zero.
So therefore, it will mean all of these a1, a2, ak vector, they are at least not the zero
vector to be linearly independent.
Furthermore, you cannot find any other b1, b2 to make it zero, except you make all of
them as zero.
So that's a two-bit one.
This is very important.
The meaning of this is linearly independent.
By using any of the row vectors, you cannot linearly compile by using the rest of the
vector.
Just try to linearly compile.
So that means each row is in the same linearly independent to the other.
If you look at the space, look at the two-dimensions.
Just assume you have two vectors.
So these two vectors, being linearly independent, as long as they are not lying on the same
line in the 2D plane, so it will generate the true 2D plane.
If the two of them are in the same line, of course, you can only generate one line.
So the meaning is it will be clear.
If you have two, generate a plane.
If there are three, generate a three-dimensional space.
Higher one, and we cannot visualize, but you just imagine you get higher dimensions, but
they must be linearly independent.
So this is the first thing you need to remember.
As I say, I may put this as one of the basic requirements in the course.
And then the row ring of A. So given a matrix, as you will define the ring, it's very important.
We call that as maximum numbers of these linearly independent row vectors.
So given now we have M rows.
So if it happened to be all of the M rows linearly independent, the row ring is M.
But if less than that, say M is 5, but you only file three of them independent.
They will call this row ring 3.
So that's easy to understand.
So the alternative definition defines the greatest integer D.
Here is determinant of the sub-matrix.
It's not equal to no zero constant.
These are also very important concepts.
We call sub-matrix, sometimes we call it as the determinant of sub-matrix.
We call it as a minor, D by D minor.
Because in general, as I mentioned, this matrix may be a no square matrix in general.
But given a no square matrix, we can always pick the sub-matrix where this sub-block,
they are square, for example, 2 by 2.
If you have, say, 2 by 3 matrix, then you can take the first two rows, 2 by 2,
then the first row and the first column and the third column,
and get another, generate another sub-matrix.
So as long as you try to get as big as, as big as the sub-matrix,
as possible you can get, say, among the, usually say you have 5 by 10.
5 by 10 matrix.
You always look at the smallest one.
So one by one, of course, as long as the matrix is not totally zero,
then you have ring one at least.
Then the second one, you just took some of the 2 by 2.
If the determinant of this sub-matrix is not zero, then it is ring two.
Then, after that, you keep increasing up to the maximum.
So this is another definition.
Sometimes late home, we'll get more into that.
And then, leaving the ring rows can be defined similarly.
Actually, for giving matrix on any side,
the maximum number of is leaning dependent row vector always equal to is leaning dependent column vector.
So even if the matrix is not square one, you may sometimes think I'm more column, like 5 by 10.
Then it may be possible I'm more independent column compared to independent row.
Not possible.
So that's why eventually we talk about ring.
We just refer to the maximum either column ring or the row ring.
The maximum one is the same.
But the matrix can be of full row ring if the ring A is equal to N.
And then similarly, or full column ring if ring of A equal to N.
Because the number of column may not be the same as column number of row.
But then the maximum one, they must be the same.
You cannot be one is larger than the other.
But dimension can be different.
So now let's see the M by N matrix can be both of full row ring and full column ring.
Only if it is square one, square matrix, M equal to N.
That's very important.
So therefore, that's why we call the ring of matrix.
Just take any of the sub-matrix which give Nd by D, the largest sub-block.
And some of the property I think I mentioned before.
The ring of a product of A and B must be smaller or equal to either ring A or ring B.
It cannot be greater than the ring of each of them.
So when you multiply, then the ring, normally you are lucky, you keep the same ring.
But it can reduce.
So rather than you add two matrix, then you get the bigger ring.
Sometimes it depends.
But the ring may increase but can never be bigger than the sum of each of the ring.
That's also a very useful property.
And then there is this power, so convention.
The convention is similar to the scalar.
Any number raised to power 0 is equal to 1.
But matrix, we say D5.
A matrix, only for square matrix raised to power 0 is equal to I.
And then A1 is just by itself.
A2 is a product of two.
Being square matrix, you can even break using the sum of the exponent.
You can use the product of each of these, knowing the negative integers.
And this is, for being, we don't need to know much here, projection matrix.
If A squared is equal to A, then this is a special one in some cause.
And then the null matrix, A is a null space.
Null space, no null matrix.
If A exists at least one null zero column vector, then you multiply this, become zero.
That means, you see, we start with a null zero column vector.
Somehow, if A multiplies this null zero, then make it zero.
So that means we have some kind of non-space.
So that your change, a null zero vector, becomes zero.
But of course, this is, it won't happen in the scalar case.
If your A multiplied by x, unless A equal to zero, then, you know, if a scalar case, A,
no equal to zero, you multiply by a null zero number, you will never become zero.
So that's something very different between matrix and scalar.
So that's something useful.
And also, you know, it's a, yeah, that's concept very useful.
It's also not a rule of that.
If now we have set of linearly independent column vector, that means, yeah, you will be A
multiplied by this.
All of them equal to zero.
So that means you will have this.
If only if any column vector be satisfied this.
So that means our A multiplied, if we have A multiplied by B equal to zero, then our
B will be a linearly combination of all these x1, x2, which satisfy this.
So, yeah.
So therefore, from here, you can say the non-space of A is generated by this x1, xl.
And then the dimension of this non-space equal to l.
So, you see, I have at least all these.
So, and then we can define the range.
Y is in the range of A.
If we can find some vector such that we want to create this Y from the A matrix.
Of course, you must multiply by some x.
If you can find this, then that means our Y is in the same, generated by the A matrix.
You see, the other one here is how we multiply by, you can think about this, zero is also
generated by this A in the same.
You'll find some x.
That's the equal to zero.
So here is other way.
So, we're breaking five x such that this A multiplied by x, generally this is Y.
But not always, you see, some of the Y, depending on the property of the A, you may never find
any x to satisfy this.
So, these are quite different property of magic.
And one of the very important concepts is eigenvalue and eigenvector.
So, that's very useful also because in general, you see, given the A matrix, I multiply by,
you can try it out by yourself, using whatever.
If you, in general, your A matrix multiplied by a vector, you will give another new vector,
which is not at least not in the same direction as B.
Because now in the space, okay, it will take a vector, multiply A from the left, it will
become a new vector.
And this new vector happens to be just in the same direction.
It will be a scaling of this given B vector.
So, this, that means after multiply, you will steer in the same direction.
But the, but the coefficient may change, say, from B, from becoming 2B, or 3B, or half, or 0.5B.
So, in this space, okay, this lambda is a scalar.
Then, we have the, we call that lambda is eigenvalue, so here is that.
And this vector is a eigenvector.
So, given an A, you only, you can find some eigenvector, which is this property.
But this A is a square matrix.
So, remember, eigendecomersion is requiring a square matrix.
Later on, the singular value, we can deal with a no square matrix.
So, how to, how to verify that, get eigenvalue and eigenvector?
Very easy.
So, always, given A, you'll minus this lambda times identity matrix.
Then make this determinant.
Determinant, if you expand it, it will be depending on the dimension of A.
It will be a polynomial of lambda.
And then, you all know polynomial, whatever, the order equal to 3, you will find 3 rules, 3, 0.
It could be complex, but here, we allow complex numbers.
So, yeah, okay?
So, that means you make the determinant equal to 0.
Then, you can, you can get this is one of the eigenvalues.
And after that, substitute this, you can solve and you will get the corresponding eigenvector.
Because once this determinant equal to 0, that means you have a non-space, okay, for square matrix.
Then, you reduce.
You can get no zero vector.
And this vector, it happens to be the eigenvector.
So, square matrix A of dimension 7 will have n linearly independent vector.
If all its n eigenvalues are distinct, it will satisfy.
But this is only sufficient condition.
If the eigenvalues are the same, you may also have independent eigenvector.
But you cannot guarantee.
Otherwise, A may or may not.
Yes, so you see here, I have n linearly independent vector.
If they are distinct, then we are very sure.
But if not, then you will depend.
Then this symmetric matrix, this one is very important.
We have this.
And later on, we will see if this is expectation, you see, we will be taking the outer product.
We will see.
So, symmetric eigenvalues or symmetric matrix are very important.
They are all real.
So, these are very special properties.
And then, the symmetric matrix will always have n linearly independent eigenvector.
So, in this case, it may or may not be orthogonal, but can be met orthogonal.
Linenly independent, for example, in the two dimensional case, if I have two vectors,
they are not, as long as they are not in the same line, 45 degree.
They are linearly independent, but not orthogonal.
A orthogonal, they must be 90 degrees, but you can do some change to make them orthogonal.
Okay, so these are very important.
A is positive definite or semi-definite.
All of its eigenvalues are positive or at least non-negative.
So, later, we will go back into that in some examples later.
So, here is just some definition.
If A is positive definite, all of its principal minus are also positive.
So, yeah.
So, this one, we can define a matrix having columns to be eigenvector.
You just put them together.
Then, if A is symmetric, you can always choose its eigenvector as orthogonal.
So, in that case, this V matrix becomes an orthogonal matrix.
And that's very important because our A can be written in this way.
Because orthogonal, then the inverse, you will be just equal to the transpose.
So, you can have this decomposition.
And then you can write as the...
Yeah, this is a diagonal matrix with this diagonal.
Those are eigenvalues.
And this is what we call like the outer product, you see, because A is a matrix.
So, you need vector followed by column vector.
And then, if no singular, you can get the inverse by just inverting this.
So, it's very easy.
And then, you can also define the square of this matrix by taking the square of each of the diagonal elements.
So, that's very convenient.
Finally, the singular value decomposition is...
We can deal with a no square matrix.
So, in this case, you can see the similar eigenvectors decomposition, except the left and right matrix.
They are different matrix.
For eigenvectors decomposition, it's the same matrix, you see.
So, that's the main difference.
So, it can be more flexible.
And how to get that, actually, is we are dealing that by taking the transpose together.
So, what we get there is we make this A no square matrix become a square one by A multiplied by A transpose,
or A transpose multiplied by A to get certified with U and V.
So, then you can get the so-called left...
eigen...
Yeah, left and right singular vector for singular value decomposition.
So, yeah.
So, how to get there, yes.
We are using this either A transpose A to get this,
and all A multiplied by A transpose to get this V.
So, these are both square.
But both of them, if they are not...
The matrix no square cannot be both of them of full range.
You can easily verify by looking at the side.
Okay.
And similarly, using this decomposition, we can write this A into this very special form.
Yeah.
Then, you cannot inverse if no square one,
but we can get the so-called generalized or pseudo inverse by looking at one of the full range one.
Yeah.
So, after that, the definition of generalized is either in this form or in that form.
So, if you remember what the...
Last week, we were talking about the linear model.
Then we kept this.
Only one of them can be of full range.
So, we are looking at something similar to this pseudo inverse.
I think that's...
In reality, I think it's not a matrix.
So, that's all for today.
So, I hope this additional one can help you to understand this very basic of linear spreading matrix.
So, I think it's the time we can finish today's class.
So, I will see you next week.
Any questions?
You can stay back to ask or can email me or...
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
Bye.