What does your head feel?
Okay.
Welcome back after the recess week.
So I hope you enjoy the one-week break.
Also some doing the assignments and so on.
So let's just update the exam.
I think it's the same as we repeat a few times already.
And then for the CA-1, I extend a few days
and by yesterday evening midnight.
The good news is all of you have some me.
And I, yeah, so it's 100%.
So everyone has some me, but because the number of students
is much larger compared to previous years.
So I give it to the extension of about six days for the summits.
So I don't think I can finish the marking by next week.
So, yeah, because initially I thought you submit by Wednesday last week.
Then I spent some time reviewing the recess week.
So anyway, so the plan is since we will have a quiz for part two.
Not the whole part two is part two excluding the last chapter.
You know, part two has several chapters.
So, and I believe the CA-1 solution, I will go through the solution
after I finish marking all the assignments of you.
And now I should be able to do it during week 10,
which is one week before the recess week.
Because now it's already week eight.
So, yeah, so that's, so hope everyone can come to attend for the,
I will spend maybe one hour going through the assignment,
so-called solution, I won't say complete solution,
maybe just partial solutions so that you can see
how well you have done against the work the solutions given.
And that will help you to learn the contents of part one.
And in some sense also part two, because part two,
as you already know, quite often we use very similar technique
because for this course, part one and part two,
they are very much related, not like the 6401 on Monday
because I start to teach the part two on that course.
So, I think some of you also attending the Monday class,
just next door, LTE 20.
Okay, so I hope this is clear, it's all being said eight to nine
because our LTE is large enough to accommodate all the students of this class.
But during the quiz, I will have a few student assistants to help.
So everyone must sit one MTC to the next person.
Calculate the capacity of this LTE, it's just large enough.
Okay, so any question?
I see one already done, so you just wait for the results.
And also, as I promised, I think it's easy and the only lecturer
for some other class if you are teaching the course taught by two lecturers,
usually the first lecturer finish, then some middle assignment.
So no chance to go through.
So this is one of the bounties.
So that's about the outline and more later.
Okay, so that's about the assignment.
I will also make an announcement.
I already make several times, but I will say a reminder
that the students are doing come near.
So before going, this very quick summary of what we did for the detection.
So the first one is a week, seven.
This is similar.
I used the previous one because of the...
I don't know why it happened.
It looks like they are using a different way to...
Let me see.
Very strange.
I don't know why, but it seems not...
Okay, I think we just use this one.
So I think the detection part, as I say, is easier in a sense of
comparing to the estimation theory because the idea is also simpler
because we are mostly concentrating on the binary detection.
I mean, you have two hypothesis, either H0 or H1.
Typically, the simplest one is one has noise only.
The other has signal plus noise.
Of course, there is a little bit more extension.
You can get two different signals, which we will go through later.
This is in this case, but you can see the two problems are very closely related.
Both of them we call there as a binary detection
because it differentiates two different hypotheses.
You can also consider more than two, which we call M hypothesis.
In this case, we also call it classification.
Not a little bit different from now the machine learning classification.
So this is following more the statistical modeling approach.
But the basic idea is somewhat similar.
You're trying to differentiate two classifications.
Usually, we will be dealing with more than two.
But nowadays, we will go to machine learning sometimes.
Two class, you also call a two class classification problem.
So a binary classification.
It's not so clearly differentiated.
As I highlighted during week seven, which is the week before last week,
the most important concept and technique in this detection.
Detection theory will be an NP approach.
This is the most important one because that's more like the classical traditional detection theory.
From here, you can also extend into, not really extend, but somewhat related.
You will have the Bayesian approach.
Similar to the estimation theory, you have a classical one and the so-called more than one, which is the Bayesian approach.
But it has also been for quite some time, not really the so-called state-of-the-art approach.
So it's just the two approach somewhat different.
Different emphasis.
But later, you will see in some situations, the two of them are also closely related.
We will spend more time on NP approach even in subsequent chapter.
So this gives you the fundamental idea about detection theory.
So again, if you are talking about binary hypothesis test, we have these two.
And then for detection, sometimes we also call hypothesis test.
So in here, you have several mixed use of terminology.
And usually, you won't make a perfect detection.
Of course, sometimes it does happen, but very unlikely.
So normally, you make detection because you are dealing with noisy data, noisy measurement.
So you're likely to make some kind of decision detection errors.
So it could be two types, type 1 error.
Assume we are dealing with binary work.
Then we will decide H1 when SG low is true.
So you make the wrong decision.
And so this is one situation.
And in the simplest case, assume there is no signal.
We are dealing with signal or signal noise or noise only.
So when there is only noise, but the noise may be very strong.
So you will think there is a signal.
And this is sometimes we also call it as force alarm.
So that makes the type 1 error.
On that thing, you can do a type 2 error.
When the signal is there, H1 is there.
Then you decide SG low.
That means you think there is no signal, but actually the signal is there.
So this is what we call mixed detection.
You'll miss the target.
That's also way out here.
For B force alarm, that's because we are dealing with probability things.
So you can have this.
And this is what related to the type 2 error.
But here we introduce the probability framework.
And then normally we use the probability of detection
and the probability of miss.
But this tool in the final case like this is clearly related.
The sum, the two of them will be equal to 1.
So we'll be using that.
And then based on all these notation, definition, and our NP theory,
we have this.
So you don't need to differentiate.
Usually for capital P, there will be probability.
So probability will be just a number,
like probability equal to 1 is the highest.
And it will be probability of zero.
It will never happen in the middle, then 0.5.
So you see here, this is hyper-sacces.
And on the other hand, you can introduce the major data.
So this small p is more like PDF, or we will know the PDF.
Or we also assume, depending on your gift hyper-sacces,
then we are talking about the distribution of the data,
the major data PDF.
Or on the other hand, using the same function,
once you have fixed the data,
and then we want to see in this case what's the probability.
So we call the likelihood function.
It's the same, but it just depends on how you interpret it.
And that's the same as what we did early in the estimation theory.
So anyway, if you look at that, you'll see there will be a function of the major data.
So the NP theory is relatively simple after some derivation.
And we will decide, because here we're only at H1 and at 0.
We'll decide H1 if we take the likelihood ratio.
So of course, you need to assume you have this PDF function for the given data.
So you just take the ratio of this.
So again, the ratio itself is also a function of the data we call the likelihood ratio.
And then compare with a threshold.
So this threshold is, again, in the NP approach,
it's determined by the probability of false alarm.
So you can also see here, probability of false alarm is this likelihood function.
And you need to be clear to see whether it's on H1 or H0.
So in this ratio, H1, the one to do the decision will be in the numerator.
The one, the other hypothesis will be the denominator.
But when you get the probability false alarm, you calculate to integrate based on this,
based on the one and the hypothesis of H0.
And that's also for our definition, because probability false alarm is when you are on the hypothesis H0.
Then you'll make a mistake by thinking this data.
You'll make a decision using this ratio to assume those are greater than this threshold.
So you decide that there is a target there.
It's on the H1, but this is wrong.
So that's the meaning of probability of false alarm.
You calculate, accumulate all of this.
And then under NP, we're required to be equal to a given constant, say, alpha.
Of course, being PDA, absolutely, being a probability will never be greater than 1.
And also greater than, it should be greater than 0.
So it's some small number, depending on applications.
You have seen, for example, it could be 0.5.
Or if your requirement is very high, it can go up to the smaller you're required.
Then the smaller of this value, that means your false alarm is very little.
But that will affect your decision, because these two are always contradicting.
You need to compromise.
So that's how you will be doing that.
And we already studied some examples.
And then, again here, particularly in the detection one, it's very, very clear.
You have data.
You'll try to combine the data to form a scalar function.
And this scalar function will produce some value.
So we need to see when it will be under H1, when it will be under H0.
And so that's how you make these decisions.
And then we also talk about the performance.
And then for NP approach, typically you'll give this.
You will see how high we can get this probability of detection.
So the detector, when I say try to solve, try to find a detector, is try to find this T function.
How you combine this data in what way.
And once you have created this, you can do the expectation.
So again, coming back to what I highlighted earlier, which you already know in the assignment in Spain.
Almost every question you need to deal with expectation.
But here, even if it's given the T, then you always need to consider under H1, you do the expectation.
Under H0, you need to evaluate.
Different from the parameter estimation, where once you get the estimator, there's only one hypothesis.
You will be just looking at how good this.
So here, if you are doing finally, you evaluate E of T under H1 or E of T under H0.
And if you have multiple ones, more than two, then you need to evaluate several.
And at the same time, you also need to evaluate the variance under H1 or under H2.
Typically, at least quite often, I won't say probably always, but at least quite often, this variance under H1 or H0 turns out to be the same.
But I won't say 100%.
So you still need to give some example.
You'll try to work out this.
And then from here, one measure to see how good the detector is is to look at this diffraction coefficient.
So you see here, we...
Because this under H1 under H0, there should be difference.
We try to differentiate these two.
So there must be some difference.
And take the difference, raise the power too.
The difference can be negative, could be positive.
So usually, we see the absolute difference by square.
And then do a normalization by dividing variance.
Then this is under H0.
So again, here, both are of the same unit in the same because this is...
E is the first order statistic.
So variance is the second order.
But when you raise the power too, then it will become at the same level.
So the ratio here is a coefficient is no unit one.
If you're thinking about unit.
Okay, I think that's about...
I don't know this.
So you can also study the so-called receiver operating characteristic or ROC curve.
This is available nowadays in machine learning.
Very often, you try to see the compromise.
So from here, you can see ideally, you see, we want to have probability of force around to be zero
and probability of detection being one.
So this corner is the idea like the 100% perfect detector.
But normally, you won't achieve that unless for some very special case.
So the way looking at this curve, you will see how closer this near this corner.
So typically, you follow like that.
And this also tell you the compromise you can make.
You want to reduce the probability of force around.
You'll reduce the probability of detection.
So you want to increase this because it explains of increasing the probability of force around.
So I hope this give you a good picture after you come back from your research week.
Strange, this one is stuck somewhere.
I don't know this computer.
Close.
I close the window. It doesn't work.
So let's see.
This Microsoft.
Let's try this.
In case I need to sign off first.
I think I need to start with this.
Close that.
That may be better.
I hope it works now.
So let's see what I have.
I hope this works.
So let's continue from what we left last time.
Any questions?
So far, what we did the previous week up to this point.
Anything you would like to ask before we continue.
So these are being covered before.
And the NPD detector.
We also have done it and we go through an example.
And here I need to highlight if you look at the ratio.
So you see this PDA for likelihood function under H1.
In this case, they both follow the same Gaussian distribution with different means.
But it's not necessarily always so.
It could be under H1, it could be one distribution.
Under H0, it could be another one.
So this example is a simple one but not always like this.
For example, in this case because of Gaussian and this special case, our detection threshold
will be just dividing the royal axis into two portions.
One is you do the detection, the design on H1.
The other is design H0.
But not necessarily, it could be several segments.
And that's the one later on you will see one example where you decide the region in the middle.
And the other region is outside this middle range.
And it could be even several reasons.
But of course, it will become more complicated just to highlight this.
And that also values the compromise in this case.
And then we extend to N sample.
In this case, it's similar because the ratio, these two follow the same distribution.
Except there are more data and the means also the constant means.
So the technique is quite similar.
And then we evaluate this E and B.
In this case, you also see the two E, of course, as I say, they must be different.
Otherwise, you cannot do the proper detection.
That means you cannot differentiate H1 and H0 based on this.
But the variance under H1 and H0, it turns out to be the same in this case.
So therefore, you can see our T of X.
This is because T of X means you are combining the major data into one single analytic function of the data.
So therefore, being a function of the major data, the major data random variable,
as we already defined at the beginning.
So therefore, this is also random variable.
Being a random variable, you follow some distribution.
In the case of Gaussian under both H0 and H1, we can verify this also for all the Gaussian distribution.
Under H0 is 0 mean.
The mean is 0.
So that agree with this under H0.
Also, the variance, if you compare with the variance of the noise, which is the sigma part of 2.
So some work reduced by how much?
By the number of samples.
So therefore, you can see if you have more sample, then this is more reliable.
And similarly, under H1, the variance is the same, but the mean changes.
One is at 0, one is at 8.
So of course, you can see the difference.
A and 0, A is much larger than 0.
Then you can detect the signals much easier.
So therefore, with that, because this is being Gaussian, we can get the probability of four salam very easily.
So that turns out to be a Q function.
And this is under H0, we will follow this.
And then Q function, you always need to normalize them in the value equal to 1.
And make the numerator, the mean become 0.
So in this case, the thing here is already 0 mean, so you only give the threshold.
But on that thing, under H1, you have the mean, so you need to subtract the mean first before you calculate the Q.
And since the variance is the same, you do the same normalization.
So this is to get the probability of detection.
And then you can also relate it because our threshold is related to the probability of four salam in this way.
It's not analytic, but at least you can.
So Q function, you have to see by looking, you'll look up table or nowadays, you have the computer, you can install all the most of the value to the precision.
You require say four digits after the decimal point and so on.
So that's how you can get the PD.
And from here, you can also find out the relationship between probability of four salam and probability of detection and under the different energy to noise ratio.
That will tell you how good is the signal given or how bad is the noise because we are getting the ratio.
So I think this is also very clear.
So this one listing a few choice or probability of four salam, you see.
So as I say, you can see if you have a larger probability of four salam, then you can have a better PD under the same energy to noise ratio.
Here is the thing this way.
And if you require probability of four salam to be very small, so your PD will be in general very low.
Unless you have the signal energy to noise ratio to be very high.
So you require signal very strong.
So these are very clear.
I think last time we stopped at this point.
So let's continue to extend to the more general case, mean shift, Gauss-Gauss problem.
So this is what we are discussing the simple example where zero and A, you can extend it to the case where the two means they are different to each other.
So you see here, mu 0, mu 1.
So we call this mean shift Gauss-Gauss problem.
So I think the elevation and the result are quite similar.
So you can easily calculate that there were the performance.
It's the same measure by the diffraction coefficient.
In this case, you will see.
So it turned out to be, it was determined by how much these two means, how much different.
And this is what our special case is as before in the example.
And you can also derive very similarly probability for salam, PT, and so on.
So here we can see the detection performance is monotonic with the diffraction coefficient here.
So from here you need to see even if you don't calculate the actual value, you try to figure out the tendencies.
For example, if you are given the probability for salam, which in the NP-detector's case is always fixed.
So give the required one.
And then from here you can see here, if in order to get PD, you remember the Q function.
The Q function is the bell curve.
And the Q is already normalized center at zero.
So to get the PD is bigger, the argument of this Q function, you need to make it more negative.
Your Q function is the, let me maybe show you here.
We also need to discuss a little bit more later.
So that's our Q function of X at zero.
So depending on, yeah.
So the Q function is the integration.
This curve is the Gaussian.
So what you get is you are getting the area under the curve.
So this is, if this is X value, say, you see the Q function you integrate from here all the way here, infinity last.
So the argument, the more negative, you see, this Q function value will increase when X is getting down.
So that's the, yeah.
That's the relationship.
So in order, you see, the PD is depending on this Q.
So in order to increase this, of course, if this value is bigger, you will be more negative.
So that means your integration will get larger and larger value.
Of course, the limit will be one.
So that's how you look at that.
So then we can extend to one more example where this is the change in variance.
So we want to, let me see where the, yeah, extend this.
Make it full screen.
So I hope this works.
It's not working.
Anyway, let's look at this new example where we have two hypothesis, S0, H1.
Again, you follow the Gaussian distribution.
But in this case, the difference between the two is not at the mean, you see.
This is different from where you are trying to differentiate based on the mean.
Right here, the difference is in the variance.
So we call, we try to differentiate based on the variance.
Again, we're assuming we have the N, capital N sample, and there are IID, IID mean independent and identically distributed.
So following our previous discussion NP approach or NP test, you take the ratio and then you see here.
Always remember this is under H1.
So under H1, you'll be using sigma 1, power 2.
And both of them is zero mean, so you don't subtract anything.
And the variance are different.
So how are we going to simplify?
I need to emphasize to get the detector.
You cannot just say or you'll stop here because that's an NP test.
So yeah, that's also, I look at some of the students' assignment and service.
So then it's not showing any step or skip the middle of the step.
Of course, in final exams, if you don't know the, I mean, if you don't have time, you directly get the results.
You may step, okay, but quite often I require at least some steps.
But here, for example, you cannot just say, oh, I simply, you know, write down this.
You have to at least simplify until you look like you cannot simplify further because, yeah, this is the definition.
So you may not be able to succeed.
At least to memorize this is step one, but you need to continue to work on that.
For example, in this case, because both are exponential, so you take log.
And that's why very often we suggest to take log.
But because it is not exponential function like uniform distribution, so you may not necessarily take it.
So taking log, you will be dealing with the exponent so you can see we don't see any exponential.
But for those constants which are not exponential functions, you will get a log.
But it doesn't matter because here, you see here, very often when determining the threshold,
usually we can always combine constants to make it a new threshold.
Instead of gamma, we call it gamma prime.
So in the detection, the most important one is to come up with a proper detector or we call that as a test statistic,
which is a function, you know, the t, t of x, depending on the data in what way.
And now you can see here, in this example, what you get is not just take the sample mean
because what we will be dealing here is the sample square, you know, the so-called power of two of the sample.
So you sum this, sum that.
And also, of course, we are assuming this sigma one power two is greater than the other one.
Otherwise, if they are equal, you cannot tear the two if they are identical.
So it must be some different.
To make it easier, we say this is greater than the other.
Then, therefore, why this is important?
Because if you see here, you can see this is greater.
So this will be smaller than that.
Then you take the different, you will get negative.
And if you get negative, you have a minus sign here.
So this whole factor, it will be a positive number.
So if you are dealing with inequality, it's very important.
If you get a positive number, you will not change in quality.
But if you divide a negative number, you have to change from greater to smaller and vice versa.
So therefore, you divide that and then because this is a constant, you can observe into that one.
And also, you can also divide capital N.
The N is always positive.
So in the end, what you will be changing is always only on this lying side, the threshold.
So therefore, in this case, you will establish this.
And you really need to get the threshold.
Sometimes, we may just lump it into one new value.
Sometimes, it may require to give the extra expression.
But as I say, this will be more important to get the correct form.
And then now, in this case, this is what I say is not always like the previous one.
You're determining, you differentiate these two processes just based on one threshold,
dividing to right or left.
So in this case, you can see we will decide each one.
The power in the observed sample is large enough.
So we'll be somehow here.
So with this H1, either it's larger than this square root of this threshold,
or it's more negative.
The absolute value is larger than this minor update.
So in the middle, it doesn't satisfy the likelihood ratio,
quite dearly, greater than the threshold.
So we will decide H0.
So that means you will go back here.
So that's what we call, if not sample mean, is a power sample mean.
So it's a power of 2 first.
And then, yeah, and then we will make a decision.
So you may just consider taking a square root of that.
Then, of course, you will be compared with the square root of this threshold.
So it's very much you depend on case by case for the given problem, given data.
And that's why it's very important you try to simplify the expression
so that you have clear pictures rather than right at the very beginning.
Any question?
Anything you'd like to clarify?
So again, here you can look at ROC.
And that's very similar to what I mentioned earlier.
So if you make the threshold to be large enough,
then the probability for the alarm, because the likelihood ratio always fix value.
It cannot be arbitrarily large.
So you are not satisfied that.
So you won't make any false alarm.
But then, on that thing, the pt will be almost zero.
Because it's very unlikely you can have the measure data, the square of the sample value,
take the square, get the mean value.
And then, still greater than this, we go to infinity.
So that's one case.
And on the other hand, if you go to the other side,
actually you can't, we allow to go to negative, minor, infinity.
But this one should be always positive.
I think it should be near zero.
So that's the other way.
The other extremes.
So anyway, ideally we should try to oppose that.
But anyway, it's better than the random guess.
This 45 degree is what we call the, yeah, it's always about this.
Because this is when you don't have any information,
or you are doing, being binary, just do random guess.
You always get halfway, 50% right.
Because you only have two binary hyperceses to make.
Yeah, okay.
So therefore, yeah, I already explained this.
There will be a compromise between this probability for the alarm
and the probability of detection, depending on the given threshold.
And then here, we want to specifically highlight the dependence
on the diffraction coefficient.
So as you hear, ideally we are hoping to achieve that.
And then you can see it depends on how large this diffraction coefficient value.
If you keep increasing this, this is equal to one, it's the one we see just now.
But if you are able to increase the difference,
you will see you will be getting closer and closer to this corner.
Okay.
Any questions?
Before we move on to the new topic, which is Bayes criteria.
So in the detection theory, you can mainly classify into these two approach.
One is the NP criteria, NP approach.
The other is Bayes criteria.
And that's all given in this chapter two.
It gives the so-called detection theory.
And after that, you will see some applications.
So in the case where the signal is deterministic,
but you know, and after that we move on to the case where the signal,
your intruding will be rendered.
But in either case, you are applying the Bayes detection theory.
We learn in this chapter two.
So these are the fundamentals, like the two theories.
And then there is based on the given data, given models,
given scenario, you need to apply and see how this detector looks like and so on.
Okay.
I think it may be better to take a break now than we can,
after the break, we can continue to cover this part.
Now it's 7.28.
We come back at 7.45 according to the clock behind.
I mean, if you have any questions, you can approach me as your judge.
Okay.
you
okay so let's continue lectures so I hope you find this detection theory this
part somewhat easier compared to the estimation particularly you have a
good understanding of the parameter estimation theory after doing the
assignment one so talking about assignment one I since I'm one of the
two lecture for the 6401 maybe not many of you taking that course for for that
cause the lecture one as Pro Woon teaching part one then he said assignment I
think the submission is also during the end of the recess week and all the the
very similar we have 160 the other is 158 so it's about the same because I'm
I'm not involving in part one but I am now teaching the part two but I I
download the assignment of the you know the discourse and the other one so so you
can see the quite a big difference in terms of both the total I mean the
number of students the same but the the fire size you see the besides how many
time our causes compelling to the other cause the same assignment is cover half
of the cost same one and also in terms of the average number of pages for the
for the question also significantly more I think the other cause usually I will
say is about four pages each if it only three question and then three about three
to four pages and our cause the average are probably about 10 to 20 it's about
three or four times and also it coincide with the the fire size the other one is
about 300 but less than 400 Mac in total you know how I was over over one gig
one point two gig it's about four times yeah so very impressive of you doing
spending the time and effort doing the assignment yeah so I hope you learn from
doing the assignment and prepare you well for the second part two and also the
final exam and of course for your future projects or future study and so on so I
do hope so yeah so let's continue from here so we somehow switch to another
criterion Bayes criterion so you're already more or less known Bayes
theorem before in the estimation where there is a little bit more difficult
where actually here is not not that much difficult compared to the NP
criterion I will say is very similar in yeah in this case so so let's see why the
way want to introduce this Bayes criterion is similar to the estimation
theories by using this Bayes approach we can incorporate some kind of pride
probability into the discussion and in in in the detectors and and also yeah of
course you can reduce to the special case if the two have a session at the same
then then you you just not yeah you can see in this case not much additional
information because both are equally important but as you can see here we can
also incorporate if you have some like the like the pride probability into the
consideration yeah also introduce the conditional probabilities here okay so
let's see what's the formulation here instead of you know in the NP detector we
have we are trying to reduce the two type of arrows because you increase the
probability of detection is the same as you are reducing the probability
of missing detection so we but you fix one and maximize the pity where here you
combine the two two type of arrows into into just one something like you're
doing doing the waiting and then we will all minimize the total probability of
arrows you in this approach so you can see the formulation here P is probability
of deciding as zero if h1 is true so this make one this is type 2 error and
then plus if h0 is true then you decide h1 this is type 1 error and then here we
also highlight we are including the probability of hypothesis one into that
because that's where you make h1 true so you make the error and then we also call
this as conditional probability okay so that means the yeah it's not conditional
PDF so don't get confused with probability and probability density function so
this is just a probability okay so this indicates how likely you're deciding
hi when hj is true so of course if I equal to j then you don't make an error but we
use this formulation particularly will be useful if you are dealing with multiple
hypothesis as we will briefly introduce later also so there is a little bit
difference at least in terms of the notation here in Bay in the Bayes approach
we use this vertical path make it clear is a conditional probability while earlier in
the NP approach we put this semi column so yeah so in early on we when we say using this is
we are talking about probability of deciding h1 si if hj is true but we don't
adding this probability meanings aside to the likelihood that hj is true so yeah so so that
was also why early on we don't include that the probability of the either h1 or h0 so it's not
the probabilistic setting where here we since we are looking at the Bayesian approach so we use this
conditional probability to highlight dealing with some prior probability of the h0 or h1 how likely
this is going to occur yeah okay so based on the meaning of this you could assume this outcome
of a probabilistic experiment such as dimensionally like free the coils or so it's observed to be
hj when yeah and the probability of this deciding as I condition on that outcome so that mean
first our h i is condition on that hj but hj it could be very likely to happen it could be
very likely not to happen the probability is low so so so that's
very much depending on how high this this is true or not in the probabilistic setting so that
if you go back to the no working so if you go into that is that we are not just looking at this
we also take into account how what's the probability how likely this h1 is going to happen if this one
is more likely to happen compared to ph0 so overall this term will be more important because you will
give a larger contribution to this total total errors so that's that's the reason we are using it here
yeah and then later yeah you can also interpret it is a kind of waiting
is a the error is a weight based on the prior probability of the each of the hypothesis
so in this various approaches we want to this desire detector that minimize this overall P
E and then later after we generalize this detector into another more general form we will prove
a big similar to the NP approach then you can see it turned out to be this under this
finally hypothesis we will decide h1 again also based on this so this is like the conditional
pdf you see we have a small p here you know that means we measure this will tell you the
distribution of this metadata condition on the h1 is true and this is vice versa
condition on f0 but it's this side is similar to our likelihood ratio but the right hand side
the threshold is different because here we don't have we don't defy the probability of force alarm
or at least we don't fix it to a constant but instead in the Bayer's approach we are given
you need to know the p of h0 and p of h1 so you take the ratio of these two so be careful
on this left hand side is h1 is on the top numerator this is zero but either ratio is a
other one you see the probability of a zero is numerator versus the probability of the h1 so
so a lat is equal to new threshold so what we are doing is we are compared with this one
greater than with the side on h1 okay so yeah so you can see at least in this case you
see the similarity and also the difference so the the difference is here the threshold is
determined by the prior probability of the of the events of the of the two hypotheses and in the
special case where the prior probability are equal and then of course just in this case
then the ratio you can see is equal to one so therefore the decision is Bayer's we are decide
h1 if this is greater than day one because you're comparing to one so that means you're
you're basically just compare you see if this is equal to one then of course this greater than
day one you mean is larger than one so so that reduce this simple pass so therefore in this case
because as I say we're keeping in mind later we'll extend to the multiple hypothesis more than two
then we say if the if you're dealing with two hypotheses we will be choosing a larger
condition like they hope but if you are dealing later you will see dealing with more then we'll
take the maximum one in your head say three or four so the comparison is you will just
pick the largest one and and that's why we call that there's a maximum also maximum likelihood
detector is very much related to our maximum likelihood estimator but here there should be
more accurate by adding the is a conditional likelihood because our MLE in the detection one
we are dealing with deterministic parameter so it doesn't have the conditional where later the
map MAP is having this probability setting so here but then since in convention people just call it
without adding the conditional maybe you want to get the similar name as MLE so we call that this is
M MLE B maximum likelihood detector in this special case
so let's look at the same example as we had before but previously we use the NP approach
so now if you're you know the same setting and also assume the A is greater than zero and the noise
is white Gaussian noise and it's this it's very and in the if you are trying to link with the
communication problem where you have two signals so this will be corresponding to the
case where one signal is equal to zero the other signal is just equal to
to a constant DC value that's in comm is called on off key or over key
yeah but of course later you will see maybe next week we will have the more general case the S0
S0 and S1 they can be proper signal but they are they'll be different so you can see this is a
special case of the two signals two different signals okay so if we assume this
this prior probability are the same then we will just minimize the PE when the threshold is equal
to one and I won't go into detail because that's very similar to our previous discussion and even
similar to the estimation theory you are just getting plotting this this is all Gaussian assumption
so it's very easy so in the end we also get the same the same statistic test and also yeah
some for me but the only difference is the threshold where here you'll base on this ratio we
we simplify and then you will end up with this threshold so so this is determined by the
the ratio between the two hypothesis the prior probability of the two and also
here we simplify the other part we want to get the same sample mean then end up with
which are different threshold so as I say early in detection is most important to get the correct
detector and after that the threshold is you know you will get the RLC curve it will just
determine where do you want to like like like cut out yes in particularly in this case you're
making one threshold you can yeah you can you can decide the value you know based on
your application requirement but in this Bayer setting since we are following yeah so Bayer
setting is you can say is it is determined by by the prior probability you know about the two
hypothesis of the two hypothesis okay any question before we move on
so yeah so therefore this is again the same as before but here we want to get the PE
and assuming this case the prior probability for both types essentially are the same one
you're gonna have they'll pull out and now quite similar to before we can work out this and
here is because our threshold is A divided by 2 so it turns out to be
these two terms you can simplify so let me this is a very important property so maybe I can
uh follow what the earlier discussion on the Q function and see how how do
let me see which one the the Q function is
is uh is even function uh not very even function the the Q function is the right there you know
the correct the correct the right there it's based on the even function of the Gaussian
distribution the the PDF so let's see how how we work out this relationship so if you all assume our
x maybe in the case I call this this as t for example it doesn't matter so the so the x value
is here is one fixed value because it's like x okay now
therefore the the uh the lighter one Q of x it will just just measure this area all right so that's
based on the Q function is measure this now weapon if assume x is greater than zero so
if you all have minus x it will be here it will be at the at the other side so now weapon if this
how are we going to get this Q minus x this is so but then again being being a right one
you will just integrate starting from here and then all the way to the right so if you all do
take a look carefully you will see uh you know this this part is the same that the area you you'll
integrate assume you integrate from minus x all the way to minus minus infinity you see this
reason is the same as that one because uh because the Q Q Q function itself is not symmetry but it's
based on the symmetrical you know Gaussian distribution which remember we must always
normalize to the to the to the zero okay so so therefore in this uh in in this case that you
can see if you add this add this two together it will be equal to one you see you you add this
this area is the same as same as that area and then your Q minus x is this part so you will be
your at that part the whole area you integrate you become one and then of course this part is equal
to that part so that means these two uh sum together equal to one and and that's why we can see here
in the future you may use this several times Q or minus x you can simplify into one minus
keyword base if you are you're making good use of that so why do we have it here you see here
uh okay so so this part is easy this is under h zero so the mean equal to zero so you'll have
normalized uh barrier you'll be uh dealing with just Q of certain uh you know uh barrier
where this side is you're under h one so h one the mean is like a uh and then our threshold is a
over two so you're you will need to have a over two minus a so this of course uh
end up with the the value of uh minus a over two all right here you'll have a minus sign here
the denominator is the same so therefore you'll make good use of this you see one minus
uh Q of a negative value so you you'll uh and this minus a over over two is the same as this
a over two so in this example our x is this one a over two which is we assume a greater than zero
so this x is greater than zero therefore it's uh end up with your making good use of this
you will become one minus one and plus this thanks all the one and end up with this the two are the
same so this part is the same you add together equal to twice you divide by two so p in this case
finally uh end up with uh this uh we want to make make the square root for both numerator and
denominator okay so therefore you'll just square this one and then take the square root so square
first become a square and then square this one become four so that's right here this okay so
that's how you get this p in this special case because our Gaussian or something so end up with
very uh simple and analytic expression in terms of the Q functions and all those
and here I also explained the property of this Q function
yeah okay so let's come back to our discussion on this Bayer's criterion
if we rely the condition in this equation four into this so we'll become
uh a product of that and then this Bayer's rule also apply uh so you see here this is
Bayer's rule apply to uh to a mixture of one is a pd conditional pd a where the other is a
property so so you can consider this is like the
yeah it's a product uh p of h i is the prior property where this one is the conditional
pdf and similarly on the other one so other one is your reverse so
it works because if you can see here you see this one is pdf if you multiply maybe easier
you look at that so so you don't so you need to make sure the if you're compared two things they
must be of the like the same unit or the same dimension the the same functions particularly
when you apply the Bayer's one so that you can you can compile so this is conditional pdf and
at the same as the same as this one and this is probability okay just a value
and then if you use Bayer's rules is we are we are changing this this is you see a product
probability can this uh p or x condition of that so this is a conditional pdf now and if you look
at this it's the other one around you see our prior pdf is with respect to the data if you
multiply by that but then our our hypothesis the probability of this is conditional probability
condition on this given data so so the concept is somewhat different you see one is so let me repeat
again so this is a conditional pdf is a pdf is it describe the describe the distribution
distribution of the of the data being random and then the data as you can see early depending on the
hypothesis for example simple one is hypothesis is noise only then of course it will be zero means
in the in the noise only case and yeah then on that then so let's look at the other one so
so this is the probability that means once you have the data you see your measure the data
then the our probability of this either at zero or h one is given by one after your
measure the data then we we have a new probability is how high after measure data
how big is this h one or h zero okay and this p of x is very easy it will be the
initial the prior pdf of the data because the the measure data itself can follow some
these distributions okay regardless it's either at zero or h one so yeah
yeah so so you can see here being a prior pdf this does not depend on the any true hypothesis
so we don't uh yes the data itself it it doesn't matter which hypothesis
so therefore uh in this case we will choose h one if because you'll be following you'll be using
using this to do the comparison what we are trying to trying to see argue here is
so let's see this is the one we already know from the previous detection so you're both
divide by p of x you see to make it to make it easier to divide by p of x then divide by p of x
so this so this side will become p of h one condition on x this is data is p of x
h zero condition of x so therefore uh since you know both sides uh p of x is the same
you'll divide and then your comparison your n tau is this along the design h one you'll just
uh use this uh must be given with data then the probability of h one must be greater than the
given the data the probability of sg o and that also makes sense if you look at the look at this
uh because uh in this case given the major data if the probability conditional probability of h one
is greater than conditional probability of sg o because we will choose this we'll decide on h one
otherwise if smaller or equal we don't care equal is the power decay you can you can decide either way
okay so that's how this looks simpler compared to that day one
so therefore in this case we will choose the hypothesis whose a posterior posterior mean after
observe the data posterior probability is maximum in the multiple hypothesis case but if you have
only two then we choose the larger one so therefore in this case the detectors you see
we call that the maximum a posterior probability or m a p detector
yeah so therefore uh you can see compared to our early discussion on the ml detector this
map detector here is uh allow the different prime probability you can incorporate that so the
similar to actually is not the same in the estimation theory or m a p and the ml the
difference is the one is deterministic parameter the other is you are dealing with the random
parameter so here we do not really look into the whether the signal on the detection is deterministic
or random we are going to that later but but here the difference between m a p and ml is
is just depending on whether you are dealing with equal prime probability or you allow it
to have different one so it's so in a saying you can see the ml detector is a special case of m a p
m a p detector in in this in these settings
okay any questions before we move on to a generalization of the Bayer's criteria
uh and anyways this we will give a proof for the Bayer's detector
okay so let's see uh what we we have here uh the
uh the main
consideration in this case is uh you know
other than the prime high probability of the hypothesis we also want to assign a cost
cost to each type of error yeah you can say it's a big similar to as you remember when we're doing the
Bayesian estimation we're talking about the cost function here so yeah so uh we want to we want to see
uh what what difference we are assign a cost to each type of error you see
early on remember we are taking the p with the the sum of the two error only considering the
prior probability of the each of the hypothesis but not that when you are making the
making the error itself that so but then in some practical applications is very important the
the two type of errors one is more critical compared to the other so that means we may be totally late
one type of error but more more important to to try to avoid other type of types of
uh errors and that's why the motivation of adding some cost to uh so let's see what uh what's the
motivation uh here uh if you are looking uh if you're saying uh factories will be
uh trying to inspect a machine's part and is whether this part is satisfactory or otherwise
if if good we will keep otherwise we will discuss yeah that's just a good example you know you
you see here the recent MRT MRT problem so so here is a good lesson if you just one one trains you
know the here the that that that 40 train you can consider it's as a part here so uh
it's it's comparing to the whole transportation system one MRT or even one of the uh mechanical part
there is maybe uh maybe you can consider uh in this example our part here so so let's see why because
we are doing a test we set up a hyperset test for this problem s0 is the part is
defective and h1 is a part is satisfactory so given a part you only make when we inspect each of the part in the
part in the machine of course it's a finally decision whether this part is good or not okay
so here h1 is a good so the part is satisfactory while s0 is a part is not good so we of course
the parts is no good we need to replace so in this case it's very
obvious uh let's let's see what yeah uh yeah so let's see here starting from the
motivation uh if uh for example if the if the part is
it's defective one you know the the part itself is is uh wrong but then uh not good but we
make a wrong decision by deciding it as satisfactory so so this is the what type of the error if uh
let's let's go back to this try to get right uh if the the part is wrong is
defective uh under s0 but then we make a wrong decision saying the part is satisfactory so this is a very
very serious very serious problem because then you put the wrong part in a in a big machine
or the whole machine may break down you know like our MRT system recently because one thing
causing problems because all the the the rail is damaged and it took six days to recover uh okay if
of course if we uh apply this able to apply the detection uh it's early there do an early detection
then uh detect all that that uh train cannot pass some kind of some kind of uh test then we will send
it to repair first okay then it will avoid that that that that big problem so therefore this is
more serious uh we should somehow uh penalize and give a higher cost try to avoid this kind of
mistake happen okay on the other hand if uh uh if the pie is okay satisfactory but then we
we make a wrong decision by saying this pie is it's wrong and then we throw that part away
they always are a little bit on the on the small part is but uh that kind of error at least in this
case assume the pie is you know the the 40 uh the cause of that small part is much less compared
to the whole machine so it's uh we can allow to make this kind of mistake uh okay so that means we can
sign a smaller cost to this so therefore the motivation here is uh we want to introduce the
cause uh when i you see when we make uh uh we may decide on hi but hj is true so again here
we use this i and j to be able to explain to the more general case not just uh zero and one it can be
say zero one two three and so on okay so so that's why in in that case we uh like in this example
we will put the higher cost on uh zero is true but you'll make a decision of uh
deciding as h1 you know h0 is true uh rather than not at this one so that's the motivation of
introducing the cost so therefore uh our uh channel lines of the pay is criteria is uh
rather than you know previously we are just each term we only have this product uh now uh we
minimize the expect cost or the pay is raised given by this is uh this is the uh by including the
cost cost here the cost is just some value it's like the like uh uh usually like the uh say for
example you can get zero or one or two and so on it's a simple value to to compare the uh you know
the different different cost so depending on how much weight you want to give to one arrow
compared to the to the other so our formula here is more general you see we in the binary case
we are considering uh all the four possibilities including the case we are doing the doing the
correct decision uh because we want to make this formula to be more general so it will cover the
more general case but in practice you can uh if you are making the correct decision you can just
let this cost say c00 and c11 equal to zero so that's uh that's no harm okay in in this case
but we keep this as very general uh and uh also if you want to go back to our pe you see this is a
generalization of the early p or pe just happened to be uh if you do not make mistake correct way
the side is equal to zero where uh make the cost of making the type one and type two arrow
with the same cost equal to one okay so but you're now here you can allow it to be more
general uh introducing other values as i mentioned earlier uh the MRT uh examples also
so let's see in this case uh what to get well to minimize this pay-as-raise the
newly introduced one uh so that to decide on each one uh so again in that way the ratio is the same
as what we we derived uh early except now the threshold also uh changed because we incorporate
this uh see in the binary case we have c00 c11 and c1 0 c01 and uh of course based on common sense
uh even if you don't let this c00 uh equal to zero uh you can uh you always want to to ensure the cost
of making a wrong decision is higher than you make the correct decision am i right so that's
common sense so assume this satisfied this satisfied so that means this difference is greater than
zero this the same as this this one so therefore you are dealing with a positive uh value you can
easily multiply divide to the left right side without affecting this in equality okay so this is a more
general uh detectors we can uh yeah we can we can derive so again this is a conditional likelihood
ratio compared to a threshold and how to derive that and that's how uh this is uh prove is quite
similar to the NP approach but this uh a little bit more complicated because uh now you can see here
we are uh having four four terms because we are uh assuming the cij in this case i equal to zero in
one j also zero in one so in total there will be four combinations so we are assuming we are with the
right assuming all of them are not zero in the general case but again for the special case
you want to reduce to p then you can just take this special value so our proof here for this
it works for the general case so let's see how we derive this result similar to the early one because
we only show the binary case then we have the R1 where we collect all those x when you decide
H1 so remember here you decide H1 it may be correct may be wrong you see so whenever we decide H1
we we call all those x vector in the i n space the high dimensional space depending on how many
data samples you have and similarly the other complementary one it will be decide H0 and
and the whole space is part partitions by either R0 or R1 since we are doing the
binary decision then this R will be if you explain this into into four terms so you need to
to be familiar how to explain the summation this is a double summation so each summation here is two
then two then you have another index you have another two so n double is four okay so if you
explain this you will see it has it has four terms here so be careful about here you see all these
probability there is you see in this course so either prior probability or condition
conditional probability when you make the wrong decision but how do you get the probability
based on the you see this is a conditional probability you'll get the conditional probability
based on conditional pdf you see when you integrate you see so integrate over all these r0 so this is
your pdf is a condition on H0 then of course you you decide on r0 you see so this is this is the
correct one so you're multiplied by these two similarly you can work on all the other four
other three terms so you need to to be always based on first H0 or 1 okay and then whether this is
H0 or H1 so in total there will be four combinations so they can see each of these four terms they are
all they're all different and to manipulate that is not easy so what do we do as we we did before
we make gugis of this relationship because they are partitioned the entire space so therefore if you
uh uh take note of that this must be the same conditional pdf if your integral over r0 is the
same as your integral over r1 but uh take the negative and plus one so that means uh why because
uh you'll integrate over both r0 and r1 then of course give you the whole space will be equal
to one so therefore uh you can convert this using this formula if you want to change the region into
r1 you'll do that so therefore using this relationship you can uh you can put in and do a little bit of
simplification your end up with the two of them you deal with this constant you pull out you
and then the rest you can see here all of those previously under r0 these two terms you change
into r1 and then it produced two constants term here then the rest is uh you can lump together
all under r1 now so so these are in one integrant your the integrant will become in total four
four terms sum together and determined by each of these conditional pdf one conditional r0
the other conditional h1 because they are only two conditional pdf okay so
so
and then after that we are doing the in the same way so let's let's go back what we are going to do here
we want to minimize this am I right we want to minimize this and this is uh this is already fixed
because all those costs those pried
probability of h1 or h0 they are all given so what we can we can manipulate is to
to decide how to choose those x you see under the r1 so so we want to minimize this
uh you try to make this make this term because all these two terms they must be positive okay
so so in the end if you're based on formula this cause you will never be it will always be positive
but so therefore we want to make this term as negative as possible to to make it at least
negative so so that you already deal with this these are fixed term they are usually
at least greater than zero we don't know how big the value depending on this cost but we want to
make this one as negative as possible so that the combined arrow will be as small as possible so
that's the motivation okay so therefore we will include the x in r1 if the integrant you know those
are inside the bracket it's negative so I you see here you'll go back so all this integrant is the one
within the bracket you see the square bracket so we want to make this negative so that means this is
smaller than zero and then you can do a simple change by putting moving depending on
wisdom your for example you'll move this term to the to the uh right inside yeah it will be for example
this one previously here you're all the four terms smaller than zero you move this part over
it will be this one smaller than that okay so therefore as I say assume you'll make mistakes
you have a higher cost that's a common thing same as here therefore we can see this is positive
this is positive so and then of course all these are also positive so you can take the ratio
and then you'll keep this greater side because you are dividing this one to the other side
become denominator so so therefore you divide this one to the this side divide this one to the other
side so therefore in the end we of course you'll keep this one there so we will still want to keep
the ratio this is the likelihood conditional likelihood ratio must be greater or equal to
greater than this and that's how we get our generalized Bayer's criteria by following this
same similar argument yeah okay any question at this point anything you'd like
to know okay so we move on I think we should be able to finish this chapter
today so now we move on to the multiple adversaries test so this is just an extension to the m greater
than two k's and sometimes we call it as a classification problem
yeah we can using the NP criterion but in practice greater than two then is
commonly we use the Bayesian approach because here we also want to introduce the
taking into account the the prime probability of the supply of the chassis so our derivation
below using the Bayer's approach that's commonly used
so here we want to decide among m possible hyper
chassis as we know up to h m minus 1 to see which one it will be the it will be the
minimize the Bayer's Bayer's risk so similar to the final case and that's now you know we
introduce this formula because it's easily extend to the case of m possible hyper chassis
so the formula is the same except you are summing up from 0 to m minus 1 also j from 0 to m minus 1
previously it's up to 1 because you only have to finally k 0 1
and the derivation is somewhat similar but a little bit more complicated so we are just quickly
go through the the result without spending like too much time because this part has become
a bit more complicated and not our main focus of this part two we are trying to
get a good understanding of the finally detection problem also in the subsequent
chapter okay so let's see what we can do here in this case
choose the library see that minimize that one okay so so what we are doing is you are
considering you see i you see we are breaking down the the two double sum into
total of m simpler single sum so that means for each of the i we minimize this
a cost because if you are able to do that in the end you sum together it will also minimize
that so for the special case if i go to j you see so here we try to
link with our p case p case again you know if i go to j
then we make no mistake so we call this zero or and if otherwise then we just make them equal
equally equal to one so in that case we are minimized minimum error p k so we will we will
end up with this is just equal to so you see here you see we remove all these costs and then because
this one got a zero so and the other one so we will be take a simple sum but excluding the
j equal to i case because in that case your the cost equal to zero so we don't have that term
otherwise one and then that's the same expression as now if you are sum all of them including the
the case you know i equal to j but then of course you need to subtract this this is the correct
correct decision you see i and i so you need to subtract that one so this so hopefully this is
clear now we want to minimize this it's the same as we maximize this maximize this p of this
it and the x the condition condition hypothesis condition on the
on the on the data because the first term is independent of i so therefore
under the minimum p so here is we're dealing with the spatial k not the general decision
rule is but decide on edge k if given the data you see we we work out with all the
you see given the hypothesis edge of k we look into all the possible m hypothesis conditional
hyperspecies then the one the edge of k if the the one is the largest then all the rest we will
just decide edge of k okay so that's the that will be remember early on in the final case
we have two we just choose a condition hypothesis condition on the data the large one with this
now you're you're more than two you'll work work out each case and pick the largest one so that
also makes sense therefore we try to maximize the a posterior probability given the data
then we will try to maximize so that also makes sense and that's why we call it as
mary that means multiple hyperspecies maximum a posterior probability or max decision rule so
that again we come back to this m maybe in the multiple hypothesis test
again in the spatial k of the prior probability they are all equal then you again you know this
Bayesian approach you will see is it all this you're in total of m so each must be one over m
and double step then the k one to maximize that is equivalent to maximize this so so we
should be careful one is the probability condition of the data the other is the
the data condition on the on the hypothesis of h i
so therefore in this eco probability probability case we will decide
h k if this you see your your macro yields this relationship then this independent line
will just pick this up greater than all the all the others so that will be since we are assuming
prior probability so this is the mary maximum likelihood or ml decision lose again is a spatial
k of the map so let's look at one example where we have multiple hypothesis and just make it a
little bit more complicated the three hypothesis instead of what we are familiar the two finally one
and it's the formulation is also similar but you will see this is getting a much more involved so
there are three hypothesis the middle one each one is the one noise only and one is s zero is the data
you have negative minus a dc or the other one is positive this possible dc and our a here is a
shume is positive the noise is white Gaussian noise with this so a shume here we will we have the equal
hypothesis the k is equal to one over three so that we are just looking at the ml decision lose
which is easier so in this case we our condition pdf you see here condition on this h i so you
you need to check again like under each case h0 h1 h2 so we use just one the same formula because
all of these are Gaussian distribution with the same value except the the means the mean
value are different so we call it gets a i and i equal to take three value 0 1 2 and then correspondingly
you see a a 0 here is what we call the minor a a 1 the middle one could 0 a 2 equal to a so you
use one formula and then to maximize this is it's the same as we are minimizing this
exponent exponential term so let's let's do that this is a very useful observation and a very useful
technique we will apply this again in the subsequent discussion maybe next week so you see here
yeah look at this this is a exponential signal and then exponential no take note of the minus side
here and this is positive minus something okay so so you see here we want to our idea is we want to
maximize this maximize that exponential function if you have a minus some value is the largest value
is the one close to zero zero is the largest value so more negative you know is a is a bell
curve it will be getting down so so idea here is we try to minimize this if this one is smaller
then you will get the overall larger value so that's why maximize that it's equivalent to minimize this
so-called distant term I mean they give the data we want to see how far is from each of the AI you see
they will give you the different DI i equal to zero we we put this as minus a and so on
then again we use almost the same technique remember in the
estimation part you see we want to separate you see we want to separate this sum into
something more manageable because here the AI is mixed inside the summation term
so one easy way to do is you can verify this you can make some kind of perfect perfect square
and we want to reduce this term is independent of AI you see okay so yeah so we can do that and then
of course you'll have some residue left over and the residue is precisely here but that one now is
is outside the summation it's independent of the oh it still depends on the data but in the
collective way because this is a sample mean it's it's not on each of the each of the sample you
lump together so therefore now I think this is independent of AI you see we you want to minimize
that it's the same as to see this term is smallest given given this sample mean okay so
so should be clear here you see this is independent of AI so we minimize that
okay and then therefore how to do the decision if so again here it's good you sometimes you'll try to
draw the draw some graph you have zero and then a minus a you'll break down the whole
axis into partition zero a and then minus a so therefore of course if they or now you look at
case if the sample mean of it is even smaller than the maybe I do it here yeah yeah so see
uh easier to look at so so if you all see here
okay this is yeah if you all see here zero here this is minus a then this is a so
uh if the x sample here is smaller than this side uh actually uh you can you can divide it into
draw another line here draw another line here also yeah you see uh so as long as
uh smaller than minus a over two okay uh then it will be closer to this to this uh to this minus a
okay because equal distance at this point is a equal distance to here and here there this is zero
so so this part then we will decide on x zero and then similarly for uh x two is you'll be yeah
you'll be go up one is the other go up go to the other direction greater than a divided by two
so that you will whatever sample mean for in this region you will close to this one and
otherwise if you will be falling in the middle then you will you will decide on h one that
closes to the to the to the origin which is uh the a one so therefore we yeah we get this
now uh finally we need to determine this p then we need to work out a sixth type of of
error you know if you have finally one you you have two uh the combination if you have three then
become six six times you can work out by yourself so it will be very tedious so what we do is to
determine the probability of correct this correct detection yeah remember uh correct detection is
always equal to one minus the probability the the wrong detection these two sum together
will be equal to one so the correct is the detection in this case there will be three
because you have three hypothesis you make the correct decision then it's to get three is easier
than six okay so so that's how we'll be doing so all of them uh the equal uh assume they have equal
probability for each hypothesis so we uh we put this out and then we we work out each of the
probability you see so that's very similar to what we we discussed earlier but other than now we
have three hypothesis s0 h1 h2 so uh you can see the middle one is uh you see all of these are
evaluating the Q function but uh the middle one is you're calculating from one final starting
point to the final ending point so you will have two Q function okay you're taking the difference
or at the other one is you're dealing with smaller than negative value so uh so we will be
using this one minus this Q because this is a smaller one Q Q function you are getting the
right there so it's to the other side but this is the proper one you get one Q so therefore
you can see uh they were in total so this is smaller is one minor death so yeah and therefore uh
make good use of the property I mentioned earlier this this argument give you a negative value
you combine this similarly for this one this one negative you combine this one is a positive so
this one so in the end all of them uh end up with the the same this Q of this A over two of this
and then finally you can you can see in the end you will give you all this one minus this
and so how are we going to
compare that's PC but to get a PE you'll you go to that you have three every this is finally
it's three half a session so you can see here this PE compare this on good this Q function exactly
except you have four over three where this is one and of course this is
larger value the coefficient is larger than one and that's also makes sense because given the same
data instead of guessing two you're deciding two now you need to decide three half a session
and you'll have a higher chance to make the total error so I think with that we yeah we finish this
chapter two so I think it's a good timing we can stop here and this chapter two give the very good
foundation for the detection theory uh subsequent having total three chapters so we should be
yeah should be able to uh let's see as I say next week eight and nine uh this is week eight next week
week nine so I will go through the solution of the assignment one of our spank half that
you got the many questions and I try to discuss that so it may take like one hour so divided
week 10 and then week 11 we will have again half of lecture I hope by yeah by week 11 we should be
able to more or less finish the this remaining three chapter or if not we will stay up with 12 and we
we're starting maybe yeah so in any case by week 11 we will certainly finish the part two up to
chapter four so the the quiz were only for part two and we'll cover part two chapter one up to
chapter four that means excluding the last chapter in this lecture note okay so you have some idea
it will be one hour's close book quiz in this okay so yeah I hope it is clear
any question you can stay back if not then you're free to leave see you next week
you