I can see you.
Okay, so let's start.
Since some of you emailed me to ask.
So, yeah, try to clarify the quiz.
Yeah, so this consider is an announcement since you're staying here and post you think
can also watch video.
So, we already done the Simon one which I'm still marking and I should be able to discuss
the answers next week and which also help you to prepare for the quiz which is week 11,
two weeks later and also could be for the final exams also.
So, for the CA2 which will be the quiz, the contents will be for part 2 only.
That means the detections we are doing now and we cover the first four chapters we have done
for part 2 and today I will finish one more chapter.
It should be chapter 3 and then next week chapter 4 is a short one.
It should be able to do it in half a week and then there will be another one hour for
the discussion of the assignment.
I will not be able to mark each of you but I will give you the mark and I do take note
which part you do not do well if you have some doubt you can check with me.
I will give you the mark in NTU.
But you all have short copies since now is submission by short copy.
So, that's about the arrangement and for the quiz it will be one hour here.
I already announced this before.
And for the format of this quiz, I think maybe different courses, different lecturers,
have different arrangements and so on since our class size is big but not that huge.
We will still follow similar to last year which is roughly about two simple questions
like the exam paper question.
Not the full question because usually if you go to the final exam paper, I think NTU
will learn, not NTU, NTU will learn, NTU will learn.
You can get a few past year papers so you may want to take a look and study and prepare.
Anyway, you have done the assignment one which is for part one.
So, the contents are different is for detection but the first seven questions are also similar
to past year paper questions.
Actually some were taken from past year papers maybe quite a few years back.
Anyway, we only implement the quiz for this course only since last year.
The early one is all by assignment since at that time there was only 20%.
So, the final change to 40% for the CAs so it requires at least one quiz.
So, roughly the performance is about similar.
Every student gets similar math compared to assignments.
So, I follow these models.
There are many more students.
That's also why I haven't finished going through the homework because in the past year
we only had maximum 50 something.
I do finish 50 something so still another 100 to go.
That's why I take one more week to finish.
So, any questions?
Our quiz here is not like multiple choice nor even short answers.
It will be a proper answering question.
So, it may not be too difficult.
It may not be an exam paper.
Usually you have one or sometimes half of the questions may be more challenging.
So, try to make it just like an average.
That's a little bit more detail in case for those students not here.
I will also maybe say an announcement also confirming the day and time
which I believe I have done it before.
It will be in the second half.
We still give lectures for the first one hour plus and then 20 minutes break.
So, come back to take this one hour quiz.
Again, this is only for part two and first for chapter.
By today you already finished chapter three which I believe I will do it.
And then next week I will finish chapter four in half a week.
So, if no questions, we can start the lecture.
Anything you would like to ask?
Let me give a summary.
I will also upload the summaries I prepared before.
Usually only handwriting.
So, let me do this.
Open this.
So, in general, my feeling is this part two.
Of course, assuming you have a good understanding of the part one
which I hope you did the assignment mainly by yourself.
Then you should be not much problem based on my experience.
So, for last week we mainly focus on Bayer's detection approach
which we call Bayer's criteria.
And you can see here, just consider the two types of detection arrows
to a weighting based on the probability of the two hypothesis.
We are mostly focused on binary detection which is just two hypothesis, H0 and H1.
And then, since you combine together with one objective function,
so we can also minimize that.
And it turns out to be the detection or the detector.
Sometimes usually there are two names called as detector or call it as detection statistic.
And in terms of the function because this is like the condition likelihood.
This is a small p. So, don't get confused.
Small p is like functions which are depending on the data.
And it's based on PDA part way interpreted as you are given the data, the realization.
So, therefore, this is condition likelihood.
And then the line size threshold, this is a probability, it's a capital P.
So, this is a small p that give you the threshold.
And it's quite similar to the NP approach.
So, this part is the same where this one is...
the NP approach is depending on the given probability or force alarm.
And then in the special case of these two, the probability of both are the same.
And sometimes, then you only need to compare this condition PDA.
This is our ML or maximum likelihood detector.
It's the same similar to the ML estimator.
And you can also, based on the patient theory, you can write an equivalent.
So, this is under the equal probability.
And you can also compare the posterior probability.
That means once you give the data, based on the given data,
we will see which probability are more likely to happen.
All these are deciding H1.
So, then this posterior probability is higher than, of course, your design.
That doesn't mean that H1 is surely to happen.
And that's why we have detection errors.
When you make the decision, you mostly will hope it's correct,
but it may sometimes be wrong.
Then we also generalize this into Bayer's risk.
So, if you compare this one with the previous P, you can see this is more general.
We're adding the cost here, the Cij.
And again, the final case, we will consider all the possibilities.
Even in principle, we may also consider some risks,
because even if you make the right decision, in this format, there will be four of them.
Also, you may say, I'm posing as zero, or make a very small number.
The way we write this is it will be more convenient.
You want to generalize into the multiple case.
Then, again, you minimize this R, then you can prove.
It gives you the same conditional likelihood ratio.
And then the threshold is also depending on both this P of H0 and P H1.
Also multiplied by this cost.
So, they will be decided by the users.
If you fear the two types of errors, they are not equal.
One error is more critical.
You can put in heavier weights.
That's why I told you earlier, the good example is the MRT breakdown.
That one is more serious, because it affects many people and disrupts them.
That's why now the Singapore Parliament is debating to spend more money
to do a more frequent check to prevent that happen.
But you will incur higher costs, because that's why the companies,
the MRT, the arguing sale, I need more frequent check.
The fare will increase further, because you cannot have the high costs.
So, you need to decide which one is more important.
Of course, in the end, you will try a balance.
But this gives you a good example of introducing the cost.
Okay?
Then we can also explain to multiple other testing.
But as I mentioned, this is not our main focus.
I think for those students who need to learn more,
particularly applying to research or project, then you can spend more time.
But for most of the students, the final test will be the basic requirements.
That's also what I usually give the scope for the quiz and also for the final exams.
So next week, I will also discuss briefly among these four chapters.
I may exclude some of the contents.
And that's also for the final exams.
That's about the very brief introduction before we move on to the lectures.
The chapter follows this.
One, two, three, four.
Any questions before we continue from here?
Okay, so if not, then we can move on to this.
Let me try this.
So chapter three and four will be applying what we learned in chapter two,
which I'll give you already, the two main theories.
One is NP-detector.
The other is the Bayesian detector also.
In this chapter, we will just apply mostly the NP-detector.
Also at the end, we will also discuss a smaller part of the Bayesian approach.
And we will be looking at some applications.
And in this chapter, it will be deterministic signal with known parameters.
So it's more or less an easier problem.
And the next chapter is a random signal, but also with known parameters.
So you can see that chapter four will be slightly more difficult
because you involve the random signal.
And finally, chapter five, which is unknown.
You will have some unknown parameters.
So typically you need to combine what you learned in the estimation theory together.
Okay?
So you can see here, if we are moving to some specific application scenario
to see how we apply both the NP approach and the Bayesian criteria.
And since in this chapter or this week, we will discuss the case where the signal
with known deterministic signals.
And of course, it's not just the signal except as I already highlighted here.
We always assume we have some noisy measurement.
So in the end, what we add to noise will be random Gaussian.
So that's why we call this course a statistical signal processing.
We are dealing with some random signal or noise.
And since in this case, we mostly assume the signal and the PDF of noise are known.
So it is a relatively easier problem to tackle.
And sometimes we may be able to get the optimal solutions in close form, but not always.
We will see how much we can do for this.
Okay?
So again, this is the application of these two and how to apply what we will see in the actual applications.
We are mostly assume this Gaussian noise and not necessarily why it could be color.
But the idea you can also explain it to other type of noise assuming you know the PDF.
So don't take it for granted only Gaussian noise or Gaussian signals.
Okay?
And once we get the test statistic, we also need to look at the detectors performance to see how good it is.
So this is also part of the things we need to learn and we need to apply in the application.
So one of the very good application is we can link to what I hope you have learned DSP.
So at least filters which is very fundamental.
Actually for NTU, the undergraduate students, they can take an optional course in DSP, but not like compulsory, not like signaling system.
So if you have the knowledge of filter, it will help, but if not, I think it's not too difficult to learn from here because we are only using very simple concepts of mesh filter.
And it is IRR filters, so it's a IRR filter which is easier comparing to IRR filter.
Okay?
So let's see what we can do starting with NP criteria because we already know the tools are quite related.
So we will focus more on NP detector and later we can move on to the Bayesian criteria.
So let's start with the very simple detection problem which is quite a typical one and it's slightly more complicated comparing to the easiest one is, as I already mentioned,
if you have DC constant value, DC value, A in white Gaussian noise which is the simplest in both estimation and detection.
Well here we make it a little bit more general by having the signal as a non-signal but it's not constant.
So you need to differentiate the different situations where the given problem may be related but not exactly the same.
Okay? And for the time being we assume this S-n is non-signal, so it's like given one.
You don't need to estimate. You already know some sideways or exponential signal and so on.
And furthermore the noise here is white Gaussian noise ensures WGN and then with a barrier that's the typical symbol.
This is also known as given. So we assume we have capital N sample here and of course they are different from estimation.
For detection we always need to give at least the two hyper-excesses in this case H0, H1 or sometimes you may add more than two.
And this is a little bit simple knowledge in signal processing. You see we have the auto correlation functions.
We can define in general for stationary random signals. But in the case here for white Gaussian noise then it will be just given by a discrete time delta function.
Assuming we are dealing with discrete samples. So that's very clear. You are given here is the noise, white Gaussian noise.
Then the auto correlation is the sequence of the signal auto-correlative with a shift version of except depending on how much shift K here.
And white Gaussian noise that means this tool you can also consider as two random variable.
Because it comes from random variable at each time instant.
This result tells you that this delta K of course you should know the meaning of the discrete time delta function.
So don't get confused with a continue time delta function which you will define as infinity large at t equal to 0.
Here K equal to 0 the delta function take a value of 1 not infinity large because discrete time delta function.
Equal to 0 for any K not equal to 0. So the meaning here is only when the random variable auto-correlative with except without any shift.
Then of course you will have E W N raise to power 2.
Like the second moment and remember here even for random signal.
The random signal you can also talk about positive negative.
Also we don't know the actual value but if you talk about random of course the real signal raise to power 2.
Then of course you can never be negative since for whatever realization it could be positive negative.
But once you get the value even if it's negative the raise to power 2 becomes positive.
So still follow the similar or same you know like property.
And so in this case if you have a random variable raise to power 2 you will not be 0 unless the signal is not random.
If random then it must have some value in the case of 0 mean.
So that will give you all the value because for white Gaussian noise assuming is 0 mean.
So that's how this is just a brief review for those of you who may not have learned this before.
Now going back to NP approach we have done this several times and go through some examples.
Then you just take the likelihood ratio and here this is the given threshold.
Then for NP approach it will depend on the probability of false alarms and so on.
For the moment we just assume that's a threshold without knowing its value yet.
Now as you will only know for noise only then of course this major data will follow the 0 mean Gaussian distribution under H0.
And if under H1 you will have some signal.
So the mean here is S of n.
S n is deterministic so that give you all the mean.
It could be positive, it could be negative but it will in general change over time.
So that means you can think about it will be Gaussian random variable.
But over the time the mean value will change depending on the X of n.
It's not the fixed DC constant value.
But in terms of the period of likelihood function you will get the same expression for both of them.
Except the mean of course here.
This is you can think about 0 mean this is the mean equal to S n.
So both are the same if S n is equal to 0 all the time.
But in general we will be unable to tell the two if S n becomes 0.
There will be no signals all the time.
So we will see some difference between the two.
So based on that you will take the ratio.
And then because it's a financial signal I think there may be a good time to review.
Also I hope some...
It's interesting.
Let me see which one.
So this is what I left last week here.
One way so that the few Q function property are here.
So good.
No one want to take this piece of paper.
Maybe not useful for most of the people here.
But at least they don't slow that way.
So that's a good side here.
So some of the basic math I think as a master or PhD student you should always...
...know here.
So if you have E of A divided by E of B.
I hope some of the...
Not very good.
Let me try this one.
That looks better.
Then it will be the same as you can combine to A minus B.
So that's a very basic property of exponential signals.
So that's what you should remember.
In case you...
Maybe forget here.
So let's now come back here.
You see our ratio is this one divided by...
Sorry, we should remember in the right ratio on the left-hand side it will be H1...
In the numerator then H0 is denominator.
So that means this one, follow what I just showed, is A then subtract the B here.
So that will be easy.
So don't stop there.
You see our detector, the way we do is you always try to simplify this likelihood ratio in such a way where...
...you try to put those terms depending on the data.
Because this is what we are going to base our detector on the left-hand side.
Whatever those terms...
It could be more than one term, maybe several terms including the coefficient.
You try to move those into combining to the right side into a ratio.
Because as long as those terms are independent of the data, it could be depending on the signal.
The signal, if they are given, you treat them as constant.
At least in terms of comparing to the major data.
These are the non-conditives.
First, I hope you... the summation is the same.
Make sure you sum them in the same index so you can combine these two.
Once you explain this, this is quadratic.
Again, I hope everyone knows how to do...
...explain A plus B with power 2.
It will be three terms.
The first one is Xn power 2.
You have to check.
You will not have this one.
Then you have the cross term, which is producing the minors 2.
They are divided by this.
Then you have minors divided by 2.
That's why this one came out.
Finally, you have the third term, which is Xn power 2.
Because A plus B raises the power of 2.
Then the other term, let, it will be this one.
You see here, raise the power of 2, it will be positive sign.
Therefore, this minus 1 over 2 sigma power 2, still there.
These are your things.
Don't neglect this small difference.
That's a typical mistake, particularly during the exams.
Given the short time, if you are not careful, you can easily make mistakes like this.
Therefore, as I already mentioned, to do the detection,
we need to base on those terms involving the major data.
In this case, X of n.
You consider this one as no.
By the way, the difference between this one and the previous one is we take log.
In this one, we haven't taken log, so it's exponential signal.
After combining, you have this.
Once you take exponential signal, don't forget.
If later you need to get the value of the threshold, you also need to take log of that one.
Therefore, what we will take will be this one.
Again, as I said, this sigma power 2 is also considered as a non-constant.
Make sure you know this is positive.
If it's positive and no g-log, you can multiply.
In this case, it's already in the denominator.
Multiply sigma power 2, create this one.
You become one.
The other one, you multiply.
Then, this term, you combine, you move to the right side.
You can always group that as a new threshold.
That looks very neat now.
Typically, we cannot simplify further because some students, even in the assignment,
at least not many students make this mistake.
But sometimes, if you think you want to simplify further, you simplify it,
but it must be done correctly because some students pull out this x-axis outside.
Particularly, if you have the denominator, which also has the x-axis,
it's very tempting to simplify.
You want to kingsaw out, but as I said, the function of the intake,
you can never pull it out.
You can pull out if this is constant or independent of n.
Now, this term is you can't do much any further.
You stay here.
Sometimes, we may divide it by normalize, by divide capital N,
to sample means and so on.
Therefore, now, we want to, since we are using the NP approach,
if we have fixed the probability of forcing up to the alpha,
then we can be psi h1 if the past statistic.
Sometimes, we call it as a detector, because in this case,
we are doing the detection test based on the data.
So, we also call it as a statistic.
There are several similar terms.
Then, this is what we, our NP detectors.
So, you include this and also a threshold.
The threshold is depending on this probability of force alone.
Then, you can see here, this is a function of the data.
Then, this we need to choose according to our given condition.
How to do that?
Sometimes, it's easy.
Sometimes, not so easy.
We will see examples here.
So, this is simplified example in the very special case.
Xn equal to a, and become a dc level.
We assume a greater than 0.
Because in this case, we can easily divide by a.
But if a is negative, you can also do it easily.
But inequality will change, because if you're dividing a negative value.
So, in this case, later we will talk about,
even in the case we don't know the side at all,
then we will have some difficulty.
But for the time being, we assume we know either positive or negative.
So, for this example, we assume this is positive.
Then, therefore, in this case, now you'll see it's a constant.
You can pull out the a.
Therefore, this is one way.
For the detectors, they are not unique expressions.
You can write this one also correct.
Or you can divide by a positive constant.
Either this or even divide by two, as long as it's positive.
They are all called detectors.
But then, you need to be consistent.
Once you do this on the left-hand side,
the threshold will also change accordingly.
Therefore, you'll see here, we use a new gamma 2-pride,
rather than one-pride.
Therefore, in this case, you can see, for this special case,
that's the sample mean detector.
We already discussed this earlier.
We can also consider another situation where the s-n is equal to this.
So, go dump it, the exponential in white Gaussian noise.
Here, the i is constant, which is between 0 and 1.
When n goes bigger and bigger, it will get smaller.
So, let's dump it, exponential.
Weapon if i is greater than 1,
then the signal will become exponentially growing up to infinity.
That's not happening in realistic.
If i goes to 1, then it becomes constant, like that, at the DC.
In this case, our test statistic is just substituted inside.
So, we'll see here.
Then you can see this i-n, as I mentioned,
when n increases, it gets smaller and smaller.
Here, we are doing the sample mean,
but to put the weight into the data, you see here.
Since this n, our power of n, gets smaller and smaller.
So, you'll see the weight is largest when n goes to 0.
That means the current, our current data.
Then when the n increases, that means the signal is a decaying,
so you multiply by a value smaller than 1.
So, you'll get the smaller weighties.
If the noise power remains the same,
therefore, our signal to noise ratio will decrease over time.
That's some implications here.
Therefore, you can see here the concept of match filter comes from here.
Then the next topic, we will see how to do the match.
The idea here is, our weight is depending on the signal value in general,
you see our s-n.
Here, even if s-n is negative value, the larger the absolute value,
you can see the weighting is also heavy.
Because if you have a negative value, the signal, even if it's noise,
it will contain, you know, we always remember, we're dealing with signal noise.
So, you'll contain the same signal, say if it's negative,
you multiply by a negative value, except it will become a power of 2.
It will become positive.
Of course, excluding the noise.
So, that means the absolute value is larger, the heavier we are doing the weighting.
Therefore, you can see here our test statistic, the weight is depending on the s-n.
That's why we can introduce the concept of either correlator,
I mean we are doing the correlation, and this is the given signal.
Correlation, as you already know, like auto-correlation, we try to multiply,
and then see, you know, what value can we get.
So, therefore, using this block diagram, you can see our detector is given the x-n.
This is what we measure, signal noise.
But since we know the s-n, you see, so we can just create the s-n,
I think most of you are in the COM, COM, MSC program.
So, that's a little bit like modulation, you see, you have the non-signal,
another high frequency carrier you multiply, then you create the product.
The index of n is at the same time.
So, when the time moves, the x-n keeps changing, the x of n also keeps changing.
So, you multiply n, assuming total we have capital N sample,
and you just sum them together, that's what we call t of x.
And after that, you need to compare, just like in a circuit,
you have another simple function to do the compression here,
comparing to a given threshold, and then you make the decision,
either h1 or h0, just like a switch here.
So, therefore, this concept here seems very close to, looks like a filter,
so that's why we want to see whether we can do a kind of abi-f filter here.
And I hope that you all remember how to get the outputs of an abi-f filter
passing input signal, say input signal is x of n,
then our filter, if the input is from, we call it h of n.
And being abi-f, you only have finite, the input is from the length,
only have finite length.
So, therefore, the summation, you only sum over the finite samples.
So, that's how you write this yn.
At the time of n, assume we're doing the causal filtering from 0,
then continue only moving in one direction, so our yn is equal to that.
And we also assume this xn is no 0, only over the measuring time,
which is, as we always assume, you have finite length, finite sample,
from 0 up to capital A, so therefore, this is the case here.
So, what do we have here?
Our max filter is, we try to use the given signal, you know, remember?
In our detection here, we assume we know the x of n.
But to build the union pulse response h of n,
we do not directly use x of n as the union pulse response.
Instead, we free-bid, you see, free the, since our x of n,
the only capital N sample from 0 up to capital N minus 1.
So, what you'll do is, to get this h of n, you'll reverse it first.
Then the first one will become the last, and the second one becomes the second last free-bid.
That's how you rely in this way.
And then, once you write the h of n from here in this order,
when you substitute back our yn,
if you're linking the h of n, it will be in this way.
That's how you do the FIAR filtering.
But now, you want to link this h of n based on this relationship.
So, you put it back, then using the s of n, it will be this,
become this new, new, new signal in this.
So, what changes is only this argument.
So, I hope this one is very easy for you to verify.
Now, in terms of filtering, you see, you have an example going in.
It's in books, you go through a filter, you will collect the outputs from 0, 1, 2, 3, and so on.
But, assuming our case here, when we do detection, we don't get all these output samples.
What we need is only take the output at this time instant,
small n equal to capital N minus 1.
You only wait until this moment, then you say, OK, that's what we need.
That means we only take the y, when N equals to capital N minus 1.
So, what happens if you substitute this small n as capital N minus 1?
Then, of course, your kings are distant.
And then, what are the names?
Minus, minus k, which become, of course, k.
Minus 1, multiply minus 1, become 1.
So, that's precisely what we have for our test statistic.
Because, your colleague, now since we don't see any small n here,
then the index of k, you can change it back to n.
For index, it doesn't matter.
You like the dummy variable, you see.
You can call it small n, you can call it small k, and so on.
Or, you can call it small n.
And that's what we found early, the t of x, and the same form.
So, that's why we call that this detector by your bill,
a FIA filter, to match the given signal.
So, that's why it's called a matched filter.
Any questions for this?
Yeah.
So, again, here, you want to put it together into a more clear,
a broad diagram.
You can see here, this is given data.
And we pass through the FIA filter.
And the union value response is given in this.
Assuming you know the given signal.
And out of that, you'll see the output will only take the sample x,
small n equal to capital N minus 1.
Because for filter, once you have one input signal, say at 0,
you already get one output, also at 0.
And equal to 1, you get another one.
So, we, until this n equal to small n equal to capital N minus 1,
then we close, we take this value, and then do the detection
by comparing to the threshold.
So, therefore, to summarize, our matched filter is my first
free-pinged signal.
It's n equal to 0.
From 0 to capital N minus 1, you reverse the order.
Then, yeah, then you're shifting it to the right
by capital N minus 1 sample.
So, you'll see here, so the meaning of, let me illustrate this.
So, be very straight forward.
The G-lo, then N minus 1.
Then, what we want to do is this value become here,
then this N minus 1, yeah, it will come here.
So, one way to do, if we are talking about flip,
with respect to this, you can think about,
I flip all the value to the, using this angle of G-lo as an axis.
So, free-ping, you see, this one here become minus 1,
and so on, minus 2.
And then, after that, you'll shift to the right.
So, that means in the angle of G-lo come here,
then go and come here, and so on.
So, that should be quite easy to do mathematically,
and you can also think about how you're doing physically
if you are a manipulator sample.
Okay, in the case of the arrival time unknowns,
so you don't know when to do,
then that means you will become, what we were discussing,
chapter five is you'll have some unknown parameter to estimate.
So, that will be a different topic.
For now, we know the S of N exactly.
So, that's what we call non-signal deterministic signal.
And then another useful property of this mesh filter is,
we can show is maximized SNR at the output of FIR filters.
So, that's how we will briefly discuss what Y is.
So, let's see, we first define the output SNR.
Output SNR is, this is the signal, you see,
we have the Y of N minus 1 at that particular output.
Because this is random, so our signal we measure by expectation,
ways of how to. That's the user definition.
And then noise is varying, you see, even on the H1, you see,
you remove the mean is our signal,
because we are dealing with a non-signal.
So, you remove the signal, what level of noise?
So, that's the same as you are just talking about the variance.
So, that's how this is the definition.
And then now we plug in into the expression of the Y,
you know, this is, we already know this is like our filter.
At the moment here, we don't need to go back to the signal yet,
we just based on the unit impulse response, which is the FIR filter.
And similarly, here, to take about variance, you see,
now we already removed the signal, so what level it will be this,
multiplied by the noise.
And then to show that through, we substitute using vector form by using
vector SW and H, and you see here our H is relating to this by FRIP.
So, now we relate that in vector form,
so here, which is the signal, assume we do not match with the signal here,
you see we have the impulse response and given signal S.
And for the noise, you see using the similar techniques as we already discussed earlier,
again we like this, since W is random, where H is constant, you pull out,
then you, because this is a Y noise, so this becomes a simple diagonal element with constant.
So, therefore this simplifies to that.
And then here, again we use this simple expression by, you know, in the product,
you can take the transform, become scale.
And then here we use the Cauchy inequality, that's already known in the appendix,
given, so that's always whole.
And the equality holds, so you see here, if you look at the numerator and denominator,
you see, so in general, you see we will have the numerator will be smaller or equal to the product of these two.
So, one of them is here.
But in the case of H related to S by just any constant, okay, so this is linearly related.
And this property is what we remember last, during part one, several ways ago,
we are proving the CIOB, we also used similar property, when satisfied this condition.
Linearly related, then you can get equality, I mean, it becomes equal,
and that's how it happened here.
So in general, you see, we will have this, because this by definition, that will be the ratio.
So it will always be smaller or equal to that.
And then assuming we make it easy, we let the constant C go to one.
And therefore, since we already freed, so our in power response should be equal to S of N.
So in that case, we will get the maximum SNR, the equality holds, okay, when this satisfied.
And that's why we call that as match filter, in this case, the filter match with the given signal,
and it also give you the maximum SNR in this case.
Okay, but you, yeah, so this is the notation, we obtain the maximum, and that's,
this part is the inner product of the signal, that's our signal energy.
And in the case of, we have a non-deterministic signal in white Gaussian noise, as what we discussed just now,
then the match filter is also an optimal detector in terms of the NP criteria.
Remember, our early discussion is based on the white Gaussian noise and the NP criteria.
Okay, but however, we are dealing with no Gaussian noise, because just now you see our proof here.
To prove whether the output is maximized, we do not actually use the white Gaussian noise assumption.
So therefore, if no Gaussian noise, our SNR still is maximum, but our match filter here is in general,
will not be optimal in the NP sense.
That's something you need to, you need to think know here.
Then we can also obtain the performance of this match filter, which is very similar to what we discussed early in the, you know,
previous chapter, the Gauss and Gaussian, which differ in me.
So let's just very quickly go over here before we take the break.
So again here, now this so-called performance, we will see given probability for the alarm words PD, you can get that.
So again, we come based on this formulation or fix of this here.
And then you can see here, assume now we are dealing with Gaussian noise, then our HT of X is a linear combination of Gaussian random variable.
So therefore, even under both A0 and H1, both the case we get a Gaussian random variable is T of X.
And then that's what we already done before.
So I hope you know how to handle this, to get the E of T and the S0 and this is 0 because the noise is 0.
And S0 is deterministic.
Under H1, then you are playing the two parts.
So this part is 0.
So what layer is this?
And that's precisely our signal energy.
And then to get the variance is very similar since we are dealing with white Gaussian noise, then you can see it's related to the signal energy multiplied by this.
Similarly under H1, you get the same.
So therefore, we get this distribution of this.
It's a Gaussian, 0 mean or mean equal to energy.
And also, they have the same variance.
And then you can, because they only shift by the means.
So you get precisely the two bell curve with only different shift.
So you need to know the value as you will have this.
And then you can also normalize this.
So we normalize, then you get a new test, which is now the very equal to 1.
And for this one, the 0, we normalize, it's still 0.
But the mean here shift.
So you can verify how to do the change easily.
And then again, you can see the detection performance will increase with increasing value of this.
Because that's what we say.
If the variance is the same, we only compare how much difference between this mean.
Assuming 1 is at 0.
So to figure this value, of course, you can get a better separation.
And that's how you, given the probability for Solan, we can get this gamma.
So that's how you get this.
And then once I get this, we can get the PD, which differ with that by shifting this mean.
So we get this and you're substitute here.
Because we know this, so we want to put back our gammas relating to that.
You put back and simplify, you'll get this.
So this is given.
And then what will determine the change is this.
Remember, to get a bigger value, PD, we want to make it larger.
Then you want to make the argument to be more negative to the left-hand side.
Remember the Q block.
So therefore, from here, we can see the energy to noise ratio will determine the performance.
If this is larger, we will get better increase the PD and so on.
And then we have a similar curve, as we discussed before.
So these are the observations.
I think we already know that.
So to increase this energy to noise ratio, there are several ways.
Assume the noise is fixed.
So you're only determining by N and A.
So if the A signal level is getting bigger, assume here, dealing with the DC value,
then you'll see DC, then we will have here.
Or you can increase the signal length.
Of course, you'll do with both.
And also in this case, the shape of the signal does not affect the performance
since we are dealing with white Gaussian noise.
But later on, you will see for color noise, then the shape of the signal will be important.
Even with the same energy, we need to see which shape of the signal will produce the best performance.
So again, the gain-yields, deflection coefficient.
Again, based on what you write, the angle is the same result.
So we take a break here before we continue into the generalized mesh filter.
We come back at 8 o'clock.
Now it's 7.47.
We take a short break until 8 p.m.
So we can continue.
Any questions?
You can stay here.
You have to ask.
Thank you.
Okay, so let's continue.
So let me just briefly explain the use.
Okay, first we talk about energy which is, you see we have a finite number of signals,
say S0 up to S n minus 1.
So energy will be each of the sample, each of the signal sample with the positive negative,
your raise of power two, add them together, you will become energy.
If power, you will have to divide, normally you will divide the energy per sample.
So you will take the unique energy.
Okay, so and then you can write in vector form by, sorry, I think there is no need.
Yeah, so in vector form you will be just in the product and not the power of two.
The power of two is a typo arrow in the notes.
And then if you go back to this expression, you can see we make good use of the, you know,
we make good use of the Cauchy inequality, you see.
So that's basic.
You look at the expression here.
This is in general, if H different from the S vector, then you will have this inequality.
So you put this inside the numerator.
So therefore this ratio will be smaller or equal to that.
Then of course the maximum will be this one.
If only H equal to C multiplied by S, which I can assume C is constant.
Then because of that, you, yeah, this pie is correct.
That's already say it's always smaller equal to that.
But the expression of signal energy, they shouldn't have the power of two here, which
is just the England product.
So you can remove, can delete this power of two.
Okay.
So I think this part is straightforward.
So now we want to move on to the case with some correlated noise because in the case
of additive white Gaussian noise, we already discussed which is optimal.
What happened to this more general noise?
It's still Gaussian, but the covariant matrix were not necessarily to be diagonal element
with equal diagonal element value.
It can be more general as long as it's a positive definite matrix.
It will do.
So in this case, we will assume the noise to be white sense stationally.
So I hope that you have learned a little bit.
For example, some of you is taking the 6401.
We will spend a little bit more time discussing this white sense stationally.
So here you can see the covariant matrix will no longer be a unidial function as we discussed
early because they are correlated.
But it's still a satisfied symmetric topology form.
So here we are defining the covariant element value.
It depends on the difference between this m and n index.
The m is the number of the column where n is the index of the column.
N is the index of the row.
So you see here if n equal to n, which is a principal diagonal element, then they are
all equal value.
Similarly if m minus n equal to 1, then it doesn't matter what m and n value.
3 multiplied by 2.
3 minus 2 equal to 1.
4 minus 3 also equal to 1.
That means you have this property.
So we're not going to detail about this.
What we want to see is in such a case, what performance can we get for this?
The code is generalized mesh filter because later you will see the mesh filter is a little
bit more complicated than what we already have for the white Gaussian noise.
So let's again look at the library of functions and the h0 and h1.
So again here the only difference is one you have the means which equal to the s where
the other is 0 mean.
Now since we are no longer dealing with the white Gaussian noise, so we have to take the
inverse of that.
And here is a determinant and then take the square root.
So we can still work on the NP detectors.
In this case we can decide h1 if this block likelihood ratio greater than some threshold.
And very similar definition, you can see this.
Because after simplified you will take the difference between these two because you can
show out the quadratic term in terms of x vector and the constant term which is this.
So in this case we can still derive this test statistic which is equal to this part, this
involved data.
This one is beta independent.
So therefore we will have this.
And then we call it as a generalized mesh filter or sometimes filter is a similar name.
We get a similar replica correlated.
So we call that also as generalized.
Why generalized?
Because we need to do a little bit change to get the mesh filter if we want to use the
same similar structure.
So how should we do it?
We can modify the signal by multiply by this C inverse of the metric.
So we call this new signal as prime as this new signal.
So once we do that you can see it will become the inner product between these x and s, the
new signal.
So therefore in that case once you make a change, do some changes in the signal, then
we get the similar form.
Only in the case of white calcium noise then our a's become, because this is become the
I think the metric is multiplied by this noise value for white calcium noise.
So we will reduce to this standard mesh filter.
We already know.
But in the current situation we have to deal with this as prime.
So let's go through some intermediate case first before we go to the more general one.
So one intermediate case between the white calcium noise and the correlated noise is
this so-called uncorrelated noise but with unequal value.
So this is the diagonal matrix but the element value they are different not the same.
So we call it sigma 0 up to and so on.
In this case the inverse is very easy to get.
You see you will know diagonal element.
Assume they are not equal to 0.
So you take the inverse you only need to inverse each of them.
And in this case the test statistic is very similar to before except you do a more for
each product you do a waiting before your sum.
So you can see here if the sample with smaller barrier then that means we are dividing this
barrier will become a bigger weight.
Then we give a heavier weight on this product.
And that is reasonable because smaller barrier means the signal noise ratio is higher.
So this sample is a better sample.
We give a higher weight.
Yeah so that makes sense.
And then in such a case you can see we can rely this Xn as signal in noise.
And then multiply by that because this one is always positive you can divide into the
standard deviation.
In this case you can see here we are if we have the signal divided by this same constant
each signal we normalize you know dividing that.
And then we also somehow normalize the noise by dividing that.
So once you do that you can verify this new noise it will become a white noise because
after you are dividing the standard deviation then you can easily verify this new noise
because the covariance matrix becomes high.
So that's why we call that the sample is equalized or pre-whited.
And we are dealing with the new sample we have the white noise add into that.
And that's also very useful.
And that's why this is typically in practice we do the pre-whitening.
If you know you have uncorrelated but the noise variance they are different so you do
the pre-whitening.
And this pre-whitening even you can extend to a more general covariance matrix.
So you can multiply by the inverse of the matrix which we will discuss later.
So we do it one by one.
So now we move it to be more general.
Now this is a positive definite and symmetry.
So in that case again we apply a little bit about magic theory.
So I hope you know that if you use a singular value decomposition you can show this because
for positive definite and symmetry then the inverse it can always write as the product
of the D. D is a no singular in this case square and the transpose.
It becomes a transpose of that.
So this again can be proven and that's already we are known in magic theory, DNA algebraic.
So once assume you have done that then we can plug in we can make the change here.
And then you see here we can combine this into a new major data which we call X prime.
And similarly this one you can combine into a new signal.
In this case you will see the noise also do a transform.
So we are changing the noise, changing the signal and also change the major data.
And this is this matrix D. It's not directly the seeing-burst matrix but once you do the
factorization you get this matrix D's pre-witening matrix because you do that you can produce
white Gaussian noise once you multiply by correlated noise.
Of course you have to ensure this C matrix is the covalent matrix corresponding to this
correlated noise W. So how to do that?
That's again not difficult you apply this by definition because this is zero means so
is equal to E of this product and then you substitute this and then do a little bit of
manipulation because D constant not momentum you take it up and then we know this equal
to C and then you know C's inverse equal to that thing because D and D are the same
transform they are invertible.
No singular means invertible because they are square matrix.
They will invert this.
And then once you invert you can see they become identity matrix.
So this is a very useful matrix theory.
You see you have your product of two matrix.
Both of them they are not necessarily equal to the same D and D transpose.
This is the space okay.
If you have A multiplied by B you take the inverse assuming both of them are invertible
square then it will be equal to A inverse so you need to swap this.
Let me maybe show briefly.
So that's again a useful matrix theory.
So if we have A and B if you are inverse assume of course that each of the matrix are square
and invertible.
Then it will be equal to B inverse A inverse so you need to swap the position.
So using this property you just think about this is A and this is B and then A you up
the inverse you will become D inverse.
So D multiplied by D inverse of course equal to identity and then similarly E transpose
inverse then multiple by D transpose.
So also equal to identity so this is a very useful property.
So that's how it becomes I.
And then with that we can after do the pre-wited mean then we can get our generalized mesh
filter in this thing.
So now we have the measure data.
You go through D get the new measure data after pre-wited mean.
Similarly the S is available to us.
We know this by assumption.
You also do the same.
And after that you do a multiplication and now this is the same mesh filter correlation
and do the decision.
So again even when we do the whitening you are doing the linear combination.
So we still have the new variable still Gaussian because our transformation is linear.
And we do a finite combination.
In this case we can verify E of t under H0, still equal to 0 under H1.
Now the signal goes through this whitening so you get a new expectation.
So be careful.
It's not just the energy anymore.
The noise variant coming to play.
And to get the variant it's similar step then your nth double is the same.
Variant is the same.
And similarly under H1 your nth double is the same.
A little bit more complicated.
You need to do a bit of manipulation.
But in the nth double is the same value.
Because X after subtracting the E of X it will be equal to the noise.
So that's how you manipulate that.
And then finally like what I mentioned this property is useful.
You take the inverse and transform.
It's the same as your transform and take the inverse.
Assuming this matrix is invertible.
And then because this is symmetry you also get that.
Now we come to the performance.
We'll get similar result except now this C inverse coming into the pictures here.
So under H0, it's still 0 meaning the variant.
What I already did.
Derives equal to here.
Under H1 it's given to be the mean and the variant are the same.
And then using the similar manipulation, assume we know the probability of force alarm
you're substituting.
You can get this Pt.
And here we define the defraction coefficient by equal to this one here.
And then you need to take the square root of that.
Therefore, because that's basically you do the normalization.
We discussed early.
And again you go back to the white noise case.
Then C will be equal to that.
Then we will get back to the spatial case.
So do take note whenever you extend your models.
And the same as if you are doing with some other machine learning type of study and so
on.
You try to generalize.
You need to be able to recover back to the simple case.
So always verify.
That's how sometimes even dealing with jams if you are deriving something more complicated
you.
In the end you get the result.
You see where they work for the simpler case.
It must work in this case.
So the one main difference in talking about generalized mesh filter compared with our previous
white noise case is now this pt increase is the increasing value of this whole thing.
Not just with the energy to noise ratio.
So compare these two.
This one here is we only care about the energy of the signal.
We don't matter whether how the signal looks like.
As long as if you go back to my energy definition here you can.
The energy different signal if they have the same energy for white Gaussian noise we only
care with this energy.
But no longer in this case for generalized mesh filter we do need to see this different
signal.
You will give the different different value for this even if they are having the same
energy.
But that's why we want to see now we want to see which signal shape even with the same
energy will produce the best.
So that's what our discussion next.
So again we go by two case.
The intermediate difficulty is the case where signal design for uncorrelated noise but
with unequal value.
This is easier to consider but it's more general compared to the white Gaussian noise.
So this is we already know how to do that because this is diagonal matrix.
You can invert only the diagonal element.
And then in this case we want to see how we can choose certain signal to maximize that.
That's what we are hoping to do.
But then if we do not have any constraint of course you can say you make the signal value
to become larger and larger.
That will always increase.
But that doesn't consider the practical situation because in practice you need you cannot increase
the signal value or signal energy infinitely.
Nowadays we are talking about sustainability.
So you need to conserve signal energy.
Make it not increase signal energy.
So what we are doing here is if we constraint the signal energy to be a fixed value.
And then under this constraint we see whether we can design certain signal such as that
it still produce the maximum value.
So that's how.
So how to do that?
I think you all know you did the assignment and then I hope you already know how to apply
Lagrangian multiply with this.
Well the maxim I did under this constraint.
So you introduce this.
And then you need to do how to take partial derivative with respect to this SK here.
So that's straightforward.
And then since you see when we talk about Lagrangian you have one constraint.
You only have one Lagrangian multiply.
And this is constant.
That means independent of the N here.
We call that SK not to confuse with N.
That means it's a fixed index here.
So therefore, yeah that's how I think most of you did the assignment question one correctly
by arguing if this is a constant.
And in this case it's equal to zero for at most one single K.
We are here.
We are assuming all of them are different.
Since we are talking about unequal value.
So they are not the same.
So therefore, we can only have one K satisfy that.
So therefore, assume that we let this small k equal to J.
So that means only pick the signal where satisfy one of them say K equal to J.
Then we lay not equal to zero.
So we lay not equal to zero.
So we narrow down that into among all the capital N sample signal.
Only one of them can be no zero.
The other will be zero.
Then now the next question is how to choose this J.
So that will become very easy since all among capital N of them only one of them which is
our SJ is no equal to zero.
So instead of some we pick only this one.
And then remember if you have one sample the energy is just equal to the square of this
sample value except that's how we define the energy by summing all of them.
But you only have one equal to not equal to zero.
So you just equal to that.
So therefore, that's now become very obvious.
We want to maximize that and this is different fix.
Then of course our J and they will assume all these sigma zero one two and so on.
They are all different.
Then you want to maximize of course choose the denominator will be the smallest one.
So that's here it's very, very clear.
And then that also makes sense because among all those sample the sample there is a minimum
noise value.
That means the signal value is the highest.
It gives you the largest signal to noise value.
And that's the same as energy because now we never doubt our signal to just one no zero
sample.
Okay.
So yeah.
So indicate the diffraction coefficient will be maximized.
And we get the best performance.
So yeah.
So next we want to move on to the more general case where our C is just arbitrary noise covariance
matrix not just limited diagonal matrix.
Following the similar argument since we know the Lagrangian multiply technique work.
So we try to say by maximizing this and the constraint of that because this is the constant
energy.
So we call this equal to that.
Then what can we do?
Here you yeah we still use the technique by take the first derivative and I hope you remember
our formula if we take derivative with respect to S but this is S vector we want to maximize.
And then this pie is a quadratic formula and it's the matrix C is symmetry.
So what you get it will become 2A.
We call that as A previously because it's symmetry.
So you will be first I call it that.
And the second one what happened here?
Yeah it's the same here.
So this is the constant.
So we ignore this term what we have here.
So here is just our A is the I.
So what you get is very easy just equal to there.
The lambda is still there it's a constant.
And yeah so you see here this is what we can do.
Recall the formula here.
In this case you make it equal to 0 you end up with this.
And that goes to our familiar icon analysis you see.
Our matrix here is C inverse.
If you think about this is a new square matrix because we assume the C is invertible.
So it's no singular.
We just call it for B A or whatever.
And that's our S here is an eigen vector.
And the lambda here is become the eigen value.
Okay.
Then based on this result you can want to create this energy you multiply to the left.
So it's this.
And since this lambda is a constant we can pull this out.
So you end up with this form.
So again here if this is fixed we want to maximize this value.
Of course you will get the eigen value corresponding to this C inverse matrix.
Not the C matrix the C inverse which is the largest the maximum eigen value.
So that should be very clear.
But then again there is a new property since we are given C not C inverse.
So what's the relationship?
Of course the C and C inverse the eigen value they will since this is no singular so all
the eigen value they will be no zero.
Then the eigen value of C will be just equal to whatever this C inverse the eigen value
you will take the inverse also.
So this is again a very useful property here.
So therefore even now we want to link back to this the covariant matrix C then of course
if lambda is a maximum corresponding to this C inverse one over lambda will be the smallest
eigen value of this C.
So therefore this makes it easier by using eigen analysis to get our chalk down.
So what we do is compute given a C you will get all the eigen value or if you know you
can get the minimum eigen value will be good enough.
Then you will get the corresponding eigen vector which is called B minimum.
And then therefore you think this is energy is given you can see our S should be related
to the energy is it will be a scalar you take the square root multiplied by this eigen vector
and somehow need to normalize in this way to produce this new given energy if you have
a constraint here.
So that's finish the matched filter and it's generalized matched filters.
Any questions?
Up to now before we move on to another topic which is for the multiple signal case because
so far we discussed either noise only or you have signal noise we try to distinguish this.
Now we can consider multiple signal say two signal that's why I call it binary case you
have two different signal remember in the early discussion we have this communications
example in communications.
So therefore we want to try to link this if you have more than two they will become classification
problem but for the binary case we still call that as detection problem.
Yeah that's the problem the formulation mathematically I think we already discussed that here and
then in this case we assume for the moment the noise the white Gaussian noise to its
barrier.
And then we also assume at this point the cost to be equal so that means we do not impose
different cost they will make the problem more complicated and also the prime probability
are equal too.
So here we are using the Bayesian approach to deal with the problem but despite the same
anyway we have become a maximum likelihood criteria.
Okay then we again since we are dealing with white Gaussian noise you can see on the H0
or H1 the expression is the same except this means here we change from either H0 or H1
okay.
And then so you see here think this is ML problem you see remember we already discussed
if we are deciding H1 then this likelihood function under H1 it should be greater than
the one under H0.
So comparing the two we are just trying to get so called larger value because all the
others are the same except this exponent and then remember our exponent we carry a minus
sign here okay.
So for the exponential to a minus a constant value the one with smaller value here it will
give you a larger value because exponential to the minor positive value so that means
in the extreme you go to G0 then it will be the largest because whatever negative one
you will go down so minus one or minus two and so.
So this right here the problem we can simplify it into by choosing among the I here is G0
and 1 we have two only to see which one is the smallest or minimum you see we are comparing
the two you can extend that to the more general case say more than two but we are focusing
mainly on two okay.
So that makes the discussion much easier because you are not talking about exponential
signal you are only looking at the summation because you need a square and then some more
those and this case seems like we are measuring the distance okay comparing the measure data
and the signal these are the given one.
So we call that this detector is a minimum distance receiver because it often happen
in the communication and dealing with receiving signal.
So any problem so far any question?
So let's make it into vector form so that instead of sum you use vector form to represent
this your can use either it's a Ingle product or make it as a norm so that's yeah that's
a great Euclidean norm in the up ion space okay yeah so that's very very straightforward
some geometric then in that case you want to make this distance to be choose the small
one so that means the same thing is since the signal either S0 or H1 given and the X is
our measure data I want to see which signal is closer to this then yeah and then you can
visualize using the in the case of two sample they will become a prank so this is very similar
to machine learning you are talking about SVM support vectors during this case we just
given this S1 and S2 they are fixed so you draw the line link these two and in the middle
you'll you'll take the center point and then and then divide it into two plane so therefore
whenever in that half plane closer to S1 they will go with D side H1 because it's near D
side near D side the measure data near D side or on the other end you go to the other side
D side H0 that's very straightforward then now mathematically how we can do it then you
see for each eye can always be zero in one in the binary case so we again I hope you know how
to manipulate you you explain the quadratic term and then in our case here also this term
depends on the data you see is the measure data but here we want to compare this D0 and D1 so
the index is more important we need to use those data related depending on the one of the two
signal we are always talking about binary case so therefore you can ignore this term because
it's for both eye equal to 0 or 1 that give you the same okay it doesn't contribute to decide
which one is smaller which eye is smaller so therefore among this we rely this part here
that's the one we need we are kidding okay that's we call the TI of X so here is important
since we are we try to calculate this DI so you need to include this SIN power 2 first here
but remember here again we try to lean into the energy you see because that's we cannot always
increase the energy of the signal we want to somehow constrain the energy so this is a half of
the energy for the SI we call that if X in on eye because the two signal they may have the same
energy may be different so for the typing assume they may not be the same first okay so therefore
here we want to maximize this term so how to do that then you can see it's again related to a
mesh filter but in the extended version here so now our major data since now we always have some
signals either s0 or s1 okay so what we do is since we have these two signals given the data we
do the correlation using each of them to produce two branches yeah that's always you can always do
that then we create this t0 here but don't forget you need to subtract this half of the energy of
this similarly for this one you'll subtract this we call there is a bias then we create t0 t1 X so
now we need to compare this two to see which one is a larger then if t1 is larger than t0
we decide on h1 otherwise we decide on h0 and in the case of equal it doesn't matter it's the
pouty you can decide on either one okay so that's how it looks like a mesh filter except now you have
two branches so since we are using the patient approach so we want to see how this PE is calculated
you see so again based on what we are assuming equal cost so we're not talking about the bias
raise so we only talk about PE here and then assume the pride probability at the same it's p of h
you know and p of h one of the same so therefore both if you have two the same must be one over two
pull this out so our lab is here and then remember now our decision is a based on comparing this t1
X and t0 X okay so there are again there are two types of error here if h0 is true but we decide
as t1 greater than that then that's we decide on h1 so that's wrong similarly for the other one
okay then you can yeah so so we want to try to try to combine these two together because at this
moment it looks a little bit not so easy to handle here so what I do here since we always compare
these two we can be five this t of x equal to the difference between these two that's okay and then
once we do that you can substitute our new t of x equal to that and then you can
combine the term because they are the same summation you take this combine these two and
then these are independent of the sum you also combine you get this so now you look carefully
our tx is linear in x you see then it will also be Gaussian and each hypothesis so at the
h0 h1 it's always linear it will be Gaussian and then again we can get the expectation of t
under h0 so what you do is you substitute in this case h0 is under h0 you see our you will go back
our x of n you have to use the s0 plus the noise then simplify
yeah then you simplify your n tau with the result using vector form I think you should be able to
work out you try to combine that and then it turns out to be you you can cancel out this term to
to make it as as the difference distance difference between the h1 and s0 0 vector
is negative similarly under h1 we get the same result except the sides are different okay this is
minor this is positive okay so you only have the minus side different
and now look at the barrier under h0 again you can yeah I'll be able to work out this by yourself
then it's similar to this of course barrier will always be positive so this is a check
the point where you can verify if your n tau is a negative value there must be something wrong
okay and then under h1 it turns out to be the same here so you'll get this
then you can take the since they are the distribution they are both Gaussian and the same
barrier only the mean are different so you can assume some mean value then you you will get this
probe which is what we have learned before and then you can also get the p under that because
there is a receiver symmetry so you can simplify it into this simple q function here and then you
can also simplify the difference between these two is you'll have the square root the sigma power
two take the square root you pull out and the other one you don't take the square root so so that
means this one is a product of these two because you take the square root then you will cancel half
your n tau with this okay so so again here once we are given h1 h0 you can see the performance
will get better if the distance of these two are larger
yeah and they will call this makes sense because the if the two given sigma
further apart is easier for you to to tell the difference so that makes sense
yeah
and then let's do a little bit further assume the two energy may not be the same but we can
defy the average signal energy by some then divided by two that makes sense and then in this case
you can verify because this is we discussed we only need to care about this distance then square
so again this is you can it's a quadratic term you can explain it using the here we are dealing with
a rare vector so that's easier the way we want to do is we want to link this into
as this average energy signal energy okay so you can rewrite that and then
also in n tau ways you have a cross term here so this cross term is related to our
correlation coefficient you see that's how we defy this by this cross term and then divide by
normalize this is you see the yeah that's precisely this one is the energy of signal one the other
signal zero so you take the average and you can verify again using the
colleges inequality you can make sure this is always the absolute value is always smaller
equal to one otherwise it doesn't make sense because this is a correlation coefficient okay so that
means if zero then it's no correlation between these two if one it will be the maximum correlation
you're talking about the same signal if minus one it's the same but you go one go to the other
direction you know like 180 degree different so therefore we can put back to the p and rewrite in
in in this form you see so now again for q function you see we want to minimize that we will
make you know this is always positive but
but if you look at the positive value q function then the bigger the value the positive yeah
you will give you a smaller q function value you see remember our probe yeah it's very
q is normalized so so therefore you assume this is average energy is constrained is a fix you see
so what I can do here you can choose the signal such that this correlation is the minus one because
one minus minus one become one plus two plus one you have become two let's give you the largest
value and that also makes sense because if the you know once you have the signal energy
average energy is constrained so then in these two vectors the further apart there will be
there will be better the p will be the smallest so so if the two vector are the same but there are
180 degree different they give you the largest distance between the two okay so that makes
sense I think there was somewhat related to one of the assignment question and a few students did
answer that one then that that's that's quite good so at least yeah somehow you
you make good use of this correlation coefficient so finally we quickly apply to this linear model
because so far we do not assume linear model so linear model you don't go back to what we discussed
earlier x linearly depending on the theta vector so thus this could be known and unknown in our current
case we assume they are known and then this is ring them vector or Gaussian but the covariance
magic can be arbitrary and this is constant this noise so we see what we can do in this case
so in this case since assume we have a non-determitic signal then this will be our new
signal vector and that's zero assume this is zero so yeah so then you can go back to our
discussion and in the case of pc labor in white Gaussian noise then we get a special
linear model with h equal to that zero one equal to this and this got this so yeah
then we can once we decide on that you can use what we learned just now to formulate
and h0 h1 and then our np detector because since we assume this case it will be equal to this
as we already discussed and then we know the s you want to put back there you are this is what
you will need you will get here okay i think this is give the right time to finish this chapter and so
uh yeah so we can end here so that which just meet our our plans and our our schedule here
so next week we my plan is i finish the marking your assignments and so i hope everyone can
uh try to come next week because uh you may uh be uh better to discuss and we i will use another
half of the time to go through the simon one solution and another half of the time probably
one hour plus to finish the chapter four which is about half of this chapter three so the timing is
also uh reasonable so that's the plan and don't forget the quiz will be two weeks later here okay
so that's all uh any questions you can stay back uh yeah if not then you're free to leave
so see you next week
you