________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
åœapplause
Continue
we have
great
several days.
And of course now you have to come back.
This is the second half of the semester.
So there also kind of
ingenious,
kind of remind students that you have to start to now
prepare for the final exam.
Okay.
For those if you have not taken final exam in NTU,
you know, right, the final exam,
they all come together and
I don't know why the projector is not on.
Let me try to see.
Yeah.
On, on.
Okay.
Okay. Good.
So the final exam, check the schedule, check the timing,
and those should be confirmed.
It would not be changed anymore.
So you look at those timing and some of you,
if you are lucky or unlucky,
you may have a few exam together back to back.
So you have to plan accordingly how to prepare for,
for your final exams.
Okay.
And of course, the other thing is the assignment were out.
I was
trying to
think about what would be the good question for you.
So I said these two questions.
I hope that you have time.
Of course the marks are, of course,
the whole assignment whole world one will carry only five marks
of your final so-called total marks.
So it's not a lot.
Okay.
But more importantly for you to try out,
don't just copy from others.
Actually, even you don't submit, just lose five marks only.
But try out
and then you likely would be surprised, right?
Oh, in the lecture, everything seemed very easy,
very logical, but when you try out,
hey, some, some, there was some confusion.
So there's part of you to make decision.
You have to think carefully, put your comments,
justify your answer, right?
That's why I always ask this.
Justify your answer.
They could have more than one possible solution.
Not all of them are correct, of course,
but then you provide the reason.
Okay.
Immediately I would have got the students say that,
sir, your question is wrong.
Okay.
Actually that is exactly the purpose.
I said the question like that.
For example, the student highlighted that.
Let me see.
Where is it?
Okay.
So when you try to attempt the question,
you'll find that there are some which are confusing, right?
Whether you would decide to indicate this or the other.
And that is exactly why I make the question.
So look into this and then let me see.
Yeah.
Where is that question?
So basically the question actually you have so-called eight training samples.
You have to build a decision tree using ID tree algorithm.
Okay.
Based on this training sample.
And I do not say that all these training samples are so-called error free.
So when you build your tree, therefore at the end, I ask a question, can you prune the
tree so that to achieve similar performance or even same performance so that the tree
will be easier.
So these are the questions that you look into it.
So each question is one mark.
So look into that.
Try to practice yourself.
And this is another question.
I thought about it.
I think this would be a good exercise.
So I give you six training samples, right?
Tree belong to this solid class.
The other tree belong to M.E. class.
So my question is just to make sure you understand the question correctly.
If I were to so-called put any point here, right?
So if I have a, okay, I cannot draw here.
Okay.
Here.
Insert.
Maybe I put a cross here.
So if I have a data point here, okay, this test point does it belong to the solid or
the empty class, right?
I can move this point around, right?
And this point does it belong to solid or empty class using one nearest neighbor, right?
So maybe I give you a simple example.
Let me put out a simple example.
I have this one.
And that's not one to fill.
So I have two classes, researched.
One of them is solid.
And then the other one is here, assuming the symmetric.
Here.
And then I want to have this.
This is the one I just draw.
Disappear already.
Maybe easier.
I just draw here.
Okay.
Let's see.
Coming up.
Yeah.
Let's say I have a region here which I put a solid class and an empty class.
Okay.
Just illustrate this.
So now I want you to shape the area state.
If any point lengths on that area will belong to this solid class, which will be the region
that if any point I point here will belong to this rather than this.
Right?
Another question?
Okay.
Anyone know the answer for this?
It's very straightforward.
The area that you have a point located in it, it will belong to the solid class.
Anyone?
What the assignment is slightly more challenging than this?
This area.
Right?
Because any point here will be closer to this rather than this.
Any point here you draw a Euclidean distance, this will be shorter than this.
Right?
So this area will all belong to the solid class.
Okay?
So using that, do your assignment.
For this, you have to draw the area that which any point by using one nearest neighbor belong
to solid class by using three nearest neighbor, slightly more challenging than by using five
nearest neighbor.
Okay?
So any point by using one nearest neighbor, slightly more challenging than by using five
nearest neighbor.
Okay?
If you want to think about it, will the result change?
I thought about setting this, but already too many questions, I just give you.
Will the result change if you use a Manhattan distance?
Okay.
So think about it.
Okay?
So these are two questions.
Shouldn't be difficult based on what we have covered in the lecture.
You should be able to do it.
Okay?
Let's continue with the question.
Let's continue with lectures.
So last lecture, we talked about nearest neighbor classifiers.
And then again, we basically talked about the so-called matrix that you need to use or
measure.
You need to use to measure the distance between the two so-called points, the training sample
and the nearest neighbor so that you can decide which class the test sample belong to.
So today we're going to look at the other classifier, which is called support vector
machine.
And support vector machine, actually, you think carefully if it is just a binary classifier,
okay?
The simplest one, the basic one, which basically give you just like the nearest neighbor that
we show, right?
You could operate in a 2D like this, right?
So if I give you some training sample, positive and negative, right?
How can you find the decision boundary so that like this one, we call it hyperplanned?
It could separate the positive from the negative classes.
So this is called support vector machine.
So in 1D, it will be just a single threshold, right?
For example, if you want to decide whether this number is positive or negative, then
you will choose to ask whether the value is larger or smaller than zero, right?
So it's larger than zero, it's a positive value, less than zero is negative.
So in 1D, the hyperplane become a value, a threshold, okay?
In 2D, you have a two-dimensional, so you can only draw a line, assuming this is a linear
classifier.
Of course, you could have nonlinear, but let's start with a simple linear classifier that
you can separate by drawing a line.
For such cases, that seems to be possible.
And then for 3D, then your decision boundary will be a plan.
Normally the decision is 1D lower than your training data.
So 2D is one line, 3D is a two-dimensional plan, okay?
So all this we call the hyperplane for you to make decision.
And SPM basically is trying to find the hyperplane which allows so-called some possible error,
because bear in mind that these samples are training samples.
They are not all the samples that you are going to see, right?
They are just a small set of samples that you happen to have.
You try to find a boundary that can separate these two classes.
So there are many such possible hyperplanes, okay?
In this case, one line, which could separate the positive from the negative class.
For example, here's another one, right?
And you can also separate the two classes without any error, okay?
Here's another one, okay?
So among all these possible lines, which one is better?
So there is basically an engineering problem.
So for SPM, basically you'll try to find the line such that the distance from the positive
to this line will be maximum, right?
To allow maximum margins of error or margin of noise, okay?
So for example, so how then how you formulate this, right?
Assuming for example, you are looking for this decision boundary, D, okay?
Now you can consider that it's actually a margin from D1 to D2, okay?
Which you currently, based on trained data, none of these data is located within this margin.
Ideally, you want to find the line such that the margin is as wide as possible, right?
So that means if you have a test data which could have some noise or error,
turn out that it will be very so-called different form.
I mean, it will not be, even if they are different from this training sample,
you can still make a correct decision.
So as we then choose the maximum margin plan as the decision boundary.
For example, here there are two possible such plans.
One is a D1, the other is a D2, right?
So based on this, if you define the margin, you can see that the distance between D1,
1 to D1, 2 is larger than D2, 1 to D2, 2.
So therefore, this D1 is likely chosen for SSSVM, right?
So there are many, many such so-called possible decision boundary,
but SPM is choosing the one which maximizes the margin,
which also maximizes the tolerance of errors or noise, okay?
So that is just a concept.
Then how do you so-called formulate this problem so that you can,
even a set of training sample, you can solve this problem, okay?
So of course, we use a 2D data as an example,
which you are finding the line here, but the whole set of
mathematics can be applied to multi-dimensional data.
Could be very high.
It's just a vector, so-called manipulation.
So let's consider they are end training sample, right?
Each sample is denoted by the feature xi.
This is the vector of attributes or feature vector that we mentioned.
Yi is the label.
So in this case, there's label them as minus one and one, right?
And one and zero, because for the formulation, and
this later on you'll see that it will be easier to put the mathematics into a very
nice formula for you to so-called find the solution.
So if you define all these points, in this case,
they are 2D assuming you have a zero, zero coordinate here.
Then this one will be x1, 1, x1, 2, x2, 1, x2, 2, all these data points, right?
If Yi is part one, they belong to the positive class,
minus one belong to negative class.
So then your problem now can be formulated.
The decision boundary you're looking for, the green line here,
will be the w dot x plus b equal to zero.
This is a line equation, right?
In 2D, will be w1 x1 plus w2 x2 plus b equal to zero, right?
Which is, again, your line equation here.
If this x1 is x2, so any line here you can write it as
w1 x1 plus w2 x2 plus b equal to zero.
Just for, I'm not sure which one will be captured by the camera, but
any line here, if you change the w1, w2, and b, b is basically the
intersection when x1 equal to zero, right?
And b will be equal to, x1 equal to zero, b,
this point will be equal, x2 will be equal to minus b, divided by w2, right?
So, similarly, you can find the point.
So any line here can be described by different value of w1, w2, and b, okay?
So that is basically the line equation here.
Even this train of data, you can find such a line such that this line is w,
dot product with x plus b equal to zero.
There's w, for 2D, it's w1 x1 plus w2 x2 plus b equal to zero.
And then you can imagine that there's another line here.
Let's assume this is wx plus b equal to one.
And there's another line, wx plus b equal to minus one, right?
So if you define your class label as minus one plus one,
that means you only have to plug in any of this xi.
If this is your decision boundary, xi, dot product with w plus b,
if this is on this side, then this value will be positive.
On the other side, it will be negative, right?
So in your classifier, you just want to check by putting in any sample xi,
what will be the value, whether it's a positive or negative of this so-called
form expression, right?
So all your train data should be larger than one, larger than or equal to one, right?
Testing data less than or equal to minus one.
So this is basically the boundary that you are looking for.
And then how do you find this w and b?
You want to find the w such that the distance between these two,
one to minus one line, will be maximum, right?
So now you imagine there are two such a point along this line, w, right?
Then because as long as the point located at this line,
you have to satisfy this equation, wx plus b equal to 0.
There's a line equation.
So we have this x1, x2, right?
So these are the ones that because they are on the decision boundary,
they have to fulfill this line equation.
Then you subtract one from the other.
That means this x2 minus x1 is this vector in this direction.
This one, dot product with w equal to 0.
That means the w must be perpendicular to this line.
You have this.
And x2 minus x1 will be the vector which
is running across along this so-called decision boundary.
So that is basically a very simple so-called mathematics
manipulation.
Then if any of the xa is on the right-hand side,
then you know that wx plus b larger than 0.
So we talked about the size earlier on.
And then this is less than 0.
Any of the red lines exceed below this.
Then if we label all this square as a plus one, the red one
as a minus one, then the y label now
can the decision cross y now will be.
If this is large and 0, the label
is less than 0, negative 1.
So again, we're just using this charge
that you can formulate the problem like this.
So then assuming these two hyperplanes, which
are parallel to the decision boundary here,
why is xa plus b equal to k?
Originally, they may not be equal to 1.
Any k.
The other is k minus 0.
So this is our k prime.
Anything on the left-hand side is less than 0.
Then you can move this line.
You can adjust this line.
And then these two parallel lines stay such that this wxa
plus b equal to 1.
Now this line is exactly 1 rather than k.
And this is minus 1.
So these two points, xa and xc, are the nearest
to this decision boundary, one from positive,
one from negative class.
Assuming you have this.
Now xa, this line is 1 and minus 1.
You can always do that because w and b and k,
they are just a scalar, integer.
You can always move the line slightly
and then the class 1 minus 1 are equal distance
to the decision boundary.
Then you normalize it.
So the one is class 1.
The other is minus 1.
And b will be just specifying the line in the middle.
Then you subtract these two.
You are going to find that this d, which is the distance,
now is the margin.
If you look at this one, xa, xc, dog product with w, w
is perpendicular to the line.
So this is xa minus xc is this one.
xa minus xc is this dog product with w.
It will be the distance, which is the margin d.
Again, this is a simple so-called algebra vector
manipulation.
If you have forgotten this, go back to check up.
So then the margin, now we go to two nearby.
The magnitude of w, which is the length of this w vector.
So that will be the margin.
So xa and xc, these are the two points closer
to the decision boundary.
We call this support vector, support vector, xa and xc.
And then you can find the w so that it
allows you to maximize the distance d2 here.
And one thing that you can notice, the w
is the vector which is perpendicular to this decision
boundary, w.
With any line which is above this plus one,
this will be your training sample.
This is your negative sample.
So your goal now is to learn the parameter w and b
such that for all the training sample yi
equal to one positive class, this is larger than one.
All the point here, larger than one.
And this is less than one, minus one.
So you can see if yi is minus one,
because all the red point will have a label minus one.
And then this is wx plus b equal to minus one line.
Then the rest will be less than minus one.
Then you can merge these two equations into one.
And positive and negative now for all the point one to n.
Because yi is positive or negative,
if you multiply this, if yi is minus one,
then this exactly will become this formula.
So now for all your training data,
you just have to focus on this equation.
You make sure all your training data with the label
plus one and minus one, they all have to fulfill
this one constraint, which is yi multiplied wxi plus b
has to be larger than equal to one.
And then you want to find the margin such that
this is maximum, and that means w,
the square of the distance, the length,
divided by two will be minimum.
It's just the opposite.
So SVM now, basically giving you a set of training data,
xi and yi label, you now can find the SVM,
which is the decision boundary w dot x plus b equal to zero.
And such that you'll find all the possible w and b
that satisfy this two set of equation.
One is this equation for all the training sample,
and then this one has to minimize.
Because if you want to maximize the margin,
you have to minimize this opposite of this.
And this one, you can solve this problem
by using a Lagrange multiplier method.
So for those who have studied engineering mathematics,
and they are packets for you to do that,
every problem you formulate at this so-called
constraint equation, which you are given a set of xi,
you want to find w and b such that all these xi, yi,
fulfill this constraint.
And then among this, you want to minimize some of these
so-called variable that you are looking for the answer.
And that is a standard problem you can always solve
by using Lagrange multiplier method.
So I leave it to you for you to go and check
the engineering mathematics.
Once you formulate the problem like this,
you can always find a solution to that problem.
However, the word is not so simple.
What if now you have two new training sample,
n and p here?
Before then, you actually find this is your boundary,
but now you find that these two points were
on the opposite side of the boundary.
This suppose belong to the red class minus one.
This suppose belong to the positive plus one class.
But now with either with the noisy data
or is the actual data that it's just not so perfect.
You cannot always expect there is a decision boundary
separate the so-called two classes so nicely.
Then if you, with these two new sample,
if you still try to find the maximum margin,
let me erase the...
So you can find this.
Now the original D one no longer possible
to separate all the positive negative.
And you can find the D two here.
Now the margin is smaller, the D is smaller.
And it can do the job, but the question now is,
is the D one or D two a better decision boundary?
So pay in mind that this could be noisy data.
It could be actually original here,
but because of noise,
it kind of come over to the decision boundary.
Although you try to fix the problem for these two,
but for many other unseen data,
you may make more errors.
So if your goal is to still find the maximum margin,
while you accept some possible noisy data,
so D two may not be the best solution.
So then you can actually twist the problem formulation
into a new one, which allow you to have some,
this error, okay?
This side, the side, the small error that originally here,
but allow this point to move slightly over
to the positive direction.
And this one move to the negative direction.
So we call this a slack variable psi, okay?
This one now, G, why I still positive one,
before then is larger than one, right?
But you allow a small error slack variable minus Xi.
So you move to this direction.
And this one originals will be less than minus one,
but now you allow this move to positive direction psi.
You don't know how much they will move,
but based on the train data,
you, with this so-called slack variable,
you can still fit them all the data
into one single constraint equation.
We call this a soft margin approach,
applicable for car cases that which may not have a complete
or clean separation by the boundary.
Then you can now formulate the problem as this, right?
You still subject to this constraint with Xi,
the so-called slack variable here, right?
With this for all the possible sample,
while you minimize this summation of this Xi,
sometimes they are zero because they are not really
across the boundary.
For those really move across the boundary,
then you have a small value here.
So rather you minimize this, which maximize the margin,
you also have another slack variable,
you want to minimize this, right?
Minimum tolerance.
And of course you can put the weightage Xi
to see which one you want to keep more weightage.
If you make Xi small,
then you'll try to focus on maximizing the margin.
If you make this so-called Xi large,
that means you'll focus on maximizing the W, the Xi,
the all the so-called slack variable, right?
Then your margin may be smaller, right?
Rather than maximizing, which is basically,
if you put a lot of weightage,
you don't want to have any error,
you may actually end up with this D2, right?
When the C, the weightage, you start to change,
you may move from D1 to D2.
Then you can kind of decide which one
you want to give more weightage.
And with this formulation,
you can still solve this problem, right?
And again, go and check how to solve this.
And then at the end, you'll find
what is the best value of W and B, right?
This is still your classifier
for get about all the past one minus one, the Xi.
Ultimately, what you care about is the W and B, right?
So when you have a new test sample X,
you just plug into WX plus B.
If this sign is positive,
then belong to the square class.
Otherwise, it's the circle class, okay?
So that is how you compute the support vector machine.
All of this is only for linear case.
They are also more complex,
like nonlinear support vector machine,
which I leave it to you for you to explore more
if you are interested in that.
Then the next question is,
this only work for two classes,
but in the world of many, many potential application,
there are more than two classes, right?
Like the C-far, 10, C-far, 100.
You could have 10 or even 100 classes, right?
So how could you so-called extend the SVM
to cope with all these multiple classes?
So of course, you can do that by first,
there are a few possible way to do it.
One is you can perform this one against the other, right?
Let's say you have K classes, right?
Now you can design K different support vector machine.
One is whether it belongs to class one or non-class one.
Class two or non-class two, et cetera, et cetera.
Then for every test sample,
you test against all these K support vector machine, right?
And then the one produce the highest value,
WX plus B for vector machine, one, two, three, four.
So if it's the largest value, positive value,
that means that it's very strong evidence,
very far away from this decision boundary.
So you can say that belong to class number one, for example.
Or, right?
Because the other is non-class number one, right?
You can find out all these to see
which one give you the highest possible positive value
that you belong to.
This is either class one or class two, and you'll class K.
And of course there are other options.
And this one you have more classifier,
but it built in some kind of so-called wisdom of crowd.
They kind of idea when we talk about the random forest, right?
So rather than K, now you have NC2, right?
Which is all the possible pair of classes,
class one versus two, class one versus three,
under class one versus K, class K, right?
Then two versus class one, or class three,
you're going to repeat again.
Two versus class four, right?
And you are going to have K times K minus one,
thereby two of such support vector machine, right?
Then you evaluate which one class I
has the highest number of vote.
Because after you go through all this,
at this one, it is, oh, this is a class one.
Oh, this is class three.
And this is class, maybe class three again, right?
And this is class K, right?
So at the end you'll find that among all the K times K
minus one divided by two, many of them say
it belong to class three, right?
The one who appeared the most number of choices
by the classifier, then you say, okay,
it is the class three, right?
So for this one, you have more classifier,
but likely that with the multiple one,
sometimes you can actually allow more error tolerance
because if you build all this by using this
so-called non-separable class, you can do that.
Here I have one website.
If in case you are interested, you can go to the website,
okay, to play with this support vector machine,
control copy, see whether I can still access from here.
So this is the tool that here you can try to enlarge this.
It's a support vector machine.
You can start to specify the classes, right?
This is a positive class here,
and then change to the other class.
Okay, then you run.
So this is a support vector machine, right?
It is not a linear.
It's a kind of a, you can look at the parameters,
T2, so T1, run again.
I can put this a number.
You got this one is not a clear, clean separation.
You can go and check the value,
the definition of all these parameters.
The one is using the mu SVM, one class SVM,
epsilon SVM, different kind of a linear,
zero is a linear class.
One is a polynomial.
I put the zero is a linear.
Let's try it again.
This is another class,
and then change to the other class here.
So this is a linear classifier,
the one we cover in the lecture.
But even to use the polynomial,
you can put one, they'll give you a boundary, right?
It's not linear, but slightly the curve,
but there are some error here, right?
So you can play around with this support vector machine,
and you can have more than two classes.
Let's see, clear?
Okay, this is the first class,
then I change to another class,
and then change to third class.
Okay, right.
So now you can separate into three area
based on the region is similar to the nearest neighbor, right?
You pick any test point,
then you test belong to these three classes,
which one they belong to,
then you shape the area belong to these three.
Right, okay?
Yeah, if I try to use another zero here,
run, so this is the linear classifier
for the support vector machine.
Okay, so before we go,
let's, I have achieved,
so you have a few,
how do you compute the support vector machine?
If you have to do the hang calculation,
which is something that,
of course, just now we show you the two,
you don't have to really calculate yourself,
you just have to know how to prepare the data,
fit into the formula,
then you can get your solution.
But if you were to want to do these,
okay, let's look into how do you really compute
using the Lagrange multiplier
to compute the w and the b, right?
So this is optional,
in case you don't like the mathematics,
you can skip, but since SVM is so important,
in fact SVM, you can think about the perceptron
on neural network,
it's kind of a,
a more kind of expanded SVM,
because each of the neurons is also a classifier,
binary classifier.
So in case you probably did not hear,
early this week,
there were two Nobel Prize awarded,
right?
Jeff Hinton, the guy who started the neural network,
he got the Nobel Prize in physics, right?
Computer science,
there is a Nobel Prize in computer science,
so they give him one,
together with another professor in Princeton,
they got this year Nobel Prize in physics,
then the next day there's a Nobel Prize in chemistry,
by the one the alpha fold, right?
So they're doing the so-called DNA,
they recognize,
I think I haven't seen such a case so fast,
and then turned out they reward the two to Nobel Prize,
right?
And my daughter tell me,
they have nothing to do with chemistry,
it's a computer science problem, right?
The other physics is, right?
It's a computer science, okay?
So anyway,
the constraint optimization problem
is the one we saw earlier, right?
The Lagrange multiplier basically,
you can group these two together,
remember we want to minimize this, right?
And then we want to make sure this equal to this
for all the training sample, right?
So, but you have two constraints,
to solve a constraint problem,
you cannot just do that,
you can combine the two together, right?
Then it become optimization problem
by introducing this lambda i,
which are called Lagrange multiplier.
Again, if you don't like the mathematics,
you can close your eyes, forget all this,
but it will help you to have a deeper understanding
about how you compute those WMP.
So lambda i's are Lagrange multiplier,
then your objective now is,
early on we want to minimize this number, right?
Minimizing this actually will be maximizing your margin, right?
You want this equal to the constraint equation,
larger than equal to i, one, right?
This one, you want this to be larger equal to one, right?
So that mean,
if you minimize this,
you want this all to be larger than one,
because it's negative here,
it will be minimized as well, right?
So you also satisfy all the equation
if you try to minimize this, okay?
So then your goal now is to find WB and the Lagrange
multiplier, which are the new parameters you introduce.
First you will minimizing this,
we call this Lagrangian,
the new so-called cost value function.
But to minimize any of those things,
you take the partial differentiation
with respect to the unknown W,
which if you do this,
you'll find that W will be equal to this formula,
W and this, lambda i, yi xi.
Remember, yi is the cost labor,
plus one minus one, so easy to compute.
Xi is the value of the attribute, the vector, right?
For 2D, just x1, x2,
but it could be a multi-dimensional vector.
Then if you have your lambda,
assuming you find your lambda,
then W can be compute by summing up all the training sample,
xi, yi, multiply with lambda, right?
It's such a very simple calculation.
Because you know your yi, you know your xi,
once you have computed all your lambda i,
you just multiply these together,
and sum them up,
that will be your value of W.
And then of course, you still have another variable B.
If you again, partial differentiate with W to B,
you'll find that lambda i, yi has to be equal to zero
of the summation.
This is another new constraint.
So this two set of equation will be the so-called,
the computation you need later on
to use them to compute your W,
then lambda i, right?
If you do that, you can practice W back to here.
You will get this so-called,
the dual optimization problem.
Now W disappear.
The new variable will be lambda i, lambda j, right?
And then this Khrush-Kuhn-Tucker condition.
Whereby, I'll call this one, you can go and check.
By solving this problem,
you need to make sure lambda i are all equal or larger than zero.
And then this one now, in order to minimize this,
this is actually lambda i times this will be equal to zero.
So this will be the two set of condition together
with this, this, those in the square box,
will be given yi and xi.
You have to find all the lambda i,
and then if you fill all this equation
into the box that I draw there,
that would allow you to solve this problem.
It becomes solvable, right?
And once you have that,
and this condition also tell you
that the multiplier must be equal to larger than zero.
And then it will be zero
unless the training sample satisfies the condition.
So if the training samples are exactly on this plus one line,
and yi will be non-zero, okay?
Otherwise, for those, if this is not equal to zero,
this one is not equal to zero,
and lambda i will be equal to zero.
So the sample that when this is satisfied,
they are called support vector.
If you go back to the earlier on,
when we decide the boundary here,
something that we can pay attention to,
when you decide this w,
on these two points here are so-called necessary
for you to decide what is the value of w.
The rest of them are not important.
I can add all new training sample here,
or training sample here.
They will not change my decision boundary.
They only depend on those positive and negative points
which are nearest to the boundary.
And such points are known as support vectors.
Therefore, this is called support vector machine.
And those points on the boundary,
they will have lambda i larger than zero.
Those points, they are not on these two boundary,
above this, they will not have any inference
on where the boundaries are.
So in some sense, support vector machine also robust
to noisy training sample,
as long as they are not really near
to the decision boundary.
You could have outlier.
If you think about other training sample
like the neural network,
if you have outlier,
if you still want to so-called fit the data well,
and then they have to change, train the parameter
to include that particular outlier.
But support vector machine will just ignore the outlier,
as long as they are not really along the decision boundary.
So the boundary will not be affected by those outliers.
So those training sample,
they are not along the d1, i1, d2.
They would have the nunch multiplier equal to zero.
That means they are not involved in making the decision.
Because all the here, w, right?
Actually, if lambda i equal to zero,
those point y and xi would not have any say about this w.
Those non-zero lambda i only apply to those point
on the so-called two, so-called boundary,
hyperplane, and they are called support vectors.
You can solve this problem,
the dual optimization problem,
by using this Karushkun Tucker condition,
one, two, three, and then you can solve it.
And once you solve this problem,
any of these are test sample z here,
and this is actually your w.
You just lambda i, y, xi sum them up.
This is actually the w that we compute.z plus b.
Then you can solve this problem.
So here's, let's look at a few example here.
Now, if I give you this eight training sample,
one belong to the class red one minus one,
and then this is a positive one plus one.
So x one, x two, x three, x four,
then x five, x six, x seven, x eight.
So this case, of course, if you just look at it,
you know that your decision boundary
likely to be somewhere here, right?
Somewhere in the middle, okay?
So if this is here, then,
which are likely the support vector, okay?
So this x one and x five and x six, right?
Will be the support vector.
If you choose them accordingly,
then lambda one, lambda five, lambda six
will not be equal to zero, right?
And then you know y one, y equal to minus one,
because it belong to the red class.
Y five, y six is a positive class one here.
So then you can compute your w.
W will be equal to the summation early on here.
W will be equal to this,
a summation of one to n lambda i, y, x, i.
Because they're only three point,
which lambda i not equal to zero.
So you only have lambda one, time vector one, one zero.
Lambda five, time three one vector,
and then lambda six by three minus one, okay?
And then your lambda has to fulfill this equation,
which is the minus one,
because for x one, the class is y one is minus one, right?
Minus lambda one plus lambda five, lambda six equal to zero.
So here's another set of equation, and this is w, right?
Then you can plug into this formula.
This one you need to,
these three will be either on the support vector machine, right?
So here, so x one had to satisfy w,
x one plus b equal to minus one,
because it's on this so-called w,
x plus b equal to minus one.
And then the other two is equal to plus one.
So then you can write down the formula here.
This is one, and then, sorry, here,
you can write down the formula.
W one is here, okay?
So w, you can put this value here,
plus b equal to minus one.
Then you can write down all the equation.
You are going to have this set of equation,
solving lambda one, lambda five, lambda six, right?
You have, and b, you are going to have four equations
to solve this four unknown.
So which is quite straightforward.
For example, you have study, needed algebra,
you can solve it, as long as they are not really
redundant, you can find lambda one, lambda five,
lambda six, and b equal to minus two.
Then your w will be equal to one zero, right?
I think there is one, let me see,
actually, should be this one, okay?
Somehow this one appear wrongly.
So plug in all the formula here,
you can find that x one is three, two.
There is a decision boundary, one divided by five.
This decision will tell you that x one is equal to one point
five, I will move this one to earlier, okay?
But how do you know which one are support vector?
Before, of course, in here you can eyeball the data,
you know that it will be there.
But in the reality, you could have many training samples.
You might not be able to tell, right?
Of course, you can try to group them,
try to group a positive and negative one.
If you actually choose wrong one, for example, in this case,
if you do not know, you select x one, x two are support vector.
Of course, in reality, you will not do that,
but you will select some from positive classes.
Your support vectors will come from two sides,
but just assume that you randomly choose w, x one, x two.
Then lambda one, lambda two will not equal to zero, right?
So there is a condition that once there are support vector,
lambda will not be equal to zero.
Then both y will be minus one.
So you plug into this formula and also this formula,
you find that minus lambda one, minus lambda two equal to zero,
lambda one must be equal to minus lambda two.
And then there's another condition, lambda i must larger
than equal to zero.
So therefore it's not possible because first,
they are not equal to zero, and then both of them need
to be larger than or equal to zero.
And then they cannot be one is the negative of the other.
So therefore, this is not really support vector pair.
So then you can choose other like x two and x five.
Now you select x two here and x five here.
Then you plug into the formula, you'll find that at the end,
there will be some confection.
Some point will not satisfy larger than equal to one.
So there are a set of rules tell you how to choose
a possible support vector.
Then you can compute the boundary accordingly.
So there is basically the solution to support vector machine.
Of course, the two I showed you earlier on,
they already program all this.
You can just use the tool to compute
for a linear support vector machine.
And beside linear, you could also use other form
by parametric,
polynomial support vector,
or even nonlinear support vector machine.
Okay, this give you a very brief introduction
to the support vector machine.
It's learn a decision boundary for binary classification
by maximizing the margin between two hyper plans.
If you allow some error, you can have a soft margin approach
which allow you to minimize the so-called
the possible variation while maximizing your margin
by having some weight, the C and the K.
And solution to this will be
Lagrangian dual optimization problem.
You can also extend this to multiple class cases
that we mentioned earlier.
So this is support vector machine is another classifier.
And bear in mind this was a classifier
that when it came out,
it actually performed quite comparatively
compared to this neural network
that one time even the young LeCoultre learned.
And because it has a very solid mathematic behind,
I can think about the logic, try to maximize the margin,
assuming your data they all behave.
So you want to make sure that you allow a large margin
that even you have some error, some noisy data,
they likely will still perform
while to classify those the data.
So that is the logic behind the support vector machine.
Okay, with that, we come to the last lecture
on the neural network.
Of course, neural network is the network
that which now been used by many, many applications.
The one we are going to introduce is very basic,
but then you can really expand it
to many, many other variation or more advanced network,
which have the same so-called principle behind,
including your transformer, just a training data
and try to perform all these so-called regression
optimization problem, right?
Using gradient descents to find the solution.
So we will spend some time to go into the fundamental
in the early part, the neural network,
the media classifier, like SVM that we thought about it,
and then the perceptrons, then some of the basic,
like the activation function,
back propagation, gradient descents, some of this updating,
and these are very, very fundamental, right?
And although they are fundamental,
a lot of them, they really do not have a very clear
cut theory behind why you do that, right?
And there are a lot of engineering, optimization,
so-called some experience, tricking the data,
learning in order to get this, what, where we are today, right?
Then later on we'll introduce a large number of the variation
of the so-called multi-layer perceptrons, right?
Including the more reason one, the auto encoder,
the generative adversarial network for gen AI,
and even the transformer, right?
We will not have time to go into detail how those work,
but once you understand the basics,
if you have the patience,
you should be able to learn the rest from internet, right?
And there are a lot of video,
try to explain to you all the different concepts, okay?
So, one, two, three, yeah?
Let's introduce a few more
then we can have a break about two.
So what are neural networks?
If you recall that earlier in the introduction,
talk about the Rosenblatt,
they tried to design a simple so-called logical gate, right?
Allow you to learn and then make decision, right?
So why they have the confidence
that that small unit of logical so-called decision can work?
They're always an assumption
because your brain somehow operate in the way.
So a lot of so-called even the new network,
they always see, oh, try to make analogy
with the human brain.
Oh, because the brain operate this,
so we would like to propose something like this
in the neural network.
Some of them it work, some of them they don't work, right?
So they keep exploring all these possible so-called network.
So basically the neural network,
the goal is try to mimic the functioning of your brain, right?
Biological so-called neural system
to solve classification problem.
So there was the original goal.
Then you look at the human brain.
Human brain actually have many of these
so-called neuron like this, right?
They are 10 to the power of 11 of them.
And they are connected through so-called exons
and dendrites.
These are the so-called dendrites, right?
This dendrite will receive stimuli input
from the other neurons, right?
And they combine all the input for the other neuron.
You can see there's another one here.
They connect to the dendrite.
Actually between the two connection point,
the dendrite actually send chemical so-called signal
or chemical so-called reaction.
So that is pass some information to the next one.
You all happen very, very fast.
And then if you correct a lot of signal,
then you will send the signal further down
through its own dendrite.
And these exons will be the one collect
all the signal more to the next one.
And you have 10 to the power of 11 of them.
Later on we will see this.
Such operation is nothing but a binary classification
that we thought about it in the SVM, right?
You have to collect a lot of signal here.
If there are enough signal,
then it will send the signal to the next one.
You're learning when you were born,
you have many, many these neurons.
And this connection, dendrite,
how the neuron connect to the other neurons
are all very flexible at the beginning.
So when you were born for the first few months,
you have many of these dendrites.
They are not very well connected.
But after you start to observe
and the dendrite trying to connect, right?
When there's a signal coming out,
there's some response and you start to learn, right?
So the way is actually decide
how you connect the output to the next neuron, right?
If you study, if you learn a lot,
some of these neurons could have an additional seal
which allow your signal to travel very fast.
I believe some of you have this experience
if you study very hard for your exam,
like practice, practice a lot, right?
Every question come you can solve immediately.
Because your brain have been trained to operate
such that when you see this signal, you respond, right?
Therefore, learning, practicing is important, right?
But for those, if they are new to you,
if you do not practice your dendrite,
they are not connected.
Then it become harder to transmit, right?
You don't know where to connect.
Your learning is a biological process.
Therefore, it cannot happen overnight.
You have to learn regularly
if you trust the theory of how your brain function.
Every time you learn, you try to connect, right?
And therefore, they say that if your early years
like secondary or your high school, you learn a lot,
now it become easier for you to learn
because your network have been connected, right?
So in undergraduate, when you are still young,
you should try to learn as many different things as possible
so that your wire, your brains are wired, right?
Sometimes you learn some knowledge
which might be very difficult, right?
But a few years later, when you come and look at it,
you find that, oh, it's easier for you to pick up
because your brain have been configured
to send all the signal in that way, right?
And there are also times that you may have forgotten someone
because the connection have not been activated.
But suddenly, because the other thing happened,
you bring you back those memories
because they are all there,
just that you need time to exercise that.
So this connection are the one that really help your brain
to train your brain, to learn, to optimize it.
So therefore, when they decide the neural network,
they try to formulate that.
They do know how the brain learn,
how the brain connect with each other,
but they know how each of the neurons might function
based on what we just explained, right?
So a perceptron, this is the one that based on the Rosenblatt
that you have this quick to adjust.
Now you can mimic one neuron like this,
assuming you have the input signal X1 to Xn.
This will be the dense drive from the other neuron.
They send the signal to, right?
To this neuron, then you have the weight W1 to Wn,
which decide how strongly you want to react to the stimuli.
Then you connect them together.
I'll explain this B later.
This is the bias,
basically how strong the signal you need before
you send the signal to the next set of a layer neuron.
So if you look closely,
you can write the formula, this signal input X,
we call the net input here,
is the Wj times Xj,
you sum them up plus your bias B, right?
So this is the summation here.
You collect all the input, multiply with the weight,
plus the bias, right?
They give you the signal input to this particular neuron.
But before you send it out,
this is something very interesting.
You know, even for your brain, right?
When the signal is too soft, too small,
it will not trigger the signal
to send to the other foreign neuron.
It will just stop there, just die there.
So it's not like any signal can both send through.
If it's not strong enough, you'll just stop.
So therefore there's this so-called activation function,
we call it sigma.
It actually take all your input.
If the activation function, this input, right?
So this will be sigma.
Sigma X is larger than,
if this signal is larger than zero,
then the sigma X is one, otherwise it's zero.
So change this to sigma here.
So why now become your input signal,
but go through some so-called activation function
and which is defined is if this X is larger than zero,
then your output is one.
Then trigger one signal, so the other one is zero.
So this X is all the input from your so-called,
the accumulation for all your input multiplied
to weight with the bias.
So this is basically the Rosenberg neuron.
You write in the formula.
Then of course, to simplify this,
because this B is a bit annoying, right?
You could consider B is nothing but another feature input,
X zero, where the value is always one, right?
And then this weight now become right in B zero, W zero,
this B equal to W zero, right?
W zero is now equal to B.
So then you can write this formula as such.
It becomes the dog product, WX.
So when you talk about SVM, we had the WX plus B, okay?
And that B is this bias, okay?
Now I could also absorb the B into my X and W, right?
Assuming for that particular X zero,
the input is always equal to one.
Then the W zero equal to B.
Then I could write this without the B, okay?
And this is, we call this W, the B is the bias.
It's the same bias as what we saw
in the support vector machine, WX plus B equal to zero, right?
So which is a decision boundary?
For a cube like this is a plan, right?
This is nothing but now you decide whether they are larger
or equal to zero.
If the larger to zero positive, less than zero negative.
So rather than one and minus one,
now I decide whether it's a positive or negative.
So a support, a perceptron is nothing but a support
vector machine.
It's just slightly different kind of formulation, right?
And that is what a perceptron is doing.
And X now become your attribute, your input.
B, we call this a bias, a bias, okay?
In this case, because if the B, the value is too small,
then you will not send the signal,
Y will not have any output, will be equal to zero, right?
If this dot product of WXJ plus B, you sum them up,
is very small, less than zero,
then Y will not have any output.
So a perceptron can act as a linear classifier,
try to differentiate the space into one,
and zero class, okay?
So with that, we can try to define a perceptron,
which allow you to do the basic logical operation,
which was the original so-called idea
when this PICS and Rosenblatt,
they come out with the neuron, right?
They want to first mimic the logical operation.
So in this case,
you can formulate W1X1, W1X1, W2X2 plus B.
Now you have this assuming that X10, X20, Y is equal to zero,
which is the n logical n operation.
If any of them is zero, output always zero,
if both of them are one, output is one, okay?
So in this so-called plot, X1, X, right?
This three point belong to zero class,
and this one, X1 equal to one, X2 equal to one
belong to this class.
So you want to find the decision boundary,
in this case, a line here,
such that you can separate the one from zero class.
So in this case, what you are looking for is W1, W2, and B.
So for this problem, you can use SVM to solve it, right?
You could try to try yourself to find
what is SVM for this, right?
And then, like this will be the support vector.
So this one, this one, this three will be the support vector
for you to find the boundary here, right?
To separate one from zero or one from minus one.
But if you use a perceptron,
now you plug into the formula, W1, W2, and B are unknown
you want to find.
When X1 equal to zero, X2 equal to zero,
and then this should be less than equal to zero, right?
Because this is the class zero, right?
Similarly, when X1 is zero, one, you have this formula,
one zero, you have this constraint,
one one, you have this constraint.
So then you have this few constraint here,
B less than equal to zero, W2 plus B less than equal to zero
or W2 less than equal to minus B, okay?
So you are going to have one, two, three, four condition
constraint, which you need to find W1, W2, and B
satisfy all these four constraints, right?
Then you can do this logical A.
Apparently you can find such thing.
One is X, W1 equal to one, W2 equal to one,
and B equal to minus 1.5, right?
So then you can satisfy all these four conditions.
So this is the line, okay?
And in fact, there are more than one line,
if you just satisfy this,
you can actually even use a minus 1.2,
you're still satisfied, just the line now become here, right?
It's no longer the support vector machine.
So you can adjust the B, just like support vector machine,
you move the line, but it may not be the maximum margin,
but it will still be the solution for this perceptron.
Therefore, in your training, you know, network,
you could end up with a different set of network.
They all satisfy the condition,
but it may not be always the so-called maximum margin.
So similarly, you can look at the logical all function,
which is 0, 0, 0, 0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 1, 1, 1.
Okay, plug into this formula.
Again, this is B, right?
Last and theta, this is B.
Less than equal to zero.
Then you can find another set of formula,
X, W1, W2 equal to one, B equal to minus 0.5.
Then the line here can separate from positive to negative.
And then this is the problem
that they cannot solve by using one perceptron.
Logical XOR, exclusive all.
You have very, output equal to one,
with any one of them equal to one, but not both, right?
If X1, X2, they are the same, 0, 0, 1, 1, output equal to zero.
This is called exclusive all.
They apply this formula,
you have to satisfy this four condition,
and these are the simplified version of the,
I mean, you simplify, you get this one.
You find that you will not be able to find a set of W1, W2,
and B such that you can separate,
you can satisfy this four condition.
It's quite easy to see here.
There's no way you can draw a line,
which can separate the positive from the X from the zero class.
Therefore, you don't have a solution for here, right?
So this is the problem that,
when the perceptron actually run into problem,
talk about this, okay,
it is not really something possible
by using a perceptron to do a simple operation
like exclusive all, right?
That created the so-called AI winter, right?
One of the reasons to argue.
But what actually could be done is,
rather than one new perceptron,
you can build three of them.
In this case, you have this X1, X2 input still like this,
but rather than you create Y directly,
you could have built two of them.
In fact, it's here, one, you create a boundary H1,
which separate these three from here,
the other H2 separate one from these three, right?
Then you have two, you can combine this together,
another neuron, then you can have this decision boundary
that allow you to classify X from zero.
So rather than one, now you have two.
You combine them together,
Y can actually solve the exclusive all.
So I will leave this to you as an exercise.
Go back to practice.
What would be the value you need
for this perceptron one, two, three,
such that it can separate this 4.2 classes.
And there are a lot of online solution you can find,
but before then I would like you to hand calculate.
And there are multiple solution, for example.
Rather than this, you can also find the two line here, right?
Which also can do the same thing.
Allow you to separate the 4.2 classes
by using three perceptron.
Use this set for formula, think about it,
how to get the perceptron.
Yes?
Denial regression model, it depends on output.
If your output is a so-called not a class, classes,
yeah, there is a denial equation.
You can actually, yeah, think for bring up this point.
So this one, of course, in here we talk about
the Y is zero and one, right?
But in fact, your Y could be a real number, right?
You estimate the height, then you have a lot of input.
Then you become a regression problem, okay?
You try to minimize the prediction
from your target value.
So it is, when we, we will recall that we talk about
the supervised learning, right?
You could have two class of supervised learning.
One is a classification, right?
One is a regression.
So they are for two different purpose.
You all depend on your output.
If your output are binary, so-called those are labor classes,
then it's a classification problem.
If your output is to predict, for example,
what is the score of your exam?
What is the temperature tomorrow?
So that may not be just a class,
you want to have a value.
Then it become a regression problem.
But the electron can be train for both, right?
It's just a training how you want to minimize the error.
Of course, there is just one.
Then you think about it,
you can now connect them together, right?
Here I input, just now we look at a tree, right?
And then this is one perceptron to one layer, okay?
Early on we have two to one, right?
Now you have another layer,
you can continue to have many layer.
Okay?
So then this is a neural network.
It's a multi-layer perceptron.
You have one, two hidden layer,
one input layer, one output layer.
Okay?
When you combine them together,
these two are called hidden layer
because you cannot access them directly
from the input or from the output.
Okay?
You have to go through this layer,
input layer, output layer before you can reach these two.
Right?
So this is a fit forward neural network
because the signal will only propagate to one direction.
It will not come back.
Fit forward.
Okay?
And sometimes we call this to topology is the N, M, M, C.
N meaning you have a N input, feature input,
followed with M perceptron, M perceptron up to M.
Then you have output one to C.
Last one you have C.
Okay?
So for the C far 10, then C will be equal to 10.
You have 10 classes.
Okay?
So of course, if you have 10 classes,
you can also think of a neural network.
The output could be one output,
but the value could be one, two, three, four, until 10.
But which turned out to be not as good
as you have a 10 output.
Each one is either one or zero.
Right?
The one with the value equal to one
or the largest value will be your classes.
So these are a lot of so-called expedient try and error
to compare.
They find that this will be the number of classes
will be better for you to train the network
easier for a train network.
Okay?
Just to summarize, before we go for break,
actually we can go to three more slides
for most like before the demo.
So multi-layer perceptron basically,
you have one input layer, one or more hidden layers
and one output layer.
They are connected by links with adjustable weights.
So you come back to here,
all these links would have weight W, W1, W2.
Right?
And some of them may not be connected.
It will be zero.
So each of them would have a bias.
Right?
Normally you don't put the bias,
you can assume they all have a bias B.
If you really want to show the bias, you can do this.
You can have this bias unit that you connect here.
Connect here.
Okay?
You can connect here.
Connect here.
So the bias unit, remember the X zero,
this one output always equal to one.
And then the weight here becomes your bias
to that particular unit.
Right?
So weight, let's say one to B.
And this is a weight, maybe two to B.
So all this, this will become,
the weight will become your bias.
Each perceptron unit take the input
from the previous output layers
and then the input and then go to output layer.
Add a bias, then apply the input to an activation function,
the sigma to create the output of the unit.
Okay?
And this nonlinear activation function
turned out to be a key.
This sigma, the function sigma X.
If you think carefully without nonlinear,
if this one I just take the X input,
everything can be collected into one neuron
because you just have W multiplied by X,
everything you can actually collect
into one neuron with many, many input.
So this sigma turned out to be very important.
It has to be in nonlinear.
Right?
And there are a few choices normally that we will use
and which allow you to mimic how your brain
to decide whether to send the signal further down or not.
Okay?
And if you have many, many of these circle unit
and you have used a proper nonlinear activation function
and you can basically,
it has been shown that you can approximate
any classification function.
You just have this huge enough.
Earlier we talked about the classification
could be very complex, right?
Like transformer recognize all your input question,
predict what will be the next one.
Right?
And there's a very complex so-called boundary,
not just like what we show you a binary
could be very complex.
But you can show that with a proper connection
you can practically mimic any kind of
so-called function, boundary function you want.
For example, here is one example.
You have this X, Y, 2D input and there's a bias.
The first layer, the first layer basically is,
every unit is a binary classification, right?
Because WX plus B.
So the first layer basically will separate a 2D into half,
two half.
But the next layer, the second layer basically
try to combine this into a region.
Just like when we do the exclusive OR,
you have two neurons, each one separate one half half.
Where combined then you can actually have a region.
Right?
So now you can start to classify more complex region.
And then if you go further, further up,
you can actually break the area into very,
very so-called precise boundary.
When you have more layer, more so-called perceptron per layer.
Which allow you to describe any kind of a very tricky
so-called distribution of your input data, training data.
As long as they are separable,
you can always find this very subtle boundary
to separate them.
We will show some demo later how to do that.
And then the activation function, the sigma X, right?
If you have this sigma X equal to X, which is a linear.
But this is very useless.
If you use this one basically the whole,
even you have million of parameters,
it's just a single neuron.
It doesn't really do more complicated than that.
So here is another sigmoid function.
This was popular at the early day.
Rather than a line,
you basically compress all the output to one to zero.
If the X is very large value,
this one becomes zero, then the output will be one,
approaching one.
If X is a negative value, this becomes infinity.
And then the output equal to zero.
So this is the sigmoid function.
You also have a tanged X function.
I think this one was used by Young LeCun.
He's the learning network in one of the version.
So you could have output from one to minus one.
And this is the one we saw earlier.
Either it's larger than zero,
you put plus one, minus one for the SVM, right?
Or you can have a shift is a bit plus one and zero.
The third one, this is called rectify linear unit,
rect rule.
This is the most common one now.
It's like this.
If X is larger than zero, you keep X.
If X is less than zero, you zero out.
So basically the operation maximum value of zero and X.
So this is a sigma X.
And this is the one now very commonly used
in many of the network.
Why?
Because it is easy to compute.
And later on when you look at the back propagation,
you need to find the differentiation of this,
which is always equal to one when X is larger than zero.
The differentiation of this, right?
The sigma prime X.
This is something that when you do the back propagation,
you are going to compute this sigma prime X.
And the value will be equal to one and zero.
So you simplify your calculation a lot.
So there were a lot of question,
oh, why you throw away all the signal,
which is less than zero?
Shouldn't that actually the information will be useful?
But when you do the training,
if the signal is very useful,
you just have a weight, which is a negative value.
All the negative will come positive.
You can have many, many neural.
And then there are people come up with this,
in order to keep the negative so-called value,
they come up with this leaky lag rule.
When X is less than zero,
they put a alpha X where alpha is smaller than one.
If alpha equal to one,
then will be the linear function, which is really useless.
So they put another so-called slope here,
alpha X with alpha, very, very small value.
And there's called leaky lag rule.
So there are some studies show you
that leaky lag rule may perform slightly better
for some of the test data set.
But in general, many people just focus on the red pool
because of the simplification of the calculation.
Okay, let's take a break here.
We'll come back to show you some demo and continue.
Come back by, let's say 15 minutes.
By 2.25.
We'll go to retry here.
Yes.
This one is exact number.
Now we go check back.
Okay.
and calculate the distance like this.
How should I apply?
A point where on the line.
Yes, yes.
But we don't do which class?
Positive or negative?
Nothing.
It's in the in between.
Then this in between way?
Then it will be 0 equal to 0.
Then?
But if this is like very important one,
why don't we take it as a z plane
and calculate the axis like this?
No, no.
Is it a training data or testing data?
This is my testing one.
Testing one.
Testing will just make decision.
If it is larger than 0, then it's, yeah,
you are not going to change your W and B.
You are already trained.
If it's a testing data, just put into WX plus B,
see whether it's positive or negative.
If it's exactly on the line, it will be 0.
Then you have to just flip a coin
to decide where's the positive or negative.
But then I want to convert some of the data
into training because I have to work between all the things.
Then I should construct this data.
So if this is your training data, then of course,
then your boundary will not be here.
If your boundary will be moved here,
if this is something you do not allow the slack variable,
then your new boundary will, if this is a training data,
then your boundary should not be here
or it will be closer to here.
Unless you allow the slack so-called non separable function.
But then to set up the boundary set,
so we take this linearly one by one,
so there are like multiple cases where we check that.
No, no, if you have, okay,
they only will give you one boundary
with all your training data.
It's not multiple one, right?
So what is your question?
Eve?
Sorry, let me put this down.
Before you make a move Я
Okay.
Let's continue.
So earlier on I was trying to tell you that the exercise, right, and some of them point
out that number one and number four sample, they have exactly the same input but the
outputs are different.
Okay.
So it was done purposely, so you had to build a tree by considering this because you could
have an outlier or noisy sample, right?
You could classify wrongly.
So you build your decision tree, how are you going to deal with such situation?
Okay.
So this is something that I want you to think about in your assignment.
Let's come back to neural network.
Okay in here, let me show you the, okay here.
Okay here.
Let's look at a very simple example.
If you go to this website, you can find there are input x1, x2, the two dimensional data
that we mentioned, then we use one perceptron, right?
And this is the output.
Okay.
I just want hidden layer, okay?
And this is output.
Okay.
Two input, one perceptron output.
I want to separate the positive from negative class, right?
The blue and the orange class.
This is almost the same as the exclusive of the one that we just showed you.
You cannot use a single neuron to do that, right?
But you can do the training.
I select here, this is the input.
I select the rectify linear unit as activation function.
I do not use regularization.
I'll talk about this in the later part of the, why is it regularization?
You don't want to overfit the data.
Okay.
So this is your training data.
Your goal is to find the boundary can separate blue from red.
Okay.
Let's train.
As you can expect, by using one neuron, you cannot do the job.
You can only separate them into two half.
And then the error will be high.
You see, test, training error and test error are almost the same, right?
Regardless of how long you train, you just cannot do the job.
You can change your activation function like sigmoid.
You will still be the same.
You still find you one line, which, right, it will still not be able.
Okay.
I can discredit side output one and zero.
So this is zero and one.
Okay.
So the way to do it, as I mentioned, you can have two neuron.
This one, the first one I have two.
And then I have this one output.
Let's see whether this one can train.
You see now, there are two neuron.
I can have two line.
I can separate the region.
Of course, you still cannot separate them well, but in terms of the training and testing,
now it dropped to 0.1.
Early on, it was 0.4.
Right?
At least what you can do with the two neuron.
Of course, you can think about you have four.
The septron, then you train again.
You take a while because it may not start at the right parameter.
Keep finding the solution and now it will come in.
You can see the parameter here, W1, W2.
These are the weights.
Right?
You can see this one, it does poorer than the earlier one.
You have two more neuron.
It doesn't mean you're improved.
Early on, you have two.
You can drop to 0.1.
Now you have two.
By right, four should be better than two.
Because it's a more complicated network.
The two is just a subset of four.
But based on your starting point, you may not learn that network that you want.
So therefore, some type of regularization coming would help.
Let's try to create two outputs.
That might help you to do the job.
Two outputs, I could have now one and zero.
So this is the boundary if I for the four.
So the beauty is I don't have to worry about what platform.
I just use the same network to train.
I don't have to worry about the mathematics.
So anyone can do.
You collect your data, what kind of boundary you want.
Now I only use X1, X2.
You can think of some kind of kernel trick.
You can talk about X1 squared, X2 squared, X1 times X2, sine X1, sine X2.
But normally, these are not so.
You just use the data as a draw data as input.
Liddy will help.
Let's look at other more complicated cases like this.
This is simple.
This is, okay, let's look at this one.
This one, see whether you can do a job.
Unlikely.
Yeah, this is the best you can do.
You see the error coming down.
It's all by learning, right?
Sometimes it may trap in the local so-called minimum.
But you see the error keep coming down.
It's a training loss.
And by using one hidden layer, two hidden layer, this is output.
And you can get it.
And this is of course the more challenging library.
You cannot separate the data.
It's very complex.
Error is 0.4.
Almost 0.5 is quite a bit.
So this is something that cannot.
You can try to increase the layer, increase this, see whether it helps.
So it's very hard to fit the training data, the classification.
See whether it helps.
So this is what happens when they design neural networks.
They keep trying an error.
How complex your network is.
You can think about including other data like this and this.
Even this, see whether it helps.
So drop to 0.1.
Looks better.
See this is all learning process.
You can try to fit the data.
This is probably overfit.
It's not very regular.
Ideally you want to just along the count line.
But this could be the one solution to tell you that this would be the classifier.
It may not be really reflecting the original so-called concept, the situation.
So you can play around with this.
And there are many so-called options after that you can use other kind of...
You look at the linear.
This one would not help.
Whatever linear, they give you just one line.
Earlier I said that you have more so-called perceptron.
But if you use the linear function, it's just a binary classification.
Even you have a million of perceptron, everything can collapse into one perceptron one line.
So it would not really help you.
So let's do...
See whether you converge faster.
You can see the computation wise.
That rule is...
Wow.
Not bad.
0.15.
Easier to calculate.
You can separate the function.
0.14.
There are still certain parts that it doesn't really do the job.
Maybe you have to increase the...
Maybe more hidden layer.
And more neuron, perhaps.
This is what they do when they train the network.
They just keep changing.
Those number of neurons over here are caused.
These are hyperparameters.
Something that you can select.
You can choose to see whether you'll give you better results.
It may not have any so-called real signs behind.
Just try an error.
Yeah.
And then these are the parameters.
You can see all the weights here.
Okay.
This is the perceptron.
Let's continue the lecture.
Now you can go back and play with it if you are interested to find out.
Then I can configure any topology.
But how do you find the weights?
Certainly not the one I showed you.
You plug in the formula, the sigma, then find out all the conditions.
Every data point, you have one formula.
So that is almost very challenging.
Even you want to solve it by some numerical method.
So luckily, you have this big propagation.
There is the one that actually hinted and they come up with this so-called paper in nature
to tell you how you can do this big propagation to learn all the weights and bias of the multi-layer perceptron.
So the idea is you have a training set of training data.
So for each training data, you have the target output, which could be just a class labor.
It could be also a regression problem, a value, a predictive value.
For example, a classification task or a regression task, depending on what problem that you are trying to solve.
Okay.
And then the algorithm will adjust the weights, the w and the b.
So if you start with some random number, as random as possible, then it will try to fit the data to the multi-layer perceptron one by one.
And every time the data come in, you have the output.
Compare the output with your target output.
If the output are not the same, target and the actual output, then you have an error.
And the error will help you to modify the weights and the bias.
And then you do it in a backward direction.
You fit the data in, create an error.
The error actually will be propagated back.
Because if the error is too large, look at, oh, this one actually contributes to the positive.
You should adjust down the weight one by one.
So if you do that, and for many, many training samples, if they all behave in the very so-called consistent way,
you could find the network with a set of parameters that work well in classifying the data or predicting the value you want.
Although such process may not guarantee you to converge to 100% accuracy,
but if you do it right, it will always improve the result.
Unless, like the homework I showed you, there are some inconsistencies, then there's never you can resolve this.
But for most cases, you can always improve.
So the trick it does is actually very simple.
Assuming you have this gigantic network, at the end, you have this error function,
which is basically the difference between the actual output and your target output.
Of course, this function can be very complex, depending on how you formulate the problem.
But assuming you have done that, you have this error function, which depends on the W.
And W is the parameter to weights and the bias that you want to, so-called, find out which one give you the minimum error.
Like the demo that we showed earlier, there was a weight then start to drop 0.4, 0.5, 0.1.
That is the error function you want to minimize.
So you start with some weight, then you compute the error function.
If the error function is not zero, then you can always define the weights by using this gradient descent.
The gradient descent, if you recall, assuming you have this error function, JW,
and this JW could be very complex, and W could be millions of parameters.
So there's no way you can visualize what is this error function like.
But for its illustration purpose, let's look at the 2D.
You have this error function here, and even 1D, we have weight.
So just in this any value here, assuming you start from here, then you compute, you start with random weights.
Then you put in your data, it will give you the error JW.
This is the error that you get for the train data at this point.
It certainly is not zero.
But if you can find that the error is actually in the differentiation, you change the JW, DW.
This is the weight.
If you know this curve, this is the so-called gradient of this J over W at this position.
Then you know that this is in the upward train, because the gradient is a gradient in positive.
That means when you change the W, it increases, and the error function increases.
So you should minus your original W with this negative of the gradient direction.
If this is positive, that means if you move in this direction, the error is going to increase.
So you should move in the negative direction of your gradient.
But how much you have to move, you don't know.
So you just multiply with the so-called eta, the learning weight, learning parameter.
Multiplier gradient, you subtract this from the original weight.
Let's say here, you subtract here, maybe the new weight.
You can start with here.
The weight is here, W0.
Then you subtract, you get W1 here.
Then you compute the error, JW1.
Then in here, you compute the gradient.
In this time, the gradient is actually in the negative direction.
Then you should increase your W towards here.
So you are going to find the W by moving down towards this valley.
So the more iteration you do, if you select your so-called learning parameter properly,
you can converge to a so-called local minimum or global minimum, depending on which one you are in.
So there is called gradient descent.
I believe some of you have learned this in your other engineering subject.
If you can formulate any cost function, J, you start with a random initial value W.
Then it may not be perfect, but your objective is to minimize the error function.
You can do a small perturbation.
You can increase W a bit, calculate the new weight, decrease a bit, calculate the new weight to see whether you are climbing or lowering.
If the weight is lowering or you continue to move in the right direction, the error keeps decreasing.
So that is the idea.
It's very simple.
Just try it.
Just that this W could be very high-dimension.
It's not 1D.
Then you could have a million.
Which one to change?
You could have a W vector, which is one million of them.
You can change one by one, change three of them, change four of them, change thousand of them.
That becomes challenging.
So this allows you to solve the problem.
And this eta is a learning parameter, learning rate.
We call it learning.
How fast you want to learn?
It's not always easy to choose.
For example, in this case, look at the other key.
So if you start with here, it keeps moving in this direction.
It may be very slow.
This error could be very slow.
So just now you saw some demo at the beginning, no change.
You keep iterating, but no change.
You could wait for months before it starts to move.
Or you could have this a very large value.
If you are here, you point here, it keeps increasing.
Your error keeps increasing rather than decreasing.
Although you move in the right direction, but because of the valley,
actually you move here, you assume it should be here, but it could go up.
At the end, you may expose.
So it depends on the learning parameter that you choose.
So if you have a good learning rate, the yellow line, after iteration,
you want this continue to decrease.
If you start with here, the blue line is very slow.
Until you lose your patience, you keep up.
Or you run out of your budget, you cannot compute anymore.
Or if you select the learning rate very hard, you may expose.
This is the case, the error keeps increasing.
So how to select the right learning parameters, it is not so straightforward.
And likely they will not actually choose one learning rate for all the training.
They start with some large number.
Then based on the momentum, based on how fast it moves,
you will start to reduce the learning rate until it converges.
And there are papers about the atom optimizer to tell you how to compute.
When you select one of the so-called learning approach, you can select this.
This depends on where you start.
Sometimes you can find solutions.
Sometimes it traps in the local minimum.
Earlier on, we showed that there were four and two.
The four supposed to be more complex than two, but turned out the four cannot solve the problem
because it was trapped in the local minimum.
So when you have more neuron, it doesn't mean you always keep you a better solution.
The function just becomes more complex.
Easy for you to trap in the local minimum.
Then you have fewer neuron, which you only have a very simple so-called error function curve.
You may find the global minimum easier.
Therefore, regularization, some of these tricks will come in to help you to find the global minimum.
There is a gradient descent.
And again, the whole idea of the network, assuming you construct this multi-layer perceptron
with all the w, the weights, and the bias.
And how do you find these w and weight bias?
Basically, you define the output.
What is your target output?
What is your actual output?
With all your trained data, you just keep doing this.
With a set of initial w, you'll find your error.
If it's not zero, you start to move the weights in a certain direction,
which is the opposite of your gradient descent.
It's called gradient descent algorithm.
Then, liter by liter, you keep improving or reducing your error until you get to the point that you like the solution.
That is basically the whole idea of the neural network training.
Of course, how do you really implement it?
There is a back propagation algorithm.
There is considered one of the very important discovery.
I didn't call it invention because it was before RuhmerHertt.
It was already done by other.
But how do you apply it in the neural network?
It was Clinton and RuhmerHertt.
They two of them work together.
Let's look at one of these so-called multi-layer perceptron as an example.
This is one of the things that we saw before.
We can call this a 3, 4, 2 topology, 3 input neuron, one hidden layer with four neurons,
and two output units in the output layer.
We will define the Tk and Ok.
In here, they are only c equal to 2.
They are only two output neurons.
The actual output and the target output and the actual output O.
That is basically the square error, sum of the square error.
Then how you adjust the weight?
You start with W.
This Wji is the weight between the neuron i and neuron j.
You can label it 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9.
Between, let's say, 3 and 7.
W73 from 3 to 7.
This is the bias to this neuron.
With this, how many are no parameter that you have?
It's just a simple 3, 4, 2 network.
How many parameter that you can have?
Any idea?
Anyone can calculate?
It could be an exam question.
Each one would have a bias.
Every connection had the weight.
How many? Anyone?
Anyone have a number?
How many parameters?
How would I need to find a solution?
I need to adjust to solve this simple multi-perceptron network.
First, how many weights here?
Between 3 and 4, you have 3 times 4 different weights.
Connection, right?
There are 3 times 4.
Each unit can connect to 4.
So, it's a 3 times 4 here.
Weight, 3 times 4.
And how many here?
4 and 2.
4 times 2.
So, 12 plus 8, 20, and plus the bias.
You have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
So, total 26 parameters here.
Assuming input, you don't put bias.
But all this hidden and then output layer, you have bias.
So, total, there are 26 parameters that you need to adjust.
Some of them, assuming your error is E, so you use a gradient descent.
Every time you adjust this, you take the differential error,
you take the Jw, right?
With respect to the W, JK, and this is a learning rate.
Similarly for the B, the error, and then with respect to the BJ.
Of course, your error had to express in terms of W, JK,
express in terms of the BJ.
We will show you how to do that.
Because once you have a function which is a parameter of the unknown,
then you can do the partial differentiation.
So, the goal are the target and the network output vectors.
So, how do you solve that?
The training, first you initiate all the weights and bias.
Of course, if everything you start with 0, there's nothing will happen.
Your input, you multiply 0 or 0.
Unless you use some kind of a so-called very strange activation function,
otherwise output will not change.
Only you will start this with a random so-called 0 mean Gaussian so-called number
for all the weights and the bias.
That means every, you think carefully, every neuron actually is now a different kind
of a binary so-called hyperplane in this high dimensional space, right?
We got the weights and the bias are different.
They are actually pointing to different kind of partition.
Then you have all the training samples, right?
The inputs, you compute the input.
Let's say you have an X1 sample here.
You compute for each neuron, compute what is the net input,
compute the old output, old Z, going through the activation function,
which is something that we show you in the single neuron.
Of course, once you compute all the output, the error may not be 0, most likely.
This error, Tk minus OK.
Tk is your target output, depending on whether it's 1 or 2, right?
Tk1, Tk2, Tk1, T2.
So T1 minus 01.
So it is at this output here, each of these neurons you can compute
the so-called error function delta k.
I will tell you what is this delta k later on, how it comes from.
But basically, when you compute this net k, right, for every neuron,
you can compute this net j, j can be every of these network.
Then in every of these neuron now, at the output layer first,
output unit, right, you first, after the sample input compute,
you get the old k.
For each unit, then you subtract from the Tk, the target output,
then you compute this value delta k, which is the differentiation
of the activation function with the net k as your input,
which is delta tk minus OK.
We call this term, it's the error term at the output unit,
each of them, you just learn this as the error function.
Basically, because your tk minus OK is not zero,
so every output unit would have a delta k, which is not zero.
You just consider that it's the error created
because the output, the target output and the actual output,
are not the same.
So you compute for all the output unit one by one,
compute the different, which is the activation function,
you take the derivative with the net k, multiply with this.
Then for the hidden unit, this is the error that you use
to compute all the delta j, j is the hidden layer.
As long as there are no input and the output unit,
they all belong to this hidden unit.
So you can use this formula.
So what is this?
Earlier on, I mentioned this is a delta, let's say it's a delta,
seven delta, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
delta eight and delta nine.
These are two outputs.
Delta eight and delta nine.
So now you want to compute this here, seven delta seven,
which is a hidden unit.
This delta j, the seven, is also the derivative
of the activation function.
Compute based on the net j input to this delta seven unit,
plus the error here, delta eight and delta nine,
multiply with the weight, w k j, you sum them up.
Because if this is not zero, right, and there will be error.
And these two errors actually come from here.
So you also have to adjust all the weight here.
So you have to compute the error now.
At least all the hidden unit delta z.
And this is how you compute.
Looking at the error in the next layer,
you do the back work weighted summation,
compute here, multiply with this activation function.
Why you multiply?
Because remember this unit, right?
You have the net input, then you do the activation function
before you put the output.
Now if you want to propagate error back work,
you have to do the backward direction.
Rather than you go out, you want to see the change of derivative,
the gradient descent, where it moves.
So when you move to the forward direction,
you have to do the gradient of the activation function.
For example, if you use this sigmoid,
this is the derivative of the activation function.
If you use the sigmoid, this is the activation of the sigmoid
function, then your sigma derivative net k
becomes OK1 minus OK.
Which you can verify, you compute,
because you have 1 plus e minus x,
which is equal to your output.
And the derivative of this becomes OK1 minus OK.
And then the year becomes OJ1 minus OJ.
This is the derivative of this.
And this is still the same as the rest.
This is only when your activation function is sigmoid.
If this is a red rule, then this term will be either 1 or 0.
It depends on what is the value of your net k.
If the net k is a positive value, then the red rule,
the derivative becomes 1.
If it's a negative value, then the derivative becomes 0.
Then for activation for the red rule,
this delta k delta j will be easier to compute,
because this term will be either 1 or 0.
That's how you compute the error.
Once you compute all this delta from delta 4, delta 5,
delta 6, delta 7, delta 8, delta 9,
then you can adjust the weight.
This is plus delta w kj.
Delta kj equal to, look at this, it's quite easy.
For any of these weight adjustment,
which will be the learning rate,
eta w multiplied with delta k,
the one at the following unit,
the error you just compute,
that's the output from the earlier unit, oj.
You have compute delta k,
then the adjustment will be the sigma,
sorry, the eta w delta k and output oj.
Similarly, for this weight will be delta z,
oi multiplied with eta.
This is the adjustment you make.
And then for the bias,
we mentioned that you have a unit with output 1,
weight equal to bz,
so because output equal to 1,
so the adjustment is the learning rate for the bias,
the sigma z, which is the error term,
and then one output.
And this will be the amount that you use
to adjust your respective weight and bias.
And that is the backward propagation formula.
And that's it.
It's not difficult.
Once you define your error function,
in this case, this error function is this, right?
And you just follow this set of formula.
You can, for every input you need,
you can compute the difference between tk and ok,
then you propagate the error back,
and then you adjust the weight and bias.
Then for the next sample, you compute again,
you propagate the error back, adjust the weight.
So one by one, you will move the weights to the right direction,
reduce the error, like the demo that we showed earlier.
OK, so you repeat the step for every sample
until one of the following conditions is mapped
for example, the error, the value of the error function,
jw is very small, below a certain preset value.
Or the delta w, delta b, becomes so small,
you don't really adjust any further.
But that one depends on a lot of big network training.
Sometimes they actually run the whole training
for two weeks, nothing happens.
Then you stop too early, you will drop.
You don't know what is the right learning rate.
It moves slowly towards the direction.
If you lose out of patience, you stop before it suddenly drops.
Like some of the demo we showed,
it's very, very slow, suddenly it drops up.
So that is the so-called sometimes the problem
that you have to deal with.
Or until you run out of your time,
a total number of updates has been reached.
Many, many so-called months you'll be waiting, nothing changed.
But the problem is you really didn't know which one is which.
Sometimes you may terminate too early,
sometimes you just wait for nothing will change.
You just keep computing, wasting your power.
Of course, the other way rather than one by one,
as we mentioned earlier, every sample you adjust the weight,
which could be very noisy because your sample,
every sample could be a noise sample.
It may push your weight to a wrong direction.
And also very slow because for every sample,
you have to do all the calculation
for all the millions of parameters make adjustments.
So one other way you can buy using the E-Port or A-Port,
how you pronounce this, A-Port updating,
which every time you do the so-called changes,
you compute the error, you compute a delta, w, delta b,
but you do not update the network.
You use the same old network to input many, many samples,
but you accumulate the delta,
accumulate all the delta, delta, delta b,
then you do the afters, you have seen all the data,
you update once and for all, then you do it again.
So rather than every sample you change the network,
you use the same network to compute all the delta, w, delta b,
then you accumulate all the changes, take the average,
then you update the network at the end.
This is called A-Port updating.
So you can see that in some of the programs,
I'll show you, you'll see that all one A-Port, two A-Port.
Basically, every A-Port, they look at all the input data
before the update, because you do not know the sequence
of the data, it really makes a difference.
If you actually update every time you've seen the data,
imagine that if you randomize your input order,
then the outcome may be different.
Or you can do the kind of stochastic gradient descent.
So the early two cases was one is every case you update,
every sample you update.
The other is the only update after you have seen all the samples.
They are at the very true extreme case.
So you can imagine that you can do that.
You can select a small number of samples,
input all the samples, accumulate all the changes,
then you change it.
Then you repeat the same process for another set of samples.
That is so stochastic.
Every time you just randomly select maybe 10% of your training samples,
then you do this A-Port updating of the 10% of the training sample.
You update, then you select another 10% of the sample.
So this is more common, stochastic gradient descent.
You select randomly, then you perform the update,
then you repeat the same process until all the samples
have been used for training.
So now let's look at it.
These are also optional slides.
Now look at it.
Why this set of formulas?
I didn't just tell you how to compute,
but I didn't tell you why delta k, delta z look like that.
Why this is?
And this is only true when your error is so-called
sum of square error.
If today you change your error to another type of error,
then all this formula doesn't work.
So you need to know exactly how to derive all these parameters.
So this is what this optional slide shows you.
Because how to compute?
Although we still use this example,
but at least this shows you how you can compute
the formula that we show you.
So early on in the Bayek prerogation,
I told you that if you have this kind of sum of square error,
this is the gradient descent.
So you can move into negative gradient direction.
And this is how you do the so-called forward and backward.
This is the network.
You have the net input for any, let's say, Bz.
You actually have WzI multiplied with the OI.
You sum them up.
Then go through this activation function.
You produce Oz.
Then you continue to this until you get the Tk.
And get the actual output.
And this is your target output.
So let's look at these two particular nodes.
One of them is at the output layer.
The other is at the Healen layer.
So I showed you earlier that to compute the error
at this output unit, you basically
do this sigma prime net k Tk minus OK.
So to compute the error of this is this formula.
This is what I showed you earlier.
But how do you get this formula?
This is the adjustment that we make.
So this has to summarize what we just
kept what we covered.
If your activation function is this,
then this sigma net k become OK 1 minus OK.
OK is the output of the unit.
And then for the Healen unit, this is the same.
Sigma derivative become Oj 1 minus Oj.
Now let's show you how to get this formula.
Sigma k equal to this.
Sorry, delta k equal to this formula.
So again, write down all what you know.
And this is for delta k net k, delta, sorry, net k net j,
OK Oj.
And then this is what you know.
Then to compute Wkj, you want to adjust this, right?
It's basically, as we say earlier,
you want to compute the derivative of error function
with respect to Wjk.
So this is what you need to compute.
Because this E right now is written as Tk minus OK.
So you cannot take the derivative with respect to Wkj,
that I mean.
So you have to express the E in terms of the parameter like OK.
Then OK is a function of net k, which is here.
OK is a function of net k, which is just the activation function.
And then the net k is the function of this Wkj.
And therefore, you can expand this derivative of E,
which is Wkj, by using the change rule, right?
Now you have the derivative E, first OK first.
E is here.
Then because E can be expressed as a function of OK,
you take the derivative of OK.
OK can be expressed as a function of net k.
You take this OK, we'll add to net k.
Then net k can be expressed as a function of Wkj.
Then you can express this, right?
So then each of these, you take the derivative.
This E and OK is easy, because this is the derivative
of this function with respect to OK.
It becomes minus 2 divided by 2 Tk minus OK.
So this term come from here, come from here, come from here.
OK?
Then this is nothing but the derivative of the activation function
with respect to the input net k.
And then this one, net k Wkj, there's only one term,
particular term, depends on Wkj.
And the derivative here, you only have the Oj, right?
Therefore, you can write these changes as a minus delta koj,
delta koj is actually here.
Sigma net k Tk minus OK.
So this is where you got the function.
OK?
Then the delta Wkj will be the eta W multiplied with delta koj.
Then you have a minus term, because it's a gradient descent.
So that's how you get these two terms, right?
So this one, now, it becomes here, right?
This one is Wk, you multiply here.
Then you know the Oj, you know the eta W,
then you can compute the changes.
OK?
So this is how you derive the gradient, the error term.
And this one delta koj, we just call it an error term,
it is a unique k.
So this is true for all the output unit.
But for the hidden unit, it's slightly more complex,
because you still do this delta EWji, but this is hidden unit.
Your delta E is here, which is far away from your Oj.
So again, you have to apply the same rule, EOj,
then Oj over net z, then net z over Wji.
So this is something like before, but now you change the k to z.
Then this is something that we are looking into here,
because E and Oj, they do not connect together directly.
But you know that E is a Tk minus Ok, so you can write this one.
So you can further apply the change rule here,
become sigma EOj, then delta Okoj.
So this is a new term, you do a change rule,
and this is what you know how to compute,
you have done that before.
Then this Okoj is here.
So you'll find that it's only Wkz, which depends on Okoz.
So you can write it here.
Then this net k is the same, then you have this term.
And this term now will become here.
So at the end, you go through this,
it's just application of a bunch of change rule,
always from the E, but connect back to the parameter you want to change.
So to express every of the intermediate term,
we expect to the parameter that you want to optimize.
So at the end, you get this for the hidden unit,
this will be your error term,
and this will be the adjustment of the W you want to make.
And then for the bias, because bias is the same,
you consider bias is a spatial unit of W,
just the output is equal to 1,
and then this will be the formula of the weight.
Okay, then let's look at one specific example
how you compute the back propagation.
Again, it may look very straightforward to apply the formula.
I strongly encourage you to do that.
Before even you look at the answer,
it's very tedious and often that you do not know which one to use.
I'll give you an example now.
I have a 3, 2, 1 network,
which I have just one training sample, input 101.
And then the output, class label 1,
I want the target output equal to 1.
The actual output may not be 1.
So I initialize the network with all these W,
W41, W51, W42, W52, 4353, 6465.
These are the initial value, and this is the bias.
I don't draw the bias here,
but sometimes you will see that people do that.
If you want to express a bias, you can have a bias unit B,
and then connect this to 4, connect this to 5,
connect this to 6.
So this weight, the output will be 1,
then this is bias 4 as a weight,
bias 5, then bias 6.
This is how you can expressly show that you have a bias unit.
The output of the B is always 1,
and the weight that you can consider it as a kind of spatial
input with all the weights now become your bias.
Assuming your eta, learning eta, W, and B are all equal to 0.9.
The same, the same 0.9.
Okay?
So your job is to do one iteration,
and you have to know how to adjust all the W and all the B
so that the target output will be improved towards...
So the actual output O will be closer to what you want,
the target output.
Okay?
So this is how you compute.
I just want to show you the step,
but you should go back to compute,
hand calculate yourself to convince yourself
you can do the operation.
First, you have to input 101.
You propagate the unit, right?
Put into all the unit here.
This input 101, the first three units basically just put the 1 here,
and 0 and 1.
Okay?
It doesn't do any...
The input unit doesn't do anything.
Just put forward the input x1, x2, x3 forward.
Then the unit 4 here will be 1 times W41
plus 0 times W42 plus 0 times W43 will be this one, right?
You'll get the net 4 equal to minus 0.7.
Then the output O4 will be...
You put the net 4 minus 0.7 to this sigmoid function.
You have to put the net 1, the other way, 1 plus e minus x.
Your minus x is now minus 0.7.
So you have this.
So this is actual output 0.332, which is O4, right?
For this unit.
Then you compute for O5 equal to 0.525,
compute for O6 equal to 0.474.
This is output.
Remember your target is 1.
The base train sample with the current weights and bias is 0.474.
So it is not perfect.
So you have to now adjust your weight and bias
so that the next iteration, the output O6 will be higher
than 0.474 closer to 1.
Okay?
After you compute this, now you have to compute all the error
at each unit.
Now you are doing back...
This one just do the forward network, forward propagation.
Now you do the back work error.
First compute error, the delta.
The first one is to compute is this, okay?
Delta 6.
Delta 6, which is output unit is this formula.
Tk is 1, target output.
Ok is 0.474.
So you have 1 minus 0.474.
Then this one, sigma, because it's a sigma function,
you have 1, T okay, 1 minus okay.
Your okay is 0.474.
So it's okay times 1 minus okay.
You get the sigma, sorry, delta 6 is 0.1311 for this.
Okay?
Then your delta phi, delta phi is the, again,
the derivative of this active function with the input net z.
Net z now is 0.525.
Okay?
You have this 0.525, 1 minus 0.525,
plus the summation of these two.
Because you only have one output, you have this sigma 6,
it goes to 0.1311 here.
Then multiply with w for phi, right?
Then you have w56, w56 is minus 0.2, so you get this.
So you have to compute the delta 6 first,
because you need it to compute delta 5.
Backward.
Then compute delta 4, you get this three term.
This is the error at unit 456.
Then you compute the so-called changes,
compute the wkj based on this formula.
You have all the delta, you have all the output.
You need oj, oi, delta k, delta j.
You know the learning rate is 0.9.
Then you compute all this, including the bias.
So this will be the new set of weights and bias
after just one sample input.
Okay?
11 parameters that you have to adjust based on one sample.
If you plug 101 input with the new set of weights and bias,
you should see that the output now is closer to 1.
Rather than originally, you have 0.474.
It should be higher than 0.474.
You can repeat this process again and again
until the 0.474 is very close to 1.
This is only for one sample unit.
You can always do the iteration.
Okay?
Go back and try yourself to convey yourself
that it is not really something mysterious.
It's just very tedious for you to do that.
Yeah, I think we'll stop here.
In this lecture, when we come back,
we will just tell you a couple of the network,
like convolutional network and auto encoder.
Going too much detail, I'll just tell you that they are similar like this.
Just that they have a different configuration,
different so-called parameters for you to train and optimize.
I will see you next week.
Thank you.