坐ar기經常訪問者 馬府學院  nég-il-i-lnar
不忍 concerns
辦公錯
不忍
Okay, shall we continue?
Okay, how are you?
I hope you have taken a break just now.
I may not have a break after this,
and we will continue until 3.20 or 3.10 after I finish.
You can feel free yourself to walk out to take a break if you need to do so.
So I am Tang Yaping.
I am going to continue the lecture for the second half.
But today I will cover the introduction,
very basic introduction to machinery.
Next week I will be here, so Professor Wen Gi-Han will come in to tell you about the projects that you are going to do for this lecture.
And I will come back in week 7 again to resume my lectures.
So again, by far I hope that you should know this is a very basic introductory course.
But it doesn't mean it's going to be easy.
For those of you who have learned some subjects before, you will find that you are quite confident.
But even though that is the case, because this field is moving so fast,
if you do not keep yourself updated with the progress of some of these topics, you will get outdated very soon.
So with that comment, we are not going to cover a lot of very advanced topics.
I may mention some of those examples, but I will mainly focus on a very fundamental concept,
which I think is very important for you to know them so that you can learn the new advanced by yourself.
And do pay attention to this because the content is quite a lot.
We assume that you are going to learn more things yourself.
We will cover the basics, but to really understand some of these topics, you do need to sell them because it's a great course.
And that's how you can find it by email will be easier.
If you have anything you can contact me, you can email or even team me.
So the learning objective, just to remind you, is to introduce the fundamental theories and concepts of AI and data mining.
Of course, AI is very broad. There is no way that we cover everything about AI.
But AI today is very much driven by machine learning.
AI has been around for many years, but it has up and down, up and down until more recent 10-plus years.
Suddenly, there is a so-called new approach to AI, which is called machine learning, which is what we are going to cover.
So of course, Professor Chen Yi Hui has covered this state space representation, search, and even association rule mining.
So I'm going to focus on supervised learning, some classifiers, including K, K nearest neighborhood, the simplest one you can think of, SVM, and neural network.
And some of the applications. This is what I will cover.
Of course, the outcome, you should be able to understand the basics of machine learning models and algorithms, and then how to apply them to many popular applications.
I will also give you some toy programs that you can play with, so that you get a sense of how those algorithms work.
Today, you are so lucky that you can find a lot of information online, a lot of free resources.
Although I listed some books, these are the topics I'm going to cover.
They are quite basic, but they are still very useful because when you try to solve some problems, you find that some of the fundamental methods are still quite useful.
So here are the textbook and some reference books, which we think could be useful, but not only this.
Again, I will not be surprised today if you don't need to even need to have any textbook.
That's just so much online information on my YouTube website.
I can go to some of those big companies like OpenMine, OpenAI, StickMine, Google, Microsoft.
They all have all these content you can learn.
But if you only need to buy one, I will suggest the textbook that we will use is this one.
Tantang Ming, Interduction to Data Mining.
I think this is the book covered.
If you happen to like to read the books in very so-called detail, I think this is a rather surprising thing.
It's not a new book, but surprisingly it is quite comprehensive.
It covers many, many topics including machine learning, neural network, support vector machine, decision tree, many, many others.
In one book, some of them are available online.
You can go and check.
But they are not necessarily easy to read.
For example, this one, the Murphy and even the...
I think Christopher Bischoff had another new book on machine learning.
You can go and take a look.
But depending on how much you want to devolve yourself to this.
Of course, the content again, of course, we didn't create all these fields.
Some of these are from other reference sources in our mind, material.
So do respect the copyright of the respective so-called content owner and use it properly.
So we are going to meet every Thursday, 12.30 to 3.20.
And there is another equivalent class from tomorrow morning.
I think it's 9.30 to 12.30 in LT 22.
In case you prefer the other one, you can also come.
Assessment, there will be two homework assignments, which will be one or two work problems you have to solve.
Make sure that you can go through those so-called exercises yourself, which are very similar to your final exam.
So better do it yourself.
I remember there will be a quiz, so I think Saturday is it.
Prof. Chen from Udo come because we have quite a lot of students.
So make sure you stick to the schedule.
And there will be a project from next week onwards.
This is Prof. Long Bi Han, who tell you, I believe he has sent you an email about the project.
And all these are actually not really very difficult.
You just want to make sure that you keep up your learning, put in effort in your study.
So once you submit, you will score some marks.
And if you want to pass a course, you better try to get as many marks as possible from the first three.
Because the final exam is open, it's a sorry, it's for all kind of restricted open book.
Open book, I mean you can bring a piece of A4 paper.
Has Prof. Chen told you about this?
So you should start preparing what you want to put on the A4 paper now, right, until the exam.
So if you refer to past exam paper, you'll find that there are normally quite a number of questions in the final exam.
So if you are not really familiar with solving those problems through practicing in the assignment, quiz and even project yourself.
And I will probably also show some example during the lecture.
You'll find that it will not be easy for you to finish all the questions within the two hours, is it?
So do practice because you'll be a lot of questions.
You need to be very familiar with the content.
So there is assessment part.
Just to recap what you need to be aware of.
And understand this video lecture will also be recorded in case you need to refer to the lecture you can also do so.
I will focus a lot on machine learning.
And of course, this is not the advanced course, it's the introductory course.
So in case you have learned some of this, just try to look at it from some of the perspectives I'm going to cover.
Okay, so what is machine learning?
Okay, so I will cover this topic, an introduction of this topic today.
Then see how we go.
And if you have any questions, certainly you are free to ask any questions.
So here are some of the key topics I'm going to cover, very brief.
And I have some of the key terms.
This key term is to help you to make sure that you learn the important point of concept.
Like what is machine learning, what is deep learning?
Classification, regression, you should know the difference between this.
And unsupervised learning, supervised learning, and some of these.
So we will go to such a topic.
So what is machine learning?
You probably have heard a lot about machine learning or deep learning.
So machine learning, of course, if you are a full-time talker,
basically is to try to ask a computer to learn so that you do not need to program it explicitly.
For example, when I was, we're just students like you,
I was involved in a project with a big company in the USA.
So the project wanted to develop a phase recognition so-called program,
allowing users to use it to get entry to a company, for example.
So at that time, there was no machine learning algorithm.
So what we did was trying to write the program, which was the old way to solve the problem.
We had to write, for example, what is a phase?
Then do the image processing.
You're supposed to find some symmetry.
There are eyes, intensity, you go down, up.
Then you make sure that the distance between eyes, the ratio of the mouth and the eyes and nose,
you write all this in the so-called programming.
But it works for a small data set, like 10, 20, more, you're so happy.
But then when you go to the company, you find out after 100 employees, it starts to fail.
It doesn't work as well.
And worst is you cannot expect that people will come with many kind of so-called makeup or glasses or head.
Even in front of the camera, we have to write the program to ask the person to step in front of it.
Make sure your face is inside the circle, remove your glasses, comb your hair.
So many, this thing, we had to write all the program ourselves, but still cannot work.
And that had been the old approach, computer vision approach to such a problem.
We have struggled this with 50 years.
So there was not a project and people had put in a lot effort.
Even I remember there was another dissertation to solve similar problems.
The PhD dissertation asked to remove glasses.
If you are wearing glasses, so they'll process your face, remove the glasses so that you can do a so-called proper recognition.
Your remove glasses, not easy.
So again, think about the time that for those unfamiliar with machinery,
think about the time that without machinery, not for reason.
So you have to find a way to make up a so-called dissertation.
Those are areas which are blocked by glasses.
And all these problems, anytime you have a new problem, then you have to develop a new set of algorithms.
I still remember at that time, another company was very interested in human sport.
So Olympic, there was 1986, there was Olympic in USA.
So they tried to analyze a video so that you can identify this sport is a skiing.
So how do you describe a skiing process?
They find out the motion, had to have a zig-zag like this, and you come down there.
If you move the camera sideways, then everything is different.
It cannot detect. It's very difficult because there was an old approach.
Computer cannot learn.
You have your input data, you want the output for the detect who is this person.
They are to write a program, and the task is the program.
You think about writing the program line by line yourself to do this kind of a human approach thinking,
to do all these so-called analysis.
So it was challenging. It just cannot really scale up.
It cannot be generalized to any other scene or configuration or camera perspective that you did not think about.
But machine learning is different.
Machine learning assuming that you have the inputs data, a lot of data, the faces you collect.
You know the output, who is this person.
And then you go through the so-called training, training process.
We'll talk about how to train.
Then the output is the program, the so-called network, the models.
They can detect who is this person.
So you do not need to learn what is the structure of your face.
You have to learn how to detect eyes, how to detect nose, how to detect eyebrows.
You do not need to know. You just collect all of the data.
Anyone can train them using a known so-called model.
Then your model will be able to classify.
But even then we are not happy with that approach because even if you can train,
you can only perform one part, recognize faces.
Today I want to use the algorithm to recognize the motion of the sport.
It cannot work.
Then you have to find another training algorithm to do that.
So machine learning today, it can do well for one specific task.
But when you try to use the model, you build another problem,
it will not work.
Or at least it will not work as well.
So that is the machine learning approach.
So you understand the different entities too?
You have to appreciate right now you can write program to do a lot of very advanced processing.
You may not even know how it works, how the model, RESTnet, all these so-called yoros, how they work.
You just have to follow certain data collection, go through some training.
You can create the result that you want.
That in the past was something like that.
You had to really be the one building the program, identify step by step how to recognize a person.
Which is challenging.
So you have a beauty machine learning basically.
You can have a model, then you can use a very straightforward approach to train the models
and which can do for some even car, you can try the car, the robot taxi.
And use computational method, not explicit programming.
To learn from data, you need to have both input and output.
About the process of mapping or the problem that you need to perform to make a good decision or prediction.
That is machine learning.
You do not need to write a program.
You just need to collect a lot of data or your experience based on, let's say, if you want to perform certain tasks,
your experience will help.
And then at the end, you can perform all the different tasks easily.
So there is a main difference between traditional programming, which is time consuming,
need a lot of domain expertise, need a lot of time, need a lot of detailed programming.
Then today, machine learning, I think many of you should have tried it before.
While you may not even understand how it works, you can still train the data, you can still perform the tasks to some extent.
So that is the power of machine learning.
And deep learning, so what is the difference between machine learning and deep learning?
Deep learning, you can consider that deep learning is a subfield of machine learning.
Basically, it requires a bigger network, a bigger model, or a lot more data.
For example, machine learning, in case you know about this, like K-Nearest Neighbor classification is a machine learning algorithm.
Sort of.
Or decision tree is another machine learning algorithm.
But the tree, because the structure is quite simple to some extent.
So when you try to apply it to a lot of data, like recognize all the human in the world, it won't work.
But that you need deep learning.
Deep learning is you have a bigger model, you have a lot more data, and the performance always continues to improve when you have more and more data.
I think there is a data somewhere.
If you read the slide, there is a data, a amount of data.
And the traditional machine learning will, even if you have more data, you cannot improve any further.
So that's the difference.
Of course, it's not really important.
Sometimes deep learning is people because they have done one, they publish a lot of paper on machine learning, you know, to show that their result, their model is much better.
They call it deep learning.
It's just a different term.
But it's still a machine learning algorithm.
So in case you wonder.
So machine learning or deep learning has achieved very good results in many applications.
And if you further understand it is the approach is very versatile, meaning that if you can model the problem into some kind of classification or machine learning problem,
you can solve many, many problems including speech recognition, language translation, your church epiti.
In fact, it's also some kind of advanced machine learning algorithm.
It is more general that you can understand a lot of tax information.
Even for autonomous vehicle, you look at the picture, then you now make classification.
So you continue forward, so you turn right, so you turn left, so you slow down, so you.
So output, there will be a few of the classification tasks.
So once you can model the problem as a machine learning, then you can train that the problem will be how do you more formulate the problem into a machine learning problem.
How do you collect the data, enough data, and do the training.
Do you have enough computation resource to do so?
So that will be the remaining problem that everyone can do, hire a lot of engineers.
If you are lucky or unlucky, you might be hired by one of the big companies.
It could be Google, Alipapa, Tencent, Huawei, to do some of this.
Many of your seniors now work in those companies.
So doing a lot of the training data.
Okay, among the machine learning, you can subdivide those problems into different tasks.
You should be able to roughly understand, is this task a supervised learning?
Of course, there are many, many other subcategories, but generally a supervised learning is you have a set of input and you know what are the output of those input.
Okay, then you learn the function, the mapping or the decision from input to output with as few errors as possible.
So here is one example.
But if I give you all these dots, they belong to two classes.
Okay, now I would like you to find a decision boundary classification, which can tell a new sample.
Maybe I have a new sample here, come here.
Okay, let me see.
Ten.
Okay, I have a new sample here.
So I ask, does it belong to the plus class or the circle class?
You need to find the boundary so that you can make decision.
Then you go to the machine learning approach.
You have this input data set, you know that this is a circle class, this is the plus class.
Then how do you, you then you select a model.
The model could be a decision tree, could be a support vector machine, could be a neural network, could be a K-NAS neighbor classifier.
Then you train the machine with the data, which you have the input, you have the target output.
So once you train, and of course when you do the training, you will know that whether the decision can do well on your training data.
And then when you put in the new data, you hope that the decision can also do well for the new data.
That is called you have a good generalization ability.
Okay, and that's one type of supervised learning problem classification.
So another type is called regression.
So the classification, the output is a finite number of classes.
Like, in the example I say the autonomous vehicle driving, are you going to go forward, slow down, turn left, turn right.
And even turn right, how many degrees, how, what, what is the speed you're going to turn.
All these are different so-called decision classes you can make.
So the other problem is called regression.
So regression is, I give you, of course this is a very simplified two-dimensional, one X and one Y is output.
Given the X, you know Y is a Y.
So now if I want to find a simple way to describe the set of data, this could be the line.
So once I have a new X input, I know Y is a Y.
Or even X could be outside here, I know Y is a Y.
This is called regression.
You are going to find a simple model in this case which can describe a lot of input and output relation.
So this is called regression.
Okay, you need to understand what is the classification problem, what is the regression problem.
So for classification, the output could be only a finite number of classes.
And the number could be huge, like your church ABT could be all the tokens available, a few thousand different type of token output.
And for regression, you do not have a fixed number of output.
You have a real number and a lot of output.
But you have a formula or you have a so-called way to describe when you are given an input, what is the output value of your regression.
Okay, here is another example.
Let's say you want to...
You know that, let's say you are finding a place to rent in Singapore, right?
You look at us, a couple of our friends, where do you stay?
How much do you pay per month?
And you say HDB, a condo or share with others, so you collect a bunch of data.
Then you kind of find how much they pay per month, right?
Then you know roughly what is the rent over the place that you stay, right?
Then now you look for a new place, right?
Someone ever ties a new location, look at it.
Then can you tell how much you should bargain to a group pay, right?
Maybe $1,000, $900, right?
Then you can use the curve.
It tells you that that place has not been rented out, so you do not know how much you need to pay for it.
But you can fit into this curve.
I find out, okay, how much should be a fame value of the rent.
So that is a regression problem.
Of course, the input in here, I will use the side of the houses.
But you can imagine that the input could depend on many, many factors, right?
How far away, right?
Which level of the unit, right?
Is it a condo, HDB or a hostel?
And who are the people staying in the house?
How many people stay in the house?
So a lot of this could be your input value.
Then you try to predict the output, how much rent that you need to pay.
So that is a regression problem, right?
So you may be able to convert that into a classification problem if you want to.
For example, when you call it data, you can say that, okay, all these rents, right?
And I keep very specific value.
I say it is from $600 to $650, right?
There is one cost.
$650, $1 to $700 is another cost.
Then you would have a few number of classes.
Then your data will be an input and output, then you become a classification problem.
But for that problem, there are some limitations.
And because the classes output, they do not really have any relation underneath, right?
You only have a class ABCD, but it doesn't guarantee that your class C will be always more expensive than class B.
So these are the problems that you decide.
Is it better to formulate as a regression problem or classification problem?
So this is the job that when you go to work outside, they will tell you that it's a problem,
but they do not know whether it's a classification, which is a regression problem.
You have to think about it.
How should you formulate the problem?
And then these are some of the popular supervised learning approach.
So this is, again, supervised machine learning.
You can have K nearest neighbor, decision tree, support vector machine,
Newner network, linear regression.
This is a linear regression.
So these are some of the topics that we are going to cover in the lecture.
Of course, sometimes you see this chart.
This is, again, a very common way to express this.
You have an input, then you try to build your train, your model.
You get an output, but the output may not be exactly the same as your target output, data with labor.
You know why it's a target output.
Then the difference between them will become the error, right?
And the error will be used to feedback to the network.
Then you know where you can adjust the network.
To go through the process with all of the practice training process.
So we'll go through one of these examples.
Some of these examples, like the one that you get, the learning model, which is the,
give you the least amount of error.
Another type of problem is called unsupervised learning problem,
because you are given a set of inputs like this, right?
Whose target outputs are unknown.
I didn't tell you what they are.
I just give you a number of these dots.
So you can also store all the points, but then it may need a lot of storage.
Even then you cannot really gain any inside of this box, right?
So you want to find meaningful patterns from the data.
For example, if I look at this class, and of course I come from another planet.
So I look at all of you, I classify you into groups.
I can imagine that, okay, maybe they are boys, they are girls, they are long hair, they are short hair,
they are wearing different kind of outfit.
So then I can have certain so-called summary.
So in this case, you want to apply one of these so-called unsupervised learning,
like clustering, like association analysis, I believe Professor Chen covered this,
the data mining approach, and some kind of dimensionality reduction.
For example, here is one example.
You have a 2D data, you can simplify data into two, whether it is larger or smaller than a particular value.
This is another way to simplify your data so you can make sense of it.
For example, if you do the k-means clustering, you can find that all this data belongs to three groups of data.
Then for any new data, then you can decide whether they belong to green, red, or blue cluster.
So that's enough for you to simplify your storage, and then you can,
and then for this case, you have only to store the center of this tree cluster.
Then any new sample come here to find a way to measure the difference
between the new data and the respective center representation,
then you can tell whether this belongs to which class.
So that is called unsupervised learning problem.
Can anyone give me some example of unsupervised learning problem that you come across?
Anyone?
Think of. It could be an exam question, you know.
I say give listed three unsupervised learning problem that you come across in real life.
Anyone?
Second and...
Sorry?
About the problem you came up with, and second and...
Segment?
Yes.
Anything?
Segment anything, but you know the things, right?
Is it a classification problem or unsupervised problem or supervised problem?
You can divide the class, and divide many things, like the door of the car and...
You see, segmentation in those segment anything algorithm, right?
In fact, they will try to judge this belongs to which group.
Of course, they have a training.
They already learned this is a car door.
So it's kind of a supervised learning approach, right?
So what are the unsupervised learning approach that you can think of?
Recommendation, like what?
Give me something more specific.
That is supervised, because you know what is good or not good, right?
Recommended or not recommended.
So it is a supervised learning approach.
Because you have a group of training leaders, you already know what you like, what you do like.
Generating fake news.
Generating fake news, right?
Fake news, right?
Fake news.
It depends on how you generate the fake news.
The moment you tell me it's a fake news, that means you know they are true and fake.
So that is somehow kind of your known classes.
So it's a kind of supervised learning or detection problem.
In Google News, we get similar articles today.
Similar articles, okay?
Okay.
It actually depends on how you formulate the problem.
For example, following what you just suggested, right?
The news, right?
Let's say music, right?
You hear a song, okay?
And by different instruments, but you do not know how many instruments you have, right?
I just give you a couple of those.
Music play with different instruments.
But you do not know all the instruments.
I don't have any, so I can tell you that the song 100 of them you just heard,
and roughly how many instruments play for each song.
They will somehow find some kind of grouping.
Those songs with similar voice that they belong to one.
Similar to your fake news or news article.
So of course, if you do not really need to...
Yeah, but if you know how you solve the problem, right?
If you detect the keywords of the news, then you try to group them, right?
I think you could formulate as a class in problem.
Assuming that you do not know how many different types of news on the newspaper, right?
I just give you maybe a thousand of news articles, right?
So I say, okay, can you roughly tell me how many classes of news?
How many... are these the news for those certain patterns, right?
So you can, for example, try to do some kind of keyword extraction, right?
And then, of course, when you have keyword, then...
Yeah, if they are the same or they are similar, you can cluster them.
Then you say try to cluster news.
So you can always formulate the problem into some kind of clustering problem
because you do not know how many clusters you have to start with.
There is one of the very challenging problems of unsupervised learning
because just now, the thing that I didn't say is
I didn't tell you whether there are three classes of four or five or one or two, right?
Before classification, you could think of every data belong to one class,
but the real one could be three, right?
There is one of the unsolved problem in such a clustering unsupervised learning
because you do not know how many groups of data you are going to have, right?
So then you can apply some kind of clustering
and there are also methods that help you to decide the good number of K in the cluster, right?
And one way is you start with a large number, then you start to reduce the number
to see how those clusters change until you find a spot that suddenly doesn't change or change a lot.
Then there could be some idea number of cluster technology problem.
You have to behave in charge.
Are you going to formulate this as a machine learning unsupervised or supervised problem?
Good.
And this is the reinforcement learning and this is of course another type of problem
and this problem is more complex.
Basically, for those problems that you cannot answer, we want one answer quickly, one simple answer, okay?
For example, you want to play this game, right?
I believe some of you have played this game before
and this game depends on or even a chess goal, right?
So you have many possible options that you need to take, right?
You cannot really find an optimal solution out of so many, many options.
There could be billions of other choices because the next step could be on this step, right?
How you do it?
Then you can formulate this as a reinforcement learning.
For example, you want to play this game.
You assume that you have one agent.
This is a Mario butter, it's an agent.
So every time you make an action, you move forward, right?
You see the outcome, right?
And you basically when you move forward, it changes the whole environment.
Now you are at the second step of the whole environment.
And see whether any happened.
If you somehow get a reward, you score a point, then it is good.
You make the right choice, right?
If you somehow die, right?
You change the state.
It's not good.
Then you should rethink of just how you should have made the move.
You go through this again and again.
What you now develop is the policy, the decision you are going to make.
When you see this, when you are in this state, when you know what is the environment,
what should be the next step you should take, right?
Just like you play a chess, when you move, when you see the opponent,
what is the organization or the pieces.
And then where your color pieces, they decide which path to move, right?
Then based on the reward, whether you gain or lost,
then you adjust your policy accordingly.
So this is called reinforcement learning.
Even the state of an environment, okay, this is one environment.
This is one environment, right?
This is a chess alpha, go chess playing.
And the task, then how you are going to gain or penalize,
learn how to behave, how to act, to maximize the rewards.
Your goal is try to gain as many points as possible.
So you need to have this good decision.
This human support knowledge, right?
If you learn how to play a chess, right?
Or go.
At first, you are not very good at it because you haven't learned, right?
You are often defeated.
But after you play again and again, you know what are the moves that you need to take
after you see how these pieces are organized.
So that is reinforcement learning.
And this is still a very challenging problem because the training is very challenging
and often that you do not really have a good solution.
So here is one example, right?
And of course, these pieces are method, different kind of learning to compute the many optimizer rewards.
And this simple learning is you have this pole, inverted pole.
You want to keep it upward.
And then your goal is to move this cart left and right.
The pole will not be perfectly straight.
And if it is a bit, then the center of gravity will pull it down.
Then your cart has to move.
So you keep adjusting this.
And then you can learn.
So here is another example of this.
So this is another example of using reinforcement learning by this big mind to play a game
which of course is a very old game and many of you may not even play this game anymore.
So it's all go by training.
Look at the images and then to see whether it's called, then you adjust.
The goal is actually you want to hit the ball, stop the ball to go up.
And the input is the images, these images.
They don't even tell you how to score.
And then plus the number of scores you gain.
And then they train the machine with a lot of these images and then they train the machine.
And the machine after two hours of training, if it's very poor, now it can do better.
It can start to score faster, which without human telling the computer how to play the game.
You just look at the input image, the score you gain.
And then, now become quite professional.
Then another two hours, then you find that you find a loophole that try to create a hole on the left.
Now you can kill the very fast.
And that is all learned by this reinforcement learning.
And when you see this happen, you may start to wonder, is it an intelligent?
It's all even more scary version.
You can go and Google it and apply the same thing.
Basically ask a tree, there is a one person running, try to hide, and then the other one or two try to kill the person.
And regardless how the defense try to come up with many methods to defense it, eventually they will learn a method to kill it.
So think about, this thing could happen if you are not really careful and you could create all this at the role of the future,
you hunt you down and kill you.
And they will stop as long as they have energy.
In fact, there was a movie Black Panther talking about that.
And they will just hunt you down and kill you because they will keep learning.
They have the computer and that is how it's possible.
In fact, one of the thing that you are using a lot today is this.
Church activity would not be possible without the reinforcement learning by human being.
Remember when you use a church committee, they ask you thumb ups, thumb down,
or sometimes you ask them to regenerate, you keep asking the same question.
In fact, you are training the church committee whether the output is good or not.
You give reward.
In fact, every day they are one month, every month at the time, 100 million people use the church committee.
And they get this to train the system.
So for those who have been using church committee, you know that over the past one, the performance has progressed a lot.
Even the same church committee, number 4 or 3.5, the performance has improved because of this reinforcement learning.
It has always tried to optimize the reward to tell what the person really wants.
At first, the same order came up was not very good because it's not well trained.
And the answer may not be always what you want.
Then you always ask the church committee to regenerate or give a thumb up.
They know it's a penalty to the church committee.
The next time you try to come up with a better solution.
So you keep upgrading as a model to get a better result.
So there is reinforcement learning by from human feedback.
And one of the key breakthroughs by church committee.
In fact, the church committee, the model is not something new.
But this is the one that OpenAI introduced to make the output more user friendly to us.
Okay, then let's talk about the history of machine learning.
Of course some of you may find the history so boring.
Why we should look forward, why look backward?
Some always say the best way to learn is to look at the past.
Then you know how people have progressed.
I think Professor Chet Ladi have showed this figure.
But we have to focus on purely machine learning.
She probably introduced more AI.
But AI and machine learning, they are closing later.
In the field you can think of starting in 1940, something by these two gentlemen.
Macalick and Pitz.
And at that time they were trying to see,
okay, how can we build machine which try to think like you?
Which is very difficult task.
So there is no way you can build a brain from the beginning.
And this Pitz is a very interesting person.
He is always so-so.
Very interesting and smart young man.
This is a professor in Cambridge University.
And this Pitz was known that when he was 12 years old,
he spent in the library for three days.
And then read the books.
And then of some of the professor, mathematician professor.
And then wrote the professor a letter to suggest what are the problems
that books actually should come.
12 years old.
And then he was invited to go to study in Cambridge University.
He refused.
And all along his whole life he was such a pretty gentleman.
He actually homeless for quite a long time.
But he was so clever.
Every time he introduced a new problem, he would study and then talk to the professor.
Most of them tried to find job for him.
But he didn't want people to know about him.
So even at the end he was in MIT, he also didn't get his PhD.
He worked in MIT for quite a long time.
So one of his important contributions together with this megalithic is this so-called logic.
And that is the earliest thing that you can think about the sector of the neural network that we know.
So basically it can take input 1 or 0.
And then output could be some of the logical gain.
At that time they said, oh, if I can solve the logical gain problem and or xor neural problem,
then I can build a machine thing like human.
So how do you solve that?
You have to think about 1940, right?
Even computers were not popular.
And then they were thinking about how to build this.
And these are all very smart people.
And that is the best they came out with.
Input pass 1 minus 1, then you can make a decision whether the output is 1, 0, 1, 0.
The earlier contribution.
And that was good.
And people accepted it.
The treasure logic gig.
Then until about 1950s, this Rosenblatt professor in Cornell University,
and he came out with this perceptron.
This is the first time.
The perceptron is now the basic unit that you use to build the neural network.
So you come with this perceptron, which is an improved version of PITS, the logical gig.
So the difference is, it introduced the weights.
The problem with PITS, the logical gig is, you have to hardwire the pass and minus into the circuits.
And once you hardwire, it's always the same.
Regardless of what data you input, it's always the same.
So this Rosenblatt introduced the weights.
Your input can still be 1 and minus or 1 and 0.
But you have to adjust the weight based on the training that output input and input.
This is the first time.
And then, of course, you come with an output result with some value.
It's still a treasure.
Very much like this, but the difference is it has a set of the weights.
This weight is the parameter that you heard about today.
For chat GPT 3.5, they have 176 billion parameters.
And this is the weight.
So it was 10, but adjusting the weights that you learn.
So he built this machine in Cornell, I think later on.
So here I will show you the machine here.
This is the machine he built in Cornell, which is all wires, all the circuits, combine these.
And at that time, they try to adjust, recognize some kind of a simple so-called cut input.
Then you can recognize whether this is the dog on the left or on the right.
And the adjustment of the weight is also very interesting.
But they introduce a learning algorithm.
And basically, when you have the input and the target output is 1, if the target output is not 1, becomes 0,
then you go to those nodes that have input equal to 1, you reduce the weight.
If the target output is supposed to be 0, and then it turns out that it becomes 0,
then you go to the place that reduces the value or increases the weight when the input is 0.
So it's a very heuristic way to adjust all the parameters.
But at least there is a approach.
Before then, no one knew how to build this learning.
Now his base contribution is to introduce this weight so that you can now really let the learning happen.
Compared to the PITS model.
So 1957, Frank Rosenblatt, this is the perceptron.
So he was quite well funded by my navy by university at the time because people think that,
oh, that is the first time now you can build a brain, a machine can think.
In fact, there was even some news article saying that, oh, human are going to conquer the world,
the outside space and send people to the moon or Mars.
Because of this simple new-run video.
I think there was a video somewhere.
I think later.
So that was 1957 by Frank Rosenblatt.
We will see the perceptron again when you talk about the neural network.
Unfortunately, in 1969, this Marvin Minsky is the founder of the AI lab in MIT.
Professor in MIT, he actually wrote a book called Perceptronist.
He kind of a quickie-scied that whatever the model they talk about,
they can solve all and end problems.
You can learn this, but you cannot solve a simple problem like XOR.
That actually creates a lot of doubt about the approach proposed by using this neural network to train the parameter.
Marvin Minsky, if you go and read the history, he is so influential.
He can go to conference when people talk about this concept, he will just quickie-scied.
And they ask people to leave.
He says, this is going nowhere. Wasting your time.
Don't work on machines, this neural network.
So he wrote this book, quite a famous one, and then quickie-scied this perceptron ability.
People somehow over, so-called, operating states about the approach.
And then they create the first AI winter.
From then on, no funding, no people want to work on this problem.
And that was his so-called, you can say, contribution or disparagement.
But indeed in his book, later on people kind of give him some credit.
He did mention that by using one single layer, you cannot solve this problem.
But if you have multi-layer with all the perceptron, and you can solve this problem,
but just do not know how to find the width and the parameter.
You cannot heuristic, go in a jazzy.
And not until this, I think this happened in 1974,
Paul Weber, a PhD student, he wrote in his thesis about this big propagation method,
which of course is going to be a very important solution to machinery.
He is a PhD thesis in 1974, but he did not publish it
because people were criticizing neural network approach.
He find this solution will not be well received by people.
So he did not publish at the paper, he only put in his thesis.
Then until 1986, this Luma Cup and Hinton, and they worked in San Diego,
they talked about this big propagation problem.
And then they wrote a paper sent to me, I think it's a nature paper, which was published.
And they did clarify that they are not the first one invented this approach,
and many people had thought about it, but they did not really formulate the problem
or mathematics clear enough.
In fact, if you go to read the paper, the formula to use is very much we are going to see later on.
Because they can describe the problem so clearly, and a lot of people start to now gain confident interest
in using back propagation to do the machinery.
Right now, all the new big models of machine learning tools including your church activity,
be it of the matter, they all learn back propagation to do the training with the data.
Just now we talked about why you have the input, you have the labor data output.
But how do you learn?
That is not easy.
And the learning process you need to use back propagation,
which allows you to continuously find the weeks to get the optimal output.
That is one of the many contributions of Jack Hinton.
He is one of the so-called the tidier in machine learning or AI.
I think there was a review here. Let me show the review.
There was a time there.
I think it was very hard.
They asked me that question for two years ago, and it was very hard.
They asked me that question and I don't really know.
I suspected they would come back in four or five years, but I am not sure if they really knew.
So I am sure they would use back and have a good answer.
We are just really beginning to understand the capabilities of the computer.
I have got to fill in those papers, which I think will lead you.
And playing chess against a computer is pretty well done.
While most computer scientists slide us on a mere number,
a small group thought that digital computers had much grander destiny.
Being a general purpose machine, it could be programmed to do things
which in humans require intelligence, by games like chess and chess,
as well as brain teasers.
How do you become known as artificial encounters?
I am a machine critic. Even a subject of sex is a thing.
I am convinced that machines can do a thing.
I don't be in a machine with a tape like them.
I don't need to be in a machine for a long time.
We are going to have a difficult problem distinguishing a man from a robot.
I don't think I will be able to work on a computer.
But I think the computers will be doing the things that men do when we say they are thinking.
I am convinced that we can do a thing in all that time.
I am convinced that we will not have a count of 15 years,
coming from a machine along the way.
Count of five?
Some years from now.
The count of more than anything.
They had to bring with them the security when they set out to use computers
to translate languages.
A $500,000 single calculator, most personal and funny brain known,
translates roughly in English.
Seven man's bag of a bag.
While the person now in the US has to apply to the computers,
it will now give the solution to the code war of session,
keeping tabs on what the Russians are doing.
Okay, you get the idea.
And you see, $500,000 computer to do the translation of Russian to increase.
Today, you just go to any free website you can do that.
And not just $500,000 Russia to increase,
you can translate thousands of or hundreds of languages.
And with my whisper, open AI whisper, with great accuracy.
I pretend this.
So there is a progress, 1970 to 2002 for about 50 years.
Look at those people, the machine, the card stand-up in the TV.
So people have been thinking about AI for many, many years.
And then you can consider yourself very lucky born in the age of AI
and now become seemingly possible.
These are the problems when I was a student,
cannot think of we have this solution.
So there was an explosion in terms of the solution.
And this is young Le Koon.
Of course, he is one of the major contender.
1989, he was in AT&T Bell Lab.
And he came up with this first time convolutional neural network
show that he can work to recognize DJ.
And the company, of course, Bell Lab,
worked with some company that tried to read the Jeep code
of those letters in the US.
US polls received a lot of letters.
In the past, they humanly, they have a Jeep code,
a 5-digit Jeep code.
They look at it and then dispatch the letters in different places
so that the postman can send,
based on the postcode, they send the letter to write the patient.
So we need a lot of human labor to read the Jeep code.
So then they're higher, not higher,
commissioned Bell Lab to come up with this solution.
And then young Le Koon, he was one very passionate about neural network.
He actually was a Jeff Hinton postdoc one year.
And they met in a conference, Jeff Hinton from French, right?
And this, Jeff Hinton from UK, and then young Le Koon from French.
So because they like the machine learning, the so-called neural network,
so young Le Koon went to Toronto with Jeff Hinton for one year as a postdoc.
Then after that, he moved to Bell Lab.
And the only requirement was he went to ask Bell Lab interview for a job.
He said, I have one requirement.
I don't want to share my computer with anyone else.
At that time, because of limited computation, I really had to share the workstation.
So he got a sun workstation for his tone.
I think it didn't very fast.
The first few months, he came up with this CNN network,
which can recognize digits for posts, Jeep code, and also for the bank.
He would write the checks.
So at one time, they were saying that 10% of the checks in the US were read by his machine.
So he came up with this.
We are going to go to his network.
Yeah, that's him.
Baby face young Le Koon when he was young.
And that was one computer that he asked for in order to accept,
so that he wanted to accept the job.
So there is a demonstration of...
Right now, you can actually program this yourself, right?
With maybe less than 20 lines of code.
I will show you the code and how to do that.
In fact, it was a very simple exercise for everyone to try out to learn the digit.
And handwritten.
I think there was earlier approach, but they only can recognize the type of digit.
And this is the one that purposely writes in a very different form.
He can still recognize it using the neural network approach.
Yeah.
But even then, at that time, you're not obliged to recognize the...
The network was like that.
Actually, in fact, I worked with one of the lab near to your lab at the time.
All look like this.
Okay.
And even that, even his approach can solve your problem.
And he still lost it.
Because then sooner or later, you'll find that,
or when you try to apply this to solve other problems like recognize objects, recognize animals,
it doesn't work well.
Because at that time, you do not have enough data,
you do not have enough computation power,
you do not have the good model, the weak model, right?
To do those tasks.
Okay.
And then 1997, this is a long-shot term memory by Smith-Huber
and called Klyther.
And they come up with this approach for languages or sequential data.
And which somehow you can...
Because for tasks, for those translation from one language to the other, right,
you need to memorize the whole sequences, right?
And how do you memorize it is challenging.
The traditional CNN network cannot have the memory.
So they create this long-shot term memory to make it that,
oh, I can remember a long task and then do the translation, do the analysis.
But unfortunately, it cannot remember too long.
Therefore, LSTM and ENAW lose to Transformer.
So it was considered one of the very good advancement at the time.
And then, of course, as I say, even with young and cool method,
and people still believe that it can solve many, many advanced problems because of the limited...
So the capacity of the neural network that can build at that time.
And also because other methods, like support vector machines, right,
and also the forest trade decision forest came along here.
So the second winter, because they have this support vector machine by WEMIC,
WEMIC was a researcher in Russia, right.
And then he had many years of research in this support vector machine.
But not a lot of people in the US, in the Western country, knew about it.
So when you make a visit to the US, start to publicize his or her work,
wow, people were so surprised by the result.
And it's very elegant.
I will talk about support vector machines.
And you formulate a problem, and you know what exactly the score is trying to minimize and how it minimizes.
And which is slightly different from CNN.
Although it works, but you really do know what kind of decision they make.
So they actually have a second so-called AI winter.
Then until this 2012, Alex Knack is a PhD student of Jack Newton in Polymer University.
And they start to address this image net competition,
which is a competition that created for such problem, classification problem.
And it's the first CNN approach, and this is the network they use.
And the network is actually very much similar to Young Le Cron network.
Just that now they can learn how to play.
What an important thing that they do is they use GPU.
In fact, it was not Alex, it was by this Ilaia Suskeeper.
Some of you might know him.
He was the person fired the same element.
And the one behind open AI, he was a Jack Newton machine.
So he was also a researcher or student of Jack Newton at that time.
He suggested to use the GPU to do the training.
And they are very good in programming.
So Alex actually spent two or three weeks to do a lot of training.
At that time, the data cannot fit.
The memory is not enough to fit all the data, so he had to split the network into two GPUs.
So they were slightly different from Young Le Cron model, but in fact, very similar.
And they also have a deeper on how to wear the data crossover so that you can optimize the training.
You will go through some of the training in the later part of the lecture.
And that changed everything.
With this, your people have been working on other approaches to solve this ImageNet competition.
And when they start to introduce the neural network approach, the convolutional neural network,
and which won the competition by a large margin compared to the second one, right?
The error percentage is more than 10%.
If all the people that reduce 1%, 2%, any year, so this came out and kind of won the competition, surprised anyone.
And from then on, the foreign solution of CNN is machine learning.
And there was a story that actually after that, they created a company.
They upset the company and sold it for about 40 years.
Three of them, three.
Actually, they went to Las Vegas, the place that they had the NICS conference.
And then they start to, actually the codes you can now see online, maybe 20 lines of program.
But at that time, it was still fairly new.
Many companies tried to acquire the software IP from them.
In order to sell this, and this former company, suddenly like once, NUNERNEC was something like this.
Then they went to Las Vegas, decided to auction the IP.
And many companies came to bid, including PY2 from China.
And at the end, actually PY2 gave a higher price, but they decided to sell the IP to Google.
I think for P, 40 million or 40 more million.
Just a few lines of code and three of them will share the 40 million US dollar.
And PY2 actually want to give more, but they decided not to.
Because beside the IP, they also need to agree to work, to join the company to work for them to transfer the technology.
And that actually Alex and Pia, Susiemer, they started to continue.
Alex already somehow outside, they somehow he decided not to involve in machine learning anymore after a while.
So that was the key.
So Konec worked and changed everything. People now start to gain the confidence on this.
And here of course, why machine learning now becomes possible?
First, you need to have truth. You need to have, without object rotation, you need to have an algorithm.
You need to have a good model.
Second is you need to have a lot of computation, right? GPU.
In fact, Yang Le Koon was one that suggested something like GPU idea in the early day when he developed.
He said Yang Le Koon learned more.
So he thought about, he even developed a project which designed the chips to do a fast computation.
But they did not continue to push forward and media came over.
And then it becomes successful, very successful.
So I think I want to figure out, they need a lot of computation.
And third is the data set.
And these are the key components that you need to have in order to solve machine learning problems.
So early on, they had some of these limitations, so they could not really create a good solution.
So here are some very small data sets in today's standard.
So the green list data set, which is the Yang Le Koon, he used, the data set used to create the Learned Model to recognize digit.
You can download for mine, Yang Le Koon.
About 60,000 28 by 28 gray-skilled images like this for training and then 10,000 for testing.
And in fact, you can now quickly change your program to beat Yang Le Koon model.
Just change the network.
I will show you some code to do that.
And then this is another popular CFA 10 and CFA 100.
And these are 10 classes for CFA 10, recognize very small 32 by 32 color images and recognize 10 types of objects.
60,000, for example, you can use 50,000 for training, 10,000 for testing.
So for 10 classes, each of them then will have about 5,000 images.
Then the CFA 100 have more classes, 100 classes, because they also have subclasses.
But the number of images available will be less than 10 times less fewer.
Then ImageNet, this is the one I think many contributed by B Fei Fei.
And she actually started this project when she was at Princeton as a assistant prof.
He's a post-doc, a research student, started to collect the data.
Before then, he was in Caltech.
And then he probably started working on the project back then.
So with this data contribution, then you have ImageNet, 2010.
Then people now start to compete based on the same data benchmark,
and to know who has a better model.
That's how you make progress.
In fact, a lot of the standard is all because they have this so-called standard data set,
like your JPEG, your MPEG, your video compression, your JPEG.
All start with this kind of a common data set.
Then people start to propose new ideas, new algorithms,
and then they meet regularly to see who has a better result
and what are the ideas they introduce.
And then that's how you move the solution forward.
Okay, here is a small sample of the ImageNet data set.
So you think about it.
Today you join a company or university and ask you to collect 14 million images and label them.
And you had to also crop them into 32x32x3.
How do you do it?
And there's a lot of...
In fact, a lot of machine learning jobs,
you're going to do a lot of this very so-called low-level engineering work,
rather than all new algorithms.
There are not any new algorithms anyway.
Everyone just fine-tune, just do a lot of training here and there.
But to collect the data, there's called data engineering,
which is actually what is very much needed in many companies.
How to collect data? Where to collect data? When to collect data?
What to collect data?
All these questions that you need to have a lot of experience.
About application, I don't really have to go through this.
You can see that with that simple machine learning approach,
there are a lot of many, many possible applications.
And which in the past, they have very vivid performance.
And now seem to be a lot.
Everyone think that it should be like that.
And even the coloring, right?
We have done this problem using traditional approaches.
Not easy.
But now you can go to the website.
These are some of the applications.
Now it's creating a lot of potential value to the company.
Here's for example, the face recognition.
Also in the young LeCune, using the LeLab
to try to do the face recognition.
And tracking as well.
So I have a classmate work on this face detection.
Not using machine learning approach.
You can find out, it's not just one actually.
A group of research PhD students,
they were trying to track faces and detect faces.
And that was very challenging without machine learning.
Think of many ways to write a code.
With the learning now, you can do it very well.
Of course, not just that.
If you use a YOLO, you can detect many many objects.
Very fast.
And which of course, they keep upgrading their performance
and also the speed.
And now it's a common tool.
You can also detect all the faces.
And with faces now, you can sort of count how many people inside the scene.
Which is humanly impossible to do so.
Because people move.
You capture the images, then you can really know what happened.
And these are some of the very basic.
All these can be formulated at a supervised learning method.
For example, semantic segmentation.
In the segment, whether there is a sky, object, grass, or tree.
And this is become a classification problem.
Every pixel, if you formulate YOLO training,
you'll ask, is this pixel belong to one of these four classes?
Or it could be more, we have, but that can be four classes.
Then you start to do some kind of grouping or unit.
You can create this kind of semantic segmentation.
All you can do, the classification is to,
given an image you identify, there is a cat.
And where the cat is, it also localization.
Put a bounding box.
The way you do a bounding box is to detect a kind of regression problem.
Where is the top left corner of a bounding box?
And also the side of a bounding box.
And then you do the training.
Every time, when you do a training,
you will give out an example, you will use a label,
here is a cat, here is a cat, here is a cat.
Then every time you go through this support training,
then you can output, one is the class of an object,
it's a cat, it's a label classification.
And also the location of this cat, the bounding box.
Then you become a classification of the question,
machine learning problem, a supervised learning problem.
And then one of my PhDs to work on this facial landmark detection,
so you detect a lot on, so that you can now do the defect change of face.
So first you detect where they are,
and then you can do a lot of these post processing,
equally recognition.
And then object detection and instant segmentation.
So these are the term they use when they read the paper,
they want to segment, let's say they want to detect dogs and cats.
So you have to do the segmentation.
The segment everything can do it very well now.
Before then it was still not easy.
And then this is the skeleton detection,
and then you can use it to estimate the pose,
the spot action of the person.
You can use a 19 point or 39 point skeleton,
which is also a supervised learning.
You do a lot of training data,
given an image to identify where are those points.
And then you do a lot of training,
then given a new image you can identify those key points as well.
And then these are some impending applications.
You can actually try to collect the images
by fielding, remove certain parts,
and then you make them that you didn't want.
And that's not even the diffusion model.
You just do kind of a change of the content to estimate the basic.
But using learning approach,
we cannot use image processing approach.
Here is the one that change the photo style.
You have a style photo,
and you have the target content photo.
Then you combine it together,
you can change your content photo into a new style.
And many of these things you go there,
you can download the code,
you can actually compile it,
you can upload the images,
you can do exporting it yourself.
Of course, this is not possible
if you use a traditional image processing.
Because they are also like animation.
You can use the one driving sequence,
and this is target image,
and then all of them will behave the same as the driving video.
Again, these are the codes you can also follow.
Even if you don't know how it works,
it just becomes so easy now for people to train and do.
Of course, style gun is another.
Style gun is another model.
This young fellow, they come up with this idea.
I think this idea was very interesting.
We will talk about their two networks.
One tried to create a scene generated in the image.
The other tried to judge whether this is fake or real.
They trained these networks together.
The idea came from, I think,
gathering in a bar at night.
And then the challenge was,
oh, machine learning can do a lot of
classification regression problems,
but they cannot really create new content.
Then young fellow was there,
thought of it.
If I can create a two-network one,
try to recharge the classification,
fake or real.
The other tried to create the content.
And then I managed to do it.
So he was hard drunk.
He just had his idea.
Then his friend not believed that he can do it.
So he went home that night.
He sat down.
I think he programmed until the early morning.
Then he had created a model
which created very small images,
which looked like the content can be generated
by this simple model.
So he just had a very simple idea.
And that also tells that the approach is
query versus path.
If you can model the network,
and you can combine them in a very useful way,
you can solve problems like this.
And all these are fake faces and cars.
They don't exist in the real world.
I believe you have seen some of these.
So for example,
let's look at this.
These are fake images.
It is not a real person.
It's created by a computer.
Why? Why is that?
Let me do this.
It's so real.
You want to humanly try to paint a face like this.
I don't think it's possible.
But computers in the same way are smarter than you.
It's a artificial face.
I can look at it in another one.
Just update again.
This is another.
You can have as many as you like.
All these are fake faces.
It's just created.
You can create other objects.
You can find quite a lot of examples.
You can train different types of furniture.
You can create horses.
You can create those.
You can also test yourself
whether you can do better than the computer.
These two.
One is real.
One is a fake person.
Which one is real?
Can you tell?
Right is real.
This one is easy.
I think this one is real.
Let's check.
In white.
Oh, I was surprised.
That's interesting.
This is real.
This is a fake.
Try again.
I'll show you the real.
I'll tell you where to look for.
You'll be taken with a yellow frame.
Anyone?
Right is real.
Left side is like left.
Let me take a closer look.
I think left is real.
Yes, yes.
Why?
Why those that you can judge?
Let's try again.
See where they can...
Now we are doing the machine learning.
See whether you are smarter than a machine.
Can you figure out a way to decide classification problem?
Who is real?
I'll show you now.
But training is important now.
Okay?
Play again.
So who is real?
Who is fake?
Left.
Real.
Okay, let's try.
Correct.
Okay.
Now let's do a training again.
Left or right?
Right.
You see?
Isn't that how challenging it is?
We are going to the machine learning now.
I think this one...
I think it's right.
Oh, you are right.
Okay?
I'm surprised.
Okay, where to look for?
Because this is very old.
This is 20...
20, 19, take out of work.
Today, our quality will be much better.
So where to look for?
Because it's a very old coach.
Nobody look at the background.
Right?
This case is not working.
The background, it can simulate the face very well.
But the background may not be.
Because the background will be many, many unthink.
Also look at the symmetric of the face.
The ears in particular.
Sometimes they have one ear disappear.
Or in the other shape.
Or the ear ring.
And also you have paper to look at.
Even the eye, the gait, where they look at.
This side here.
This one should be easy, right?
Which one is the real?
Left.
Left?
Right.
Left.
We'll see what is this.
So computer doesn't have knowledge about what is human.
They just try to give an image that looks like human.
But we know this.
It's not human.
So that is...
This one is easy.
Right.
Left.
Ear rings, you see?
Not symmetric.
Disappeared.
But it cannot tell that it should have symmetric ear rings.
It could have a natural look.
It could be like that.
But normally it's what you look for.
The background also looks a bit funny.
I don't know why it's this person.
And here there's a text.
It's a text in to be real.
Okay?
So this is what computer can do now by using the machine learning approach.
You can also create, change a phase, right?
Which is, you can do it now, actually.
A lot of free program.
And also this one.
Or entering an era in which our energies can make a whole wide animal out of the same, anything at any point in time.
Even if they would never say it was planned.
So, for instance, they could have me say things like, I don't know,
Kevin Longer was right.
Or a man person was in a self-implex.
Or, how about this simply,
President Trump is a total and complete dipshit.
Now, you see, I remember saying these things.
At least not in public address.
But, someone else would.
Someone.
Got a Jordan heel.
This is a dangerous time.
Moving forward, we need to be more vigilant with what we trust from the end.
That's the time we need to rely on trusted new sources.
They sound basic.
But how do we move forward?
And the age of information is going to be the difference between whether we survive
or whether we become some kind of fucked up disorder.
Thank you.
Stay well, bitches.
Yeah.
So, be careful what you see on the internet.
And many of these could, may not be real.
Including your voice.
Right now, they only need about 15 seconds of your voice.
They can clone your voice to say anything they want.
It's available technically.
You can go and download this too.
I think Alibaba have won.
They allow you to do so.
And image and video now can create.
So, yeah.
You should start.
I think a lot of this will be very advanced.
In the future, you may not be able to tell the differences.
Let's go back.
Of course, in actually 2022, even with those things, right,
2022, people start to lose patience about machine learning.
Because they say, oh, we have all these fancy applications.
But autonomous vehicle is still not there.
Not here.
It's still limited application.
And until the church APT come along, the transformer,
attention is all you need.
The paper in 2017.
But it doesn't, people do not really know about it until you start to use the church APT.
I think the first time, I'm not sure you can recall when you use the church APT.
You doubt that it's really a real person behind.
And that was even very beginning.
Now it's so advanced that you take it for granted, this should be the case.
You should live like this.
Even programming.
Right now, in the past, we're going to forum to ask questions,
how to solve this problem or go and read.
Now, all these co-pilot tool can help you to depart.
So because of this, a lot of companies, a lot of resources,
every big tech company, they focus on church APT or large linkage model.
Everyone try to develop themselves.
Because there seem to be something that application can be realized easily.
And in fact, now you are using those tools quite regularly.
But the problem is, these things are not easy to duplicate.
You need a lot of data, but many companies still try to do it and get a lot of people
to collect data, do the training, find a team, and we purposely the application or target
and a particular application like the medical large linkage model like Huatuo.
And I know one company try to target weather prediction, collect all the weather data around
the world so they can build a model to predict the weather.
A financial application.
And all this created a lot of need in terms of computation, in terms of data,
and create a lot of ways as well.
So in order to build a model, you need millions of dollars.
The energy, even you use it, it also costs a lot.
Although many of you may use a free version, but if your company subscribe,
organization subscribe to it, they have to pay quite a big sum.
They have to generate profit out of this.
And this is how the model, church APT already have 175 billion parameters.
Those few parameters we talk about when this Rosenblatt come out with a simple neuron
and now they have 175 billion of the parameters.
Think about how do you train those, come up with a value of those parameters.
In fact, I think when they trade the church APT 3 or 3.5,
and halfway through they found it was a bug, it was an error, but they couldn't stop.
Because there's a lot of money, it's very costly to stop and be trained again.
So many of these companies, like now, all these so-called, for example, the next one, right?
Church APT 4 claim to have 176 trillion, right?
And you also have the 4 or me.
And also now you have the German 9 by Google, right?
Crowd by this anthropic and Olympus.
And higher the larger the parameters, the more capable.
Even this is a chain, right?
For Alipapa, all have this so-called model now available.
Some of this like Lama, the Meta one, which is a free open source.
But the problem is you may not have the machine to train or fight him,
but you can only use a smaller model to do the exercise.
And all these, and you go to the website, you can find a lot of information about such a model, what they are capable of.
And of course, with this model, the thing is how do you compare?
There are so many choices and options.
If you develop your application or apps or agents, and which one you should use?
Right now, of course, when you choose, you choose a free one, right?
But for the company, of course, they will talk about their product, right?
If they develop, they invest so-called manpower to develop an app, and they cannot change it.
They need not easy to change the application.
So there are different kind of evaluation, like this one based on the text evaluation.
You can also based on the audio translation and vision understanding, right?
The pink color is a GPT4O, right?
And then you can see that this is a cloud, the entropic, right?
Cloud 3 is actually quite performing quite closely to compare to the GPT4O.
And the free one is a Lama 3, but this one, 400 billion parameters.
You cannot really follow your computer unless you really have very high end computer resources.
But this is open source. You might be able to use some kind of training for data using at least a smaller number of parameters.
And you can see they are competing with each other.
But you see, the data are just so much.
You can go to some website to find those data in your training model.
But the data, because they just Google a kind of scrap from the internet,
some of the quality are not always good for training purpose.
In fact, people find that the cloud model somehow in certain aspects they perform so well
because they have very good quality data.
They find a way to clean the data to make sure the data are reliable.
And that is how you can improve the quality of your model.
Of course, with tab model, because then you can also now using the text prompt as input
and create such a so-called generative AI, like Dao Yi, Min Chie Ninh, stable infusion,
which you have a text, then you also have the so-called image input
where you do the quick model, create the image pair.
You can create this very nice picture by just giving a prompt.
You describe the prompt.
There are different ways that you can create a prompt so that output will shoot you better.
Here is another one, stable diffusion.
It looks nice, but also not really real.
There now is a newer version that makes it look more realistic.
But this is something generated.
Actually, the way it is generated is using a very small one that you remove the noise,
continue to enhance the quality using the text input.
Here is another application, out-painting.
By Dao Yi, you create a lot of content.
It's similar to the in-painting that we saw before.
See how easy they can create content.
This is one of the areas that people worry about in the future.
You might have too much content to consume, right?
Because all are generated by machines.
Here is another one, you can modify it.
This is one of the professors in computer science school.
The background also changes.
It's so easy to manipulate.
It's just the beginning, you can think about the future.
This is the Archie Sora by OpenAI.
Using the text, you can create this video clip.
Very consistent and high quality.
You can go and use it, because it limits you a few seconds.
They are all created by this prompt.
Only better than your camera can take.
I think one of the models in Alibaba also created a version of Chinese
working in some of the Chinese city.
Just similar description.
Very high quality and high detail.
All based on just one prompt, text.
You can create content.
In the future, hopefully you can turn a novel into a movie
without all the actors and actresses.
You can go to the website, there are many.
You can go to see, explore yourself.
There are many, all created by this text.
All generated by a prompt.
This is also created by prompts.
You can go and explore if you are interested in that.
I think that's all the summary.
See, all come back to this.
Once you unlock the need for humans to write a program,
you have to create an approach which you only need
the input and output data you want.
Then you cannot unlock a lot of possible solutions and applications.
Which you do not need to be the one writing the program or finding a solution.
You just need to think about how to formulate the problem
into a machine learning approach.
Then collect all the data.
The machine can learn by itself,
give you the algorithm, give you the model.
We are just at the very beginning of this era.
You can say it's the best of time.
You have so many possible applications.
You can go forward too.
It's also the worst of time.
You have so many things that you need to learn to update yourself
if you work in this field.
One week or one month, you will not be paying attention to the new development.
You are outdated.
My students, when they submit a paper, miss the deadline,
then they will just have to so-called forego the paper.
Because next year you will be outdated already.
Some of the top conferences you need to compete with time.
So every time they have to rush to submit a paper early
because if they do, someone else will.
There are so many people working in this field.
Some money, yeah.
Empower computer.
Now with this approach, there are many, many solutions you can come up with.
Even my son, my daughter in primary school, they learn machine learning.
They use that to...
My daughter even teaches her classmates machine learning.
Without my help, she doesn't need my help.
She is younger and she can teach and write programs to do that.
Of course you already need to still understand the fundamentals.
Different kinds of learning, supervised learning, unspoiled learning, reinforcement learning.
And then...
And generative AI of course is the upcoming.
There will be a lot of content created by machine,
and fake content as well.
So how do you detect those content?
What is the issue about ethical security, privacy concerns?
And because they are so easily made by computers,
and anyone can target you.
In fact, while the celebrity singer just puts a pose that someone has used a voice
to create a speech to support,
while the president came here in the US,
she clarifies not from her, it's a fake kind of voice recommendation.
For in the election time,
so there will be all these fake news and fake so-called image review.
You need to be aware of that.
So good to get yourself aware of this.
Okay, that's all for today.
Next week I will be here, and our professor will come here.
Then I will resume my lecture in week 7.
I will upload the slides.
I'm still making changes, update some content.
I will upload the slides when they are available.
I will see you in a week after next week.
Thank you.
Yes.
What is the dissertation project for this good project?
So what project is interesting?
I'm hearing something under the sun.
Yes, many generally.
But what have you done before?
I was doing an interview for the recommendation.
You seem to be in YOLO.
YOLO?
Yes.
You think about an interesting problem and let's slide your email
and see if I can put a problem forward.
Car break condition is the whole problem.
Okay, so I may need some time to prepare.
Yes, think about what kind of problem you are in.
Look for some interesting problem.
Okay, so tell me your cast.
Okay, good.
I better clear this.
Do you know how to lock out this?
I cannot find it.
It's here.
No, it's here.
Oh, I did?
Thank you.
Yes, Chen Long, right?
Yes, yes.
Digital human.
Yes.
You go and study those things first.
My research will join end of the month.
I'll ask you to meet her.
But before that, you get yourself prepared.
Okay.
Thank you.
What lecture is it?
Physics.
Physics on a grid.
Okay.
How was the quiz yesterday?
You should be able to see your result, right?
Hello.
Do you meet your expectation?
Okay.