you
sorry
my level is very high
okay
just to
just a reminder
today is the due date for
this homework one
I have received a couple of
emails asking about this
just in case you missed
what we discussed last week
so
and just in case you have not
submitted your homework
but you can do multiple attempts
right we will use the most recent
submission as your final
submission for marking
so for this question again as you
can see that
sample number one
and sample number four have
exactly the same feature
but different classification
right so as I mentioned last week
this is not an error but it's
kind of a noisy data although we only
had eight samples here but you can
imagine that for a big database of
millions of data and three you
bound to have some inconsistency
with the same feature but the class
labors are different which could be
due to laboring error or noisy or
anomaly so when you build
decision three you have to decide
how to deal with this situation
okay for the part a so you can
make a decision because in here you
are using information gain to
construct the decision three
therefore your objective is to find
the features and then the classes
which allow you to
maximize your information gain right
and then for part c is the one
that you have to now think together
with part a what can you do
with that situation so that you
can prone the trees into
perhaps something more meaningful
and can still achieve the same or
similar performance right so that is
what the question is asking so think
about it just write your justification
it is meant for you to
to exercise your judgment
then the second question is
I think I show one example in
last lecture you do not need to show
me all the detail calculation which
of course you can do that right when
you try to figure out if you really
have no clue what I'm asking is within
this box right if there's any point
located within this box what class
will it belong to if you use the
first sorry one nearest neighbor
three nearest neighbor or five nearest
neighbor classifier right so if you
really do know you can okay start with
some random point just put some point
here then you make your judgment then
after a while you can figure out some
patterns and then then you know that
within certain area it will all
classify as this class solid circle
right and just shape the areas that
you think if there's any point located
in those areas will be classified as
class solid circle okay so I only need
you to shape the region you do not need
to show the detail calculation or this
thing okay and yeah that's what the
question is asking you and of course in
here I assume you use the Euclidean
distant measure right which is a norm L2
of course if you want to challenge yourself
you think about will the answer be
different if you use L1 right the
Manhattan distant or if you use other
so-called distant measure will the
areas be different so that will allow
you to think carefully okay and yeah I
could even say that if you use an SVM
right to classify the data right so
what class will they belong to so that
of course you should think about it
okay that is the homework again due by
end of today 11.59 p.m. but please do not
rush for the last minute because whether
the CITS NTU learn will be down or not
I have no idea so give yourself some
buffer okay so let's come back to
neural networks and we have started this
in the last lecture talk about what is a
neural networks and what is the so-called
the construction basic unit which is a
perceptron a perceptron as we cover last
lecture right is basically try to mimic a
neuron like this which you receive input
which is in this case the features x1 to
xn then you multiply with respective
weights keep them more emphasis or less
emphasis then you sum them up this one
the summation wj xj after you sum them up
plus b is a so-called the bias right
this we have give this a name called net j
that mean the net input to the neuron j
okay net j then before you go out you have
this so-called activation function
sigma with the net j here this is the net
j input net j output will be y equal to
sigma net j right and this sigma is
known as activation function in this case
you will just charge whether this value is
less than or equal to zero no output
otherwise it will send a signal to the
downstream okay so this x is the accumulation
of all the input plus a bias and for
convenient and many people would like to
absorb this b as a spatial input unit
with x output equal to one then the b
become the weights so you think about it
one-minder type multiply b will be
equivalent to the b bias input okay so
that allow you to write this so-called
neuron as a very so-called elegant and
compressed dog product vector weights
dog product with a feature vector x
okay again it is basically just trying to
do the hyperplane classification to
separate the space into two different
so-called classes okay then we went
through a couple of very simple example
you can consider this as the training data
then if you want them to fulfill all
this classification result which is a
target output with a given sample
training then you must fulfill all this
condition and you can find multiple
possible solution for this case okay
and we also talk about how is it different
from SVM and unfortunately when you have
some more so-called complex so-called
classification boundary then a single
neuron cannot serve this purpose but you
could combine a few neurons combine
link them together so this one I suggest
you to try out find out what is a W and
in here how many parameter we have here
1 2 3 4 5 6 weights plus 3 bias okay so
which is totally 9 variables you need to
find solution and that you can classify
these x or classes then by connecting
all these so-called neuron together and
you can form a multi-layer perceptron
which is a very generic
neural network and basic neural network
okay so such topology normally we call
it N M M C meaning you have N unique
input right and two hidden layer with M
unit you could the M could be different
you could have M1 M2 right M3 M4 etc
then you have output unit with C neuron
output okay so typically normally if you
talk about classification this one the
output Y1 to YC will be either one or zero
right or you want the target output will be
either one or zero while indicate that
the object input belong to that particular class
then we say that such a configuration is
so-called universal approximator right
MLP is a universal approximator so that
mean regardless how complex the
classification regions are given enough
neurons enough layer you could always
train the network to differentiate or
separate the two the all these classes in
here we only have two classes of black and white
right so this show you the different layer
the first layer basically you do a hyperplane
right linear classification then the
second layer you can start to combine all
this linear hyperplane into convex region
and then by further combining all this
convex region you can create arbitrary
so-called areas which may no longer be
convex okay so that training play a very
important role and the good news is if you
use a back propagation and then you can
train we show this demo as long as you
have sufficient input data you have the
target output you can always train the
network to minimize the error that you
can define what is your target and
different between target and output as
error function one of the important
thing that we mentioned is the whole
neural network would not really work if
you do not have this activation function
nonlinear activation function right and
which is very key to make it work like
our brain it is everyone is a linear
like this sigma x equal to x so regardless
how many units and the year you have you
can call us call collapse them into just
one single unit which can only then do a
linear classifier it is not going to solve
very complex problem then we talk about
this a sigmoid function usually this
alpha of course you can select it as a
one that become one of the sigmoid
function we saw in the last lecture in
the later part of the lecture the back
propagation algorithm and and then this
actually allow the output to to stay
between 0 to 1 then 10 x this is the one
these two actually were used in the young
the Kuhn learn at activation function
and there's a sign function if you
recall last week we mentioned that
during the training of back propagation
you always have to use this the so-called
sigma prime x the derivative of your
activation function when you do the
error back propagation from the output
and that work to the input and right and
you every step when you compute the
error term you have to multiply with
this derivative of the activation
function so with because of this that
make this sign function very much useless
for learning purpose because it's going
to be zero almost everywhere except when
x equal to zero which is undefined right
so they mean if you use that basically
your network cannot learn right because
after even you have an error but it's
going to multiply with zero right no
error can be propagated back to the
network so therefore normally we will
select those function that you have
so-called non zero derivative of the
activation function in particular the
red rule rectify linear unit which is
very easy to compute because when x is
larger than zero the derivative sigma x
is equal to one here right and then zero
when x is less than zero right of course
you can have a slight variation but
normally this a leaky red rule is not
really as popular or very much different
for a red rule then we talk about back
propagation last week the whole idea is
if you have a network like this you can
have many many hidden you need output
you need ultimately what you want is to
have the actual output as close to the
target output as possible right so
therefore you can learn those parameter
the weights and the buyers by minimizing
some error function right as long as you
can express the z the cost function
error function as a function of those
unknown parameters right you think about
the this so-called neural network you
can always express this right every input
is a summation right all this summation
and then activation function and then
the output now become the input of the
next neuron so you can always express
the y in term of all the weights and
buyers in between right and then you
can now train the network by using this
gradient descent which is basically you
take the partial derivative of this error
function with respect to any of the
unknown you want to find right then you
move into the negative direction because
if the gradient is positive when you move
in the positive direction the error will
increase so you should move in the
opposite direction therefore you have the
minus and then the adjustment you try to
moderate because you do not know the
magnitude of the change whether it's too
big or small so you always can adjust it
by using a learning rate and then you
update your parameter with the new one
by moving in the negative direction of
this gradient right this is called
gradient descent right and then we talk
about the impact or effects of different
type of learning rate which would have on
the outcome of your learning and this one
showed that not necessarily you can always
reach the let's say global minimum
assuming this is somehow error function
surface and this is just 2D with X1 X2
input you can imagine that if you have
million or billions of parameter and that
kind of cost function survey is something
that you really cannot imagine and
therefore when you start in any random
so-called location in this surface where
you will end up with is really uncertain
right you keep training like this case
trapped in somehow local minimum and
these two and all end up with this
global minimum then at the end we
talk about this back propagation
algorithm we quickly walk through these
two slides but today we are going to go
through the detail which of course are
optional but I believe it has some value
if you really can understand how this
back propagation algorithm works because
this is really the core of enabling all
these new network in fact part of the
Hinton contribution and one who just
received the Nobel Prize in physics
right I think there was an interview
online he said he felt his physics how
could someone feel the physics that
eventually received the Nobel Prize in
physics thanks to this so-called some of
the new network work that he has done
so okay you we can focus on this
multi-layer perceptron network but you
can expect or imagine that the network
can be very complex or very different
from such configuration you're going to
see some of these variation later part
but ultimately as long as you can write
the okay let me move this a TK target
output to here this is a target output
as long as you can write the error
function here J or you just use E as a
function of all the parameters that you
need to find the optimum value you can
use the back propagation plus the gradient
descent to train the network right by
first define what is your error function
here is a TK minus OK OK is the actual
output TK is the target output when you
first start your training like these two
will not be the same right if they are
the same not no training will happen
right you already have the network which
can do the job so you want it to be
different then of course in this case we
define the sum of square errors right
which is a L2 norm right and these two
factor is arbitrary just that when we
derive the formula later you'll find
that you will not have this so-called
constant there which will make the
so-called the adjustment simpler
okay and then your weights adjustment
will be the gradient descent right
partial derivative with this particular
weight multiplied with the learning rate
adjust in the negative direction
similarly for your bias again these
bias could be a spatial term in this
W but you can write it separately
because the formula is slightly different
but it's also partial derivative is
still gradient descent with this unknown
variable right so the way you do the
learning is the first step is try to
initialize before the training you don't
know what will be the appropriate
weights and bias so one way is to
initialize all the weights and bias with
random so-called number and certainly
you don't want them to be all zero right
if they're all zero you think about all
the multiplication whatever input you
have it will really become zero right
so nothing will change right so you want
to you want this weights and bias to
start with the random values which are
as different as possible so you can use
a Gaussian random generator to create the
weights and bias zero mean and then
given any training input data X you
fit the data into the network you
calculate when you are X1 to Xn right
then you can now okay this is the input
you need the output here is equal to X so
something very unique for the input is
we do not apply any normally normally we
do not apply any activation function
whatever it come in output okay then
that will become the input to the
following layer units right and then
you can compute for any node J your
first computer net J net input is the
same perceptron that you have seen
before then you apply the activation
function to get the output of that unit
J okay you do that for every unit
including the output unit then you get
okay then you check whether TK and
okay's are the same if they are not the
same then you have error term and that
error term is can be compute by this
formula we are going to derive this
formula later okay but for the time being
you just kind of take this for granted
that because TK and okay are different at
the output unit TK minus okay will be
the error right that error the difference
between the actual output and the target
output then when you move this error
across this unit back propagation okay
because you only have the error at the
output if you want to move this forward
you multiply with the derivative of
activation function because when you
compute forward the net J will go to the
activation function you get the output
but what this delta K right this error
term delta K here it means is if you want
this error basically when you compute
this right your goal is to adjust the
weights to make this error smaller right
so therefore the adjustment that you need
to make will depend on the gradient of
the activation function because you want
to see where it is so that you know
whether you are going to increase or
reduce the error therefore this is
the derivative of the activation function
will tell you whether you something like
gradient descent move to the left to the
right right so that is the local error
that you want to compute for all the
output layer and then for the hidden layer
the delta Z right the same thing delta
Z is you want to see how much adjustment
you want to make at the input here so
that at the end you are in front of
the error at the output right you have
the error at the output is further away
from here this error at the output
actually will come from when you adjust
this will also affect the error of this
too therefore you have to sum the error
of output you need multiply with the
assisting weight WKJ something up back
to here that become the error before
you move to the front right once you
move to the front you have to multiply
with the gradient of the activation function
this is how you try to remember the formula
right look at the picture try to see
okay this is the error I need to compute
at first is the TK minus OK right when
I move it to the forward I multiply with
the gradient of the activation function
right then you have all the error at the
output layer then for the hidden layer
because when I change this you affect
all this error you have to sum them up
weight them back here then move to the
front multiply with the gradient of the
activation again so it's not difficult
to remember once you have a charge right
even this is very complex it just trace
the error term right and sum them up
move here right as long as there's a link
you have to make sure you move the error back
right it may not be so so-called structure
every every unit connect to other unit
so these are the two key formula you
compute the error this one is already
no forward propagation and this is a
backward propagation after you have the error
then you know how to adjust the weight
for example WKJ will be the error at this
output following node delta K
multiply with the output OZ
multiply with the eta W right when you
look at the picture it's very straightforward
right when you have the computer
adjustment do this weight you multiply the
error here multiply the output here
multiply that learning rate eta and
that's it and similarly for the bias
because the bias you can consider it is
a spatial unit of output one with the
weight BZ so the delta BZ will be
equal to again the error term delta Z
multiply with output here is equal to one
therefore you don't have the OI here
because it's equal to one multiply with the
eta B right this is all the adjustment
you will make to all the parameter here
and that's it that will be your back
propagation formula it is once you put
them into this charge it seems to be not
so complicated just trace the error trace
the output right and then you can imagine
that all this intermediate value right
the net Z because you need this the net K
the output OK the output right the OZ
OI the error term delta Z delta K
you have to store them in your memory
right when you have an input that all
depend on your input train data every
sample here you recompute all this OZ
net Z and delta ZK right then all has to
be stored in your memory then you can
make the adjustment W right so that is
a part that they need a lot of RAM and
your GPU memory right if you want to
train a big network and likely you need
to have many many gigs
typically the one that you are using
for your personal PC maybe 4G
6 gigabyte maybe 12 16 maybe 32 is
already a lot but those are server you
could expect by 100 200 or minimum 40 80
they can have a gigabyte memory for the
training purpose so if your activation
function is this a sigmoid as I show
in the last lecture you can show that
your gradient of the activation function
sigma prime it will become sigma
that net K times one sigma net K
sigma net K will be equal to OK
basically what this output like net K
is input after you apply the activation
function become the OK so it become
OK 1 minus OK and I show this in the last
lecture the derivative of this right
you can get this and similarly for net
Z sigma prime is equal to OZ 1 minus OZ
right and the remaining is still the same
right for red rule right and you can
see this is even simpler for red rule
you just check whether the net K is
positive or negative it is a positive
value then this equal to one net
sigma prime net K equal to one if it's
a negative value the net input then the
similar prime net equal to zero that
means no error will be propagated if the
input is zero yeah this way we cover
in the last lecture and of course after
that for every sample training sample
you do all the adjustment then you
continue to repeat this process for all
the rest of the training samples and
again and again if one time that is not
enough because you can see the net
work is changing right the W keep
changing even you have used this
sample before but by the time you
finish all the training sample that
net work is already different so you
can reuse the point again to continue
to move this so-called W towards the
right direction and and you repeat this
until a termination condition is met
which could be the error is small
enough the E or J W is very little I
think in some of the example we saw
earlier you can see drop then right
tapper off okay the error and then all
until all the delta W delta B the
adjustment become very small right and
that means not much change to the net
work or until you run out of time right
it's have been too long right and then
you just want to just terminate and
the weights and the bias can be updated
in the in some different way we thought
avoid case updating is every sample you
change the delta W the W and B right so
the net work keep changing for every
sample and that become very chaotic like
the example we show in the decision 3
right you could have a two feature
exactly the same but output different so
they mean in one sample you move this W
to this direction in the next example
you move it back right so it's going to
be very noisy every sample the network
keep changing so which has its merit
but normally we don't do that if you
have a lot training sample so the other
way is called airport updating or
you put up training which when you
train this train the network you do not
adjust the parameter right away you just
accumulate all the delta W delta B but
you don't change the network the input
another sample you accumulate the delta
W delta B so you can't take how averaging
all the possible changes you're supposed to
make only at the end after you have seen
all the training sample you take the
average of all the delta W delta B
update the network at the end of the
airport right so they mean the delta
delta B can move randomly at the end
you just take the mean value of all those
changes it will be more stable but it will
be slower the network will not update
immediately and therefore you can
consider the compromise between the two
previous approaches by using
stochastic gradient descent which you
randomly sample a set of training
sample and then which you do all the
compute all the W B W delta W delta B
then you take the average update the
network then sample another set of
training data so you repeat this so
they mean the network is updated after
you have seen certain number of
training sample and then you keep them
the same until you have exorbit the
selected number of selected samples
then you repeat this until all the
sample have been used for the training
right they cause stochastic gradient descent
okay that is the
that propagation so the few following
slide I'm going to show you how we
derive the delta K delta Z and delta W
delta B I label that as optional so they
mean if you really do not like to know
how those formula come from you can
skip them but I have to mention this
because the formula you have seen the
adjustment delta K delta W and or delta
error term they are all based on this
sum of square error right if this error
term is no longer the same which like
the will be the case for some of the
network you'll see one later then the
whole formula will change then you have
to derive those formula again right so
it's therefore it's important to know the
step how you derive those formula as
and when when you change your error
function which most likely so then you
can do the derivative again for those
formula this of course the gradient
descent remain unchanged the only thing
is the error function so we we mentioned
earlier for this particular error function
and this is a delta K for output unit
delta Z for any input unit and this is
the adjustment you make okay all these
adjustment formula this and this and
this only true when your error function
is this okay if the error function is not
some of square error then this set of
formula will change okay so let's look at
one how even with this error function
how do we get this set of formula delta
K delta J and delta W delta B and this
is of course this activity function you
could have a sigmoid you could have
other right so for sigmoid then your
delta K become this delta J from here
become this but for other activity
function it may not have this kind of
formula okay let's look at how to
compute the delta K here right this is
output unit and you have a TK at the
output target output here TK okay so
again this is a typical network formula
you have seen this before so your goal is
now to see how to adjust this the delta
WKJ okay and for that you need to
compute the gradient delta E and delta W
KJ this is a part that you need to see
how to link this term to the variable
that you already know or you want to
compute so E is here the error between
TK minus OK square sum of square error
and WKJ is here right so as a rule of
thumb you need to express E in term of
eventually WKJ right otherwise you cannot
so-called change the fact how much you
need to change but E is not related to WKJ
immediately but E you know there is a
function of okay so you can use this kind
of change rule right rather than delta E
delta KJ you can introduce intermediate
variable in between right E is a function
of okay you can take this partial
derivative then okay is a function of
net K right because okay equal to the
activation function net K then net K is
now a function of WKJ right because net K
equal to summation J WKJ OJ plus BK right
and that's all you have so this is a
change rule the rule that you have learned
in your calculus either in the JC or in
your uni level one right so then this
delta E delta okay is very straightforward
because only okay will change you are
going to get this minus TK minus okay
two and two cancel each other out so it's
from this term only for that particular K
right and then you have this TK minus okay
the rest of the TK okay because they are
at the different output you need they
will become irrelevant only that's
specific K okay could be two could be three
could be 100 you have this minus TK minus
okay and this is nothing but the
derivative of the activation function
right and this one is very simple
because there's only one term which is
depending on this specific KJ again KJ
can be a very specific number like three
and five okay so therefore you leave with
this OJ okay and you put them together
you can write as a minus delta K OJ
and where delta K is sigma from K TK minus
okay the error term we introduce error
term so that the change here will be
minus A W delta K and OJ here
okay so these two are the one that you
saw earlier right so it's nothing just do
the gradient descent to minimize the
error by adjusting this parameter WKJ
then you express this error in term of WKJ
if not immediately you go to the
intermediate variable like okay and net
K then you reach the WKJ applying
change rule right and then that is the
formula you use but bear in mind that this
only apply to when error is sums of
square if you change this error to other
term then you go to this process and this
term will change right and you'll see what
will happen to this term the other two
term line will remain because these are
the network then you can adjust your
formula accordingly okay then what
happened to delta Z the one at the
hidden layer although I only show one
hidden layer you can generate this to
multiple hidden layer they all apply
this same formula okay from the
foreign unit and come back here so again
what you need to do is this to find out
what is the adjustment you need to make
to this the delta WJI here and again
E because it is not really immediately a
function of WJI then you have to go to
some intermediate parameter which is
delta E delta OZ output here then delta
OZ delta net Z which is simple we have
seen this before then delta net Z can be
expressed as a function of WJI which is
this these two terms are the same as
the earlier one the only difference now is
this right because E and OJ are still
quite far away right so you can now
write this further you can OZ is actually
not immediately inferencing E but E
depends on okay and okay actually can be
a function of OZ right so you further do
the change rule here right so this is
delta okay delta OZ E now you have two
of them delta E delta okay and then delta
okay delta OZ right then this one now
net K OZ you can write this formula so at
the end this is a derivative of this then
you have this right so therefore it's a
bit more complex and this is nothing but
again you trace the error you sum them back
to link this output to the OZ so
therefore at the end you have this formula
with the delta Z slightly more complex
than the delta K but this is the same
delta WJ had the same formula okay so
optional but do take a look and and and
these two slides to be quite a while to put
everything together so at least using the
notation we have been using so that at
least you can appreciate right actually I
was tempted by I didn't so far haven't
done that is I change this error term
want you to derive all these change of
the formula right that is very typical
that for some research you had to do it
okay question anyone then we have this
example right and this example once you
understand how to do that this example
is nothing by just plug in the number to
get the output right so in this example
you have a 3 2 1 network 3 input unit
2 hidden unit and 1 output unit okay 3 2
1 right the input is x 1 x 2 x 3 output is 0 6
you can label this unit as a 1 2 3 4 5 6
right then the W will be W 4 1 normally
use the the other end 4 1 W 4 2 5 1 5 2 5 3
so you have 3 times 2 weight right 3 times
2 weight plus 2 times 1 okay plus what are
the other variables that you have
plus 3 the bias right for 4 5 6 bias right
so you are going to have 11 yeah
variables and that's here 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
right and of course the bias of course you
can although I didn't plot the bias here
by the indicator is a bias in the parameter
if you want and which some people do this
you can draw a bias unit B right which
you connect to here connect to here connect
to here okay and this output is always
equal to 1 it's a bias unit and then you
have this equal to B4 the weight B4 and
B5 and B6 right you do see some people
do that then to explicitly tell you
there's a bias unit and this bias unit
again output is always equal to 1 the
OB is always equal to 1 then you have B4 B5 B6
3 different one okay and there is a
network okay similar here is it okay
that I connect this one to here have
this a W6 1 anything wrong with that
can I bypass the hidden layer connect
the output input directly to the output
input to the output units can I do that
can okay and which is equivalent to you
could introduce a hidden layer doing
nothing one in one assuming you have a
virtual hidden unit which is taking
input and just pass the output with the
linear activity function to 6 so it can
still be MLP right just for convenience
now your W your net 6 will be equal to
X1 multiplied with W61 plus W04
multiplied W64 plus O5 multiplied W65
plus B6 okay there will be your net input
right so just look at the picture then
you can figure out how to compute the net
input and output so these are the given
number now you have this training
sample 101 the target output is one so
they mean the T6 is equal to one the
target output and then the learning rate
eta is the same for both the weights and
the bias equal to 0.9 is such a large
number then of course in your calculation
you follow the step that we show earlier
you first given this X equal to 101 you
do the forward propagation right this
input 101 to the unit 4 5 and 6 you have
101 then this is also X1 X2 X3 then you
have the 4 which is equal to the
summation of this W41 times O1 plus W42
times O2 plus W43 times O3 plus OB4
okay and they plug in the number here
you get minus 0.7 which is the net 4
this is a net 4 then to get the O4 you
apply the activation function in this
case is a sigmoid 1 divided by 1 plus E
minus net 4 which is equal to 0.332
this is the O4 okay this is O4
output of the unit 4 then similarly O5
the same thing you compute the net 5
if it's 0.1 then compute the O5 which is
1 divided by 1 plus E minus net 5
equal to 0.525 so the output here this is
0.32 0.525 then for 6
unit the net input will be the W64
multiply with 0.332 then W65
multiply with 0.525 plus the bias B6 is 0.1
B6 0.1 here right then you have the
output 06 equal to no net 6 equal to
minus 0.105 the net 06 equal to 0.4
0.474 which is different from your
target output T6 equal to 1 right so quite far away
therefore you have an error right so this is just
a forward propagation that you get your 0405
and the actual output 06 okay
then you have the computer error error is a
because now you only you now have the 06
you know it's different from T6 now you
compute the error at the unit 6 first okay this is a
step that sometimes students just overlook they will
try to compute all delta 4 and delta 5 this is a
delta unit Z here error term
and before you compute
delta 4 delta 5 you need to get delta 6 because
delta 4 and 5 had to come from 6 so you compute this
this is the formula right sigma prime net K which is
okay 1 minus okay plus TK is 1
then the okay is 0.474
just so coincident that it's same to 1 minus okay
then you have this old error term
in the unit 6 is 0.1311
similarly you apply this formula in this case you only
have 1 therefore no need to have a summation but just multiply them
together so you have the delta 4 delta 5
right so 1 you have the delta 4 delta 5 delta
6 then you can compute
changes right which is
this is original value this is the delta
K Z delta Z i that you need to compute
right based on the error you have compute for
delta 4 5 6 then this will be the new
weights and bias 11 of them you can
compute right so once
you have done that you can check your new error
output will be if you apply the
101 again you will find that the actual output
now will reduce will be will be increased towards
the 1 larger than 0.474
the original output and closer to the
target output 1 okay
so that is the back
propagation example
question anyone have any question before we move on
okay once you have the basic
MLP now you would like to use it to process different types of data
and in the early day of course the image
will become one of the popular data
that you want to recognize object inside images
and then if you apply just
MLP for image input you will find that it is going to be
challenging because the image you have
a lot of so called pixel value
it will try to connect them let's say image if you have an image input
here like image
it could be a lot of pixel value if every pixel
becomes one of your input every pixel
so you could have a very very high dimensional input
assuming you have a thousand by thousand pixel which is already
one million direction input and then the number
will be huge in this case for example just consider
200 by 200 pixels
3 here because of color image you have RGB for those
who are familiar with RGB
image you know that the color you need 3
value to represent the color so that means your input is already
200 by 200 by 3 in terms of the
feature value you just assume that you only
have 10 hidden units 10 of them
and that original every pixel
can connect to a unit with the weights
then you are going to have 1.2
million parameters the weights
so just one layer with 10
which is normally not really a big network to do anything
so therefore for
image if you want to input as image and this is the so called
data structure for an image you have RGB
you have to do something so called different because
if you are going to have many many this input then
you need a large number of parameters even just for 10
hidden units and you can end up with these
too many parameters and which
become so called a problematic in your
so called training because it will create these overfitting problems
here just one illustration for example
if you want to fit all these training data the
docs input and output by using a
line y equal to a plus bx right this could be
a so called a regression problem it's not perfect
but it allows you to estimate what will be the output
of any unseen input x as long as
it's within this range right and if you want to do better
you can introduce a slightly higher order
second order so called parametric curve
now you can see that it can fit the data better
but there are still certainly some error for some other
sample about okay of course if you are still not satisfied
with the error you say okay you just need to be perfect
then you can continue to increase your so called
order of your curve right up to certain point
it can fit to all your training data
perfectly right in fact there is a formula like how many
order you need given how many sample data but that doesn't mean
this is better in some sense for unseen data for example if you have
a one new data which you have not used for training you come here
it may give you a very high output
which is very different from what you would expect right
let's say it's a housing rental price right this is the
the side of the house and this is the price of the
rental price so this one seem to be anomaly right
smaller than this unit and this unit charge cheaper than this
unseen tax so there is called overfitting problem
because to some level you start to fit the
noise because the train sample may have noise right
rather than the fundamental structure or
train of the so called data
so here is one illustration
this green curve show the error there here you
can continue to minimize your error of the training sample
by increasing the complexity of your
model okay but for unseen data
test data the error may start to reduce first
up to certain point if your network become more and more complex
you have more and more unit of the perceptron and the test
data error may go up to another direction
so that mean your model is no longer
suitable for the test data because you
try to overfit to your training data so this is the point
that you can charge that perhaps
this will be the right order above this your test data
will not work as well as the training data
so therefore it's very important to keep a set
of test data to validate the network
trained by the training data whether it is
good enough so underfitting or overfitting
then for images
then they come up with this so called
a spatialized or simplified form of multi-layer
perceptron where the weights
are shared through convolutional filter
so I walk through this network quickly so that you get some sense
although it looks complex but in general this is a
simplified version of your multi-layer perceptron
the goal is I want to
control the number of parameters
this is immu data if you connect this data
you call into a vector so you actually have a long
input so called vector x1 to x
perhaps 28 by 28 by 3
but this would not
so called retain the so called
the specific data arrangement inside the image
because for image you know that it's a spatial
or 3D data and object who located together in
the space should be appearing together in the image
in some local area so if you
break the image into a vector then those objects will
somehow spread into different places it will not look like
an object at all so they want to keep the original
so called space conceptually like this
so then if you just look at one layer
this one layer forget about the other we call this a convolutional layer
this one layer is actually all the perceptron
unit the perceptron earlier on you see they are
in one column now I arranged them in the spatial
like image form and every
perceptron can take input from the input image
but I restrict the connection such that this particular neuron
only look at the small area of the image
right in front of it earlier on MOP can connect
to all the input value but that will create a lot of
weights and bias oh sorry weights
but now this neuron can only look at a small region just right in front
just like your eyes when your eyes try to focus on certain spot
nor all those around this but you focus your eye on this spot
okay so what it does is it now will immediately
reduce the number of weights possible to connect to this particular neuron
and not just that if I move this neuron to
the next neuron which also connect to the other
small region of the input picture right next to the
earlier one I want to force the weights to be the same
because when I scan through an image there is no reason
I look at the different location using different so called
emphasis right when you scan through it should be the same
so that allow me to reduce the weights substantially
right for the whole set of neuron
so that create if I continue to do that to form many many
neuron in one layer and each neuron can
each perceptron can only have a smaller number
of weights connected to the input right in front of this perceptron
right and then the weights W, K, Z, W, J, I
will be all the same even you come from different
neuron right neuron perceptron so that
will allow me to create one layer of hidden
layer right but then you
even argue why are so distinctive right
why there is only one set of weights by right every
perceptron could have very different weights then you create another
layer which allow you to use another set of weights
so this layer every layer
is one set of the weights which is the same for all the perceptron
right then you allow variation
so in physical meaning that mean when I look for object inside
the image this particular weight may be looking for
whether there is an H right
I can use another weight to look for whether there is a surger
I can use another set of weight to look for whether
certain kind of color appear in the image so that mean
you could have as many of this feature maps each one
of them use a certain set of weights and that
weights can be trained you do not have to figure out what
number going to that you just provide this kind of structure
so that it can learn the weights which
minimized the error at the end so that is the idea behind
convolutional neural network the reason
they do that is to simplify the MLP to reduce
or to control the number of weights and there are also
reason behind it because for those if you have learned image processing
you know that this convolution the weights is actually
equivalent to a set of filter in image processing
the filter is like what you have learned in signal and system
or signal digital signal processing like low pass, high pass,
band pass, edge detection, corner detection
those filtering process so that is basically the
idea but they do not pre-specified what kind of filter you need
they learn the weights by using a lot of training
sample that create the first
hidden layer but because of this unique structure
of the weights restriction and also look at the region they call it
convolutional layer and that has a physical
image processing meaning behind convolutional operation
okay and then after
that you could apply this called pooling this is nothing but
just reduce the number of data combine 4 of them
into 1 right the still the same 10 feature map
this had no learning process at all just try to
control the number of the data site
then you could now apply another convolution layer
but this one now is you have a filter but it is not just
apply to one layer of data you can actually apply to all the
layer of the data right just like
earlier on this filter apply to the 3 color plane RGB
plus the local spatial region now this one could apply to
a small let's say 3 by 3 plus all the 10 layer
input that is your input data now to one of the
perceptron here you still control the weights had to be the same
for the same conversion layer in this case you create
the total 20 set of filter weights
they do the pooling again and until the data site now
is smaller but you have 20 layer like this then
at the end you can also call fact then basically
concatenate all the data into a
line vector that we seen at a normal MLP now you have
a one column of x input right we call this a
fracturing process then this will be the typical MLP connect to everyone
right which connect to all the input data down to
10 so this is the CFA 10
classification at the end you want to see what object
the class of the 10 that belong then there is
a softmax activation function we will draw a body later
which give you the output of 0 to 1 and the
one with the largest output value between 0 to 1 will be the
classes that you are looking for so that is a convolutional
network and it is also known as
a CNN or convex
and the filtering process the perceptron multiply with the same
weight it is nothing but this you have this weight equal
101 010 101 basically
when you compute the output in the
conversion layer each of the value depend on the input
then go to become the net Z then go
to the activation function you compute this 434
for color then your weight will be 3 of them so is this one
is the filter of 3 times 3 you have 9 value
each time they go to your input data output
sorry the output data for the previous layer
these are the value in the first layer will be your input image
then you do the multiplication with your weights and sum them up
that will be the output
now you have to compute the output of the
perceptron unit at the next layer
so you see that if you start to
imagine the picture if you have your images
which is 100 by 100 pixel and then you have
many many of this filter K and you have many layer
and many hidden layer and your training data you could have
create a lot of computation you need for you to compute
like if you try to imagine your
black propagation all the OZ, OI, WB
sorry the delta K, delta Z
delta W, delta B for every
input send image so a lot of weights and adjustment you need
therefore you need GPU and that can do very very
intensive computation for the learning process
here is another view to look at
the convolutional layer and which again this is input
image data this is one of the perceptron unit
you have a set of weights here multiply with the input data
multiply with the weights then you just get the output of this particular
perceptron
and then this weight will be the same where you move
all the compute the perceptron for all the other
location at other location within this so called layer
we call this a feature map or convolutional layer this is a
one map feature map this feature map depend on
what filter you use every filter you create one feature
map one layer of feature map
this sometimes people call activation map because it's activation
function output and the weights that you use is called
kernel or the filters so example
you have this input image and this is
so called the weights the filter and this could be learned by
some training so you apply the first filter here
which is a particular weight you want to create a feature
map you go through this you scan through
basically you multiply this so called weights
with the corresponding input image the area
then you kind of compute them scan through then you
get the first feature map which is in the foreign
hidden layer so this feature map
basically look at whether there are vertical so called lines
in the image because of this particular filter
try to detect changes along this so called X direction
I mean looking for vertical line that create a one
feature map here one layer
of the feature map which look at whether there are vertical
so called line then you can select
the second filter which go through again create
another feature map in this case you have 3 by
6 18 feature map
18 layer in the conversion layer
ok so the number of the feature maps
in each conversion layer depend on the number of the filters
how many filter you have decide how many feature maps you have
and the feature map also depend on
the filter side and other operation like the strike
zero padding and pooling we are going to talk about this operation
in the following slides
so your convolutional
neural network is basically efficiently reduce the number of parameter
as compared to the general multi-layer
perceptron that we mentioned earlier
I hope you
you don't see this like
why there are so called deep theory behind
all the operation you are going to see later is basically try to control the number of
weights because if you just use the traditional MLP
the weights number will be
too big for you to handle so all this operation is
actually try many many operation
the goal is how can I reduce the number of weights but still maintain
certain performance right so this strike is
one way just now we talk about the filter move around the images
you can move one picture by one picture
you know that the images within the small neighborhood
they look very similar or you can move by every other
picture or every five pictures right so by moving
skid some of the local then your output feature map will be smaller
because only one location you get one output and I will get one output
so this is called strike
how the filter move around the input to reduce
the side of the output for example in this case strike equal to one so that mean
every time including assuming these three are the
feature value the connection right this one each time you move one
this is input data each time you already move one location one picture
right this one move one move one move one so you
get the output here or you can each time you move two
picture here move two picture here
stay immediately you reduce the side from
five to three and you can do this for
2D again this is the blue color is the input data
and the gray three by three is the filter
the weights and the green one is the output in the
convolutional layer the feature map so
you can see that strike equal to two every time this filter jump
two picture to the right and then you create
every time jump two picture you get one output so you change from
five by five input image to
three by three output convolutional layer
feature map and that is called strike right the
larger the strike value that mean you skip more picture you create
the output which is smaller
and you sometimes also need to do zero padding
like this case because when you want to compute
this particular so called output center here
you find that some of this filter value will be outside
right and which origin is not have value so you can
pad rows or column of zero outside
so that you can still compute the output of
this particular location right zero padding is how many
row or column of zero you pad
and you can now the input data
so that output can still get some value
for those picture at the boundary
and pooling is another operation which is basically try to reduce the number
of the output like earlier on when we talk about this
network right we say oh this is a pooling layer basically reduce
four by four picture become one
operation it doesn't really have any so called physical
reason behind I just want to reduce the number of
data as long as the performance doesn't decree much
so you can have max pooling basically
you take four value right then take keep only the maximum
value one two three the maximum value is three
then you move one picture strike equal to one to the right
so you take this four value two two three five and then
take the maximum is five so and then you move one unit
two two five seven maximum is seven
right then you move one unit down here two three zero two
then the maximum is two so this color behind just show you
where this so called mask is located
so this called maximum pooling with a two by two filter
and strike one or you can do the average pooling
right the maximum you take the average value of this four picture
become two then strike two you move two
picture to the right here right the average become four
right this how you reduce the data in the
pooling layer right or you can use even the
L2 norm computer L2 norm of the input
data okay all this operation is again
the goal is try to reduce the number of weights
and in your struct in your network
so another operation
which is again there are many many such so called little tricks
and so called small changes in the
network all the idea is see how I can
minimize the error output and make
the network can do the classification or prediction
better so one of them is called regularization
okay so in fact if you recall when I
thought about one single neuron I say oh when you try to do the n
function there are many possible lines can do
the job right you can separate the one class from the other
so that is without regularization
but for SVM you will always find the line give you the maximum
margin so if you recall in SVM
when you try to find the so called the boundary
you try to minimize this weight
the vector right divided by two right when we
try to find the SVM right not just here to do the classification
correctly allow you to classify one and zero
you also want to find the boundary which give you the maximum margin
and that margin the way you find is minimizing this
W L2 norm divided by two
right so that is actually the idea for perceptron
you have many possible line can I find the line which
maximize the margin in the training right although I do not
know it as SVM but in my training I have
a few possible value can I find the one which give me the
maximum margin which is the regularization
this is the original JW the error function basically tell the class target
and the output whether they are the same or close
to each other you can add on another error
or cost function right it's not error anymore therefore
it's a loss function or cost function which is a function of the
weights right so if you look at this L2
regularization is a risk you find that what they
try to minimize you know object to minimize this error right is this
L2 norm which is the same as this
you just append the original error by another
loss function or cost function which is
a parameter of your weights so this L2
regularization is equivalent to I find the boundary
can minimizing the weight ideally should be zero at the same time
I maximize the margin L2 norm which is
SVM therefore the neural network
by adding this regularization it
actually will make the network more robust to noise
when your train data has noise you will find the one
not just give you the best classification
or prediction possible minimizing the error
you also find the one give you the maximum margin
once you have that you can think of oh I could think of other
so-called cost function right L1 regularization
or a combination of L1 part L2 norm called elastic
net regularization you cannot introduce another parameter
beta and all this beta, alpha and this become
the weights or parameter that you can optimize
right so there is the connection between
neural network with SVM
if you just introduce this regularization perhaps the network you
train will give you the SVM result okay but you don't have to
remember when we compute the SVM we have to go through this
this is a very complex set of formula
right find the solution find the
support vector for that you decide now you just learn you don't even need to
care about the formula you just train data target data
you are converged hopefully to what you want
so another form of regularization is this
early stopping we saw this earlier right when you train your train
data error you set aside a test data set to
compute the validation or test error so when you compare this
until the test error start to increase again you can
do a early stop so this early stopping
is another kind of regularization try to regular the
network so that or control the network so that it doesn't fit
the same as SVM doesn't really
so called try to fit those
error to the network and there are many other
and some of you may heard about this drop out
drop out is another form of regularization try to make the network
more robust because the network could be very
complex you only use some of the perceptron to do the
learning in some training process
then with that
operation then how do you compute the data side from one level to
the other let me see so I will just cover this then
okay maybe two more slides then we will take a
break after you come back I will show some of the
program maybe some additional exercise
so that you can have better appreciation of this
so one of the thing that we want to
know right if you have an input data
image data side then when you try to
design your network you have a convolution layer you have
more than one convolution layer and pooling layer what will be the
output data side right so that depend on as we
look at the output data side number
depend on the strike number depend on the filter number
depend on the pooling number so if you look at operation carefully
you can delay the weight and
high of this so called hidden layer
from the previous weight and high of the
so called previous layer for example if you have this
one you have the w2h2 the width and the high and the
depth d2 right the d2 you know that how many
feature that you have depend on just how many
set of filter you have okay right early on we talk about 10
20 filter then you have 10 and 20 so called
depth okay and then the width and the
high will be delay to w2 will be equal to
w1 minus f f is the filter side early on we have seen
3 by 3 that means this is 3 p is how many
row of 0 you insert in on one side
you have by s plus 2 okay so that
you can figure out what is the width of the foreign layer
why is the high foreign layer let's take one example
w minus f plus 2 p divided by s right here
in this case your input level w1 h1 is 5
so h1 w1 is 5 by 5
your s is equal to 2 your
pooling layer is equal p is equal to 1
because you have one row of 0 or one color
of 0 on one side okay so 5
by 5 the filter is 3 by 3
so 5 minus 3
you have 2 right plus 2 times 1 you have 4
divided by 2 strike equal to 2 become 2 plus
1 you have 3 therefore output is 3 by 3
okay so if you continue through
that you can see that output if you apply another 3 by 3 filter
and strike equal to 2
p in this case also equal to 1 you will see what is the next level
output okay this
apply to h as well so your input
data this is the image you can consider this is a d0
w0 h0 d0 equal to 3 because you have a color
image w0 h0 will be equal to 32 by 32
so remember this formula later on when we look at some of the
so-called neural network like lernet, lxnet
you can use it to compute the data site verify yourself
why the number look like that right like this lernet
so the lernet actually is the one that we
show earlier yang le kun use it to compute
this
digit recognize the mnist digit
output 0 to 9 right so input
is a 32 by 32 digit number
so in the first layer they have 6
feature maps let me use a 6 filter to create
the first so-called convolutional layer
and then it does a sub-sampling this is a pooling
a pooling process 28 by 20 become 14 by 14 there is still keep the
number of layers 6 then there is a conversion layer
now they use a 16 filter right you have this
now 10 by 10 you should try to compute how to get from 22
38 by 38 to 14 by 14 then
10 by 10 but it's using some formula earlier pooling is
easy 2 by 2 you basically reduce the dimension
of 2 in each height of width then you have
another 16 with 5 by 5 then
after that you collect them into a convolutional
fully connected network for 3 of them so output
is 10 so this is the first
conversion level neural network used for
like the mdist digit recognition it has 2
conversion layer 1 and 2
with 3 with average pooling so this is a
1 average pooling layer 2 average pooling layer then
3 fully connected network 1 2 3 this is MLP
right all this can connect to each other all the input
and then the output is a softmax function
this is a very special kind of activation
function if you want to think it like that so earlier on remember
for activation function if you take the net input you apply the nonlinear function
you get the output okay so this one
OI is you have the net Z net I the net input
to the unit but rather than you apply a nonlinear function
you actually raise it to the power of E net I
for each of them then you normalize it with a sum
for all the net I so what will this do
it will make this OI between 0 the value between 0 to 1
right and the summation of all the OI here
will be equal to 1 so it kind of transform any output
value it could be negative could be positive to
a value which is between 0 to 1 and the sum
is equal to 1 kind of transform the output
value to some kind of probability space which the highest
value tell you this cast
belong to this this image belong to this particular cast
so therefore the classification now become finding the value of OI
after this a softmax right the one
having the largest OI value and there is also the
kind of probability of the object belong to this cast Y
okay so this is a very special
activation function applied to the output unit here
only here and for the error function because the output
is only 1 and 0 for classification problem so it doesn't
use the so called the sum of square error because
most of them will be 0 only the one which is the cast Y
1 will be have a value will have a value close to 1
so it use this a spatial error function TK is
the actual output okay
target output okay is actual output so most of this
TK will be 0 except the one which is the correct cast
so that mean log okay multiplied by TK
will be 0 for all the rest except
that target cast which is 1 log okay
and this okay will have a value between 0 to 1 the closer
to 1 the smaller this value will be
then the smaller negative value the smaller this error will be
for the rest will be very large value but since their TK equal to 0
it will not contribute to the error term so this is
called cross entropy lost
only for output equal to 1 and 0 so that mean if you
use the error function like this the earlier back
the equation algorithm will not apply to this case
you have to recompute all the delta K delta Z W
right because now the error function change
which you can do it easily because you can do the partial derivative of this
to okay something that we have seen earlier right it's a log function
so that is learn at
agree here function okay let's take a break here
come back at 1125
then we'll continue the rest pass some program
and exercise
okay
okay so so there is again just to try it out to see how fast and how easy it is
of course this problem can also be solved by using decision three right and in fact you think carefully
if I had this problem to you I could ask the question right if I have this two-dimensional data belonging to two classes and like this
and what are the other classifier what give me three possible classifier you can do to separate
one class from the other right we just talk about SVM right what else
three possible four at least you can learn quite a number right to separate
the to do the classification job
anyone beside SVM what else can you use
beside SVM what else can you use
huh
yes K nearest neighbor right one or two in fact the assignment
is asking you to find the region which belong to what class I just so happened I have more
point than the sixth I use in the example
K nearest neighbor can also do the job what else
SVM K nearest neighbor what else
huh
RNN
what is RNN recurrent
neural network we will talk about it but there is more suitable for sequential data
although you can still program it in do this but it may not be the most efficient
how about decision tree
decision tree
can you do decision
three to do this you have two input X1
X2 yes you can right the next one is a decision
tree right decision tree
right train the data okay and then this is a model
fitting using decision tree and you can have this
right and that allow you to create this decision
tree but now they look at X1 less than this using entropy
52 and 4 right rather than
I ask those so called classes
I say okay if the X2 less than this value X1
right so at the end I can classify most of them correctly
so and this is a boundary I use to classify
one class to the other right so it can be very
generic okay decision tree of course
yeah this is one you can program it then the other
is just how a student ask me for the
multi-layer perceptron can I have a so called
output value which is not classes not binary
right here is one okay so I show you the
simple the so called curve you want to fit a line or
curve to the data right now today I have this very complex function
these are train data I give you only X and Y of course
when I create this data I have some very simple function
right cos sign sign and then using random
variable 800 of them then I create another test
set data which is another 200 so I use 80% for training
to 20% for testing right so it look like this
if you do not know the original function
then I only give you input and output X output is Y
so can you build a MLP
multi-layer perceptron to approximate
to do the prediction given X predict what is the value of Y
then become a regression problem right so and then
you see in another way it's very easy I just create a multi-layer
perceptron input is one unit look at this
this is input layer only one unit X right the active unit function is linear
because whatever input I give to the output
so let's try to create a
a layer
which has a 64 unit okay let me run this one
okay
so I first create a now I'm using the
runtime okay a GPO it's a
CPU you locate me a CPU rather than
you do this you take a while
okay so I use the
200 okay now it's a once
one unit input then 64 hidden layer unit and one unit
output so 164.1 so now it's doing the
train the training process right using one
April or 800 sample it could be using the error
right now I train for how many
I train for
100 okay so now
this output right with 64 hidden
because the input data so compare I can only come up with this
line to approximate this yeah it does something
but really error is
8 right this is one of the training data this is a test data error
always larger than this okay certainly not good enough
right so then that's how you think about one 64 unit
and one there's only one layer right then you know that okay
it with only one hidden layer each one is a one line
right one line is one D that so each one is a basically
try to predict a value of a line
then certainly even combine many line together this is the best
it can do so apparently this one you need to have more than
one layer let me add another layer of
128 okay
okay let's
try to run everything again
so now I have a one 128 and 64
so two hidden layer the first layer had one 28 unit
the second layer 64 this is number of weights and
bias now you see the result okay it
seem to be better now like than 60
okay so I see you the training is a model 15
very simple when you do the training just call this function
you specify the network this is the network you need to construct
MLP this is the key to create the network
it's quite easy just specify how many unit you want
what is the error function what is the activation function error is a mean
square error right the one that we have and then we
use a rectangular linear unit right to all
now with 128 and 64
it does better job
then at least try to fit certain component error now
is at least much better earlier on 60 something now drop to 40
something right and this case interesting the
test error is even smaller than the training error
normally it's the other way around for some cases because the network is
still not good yet okay let's try to create one more hidden layer
another 64
I create now 128 64
and 64
run everything again
yeah this is the training
now is better less than 40
wow
even less than
3 okay now you see
this is one layer
so that is the idea of
so called
universal approximator
as long as I have many many unit
I can go to the same
back propagation the gradient descent find how many parameter
here I have about
12,739 trainable parameter
right 12,700
plus weights and mires
just by using 1,800
I can solve this 12,000
give me this right this is not bad
right not bad
this is a training error the blue one is the training
error the red one is the test error
because I create the data using the same variance
turn out test and variation train data are performing
same right if my test data are slightly different
using different way to create them it may have a highest error
so that is the MLP
of course convolution in your network this is
amnist okay I put it here I will not go through the detail again
but this is now for image data input right this is
digit image training data
28 by 28 so in here I use the
learn net file right this is how all you need to create the learn net file
right look at it the structure of the network
right so if you go
back to compare to this one you can see it's a convolutional 2D network
using the 10H activation function input data is
28 by 28 break and y image
I use the first filter is a 5 by 5 side the filter
side and then I have a 6 layer
6 activation function map this is all you need you see therefore a lot
of research once you have this template you can change your model
quickly just change the number here you do not really need to do a lot
programming a lot of machine learning is find the right sample code
then whatever you do just add one more line cut and pay
change the activation function change the filter side change the feature
map change the pooling average pooling right
fattening this is a 3 activation function using
sigmoid sigmoid the last layer is a softmax to create
output 0 to 1 and that's all you need to build a network
right if you can learn all this within a day
those writing a lot of paper
okay so let me go back here
so if you just use the network to train and this is a number of
tell you the number of parameters you have you can see that
in here the early stage the number of parameters
is not as large because we try to use
the weights to control the weight therefore the number of
parameters were fewer for those convolutional layer
this pooling layer doesn't have any weight
but at the end during the so-called fully connected network
which is MLP right at the last three layer you can see the number of
parameters increased substantially so normally the earlier part
you need a lot of memory because you have big data
you have to store all this and a lot of computation as well
but the later part you need a lot of sorry you need a lot of parameter
you need a lot of weight early you need a lot of computation later you need a lot of memory to store
all these weights so total there are 44,000
of parameters and this is the training process for the
you see all the training you need to do is this is actually the
the back propagation learning right I use a
cross entropy which is a learn that cross entropy error function rather than
mean square error and this optimizer add them is the
one decide the learning rate right it's not just fix rate
they're based on how the error change where the
direction move in term of the weight and adjust the learning rate
automatically so and then
and then this is a training I use a I think
in here how many airport 20 of them
batch size is 32 so it's a stochastic training process
and then this is a I think it take about
about a few seconds for one airport
so I'm going to run this you can go back and just use the run time run
all you can see the training so and that
allow me to get the error
here right accuracy is close
to one it's quite good close to 100% the loss is 0.050
0.560 right so I could
build another model which is a simpler
right rather than the early one but now I use a rack rule activation function
and and then I can
achieve almost the same performance
and smaller error right then this is
this is the training
accuracy or error this is the training error
and this is a testing I set aside you can see that first they reduce
then they start to speed again so some kind of
overfitting occur at the end right so this is the
blue curve is the training error and this is a testing error
variation loss and training loss
so this is the
version for the cf10 in case you want to try out for real images
so this is the one for the cf10
classes object image classification
actually 110 this is cf10
okay so and
and this is the learn it the one that we just cover
right and this again we have built this learn it before the same thing here
so total now parameter 62,000
and this is where they are so you can use the formula we cover
in the lecture to see how you get all this number
the site of the filter the data
d2h2w2 right and
the number of parameter try to understand how do you how many
weights and bias you need right get an idea so this is
the for the data you can see this one even the network
is not very good and because this is exactly
why the mNIST is good for the chip when they try to
apply to more like complex data like this it doesn't work as well
right the error is actually the accuracy is only of 87%
right sorry 60 70%
right so error is quite big right so I can
another one you can find there just use the same kernel site at
RedGru another cnn you can do and do any kind of
try and error yourself you can achieve better performance
right by reducing this error for training data
but the test data is always challenging now I can achieve 80% accuracy
for training data which I just
randomly or quickly customer another network
so this is AlexNet the one we are going to talk about next
and this is a network they use for
ImageNet the one that Alex
and Suskiver another
openai co-founder and Jeff Hinton right Jeff Hinton again the
Nobel Prize winner so the first network that came out to beat
the ImageNet in the cnn you think carefully
this is very similar to LearnNet you look at the code this is all you need
right for the AlexNet
and this is the code that they auctioned
it for 44 millions Google purchased the company
they start a dnn and auctioned it in
Las Vegas and at the end Google payed 44
million to buy this few lines of code
together with three of them will work for them for a certain
period so and this is number of parameter 21
thousand parameter and you can train the AlexNet
the same thing this is a training process
add them the optimizer to figure out the learning rate
and the cross entropy loss right and then
the training right and you can see the accuracy
here so AlexNet and this is the
validation error not always smooth but this is a training is smoother
but testing depends on how well we have the data is
and then if you train you can save the network into a parameter
and of course other can just load this one to do the training
as well and there are many such a model people have trained
for different application and they will share this as a so called
network parameter online you can go to this
website to download some of these network training
because training takes a lot of time if you have a huge network like the
large language model unlike you can train them yourself
and each training could cost millions of dollars to do that
but after they have trained they could share such a network
parameter available some of some
version or the best version they will not share so go
and try it out in case you find this
necessary for you to do your project or for
your learning so running the program at least you will let you understand
actually it's not so difficult because one of the reason why
machine learning or computer science becomes so popular because
many people share their codes or model
available online and which
you can access almost immediately and for you to do the tuning
changes you just take the template and do some kind of
find so called changes of tuning you do not need to
develop everything from scratch if you know where to look
and where to get those resources that you need
therefore many, many students can do this even
if they are done in secondary school they are doing this kind of training
I didn't teach him he didn't want me to teach so he go and figure out from
youtube and he can also do this
apply to robotics try to recognize signage robot
run away so he doesn't understand
all the mathematics behind but he just follow the step
quite easy for everyone to pick it up
next I would like to cover this
because some students have asked whether they could have
some more example
for
practicing so I have
uploaded this to NTU Learn website so in case you want
to do more practice yourself and this
is actually taken from the last past year homework question
okay so since I already have the solution
I just make it available to you and
of course this year of course your question are not the same
so therefore you can look at this to get more practice
so today in particular let's look at this network
and in this question I have solution here
you can go back to check but I will suggest you to try out
first before you look at the solution okay same password
before you look at solution
this is how you
compute the decision network
decision 3 and last year I even asked to calculate this
so-called performance indicator measure and this is
the solution for the second part is a bit
tedious but you can take a look at it
so this question let's come back to the
question again so this question asks you a
simple network a 2-1-2-newner network
okay 2 input layer 1 hidden unit and then
2 output layer I label them as 1 2 3
4 5 unit number okay and the weights
are initialized randomly as indicated in figure
1 that means W 3 1 is equal to 0.1
W 3 2 equal to 0.2
W 4 3 equal to 0.2
W 5 3 equal to 0.3 right and then
the bias at the unit 3
4 5 although I didn't plot it I initialize it as
0.500 okay so again you can have a bias
unit connect to 3 4 5 okay
assume that the back
propagation algorithm is used to train the network using the sum of
square error right that means the formula that we covered in the lecture you
can use because that is sum of square error okay
and then the
rack rule function right is chosen as activation
function max 0 adds right there is an activation function
and then the learning rate for all the weights and bias is
0.3 0.3 okay
so compute the actual output at the 2 output
unit 0 4 and 0 5 for the training
sample 1 and 1 the target output
at the unit 4 and 5 are given as a 0 1
right so when you have input 1 and 1 you expect to get the target
0 1 but of course because your network may not be
optimized yet the first output may not be close to 0 1
right so there is a question A
then after that compute the error function
at each unit right delta 4 delta 5 delta
3 right you do not have error in the delta 1 delta 2
because they do not have weight for you to adjust okay
adjust all the weights and bias accordingly after you compute the delta
with the training sample 1 and 1 then you can
adjust the weights then with the new
output unit and bias compute the new outputs
at 0 4 0 5 again right and you will see that
these 2 outputs will be closer to 0 to 1
okay
so
okay let's look at the you see the
of course if you are given this question the first thing
this one do come out in some kind of
homework you have to identify all these parameter
okay give the label properly right B 3 B 4 B 5 W
key 2 4 key 5 of function okay then the actual
output at the unit 4 and 5 right can be computed as this
right actual output you first have to compute
the output of O 3 first right this O 3
output will be equal to first why is the net input
1 times 0 power 1 plus 1 times 0.2 plus
the bias B 3 is 0.5 right so this is the one
for the net 3 input right then you get the 0.8
as the net 3 then because you are using
the output since this is a positive will be 0.8
as well right so once you have O 3 now you can go
back to compute the net 4 net 4 will be O 3
times 0.2 right the weight W 4 3 and then net 4
will be this 0.16 net 5 will be O 3 times 0.3
0.24 right because both are positive then the output
O 4 and O 5 will be the same value and positive right
that's how you compute then once you have
so-called gone through the forward propagation you get
the O 4 and O 5 then you can compute with the target
T 4 and T 5 which is 0 and 1 right then you
compute the error term at delta 4 which is T 4 minus
O 4 then this is sigma plum net 4 right because
now is a reg rule function sigma plum F 4 so
sigma plum net 4 depend on the value of net 4 net 4
in this case is a positive value early on we've seen
therefore sigma plum become 1 1 times T 4 minus
O 4 is minus 0.16 right so there is error term delta 4
similarly delta 5 this is also 1 because net 4
net 5 are positive value then you have T 5 1 minus
actual output O 5 becomes 0.76 then for once you
have delta 4 delta 5 you can compute the delta 3 which
will be equal to delta 4 times 0.2 plus delta 5 times 0.3
times the activation function sigma plum net 3 net 3
is also positive so you have 1 so you take this one so
compute this you get 0.196 so then you have all the delta 3
delta 4 delta 5 so with that now you can compute the
changes right which is just a all this formula we have seen
before right you can get all the new weights 4 3 5 3 3 1 3 2
and b 4 b 5 b 3 right then with that new network parameter
right some changes happen you can compute the new 0 4 0 5
again you'll find that it's now become 0.11 0.699
right the target is 0 and 1 right originally the output is
0.16 0.24 now 0.16 reduce to 0.11 then 0.64
increase to 0.69 right one closer to 0 the other closer to
1 so they mean the error reduce right just one training one
step right so if you continue to train at the end you will
hopefully get to the 0 and 1 target eventually solution is
available online you can go and just download from the NTU
learn to but I strongly suggest you to do it by hand first
before you look at the solution right because when you really
do it you can realize certain step you may not be one other
person sure where to find the value where to find the formula
or the step right the sequence of the step those are important
things that only you work it out yourself you realize what could
be missing okay so these are two additional exercise for you
to practice in case you really need more or if you really
even more go to check the website on the past exam paper
I believe there will be one or two on NTU library and try them
out if you want to then let's continue a few other networks
before we wrap up the section today so after learn it and as
we cover in the introduction section and as we also
suggest now learn it although it works very well for
MNIST data but we apply to those color images like the
CFAR 10 it doesn't work as well right other classifier
perhaps SVM or decision tree or may work as well or less
computational expensive so and then there was a AI winter
until around 2012 and the FAFE and a few of them started this
image net large-scale visual recognition challenge there was
slightly before 2012 2010 2011 so the goal is because people
criticize that oh neural network can only work for simple data
like those MNIST and if you really want to show the so-called
capability of network you have to target at images like this
and see who are inside the image right so that is considered
so-called a challenge for computer vision and machine learning
community so therefore the set up is a common challenge so that
everyone can propose idea to see whether they can achieve what
they want to achieve so the task has 1.2 million images right a
large number and each labor with one of the thousand categories
right so rather than 10 or 100 now you have 1000 category of
different type of so-called content so among them one
point two million actually they have more than this one point
two millions are for training purpose and they are another
100,000 test images right for you to verify where did they
your so-called model right you can assemble training error you
can have a test error but when you come to competition they keep
aside a set of images they never share with public right then
you go and run your program to see how good you are so for this
kind of competition normally they will now allow you to keep
trying right every day they may allow you to test the set for
certain amount of time right because they do want you to keep
optimizing your code to the actual so-called data so set up
some very clear rule to I mean to kind of avoid such a situation
from happening but then there will still be people using different
kind of trick try to so-called game the system and some actually
were exposed you shouldn't do that because the idea is not like
who is winning is whether you have a better network so everyone
should follow the rule right then trying to fit the noise or fit
the so-called error right so because the problem is too
complex right if only consider the correct class as a so-called
answer then the performance will be very poor so they allow each
image you can predict five output as long as the correct class is
within this five then you are considered correct right so because
1000 objects some of them could be very similar so you are allowed to
predict five top choice okay so that continue for a few years
and and Alex net 2012 the one we saw before they come up with this
this so-called structure although that it looks complex but in fact it
shouldn't be and the reason they have these two parallel path because
of limitation by the GPU right they cannot fit all the data into one
GPU they had to somehow compromise come up with the two parallel path
to train part of the so-called data right and it is very similar to
learn it the conceptually right they still have this so-called
convolution layer pooling layer right pooling rather than average pooling
they use a max pooling convolution layer then at the end they have a fully
connected network they have the output now because 1000 classes you have
1000 output unit rather than 10 right so fundamentally it's similar right
just to make it bigger more this is a so-called feature matte level
different kind of filter side early on the u5 and 5 this one they can use
up to 11 by 11 right and they have seven healing layer rather than two
now they have seven and 60 million parameter right and using red rule
as activation function here are some of the intermediate so-called output
you can see and the filter it learn that turn out to be like this the filter
of the first convolution layer you can see that the first layer
basically look for very basic pattern right the ages in different
direction and color box occur at different places and this is the
activation of feature map output at this you think about they use a red
rule then when the value is less than 0 right output is 0 only for the
value larger than 0 they keep the value therefore the output is has a lot of
0 only the partner with a strong response they have output here the
rest of them are a lot of 0 there I got the first one or first layer
level you can still see something but then this are the filter or second
convolution layer right you have about 128 of them right k equal to 128
this one you have 48 of them 128 and now you probably harder for the
see certain pattern and we go to the further the activation map because even
sparks more sparks and this only has certain sport and this show you a
strong evidence something might happen there right and this filter feature
map may be looking for a face or looking for a dog so at the end you
decide okay so then people after they perform so well and a lot of people
try to do further analysis why it works all right the training why it can
actually recognize this object right so this are some of the so-called
reverse engineer study so for example in the level one this are the
feature that will give a lot of so-called activation output and for
level two for example if you input this kind of image as some of the level
feature map you will see this have a very strong output this these are not
the actual output but it's like if you have this input to do the reconstruction
to the activation function map and this should be the feature you are going to
see you can see that it can successfully detect some of the circle right
activation map and you go further higher higher level three right just like
when we do the one b2d one layer second layer you can detect the more
compressed region similarly when you go layer three now you can start to
detect a human shape right somehow car the wheel right some kind of fans
barcode right so and then until even the level four level five right lxf
a six layer right so you can see some of the object like face right appear here
and these are dog face right as long as you were dog you can detect it so
that is the layer once you go to more and more hidden the year you can pick up
this kind of complex structure right so that was the success of Alex net right
so early on before 2012 and this is the image net challenge top five error so
these are the one which are the core shadow they do not really use a
neural network to do the deep network to do the computation
so when Alex net came out in 2012 it dropped the performance I mean improve
the performance by reaching error rate from 26% to 16% almost 10% drop right
early on you see the drop will be very minimum two or three percent now
suddenly 10% so after this the foreign network are all CNN network they just
use a different complication and the error continue to reduce and this GF net
is very much similar to Alex net they just use out the parameter right just
maybe different so-called filter side different so-called layer right layer is
the same just maybe the filter they use are different and some of the so-called
activation function could be different and then and then after that there is this
Alex net you can see a lot of once you understand the structure you can just
represent network by using this you learn by you learn filter convolution level
and and this is the output so-called how many of these feature map care how many
filter you use right and these are the fully connection network what is the
number of unit you have at the end yet the softmax activation function then VGG
come out in 2014 and the beauty of this VGG is they use the same 3 by 3 filter
rather than different side right and still the same almost same structure
convolution level pooling pooling convolution level fully connect them
like work right and you can call all these are very similar concept as a learn net
then Google net come out with 2014 they have very this very interesting structure
and this structure is like what I show earlier that you can connect sometimes
connect to the following layer and this structure turned out to be it's still
like those feature multiply with some kind of a new non network but they have
this kind of different structures such that you can take multiple path right
and just a single path now you can take multiple path what it actually does is
rather than one single network you can create multiple different version of
network at the end which are past can contribute the best to optimize the
so-called output you will be given more weight the rest will be body minimum
weight so and then the other thing you try to do is reduce the number of
parameter from 60 million up to 144 million now this start to 23 million
even they have more layer but because of this structure they can actually
achieve the similar performance with fewer number of parameter because this
is actually in fact some kind of network in the network allow you to create
different type of network within one network right so there is a lot of
so-called crevice I go into this then this the residue net come up by Microsoft
they have this a jump right and they go through this right to allow the X to
connect to the following network by skipping some of the hidden they were
the one I draw earlier so this allow them to handle the problem we call it
gradient vanishing problem if you recall the training process right when you
adjust the error adjust the weight you always need to multiply the error from
the back with the derivative of the activation function sigma prime net
right so that normally if you look at some of these software functions at the
value could be less than one right if you have multiple level connect together
then every time when you propagate the error to the the the foreign layer you
always multiply something with activation function derivative which could be
less than one so if you go through many layer and that number the error will
reduce to very very small number and then you cannot learn anymore this
call gradient vanishing problem so this keep connection allow the error to go
through this faster so you still keep the error right and make it disappear
right this is how they can have many layer early on you only have 22 layer now
you can kept up to 152 layer right those healing layer while still will not
really let the gradient disappear right okay they can see that performance
continue to improve until 3.57 yeah so and and this is considered something
significant because it was considered a cow beating the human performance
okay because there was a researcher and he himself tried out by humanly check
classification and if I they can achieve something maybe close to 4% error
but this rest net can actually first time cow consider like achieving better
performance at human right based on what they claim right so after that of course
there were many many further improvement with a bigger bigger network but people
already accept this is probably the right network to tackle such a problem and
they no longer continue to purpose this data okay okay let's stop here today and
I will talk about this recurrent network and other network and including at the
end transformer in the end I'll see you next week will be the last lecture I'm
going to cover and then after that another lecture will come into takeover
those who have questions can come here just now
you