________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Isabelle. So what happened to other students? What did they not do well in their quiz last Saturday? How do you do it with a quiz? Okay? Good. So we started the introduction to machine learning last week. And of course today we are going to look at some of the
basic classifiers. And I understand that some of you likely have seen . . .
Okay. I don't know why it doesn't come out. It should be on . . .
We try to see the projector.
Okay. Good.
So today we are going to look at the classification, one of the important applications of machine learning.
And start with a very specific classifier, a very old classifier. I'm not sure how can I . . .
I can switch off this light.
Is it here? No. This is a screen.
You know, for the video recording, I hope that the quality will be better. Now the contrast is likely not the best.
Anyone know how to switch off the light here?
Yeah. Very interesting.
Okay. Anyway. So I hope the recording you can see clearly. If there's any problem, let me know.
I will try to find out how to turn off the light in front in the next lecture.
So we are going to talk about this. And again, some of this topic might not be new to you, but it's good to also go through it together.
And to get the concept right.
Okay. No, no. Here. Here. Not the other. Okay. Not the other.
Yeah. I want to get this feel light because somehow the projection . . .
Okay. See. I think.
This one? Yeah. Good.
Yeah. I can list this better. Oh God, please do not fall into sleep.
Make sure it's right there.
So we look at classification. What is classification?
Although classification is the very simple process that you try to classify from the input data, how many, what type this data belongs to.
But in a lot of machine learning tasks, you can find that it will become very powerful too, depending on how you formulate your problem into a classification problem.
Which could include, like even for example, your . . .
Chatchity. Again, because you are familiar with that, so I will use it again.
So Chatchity, the way it works is like this, right? Based on your input, you try to project, predict what will be the next word or next token, right?
Out of the many possible tokens available. So it is a classification problem, right?
And you just have to continue to predict what will be the next word after this and this, until you hit the end of the sentence.
So it's a classification problem. So of course, it doesn't have to be a transformer.
It could be many, many other simple tools that you can use.
And Decision 3 turned out to be one of them, which have been around for many years.
And Conceptual-wise is actually similar to how we approach a problem, classification problem, by asking a sequence of questions.
So based on the answer of those questions, you decide ultimately this input data belongs to which class.
So we will go through that. And more importantly, we will look into some of the selection criteria because you can have many types of trees, right?
And in fact, when you build the trees, you can select different so-called selection measures to build the tree differently, right?
And there will be random forest. Random forest is just many, many trees.
It's nothing fancy. Just give them a name of.
You have many trees together. Then for each tree, you find out what is the output class.
And then you try to do a majority vote to make decision.
Then you also need to look into the performance measure, right?
You have many different classifiers, but which will give you the best result possible.
It will not be as simple as just accuracy, right?
And there will be many other factors like the speed, right?
The scalability, robustness to noise, right?
And whether it can be generalized to other similar data, so all these other things that you have to take into consideration.
So there are such measures like accuracy, error rates, sensitivity, specificity, right?
We call F measure and how do you evaluate those measures?
So we will go through that and hopefully, I think most likely we will finish the lecture on decision tree today.
If we still have time, we may start the next nearest neighborhood classifier, which is another type next.
And then perhaps even support vector machine after that, right?
And because I want to leave some time on the neural network.
Null network, of course, hopefully we will get the concept right so that you can learn some of the new so-called idea yourself, right?
So hopefully we would have more time on the neural network.
Okay, so what is a classification or classifier?
So again, just a word definition.
Classification basically you try to assign given an object, right?
Which you may not know what is it?
The object could be an email that you receive, right?
So your email mailbox will actually try to judge whether this email is spam, right?
Or non-spam emails or junk emails, right?
You try to move the email to a so-called junk folder automatically if you find that this email is suspicious, not really a genuine email.
So how do they make the judgment?
It's a classification process, right?
So you can have objects and often that you do not use everything of the object, you could try to look into the attributes of the objects.
Just now for the email example, you can look at some of the keywords.
Some of the so-called subject title or even the sender.
Are they from a particular so-called region of the group?
Or do they send to many, many recipients?
Are they the, is the sender in your so-called contact list?
All these are useful information features or sometimes we call it attributes, right?
An object would have a lot of so-called properties.
We call them attributes.
So with this, then your classifier basically take this feature or attribute, go to a function and which decide what is the class label, right?
Class label could be just a number, one, two, three, four.
It could be the transformer, charge APT output, the token, the word that we mentioned, right?
It could be an E. So this function F, it may not be as simple as those functions you have come across, right?
You look at the charge APT, it could be a billion or trillion of parameters,
and which is beyond human imagination, what kind of function is it?
With the input, which could be very complex, then output is one of the many, many types of classes.
And machine learning is basically find out as we introduced last week, what is this function?
Right?
Go through kind of training approach.
If you can collect a lot of data, then hopefully you can find a function which works well with all the data
that you use for training or even extend to those data that you have not seen during your training process.
Okay?
So the spam email is one of them.
And you can find another function which can do the speech recognition, right?
Think carefully.
Speech recognition is also try to recognize every words that you say, what is it, right?
So it's also a classification problem if you formulate the problem properly, right?
And many other things, image classification, whether the credit card expenses are fraudulence or legitimate,
or even this animal, whether it's a duck, right?
So of course, you can think of all these are so-called multi-moder feature, right?
And then of course, you may not know how to describe a duck,
but if you see something which works like a duck, quick like a duck, then it's slightly a duck.
There is a basic principle about classification.
So that also means that you could make mistakes, right?
If I somehow make a machine duck, right, it can work like a duck, quick like a duck, you say, oh, that is a duck,
but it could be a toy, right?
So it could happen.
So there is an error that you have to leave it.
Two main steps of classification.
So if you desire a classifier, you have to go through these two steps in general.
The first step is a so-called the learning step or training step,
which you try to construct a classification model based on the training data set given to you.
The training data set could be, right, like we thought about this image net data set, millions of images.
Each image, they give you a label.
What is the object inside this image?
So you need to have the data set.
You need to know what is the class label of the data set, right?
And that is a job that you have to collect, okay, those data.
So once you have that data set with the label, the ground through,
then you can select one of the classification model.
So today we will focus on decision three, but there will be many, many other models that you can choose from
based on your preferences, based on your experience, based on your computing facilities,
based on many, many other consideration factors that you need to take into consideration.
So after that, you have the classifier.
Then there is a so-called classification step, which is the step that you apply.
Sometimes it's called inference, right?
You use the classifier design.
Now you have a new input, the input, then you go through this classifier,
then you say, okay, this belongs to what class?
Okay.
So these two steps, okay, the first step is certainly generally very time consuming
because you have to go through a lot of iteration,
and it has to first start with a model, which may not work very well.
Then you'll find a way to tell the model, right?
And like the example I gave at Lawson Brad, when he designed this so-called classifier,
he used a hand to tell the note.
It is very much like for those, if you have the experience, try to fix some machine, right?
You just tilt until you find that it could be a Wi-Fi receiver,
it could be an old television.
You just select the so-called channel properly.
It's a kind of a training process.
So once you've done that, next time you just apply.
Apply, okay?
So therefore, a classification model is generally a function or mapping.
So is it a one-to-one mapping or multiple-to-one mapping or one-to-multiple mapping in general?
A classification process is what type of mapping?
I believe you've learned different kind of mapping before, right?
So what kind of mapping is it in general?
One-to-one, multiple-to-one.
Okay? It is generally a multiple-to-one mapping.
You could have different input data, but output belongs to a particular class.
You cannot have one input data, but it belongs to a number of different classes,
which in some applications you may want to do that,
but in general we want to have multiple-to-one mapping.
And more importantly, the model, this classifier that you learn,
it should fit well with the training data set, which you use to train the model.
So we call this a training error, right?
And which, of course, if you have a proper model,
you likely will get the error, continue to decrease.
If you have more and more data, or you have a model which can have many, many parameters.
And more importantly, that you also want the model to predict well to class labor,
which you have not seen the data, right?
If it can do well on the new data, predict their classes correctly,
then you say that this model has good generalization capabilities.
It can be generalized to unseen data.
Otherwise, the model will be only useful to the training data,
which is not really something interesting, right?
So then it comes with this problem like,
you probably heard about this, over-fifting, right?
If you do not have a powerful model,
you might overfit the data to the model,
turn out it may not behave well when you actually apply to unseen data.
We'll go through some of these processes, and how do you solve this kind of problem?
Okay?
So let's give you an example.
This is the conceptual flaw that we will go through.
So now, assuming that you are given this set of data,
okay, let's say this is your first job.
You start to work in a car dealer company.
Your job is to decide when a customer walks into your showroom,
you have to judge whether this customer is likely to buy a car from you, right?
Of course, you are not going to serve anyone walking into the room,
so you may compete with your colleagues,
try to get as high at the commission as possible.
So every time someone walks in, you can look at the age profile, right?
Look at the potential income.
You may not have the information, but if you ask a name,
it happens to be a member, then you might have such information about the income level.
Or look at their outfit, look at the car they come with,
look at their status, then you can make judgment,
okay, this person probably is quite okay.
Then, whether it's working or not, right?
If they only come after office hours, maybe like it's working,
it's coming during daytime, okay,
but not necessarily only those working will buy a car, right?
And credit rating, right?
You can check the record if they give you a credit card or you have the record.
And based on this, I've got to give you many, many other factors, right?
And you do not, these are attributes.
Before you train, you really do not know which attribute really will be the most useful factor
for you to make that decision, right?
For example, whether the person come alone, right?
Will he come with a family, and whether, what time he come in, right?
All this could be useful information, but before training, you would not know, right?
So the idea is actually before training, you don't want to make some kind of subjective judgment.
You want to collect as much data as many different types of data as possible
so that the training can tell you what will be the feature which are really useful to make the decision.
So with that, then these are the record based on your past history
after working for two or three months.
So you have deal with a couple of these customers.
That is your training data, right?
You have collect this, and you know, actually, this is your target classification output.
Yes or no?
Right?
This is the most important.
You don't care whether, how old they are, whether they are working or not.
Ultimately, you care more about whether they buy a car from you.
So, okay, after three months, you collect this data.
Okay, you say, okay, since I have taken this course, I'm going to build a model
to help you to make a better judgment.
So then you will probably record this, and this is the data you collect.
You try to fit in as much information as possible that you might think useful.
And then you pre-process or clean the data.
So this is a very important process because not all the data are so perfect.
You could have some missing data.
You may not know the age of this person.
Right?
Then how do you deal with missing data?
And there are a couple of ways to do it.
For those interested, you can go in Google and either by estimation or based on some
kind of average of the data set you have, you can, this is called cleaning or pre-processing
data or could be the, whether it buy a car or not, it's not so clear card.
The person make an order but haven't really made a payment.
So it's a yes or no.
So that becomes something that you have to think carefully.
How do you clean the data so that it becomes useful?
So after that, I'll call you to select what will be the attributes or features.
These are so-called the feature or attribute, the age, the income, the working on status,
credit rating.
Then you select, okay, as many as this feature as possible.
Then you try to divide this data set into two sets.
One is a training data set.
The other is a test data set.
Okay?
Because you don't want the so-called the model is overfit to your, all your data.
So you keep a small number of data, so-called samples away when you do the training.
Okay?
So you go through some of this training example in the next few lectures.
So after you go through the training, then you evaluate the performance.
How good is this?
And this performance have two types.
One type is based on your training data.
Right?
There's called training error training performance.
Okay?
And then once you're the model, you can also use the test data set that you get aside to
test the model.
Because you also know the ground truth of the test data, so you can also evaluate the
performance.
Right?
So in general, which error will be, or which so-called performance will be better?
Is it training data set or test data set?
Performance will be better.
So it's generally the training data will give you better performance because your model
optimizes over the training data.
Right?
And your test data normally would have a higher error rate or poorer performance.
They generally is the case.
But they are occasionally the other way around, but those are outlier.
Okay?
So that's why when you have the data, you'll find that two of them continue to decrease
based on the iteration that is fine.
But the test data error will be higher than the training data error.
Right?
But you'll find that the error decreases.
Suddenly, the training data, if your model is correct, will continue to decrease.
But you find the test data error starts to go up.
That means the point your model might have been overfit to your training data.
Right?
Then you have to stop somehow.
So these are the processes you will go through in the following example.
Right?
So once you are satisfied with the error, then you, okay, you can test them with new
data, which is beyond this the training or test data.
You can start to collect some new data to verify whether the model indeed works as well
as you expected.
Okay?
If somehow it doesn't work anymore, then you go back to the first early state to redo.
Let me select another model or collect more features or look at the data you collect.
Are they sufficient?
The cleaning process, do you do it properly?
The partitioning, is it the right ratio?
You iterate the process.
Okay?
It will not be just once, right?
After three months or one year, maybe the economic condition changed, right?
A regression comes.
The model may not work anymore, right?
So you have to update or find your model or you move to the other company, right?
The company may locate in another town the performance or the country, even the customer
performance behavior may not be the same.
Then you have to collect the new data set to verify, to update.
So that is a very typical machine learning process.
Okay?
So then let's define the data.
Normally a data sample acts, right?
An object, a customer, you can represent them as an n-dimensional attribute vector, right?
Of course, that's what you want to do.
Engineers, you have to convert everything into numbers, right?
And this vector, s could be x1 is the age.
x2 age group.
x2 will be whether they are working or not, right?
Until xn, whether their credit rating is good, right?
It could be a very high dimensional space, right?
And they're based on this input and you try to make sense out of it.
And the data samples, sometimes you read other books.
They will call it the data points or examples, objects, instance, or tuppers, right?
All these are possible names, right?
They are all referring to the same, the data sample, okay?
Each sample acts belong to a predefined class.
Like, early on the example I gave is yes or no, right?
Whether the customer is going to buy or not to buy a car from you.
These are binary classification output.
Class labels are generally discrete value, like 1 and 0, buy or not buy.
And unordered.
That means they do not really have any so-called meaning in terms of which ones would come first, right?
So there are four types of attributes and this attribute could refer to these features, right?
Just now we see the ages, whether they buy car or not, okay?
So there are four types.
The first two types are called nominal or ordinal attributes.
These two types, let's see some example.
Here, nominers are different names to tell them apart.
For example, your student ID number, right?
Your eye color, your hair color, right?
Or gender, the blood type, or interest group, where you stay, right?
So they do not necessarily have any so-called order.
They just tell you the location, the number, the type, okay?
We call these type nominal attributes, okay?
The other is the ordinal attribute, which although they are also discrete,
but you start to, you can make some comparison.
For example, the rating, right?
A movie rating, whether this is good, average, poor, or excellent, right?
Although these belong to four classes, but you probably prefer excellent over good,
or average over poor.
So there are some order you can actually make choices.
These are called ordinal data.
You can compare them based on some kind of so-called order, so-called preferences,
like strict number, right?
If you go to look for your friend at a particular street,
you look at the number, you know that in one direction,
the number normally would increase.
The other direction would be reducing, right?
If the number are random, then you have a time to find which unit that your friend stays, right?
So there are some order, okay?
And the other two types are called interval or ratio attributes.
So they are numeric and quantitative attributes, okay?
For example, intervals is you have meaning about the differences between the values.
You can basically apply addition or subtraction.
For example, the date of a calendar, right?
Every month from one to 30 or 31, right?
So you know that one come before two, right?
Calendar that you can subtract.
It's a day seven minus day one.
There is a six day in between.
So you have meaning, right?
So early on, you may not have a meaning of excellent subtract good.
There is no meaning, no so-called intervals.
Because the higher will be the ratio which besides addition or subtraction,
you can also apply multiplication or division, right?
For example, the length of an object, right?
If you have an object which is one cm long,
if you put five of them together, it should be five cm.
So you can multiply five.
So they have such a so-called meaning.
Or if you have some number of objects, total length is 100,
then you know each of them is about 2.5.
Then you divide them, you know how many objects are going to be.
So this division can also apply.
So these are ratio attributes.
Okay?
I think at one time I said a question I was asking.
So I'll give example of two ratio attributes and two ordinal attributes.
Okay?
Then you have to give example and see whether they meet some of these criteria.
So these are attributes.
And again, the attributes is happened to the features
and the class label are normally discrete.
Okay?
So that means the class label,
unlikely will be interval or ratio.
The class label could be nominal.
It may be ordinal.
Unless you are doing regression.
Remember when we in the first introduction lecture,
we talked about the housing price rather than you identify whether you buy or not
or rent or not, you want to estimate what is the rent you should pay.
There will be some kind of interval or even ratio number that you can estimate.
That is a regression, not a classification problem.
Okay?
So here are some popular classification methods.
So we will talk about decision trees.
And we talk about rule-based classification because after you build a decision tree,
you can come up with some rules to make decision.
Right?
Even earlier on when Professor Chen Yi Hui introduced some of the so-called state approach,
they can also form the rule-based, right?
Association analysis.
You can also do that.
Then we'll talk about K-near-less neighbor classification.
And these are very basic, but some of the advanced methods,
they do make use of some of these so-called simple idea to pre-process the data.
And then we'll talk about support vector machine.
And remember this was a machine.
The method somehow create another AI winter, even beat the neural network at that time.
It was not really well developed.
They will talk about neural networks.
Okay?
So ensemble method is just a collection of them, right?
And the random forest will be one type of ensemble methods.
And I will show you some tools.
I think on the website, you can see there's Orange Tool.
You can use it, try to play around with some data and then to apply one of these classifier fire
and see the result.
Okay?
So maybe at the time we can go through some of the examples during the class.
The Bayesian classifier, I think B.Hun is going to talk about it.
I'll leave him to him.
So let's start with decision trees.
It's a very old and very intuitively easy to understand classification method.
Okay?
So a decision tree, so far any question, any problem before I go on?
It's still easy.
So a decision tree look like this, okay?
Has a flow chart like three structures, okay?
Although the tree is kind of hanging down.
So it has a note.
This yellow color one, we call this a note, which could be the root note, the top.
It's upside down, root note.
All the internal notes like this, which denotes a test on an attribute.
Earlier I talked about those attributes.
Basically when you come to each note, you try to ask a question or test whether this attribute fulfills certain requirement.
And then when this note asks a question, then you are going to have a few branches coming out, right?
For example, in this case, whether this one is, you want to test whether a particular person is going to conduct a text fraud situation, okay?
Then you can ask the question like refund whether this person asks for text refund, okay?
If he asks, then of course you go down this branch.
If he doesn't ask, go down the other branch.
So this is the so-called the branch.
You represent the outcome of the test.
You perform on one of the root or internal notes.
Then each leaf note, the one I show in green color, represent the terminal note which holds a class label, right?
So, and for some, in this case, you ask whether you ask for refund.
If no, then it's not likely going to conduct a text fraud because he doesn't ask for money return, right?
So this is a leaf note.
Then this will be the class label note, okay?
So if you ask for refund, then you check, ask the next question whether the person is married or not, right?
If yes, then Lili is not going to conduct a text fraud.
Okay, this is a very artificial test, right?
And if you say no, then you ask whether what is the amount of the income, taxable income tax, right?
If it's less than 100K, then no.
If it's higher than 100K, then Lili, this person will conduct a text fraud.
So being those rich people, income, taxable income hire is more likely to conduct a text fraud.
Again, this is all artificial.
So this is, again, very logical.
Basically, it's like human decision, right?
So when you make judgment, you consider a few factors or features.
Even without this classifier, this is all for what you do, right?
You meet someone new, you say, okay, if this person Lili can be your friend, right?
You say, okay, do they graduate from the same so-called country, study the same subject,
or have certain common interests?
You ask all these questions, right?
And then at the end, you say, okay, whether this person can be your friend or not,
then you make a decision, right?
It's a very simple, typical process, okay?
So there is basically a decision tree.
That's it.
End of the story.
Of course, then it may not be so simple.
You could have, earlier we talked about two classes, right?
You could have a decision tree, which you may have multiple outputs, right?
In here, we have a tree output.
You try to judge a particular fruit type, right?
In this case, you look at the size of the fruits, where it's big, the medium, or small, right?
Then you make decision whether this is durian, apple, or lime, right?
Based on just the size of the fruits, right?
So you could have level zero, level one, level two, level three.
When you have level three, basically, you only need to ask three questions.
One, two, three, maximum three questions, you will arrive at a decision, right?
But sometimes, depending on the outcome of the question,
you could make the decision faster, like this K level two.
So it depends.
Okay?
So now let's look at one example.
So how do you design?
Of course, the dataset may not be as simple as you have just seen.
It may not be all consistent among themselves.
So today, I give you Excel data, so-called table of 10 million dataset, right?
And maybe 50 attributes, right?
Build a tree, okay?
It's humanly impossible to do that.
It is actually possible such a data is like, think about those supermarkets, right?
If they have all these so-called customers, what they buy in each visit to the so-called store of a change,
then one year record, you could have million of customer visit,
and each of them can purchase from zero to maybe 20 or 30 items per visit.
And if your store has, let's say, a thousand or maybe a few thousand different items,
then you have, according to a few thousand column, right?
Then you have to see what they buy.
And that will become something very challenging for you to design the tree, which is somehow optimal, right?
What will be the attribute when you have so many attributes?
What will be the attribute that you look at?
I think in the earlier example, you look at this basket dataset, right?
You try to see, okay, if the customer buys this few item, what would they buy in the next visit, right?
So you can build a classification tree to do the project as well, right?
And then the tree that you build could have many, many levels, many, many so-called branches, many, many levels, right?
So which would be better?
Is it the earlier association rule or the classifier, right?
Depending on what you want to judge, whether the person going to buy the milk in the next visit,
or how much or the person will spend, right?
And how frequent the person will come again so that you decide whether you give them the loyalty program,
customer membership or not, okay?
So let's look at one example.
Okay, we only have six data samples, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Each of them have three features, fever, cough or tiredness.
And then your goal is to judge, this is the labor, class labor, whether the person is slightly infected by COVID-19 virus, right?
Assuming a very simple dataset, okay?
Because if you recall the time when the COVID just started and no one knows what will be the so-called symptom,
which will be very decisive, right?
So then you start to collect some of these so-called input based on some of these examples that you encounter
and the measure that you make, right?
For a first person, it doesn't have fever, but if you have a mouth cough, it's not tired,
then you do the test, test, it comes out, oh, no cough in COVID-19, right?
So another person come in, your mouth fever have cough, but it doesn't feel tired.
Then you do the test, oh, it is positive.
So you collect a few of them, then you decide, okay, what features should you look at to make a decision?
What would be the most telling features?
In some kind of scientific or optimal decision you can make, right?
So, yeah, that is the problem, right?
So how do you build the trees?
How do you build the trees?
And all these problems are not difficult, but it is just tedious.
If I said an exam question like this in the past, okay?
It's found that students actually they can do, but often they cannot finish.
If I ask you to build a tree just with about 16 samples,
and you will think maybe more than half an hour before you can do all the computation, right?
Okay, so you have to understand what is your class labor.
This is the primary focus, okay?
Always have your eye look at the class outcome, okay?
So here, okay?
Then from here, you know that you have three positive, three negative.
So what does it tell you?
So if this is the only information you know based on the six page patient that you have examined,
50% of them have COVID, 50% of them do not have COVID.
Then there's a new person coming, okay?
Do you think he is going to have COVID?
Right, so that is a question, okay?
Without collecting any feature, you are just a random guess, 50%.
You cannot make any better decision than a random guess, right?
So this before you do make all the measures, whether you have fever, a cough, or tired,
before you ask any question, the person come in, does he or she have COVID or not?
So that tells you that, tough, 50% chance you get it correct or wrong, okay?
Then you look at it, okay, if I can now ask the first question,
does the person have fever, cough, or tired?
Okay, if you can only ask one question,
which will be the question you ask to make a better decision?
So that is the question, right?
The tree, the roof notes, right?
That is the first question that you ask.
You want the question to be as telling, as useful as possible, right?
Because the patient could be not patient enough.
After you ask the first question, you or she can just walk out.
So you have to choose a question to ask.
Can anyone tell which question you should ask from here?
Why?
Tiredness.
So tiredness, let's see whether this is the attribute you should ask, okay?
Let's examine all of them, okay?
Let's try to look at tiredness.
Oh, you are right.
Look at this, tiredness.
If I ask a question whether the person is tired or not,
and all the answers will be yes and no, right?
Turn now.
If the person says yes, she is tired, okay?
The chance is two of them will have COVID.
You look at the yes, the one with blue color,
then two of them have COVID, one of them doesn't have COVID.
Okay?
If the person is not tired, then you go to this, another branch.
Always focus on your class labor.
Two of them without COVID, one have COVID.
Okay?
Does it help?
Right?
So just by asking the first question,
now your error rate dropped to 33%.
Right?
Basically, when you tell you I'm tired,
most likely you will say,
most likely you have COVID,
at least 67% chance, right?
Which is better than 50%, right?
By asking the first question,
you make the decision easier, right?
Okay?
If it's not tired, then most likely you do not have COVID,
which you can also make a better decision.
So earlier on, without asking a question,
I say 50% chance you get it right or wrong.
That means your error rate will be three out of six, right?
Because 50%, if you have six patients,
most likely 50% you will make an error.
Okay?
But now, by asking the first question,
what is the error rate that you can expect?
What is the error rate?
Two out of six, right?
That is 33%.
Because this one, you are going to make a mistake.
Okay?
So you improve your decision,
but you still make a mistake.
So it's not perfect.
Then let's look at other attributes.
That's the first question you ask, okay?
I haven't talked about the second question.
So tiredness is one, you know that you're going to make 33% error.
Improved from 55%, 50%.
So that is the power, the value of asking the right question,
the first question, okay?
Now let's examine cough.
Now look at the, again, always look at the feature together
with your class labor.
So for cough, you have three possible outputs.
Mal, no, or yes.
No, mal, yes.
So similarly, you have this sixth sample input.
Now, based on the answer, you know that no mal, yes, this will be,
four of them have the mal symptoms,
but among these four, two have COVID, two without COVID.
Right?
So for no cough, no COVID.
We cough, we cough it.
Okay.
So what will be the error rate that you are going to have
if you ask the first question whether the patient have cough?
What is the error rate?
How many samples you will make mistake?
Two out of six, right?
So it's the same error rate as tiredness.
Right?
So that means whether you ask the patient if tired or not,
or whether it's cough or not, you make almost similar decision error.
So it's the same.
One is not better than the other.
Okay?
Then let us look at the third feature, which is fever.
The fever also had three outputs.
Again, this may be a simple example, but think about the case
whether you may have a million of samples, thousand of features,
then you have to decide which is the best feature to ask,
which will be the second feature to ask.
And then you need to have a systematic way to construct the decision tree.
So this is what we are concerned about.
Of course, there will be two helping you to do that,
but at least you need to know the principle, right?
Behind it, how it works.
Let's look at the feature, a fever, right?
The same thing.
If you have no fever, then based on this, right?
Okay.
No fever.
Look at this one.
There are two no fever, no so-called COVID.
And there are two mild fever.
Both of them have COVID.
And then two yes, one have COVID, one without COVID.
Okay?
So there is outcome by asking whether the person has fever as the first question.
So why is the error rate?
One out of six, right?
Because you can make, based on the output,
if it's no, certainly 100% you can make correct decision.
Just based on this training data.
Mild, you can make correct decision.
Only when you say it has fever, 50% chance of these two, you will make an error.
So that means one out of six, you will make a mistake.
So but this is the best result among these three features.
So go back to the question again.
What will be the first attribute you should ask?
It's a fever, right?
Okay?
So now you look at the two with the fever.
Of course, there are still errors.
But don't forget that after fever, you can ask whether the person is cough or tired.
Right?
So apparently you look at the data, if you look carefully, oh, if this person has fever,
all I had to do is ask whether the person has cough or whether he's tired.
Based on the outcome, I can tell them apart, right?
The green becomes the leaf note when it is pure, when their decisions are consistent.
So now, by asking the second question, tiredness or cough,
you'll be able to differentiate these two to yes and no.
And then you have 100% accuracy by asking just two questions.
So you may not need to have three features.
You only need to look at the two.
Right?
But it may not be consistent like this.
Okay, for example, if I now make this to like yes and yes,
and then tiredness will not be the one helping you to make a decision.
Right?
And, right?
So for example, you can also select the fever and cough to build a tree.
Then you select another fever and tiredness to build another tree.
Right?
Then you have two multiple three because there will be occasion that you may not know
whether the person is tired or cough, have cough.
Then you can choose the other three to give you the decision.
That is the basic idea about the random forest.
You can choose different combinations of features to build different trees.
Then one of them will be able to give you definite answer.
Then you combine all of them.
Maybe you can get a better decision.
So that is basically decision three.
But you have to think about it when you have a lot of samples, a lot of features,
and not all the features are useful features.
And not all of them are consistent.
They will be outliers.
You could have exactly two sets of persons with yes, no, no, one with COVID, one without COVID.
Right?
Then when you build a tree, you are not going to make correct decision to two of them together.
So one will have error.
So there will be all such a complication.
Then you need to have a better way to measure.
Just now we used the error rate.
How many samples of the training sample you will make mistake.
But that may not be the best so-called measure that you can use to select which attribute is the best.
Another measure that we use is called entropy.
Or uncertainty.
Some of you may have heard about this.
It's a Shannon entropy.
Basically, for cases, you have two classes in here.
PI, I from one in here.
Of course, I can go up to M.
But this example, I give you only two classes.
Right?
Because 0.5, you plug in PI equal to 0.5, you get entropy equal to one, which is one bit.
So which is another measure.
Entropy is a way to measure how random the so-called data is.
The smaller, the better.
That means you can make a definite decision.
The highest, the worst.
For example, earlier we talked about this.
50, 50 percent.
PI equal to one divided by two divided by two.
H equal to one.
That is the maximum randomness.
You want to have one equal to zero, one equal to one.
Then you have zero entropy.
So the probability based on, for example, how many percent of the data is positive.
Here is one over three.
The other is two over three.
So that will be the PI.
So there is one possible measure.
We'll talk about it.
So there is a decision tree.
Again, just to summarize again, you basically construct a tree based on a training set,
which you know the class label, the one that we saw, six of them.
And then it's a top-down approach.
By first getting all the data on the group nodes,
then you start to recursively partition them into smaller set by asking questions.
And if all the samples in the subset like this belong to the same class,
then the node becomes a leaf node here.
Then you label the class label with the label of this all the sample, minus and plus, the green color.
So if not, you continue to divide the data based on attributes.
And the measure you can use is you can use the error rate that we thought about it,
or you can use the entropy or some other we are going to introduce later.
So select what will be the feature which give you the best result.
And then you continue to the process until at the end you all result at the so-called one pure class label.
Then you can make final decision.
But there will be cases that regardless of what you do,
you may not be able to tell them apart due to perhaps noise in the data set
or missing so-called data attribute.
You will not be able to make all the decisions.
So there is a decision tree construction process.
So then let's look at what are the attributes that you can choose.
The one that we thought about error rate, then we thought about entropy,
which is the information gain.
And then there are the gain ratio or Gini index.
So these are the some feature selection measure you can use when you build your tree.
So consider D is a set of all the training sample.
In this case, you have six of them whose class label have M different values,
representing the M distinct classes.
In this case, how many classes you have?
M equal to classes 2.
So that is the part that unfortunately human is not so-called as good as computer to tell what is what.
So this is actually CI.
You only have two classes.
Earlier on it's COVID or no COVID.
So I equal to 2 for this particular case.
Not the number or sample.
Let CID be the set of sample of class CI in D.
For example, in this case, the D is the root node.
Be the set of sample of class.
You have class positive and negative.
So for CID positive, you have three of them.
CID negative, you have another three of them.
So this so-called number, the cardinal value, D,
is six.
And this one depends on positive or negative class.
You have three and three respectively.
We present the number or sample in D and CID.
CID is the number or sample which have a particular class type.
So once you define this, then you can compute the information gain,
which is one attribute selection measure.
So information gain is used by this so-called ID3 algorithm.
ID3 is a very popular decision tree,
which was so-called proposed by Quinland in 1986.
I think he is a professor in New Zealand.
He was very famous and even started a company, consultant company,
actually helped a lot of companies to decide decision tree to solve their problem.
So basically ID3 algorithm minimizes the information,
which is entropy or uncertainty,
in the resulting partition to achieve the best randomness or,
sorry, the least randomness or impurity.
So basically you look at an earlier example.
We want the resulting class as pure as possible in this case.
They are all belonging to the same class,
which is all very pure, least random.
And these are the cases you want to avoid as much as possible
because they are the most random for a two-class problem,
50% chance you get it right or wrong.
Similarly, these are the cases you try to avoid if possible.
This is a better, look at this, this 50% is here,
it's the highest so-called randomness or entropy.
If you have this 1, 3rd and 2, 3rd, basically you are here.
33% here, so your entropy drop, which is better, less random.
So this is the information gain proposed by Quinglin
in the ID3 algorithm.
So basically after you partition, first is you base on all the data set
in 4D, which is 3 positive, 3 negative,
in the example we showed earlier.
Then PI, you have two classes, I1 to 2, for P1 you have 1 divided by 2,
50%, 3 divided by 6, right?
For P2 you have the same thing.
So, and then this is how you compute the information in all the training data
before you partition them by asking questions.
So first you compute that, then you test all the attributes,
you first start with tionist.
So when you ask the tionist, then the D will split into two subset in here,
so it could be multiple D1 to Db.
Early on we had two subset.
I think I have this here, yeah, two subset.
So D1 is the subset we know, D2 is a subset we yes.
Then now rather than in 4D, now you have in 4D1 or DS and Dno.
So DS is actually one third with no COVID, two third with COVID.
So you plug into the formula again, but now your P1, P2 is one third and two third.
Okay, that is for the case of D2 with the answer or DS with the answer equal to yes.
Okay, so you compute the info and you know that there are three,
two percent or sample come here, so three there by six.
So this is how you compute, because each of them you can compute in 4DJ.
And two of them you just do the weighted sum, sum them up,
then there will be your information after you ask the question
about whether the person is tired or not.
In general, this number will reduce.
Okay, it's the same or reduced.
So you want the reduction as high as possible.
Basically you want ultimately this info AD, hopefully at the end is zero.
That means no randomness, very pure.
Okay, so then the gain is, the gain, the internal information gain is in 4D,
the original information in all the data minus info AD after you ask attribute A.
Okay, so then the ID tree algorithm you apply it recursively on each of the resulting partition.
Like early on, after you do one, you do the second until at the end.
Now fever, tired until at the end, all the sample belong to a same class
or there is no further gain possible around the feature
or the feature they use would not reduce the information further.
And that is the end of the classification.
So beside two, you could also have three classes here.
If you ask a fever, then V will become three.
So just make sure you know how to look at this number.
Now V is three.
So D1 now is a no class.
You have two out of six.
Then you compute the information D0, which is zero because it's very pure.
Then Dm is also zero.
So at the end, you also have two out of three for this fever.
With yes answer, info D is actually one.
So ultimately this information AD for fever will be two divided by six times one.
So it's one third.
Same as the error rate that we mentioned earlier.
So this is how you compute.
Let's look at one example.
So you see just with a 14 number, now if I ask you with four features,
now you want to decide whether the patient is infected with the flu virus.
Now you have a more simple, right?
Additional sort through feature.
Now you need to compute.
So you will try out.
You find that it's not as simple as we just saw.
First you compute the information D, which is the case that you look at the classes of flu.
You find that they are one, two, three, four, five negative and nine positive.
Therefore the information D, so they tell you what.
Without looking at any feature, if you had to do a random guess,
they are most likely the next patient would have flu, right?
Maybe a flu season.
So then the info D is nine divided by 14.
This is the P positive, the probability.
Locked two, nine divided by 15.
There's entropy minus summation PI lock, PI.
Then five with negative class, then you find that this information D had 0.94.
Entropy, the unit is bits.
They tell you how many bits in general you need to tell the result apart.
Of course, if you do not write the unit bits, it's also okay to write the number.
You understood that this is a bits.
Then look at the fever.
The fever now is whether this will further reduce the info D.
This is the worst scenario without asking any question.
This is so-called the randomness of 0.94, very close to one.
One is the highest for a two class problem.
Now you have this fever.
With a fever, you have three outcomes.
No, which you have five of them, then you have a mild, which you have four of them, then yes, you have five of them.
So five, four, five, which is the DJ, the other by Lee, this number.
You break it into three subsets based on the outcome of no, mild, and yes.
So five, four, five, okay?
Five, four, five, total 14 of them.
So when you have five of them, you look at the no classes.
You look at the flu, you have three negative and two positive.
So this is entropy of three negative, two positive, two divided by five, three divided by five.
Plus, when you have mild, all of them are positive.
So this entropy will be four, four, which will give you a zero because log two, one is zero.
So this is zero.
So the mild class immediately disappear.
You can consider this is very close to the error rate that we were discussing earlier.
Then we have the yes class.
You have again three positive and two negative.
Then you have this entropy.
So you do the weighted sum based on the number of per patient with fever, no, mild, yes.
Then you get 0.694 bits.
So which is better, right?
So asking the first question, you have reduced the randomness from 0.94 down to 0.694.
Improved, right?
If you ask a question, turn out the number remain the same.
What does it tell you?
If you ask a feature X, turn out your compute based on this in 4XD, turn out the number equal to 0.94.
What does it mean?
No, no, no.
It doesn't change the entropy.
The so-called information doesn't change.
Assume I have one feature X, then I compute the in 4XD, right?
And the in X may come to me three or even four outcome.
I compute this, I find that output the same as 0.940 bits.
So what does it mean physically?
The feature is useless to make you make a better decision.
It doesn't reduce the randomness at all.
You do not really need the feature at all.
It does not help you to make a better decision.
The information is still as random.
Basically, the gain is zero, right?
Early on the fever, if I compute the gain, it's 0.94 minus 0.694, I have the gain.
The gain means that the amount of randomness I can reduce.
Okay?
If this one turns out to be the same, the gain will be zero.
That means I do not reduce any randomness at all.
So that means the feature is very much useless for me to make a better decision.
Okay?
And similarly, you can compute the gain by going through the same process for cough,
salt truth, and tiredness, right?
So the final result of the gain is 0.029 for cough, 0.151 for salt truth,
and 0.048 for tiredness.
Right?
Look at which one gives you the highest gain.
It's the fever feature, right?
And with that, the fever will be select as the first attribute you are going to use
to split the trees into subsets.
It will be the root note question.
Okay?
So that is a very systematic and determined way.
Once you have the data, you just go through the programming.
You compute the one, give you the list.
Select the one as the feature to ask the first question.
Okay?
Now, the second question.
If among all the features, I have two features, give me exactly the same gain, not zero,
but both of them give me 0.246.
In fact, I said one question like that before.
Then they say, okay, which is the choose?
Now, I have two.
Give me exactly the same gain.
Which one?
Which one would you choose as the first question to ask?
If two different features among maybe 100 of the features, two of them give you exactly
the same information gain, not zero, but the highest.
Which feature of these two that you will select to ask the first question?
Both are okay, yes.
For example, basically, each of them, of course, give you the same so-called information to
make better decision.
But if I try to be critical, I say, no, you must select one for me.
Two of them, right?
Yeah.
In the first question, they may give you the same information, but it all depends on the
foreign feature.
Ultimately, you want to build the whole three to see at the end which give you the least
randomness at the end.
They may appear the same in the first question, but if you start to build two, three, you
will find that one may eventually give you a better outcome.
If you look at the first step, you may not be able to tell them apart, then you can continue
to build two different trees, but they are not exactly the same after the first question.
So these are things that, of course, will make the question more interesting.
Yes.
You don't have to combine.
Combine subset?
Just choose the one, give you the least random.
If you're only allowed to use one, right?
If you can use multiple of them, that is the concept of random forest.
You can build a few of them.
The first one is the least.
The idea of random forest is you may not be able to tell, although the first one gives
you the least, the most gain, but it may not be always the case when you go further down.
Then you can build based on this.
You can actually start with all so-called different features, build different trees.
You can have four of them, four different trees.
Each of them you ask a question.
At the end, you'll see the classification, maybe three, one, and two give you class no.
Three give you class yes, and then five, four give you class no.
The majority of them is no.
Then you say no.
You don't have to combine them somehow.
Each of them can make their independent decision.
So then, of course, then you can try to see which at the end give you the most robust answer.
Because after you select the fever, and then, of course, the job is not done yet, you split
them now, the original data 14 of them, now you split into three groups.
This is one with no fever, one with mild fever, and then the with yes fever.
Then, of course, this one, because the information is zero, you can make this already become a
no, because all of them is positive.
This one, the job not done yet, you can further divide them by, if you look carefully, the
through three minus two positive actually can be differentiated by sort through.
So you should ask a question in the second level for this branch is sort through.
In the attribute, they will give you maximum information gain.
And this one, you have two, three positive, two no, you can ask a tiredness, which allow
you to further break it into positive and negative class.
So after the two level, then you are going to arrive at zero randomness.
I've got that information gain.
But then, and the same guy, Quinglin found that, actually, this information gain will favor
if you have more and more classes.
The attribute have more outcome, like you will give you a lowest information, give you
a higher gain.
So that is not fair.
Should I favor the feature with fewer outcome or more outcome?
Then in 1993, after seven years that he proposed the ID tree, he come out with this C4.5.
So I asked why so the number looks so strange, three, 4.5.
Because these are the different version of the tree that he have tried to change the attribute
here, the gain here and there.
So come out with different version.
And then they find this 4.5 is the best so-called compromise result.
A successor of ID tree do the gain ratio, the information gain.
If further, gain A was the one we compute early.
But then they penalize, he penalized the gain A by the split in four, which is based on the
number of so-called classes that you have.
So let's say, early on you have, we have two examples, two class and three class, right?
Here, the information gain A, if you apply this diner, you only have two classes.
You have to divide this gain A, you compute early by this split in four, which now you
have only two, one to two, which each of them is three divided by six, three divided by
six, so divided by one.
But when you have three classes, then you have now two, two, two.
Then you compute the information gain, you divide this by a larger number, more than one.
So that means he penalized the output with more classes.
The same way to compute the gain A earlier, but then you normalize it by the number of
classes, the number of sample belong to each classes that you have.
And that is called gain ratio.
You find that for this case, it can normalize the output, not so that they do not just favor
the decision to attribute with more classes.
So here is the continuing example that you have earlier.
You look at the cough, the cough give you four years, then five, six miles, and then four
no.
Then the split info with the cough is four, six, four divided by 14.
So PI log two, PI a three.
So the gain, the split info is 1.557.
So early on, you have 0.029.
Now you divide it by a higher number, you further reduce the gain.
So when you have more classes, when you only have two classes, the maximum number of the
split info is one.
If you have more than two classes, this number will continue to increase unless the class
number is really skewed towards a particular class type.
Otherwise, when you have more classes, this split info will likely going to increase.
Then you penalize the gain and least favored feature with more classes.
So there is gain ratio.
Then there is another Gini index, which is another type of attribute measure.
So this one is used in CUT.
Sometimes you see this decision tree based on algorithm CUT.
You know that attribute selection feature measure it uses Gini index.
Gini index is easier because PI is the probability that in D belong to class CI.
We thought about this, right?
If you have two classes, the number three divided by six, then you have P1 equal to 0.5, P2 equal to 0.5.
Then the Gini index, for example, we showed earlier with six patients, will be one minus one divided by four minus one divided by four.
So it's going to be equal to one divided by two, which is the maximum number that you have for Gini index for two classes.
So one good thing is in here, you do not need to use a log two.
It's just a power so-called calculation.
But for Gini index, it's only considered binary split because you only have PI one to two.
So that means your outcome can only allow you to have two classes.
I mean, the feature can only have two possible answers, yes and no, or positive or negative, or one or two.
So then the Gini index after the feature A with two output, then assuming you partition the result into two classes,
two subset with D1, D2 number, then you compute the Gini of D1, which is based on this formula.
How many percent of the data belong to the positive class negative?
Then weighted by how many number of sample go to this D1 class, D2 class?
So the same thing as how we compute the information gain weighted, right, here.
The same thing that you compute here.
This is a dj divided by d.
You compute the info di, but now you use a Gini di.
So then you compute for all the attributes, then the one give you the highest gain will be selected as a feature to ask the question.
And for attribute which you have more than two classes, then you can try to separate them into two groups.
There's a different way to do it.
One, you select a split point, which is all the attribute less than or equal to the split point belong to D1.
And larger than that belong to D2, right.
That is how you convert from a so-called ratio, so-called attribute into binary attributes.
Or you can also regroup.
So no, mal, and yes.
Then you can say no and mal belong to D1, yes belong to D2.
That's how you also convert to two classes.
Or then you convert the no belong to D1, mal and yes belong to D2.
There's another possible way to break it into two groups.
Then with that you can use apply the Gini index.
So you have to split based on one example based on the earlier patient through example.
So you have 9 and 5 with the through.
Then the Gini D is 0.459.
Then if you now split based on the cough feature, let the cough no and mal belong to D1, yes belong to D2.
Further split after asking whether the patient have cough or not.
You break it into two groups, one with 10 patients with no and mal.
The other four patients with yes.
Then each of them you compute the Gini D1, which is the how many of them with the through or no.
And G2 you get the 0.443.
So that reduce the Gini index a bit.
So that means this cough is a useful feature to use.
But is it the best one you don't know yet?
So to examine other feature go to the same calculation again.
And the one give you the best so-called reduction, the highest reduction will be selected as the first feature.
Then you can start to see how T-ere is it.
After you select the first feature then you still have another three feature.
So you can start to see which will be the next question to ask.
Go to the same calculation again.
At the end is very tedious.
So why so many different so-called measure?
Which one is better?
In fact if you look closely they are not very much different.
So this is the graph illustration to tell you.
I'll show you this so-called entropy.
Entropy the light gray color.
But because this one the highest value is one different from those for the two class problem.
Different from the Gini and the classification error.
The one we when we went to the example I asked how many sample cannot make correct decision.
There is a percentage of error like 33%, 50%.
So you can see that in terms of the index they are just different kind of curve.
For error is this, the triangle.
And for Gini is the green color.
For entropy original is this gray color but you scale them so that the maximum all the same as 0.5.
You just divided this by two you get the red color.
So what it tell you is they are very much performing the same way.
Basically the least random they all come down to 0.
The most random they give you the highest value.
Just the way they reduce when you are more and more certain and this one linearly reduce.
This one start slowly then it favor the one with least random.
So it drop faster the rate is faster than this.
And this Gini is somehow in between.
So therefore for many many example that you try if your test data is not a huge data set.
You find that three of them basically give you almost the same result.
And but there are also cases that you'll find one slightly better than the other.
But to me they are more or less the same.
And if the three in the exam I ask a question I say build a decision tree.
I don't restrict you on which measure to use.
So which one will you select in your three building so-called exercise.
Which one.
Go by the error classification error which will be easier to count.
You don't have to further do the log or square.
Just count how many sample you still cannot make correct decision.
So the blue line will be the one you don't even need to write any formula just count.
Then you can decide which give you the best so-called feature.
Okay.
So that is a decision tree.
So shall we.
Okay maybe two more slides then we take a break they will come back.
So three pruning of course you can build the tree of course as I say when the data set is huge.
And you may create many many levels of tree and many many branches.
And this could be caused by noise right when you collect the data you cannot be certain that all the data are accurate.
There are no outliers right.
The person that you ask a question may not provide the so-called valid information to you right.
They create noise right then you make error right.
So then you need to so-called prune the tree to make sure that your tree doesn't overfit those noise or those error or those outliers right.
And sometimes you also want to prune the tree so that you can make a faster decision right.
If you certain branch you go down to many level you only make one more correct.
But you have to ask another 10 questions right.
So you find it okay they may not be worthwhile to ask so many questions at the end you only get a 10% gain whatever.
So you have to prune the tree that's how you make simpler decision and sometimes you actually make better decision because you might overfit noise to the tree.
And sometimes you want to make a simple decision which often may give you a better clarity in terms of the decision making process.
So in you have two ways to prune the tree right.
One is the pre pruning the approach.
Basically when you stop building the tree you find there a particular note.
Note that now majority belong to one class only very small number of sample belong to another class.
You will say okay I will just stop here.
95% accuracy is good enough for me right.
Some of the decision may not be so critical you need to have 100 right.
You say okay this is I can accept right.
So you just stop there you don't have to ask more questions.
So it's called pre pruning.
The other is you build the whole tree first ask all the questions you can ask and you look at the tree right huge.
You will say okay there are certain branches here if I cut here I may not need to ask a lot of questions which just give me another 2% gain right.
I think here is the one right.
So you can build a tree on the left after you build everything.
You look carefully you say okay I think that because there could be 95% or the sample or come here only 5% come here.
But with the 5% of them come here only one sample is yes most of them are no right.
So I will just stop here.
I don't want to ask two more questions.
2 and 3 5 I will just stop here right.
So that means for all the questions come here now I can only ask two questions.
I will get the result right and early on I had to ask 5 questions maximum 5 questions or possible 3 questions but you need to have the answer for all the 5 questions which path that you go right.
So this is called pruning right.
So you will not necessarily always give you poorer result because you will have the structure you train the tree build the tree using your training data.
But ultimately you want to apply this tree to your unseen data right.
So you might try both of them to the unseen data they may both give you the same result maybe even the smaller tree give you a better result.
So that is the testing error right.
So okay can we go through two more slides.
So advantages of decision tree compared to other method we are going to look at later and they are quite inexpensive to build right.
So manually is tedious but if you have a computer program you find that compared to those the neural network running which you have to go through many so called iteration to arrive at the so called minimum error the gradient descent calculation.
And this is relatively easy to build right.
So you try out some program you find the total moment you hit enter the tree is there right compared to the network you have to wait for half an hour sometime before you see the result.
So once a decision tree is built you only need to ask the order of how maximum level of question the order of W which is the maximum level this is the worst case scenario.
So you know how many level you have that is the maximum number of question you need to ask to arrive at the decision.
It's also easy to interpret right it's so called the expandable when you make the decision you can go back to the tree why you make the decision or because the patient have cough because the patient also have mouth fever and you also have salt throat therefore it likely to have the flu symptom.
So there are reasons that you can provide to the patient why he is likely have cough so easy to interpret.
So in machine learning this call explainable right a lot of the new network you don't know why it give you the output like that.
Can you explain sorry I don't know it's a black box so you don't want that just like a lot of so called medical decision right.
When you tell the patient you have certain disease cancer the patient ask you why I don't know so you don't have to trust you what why why he says the new number tell me so but it's not going to buy any so called confident from them.
It has to it's quite robust to noise and redundant attributes right if you have a lot of data is certain attributes are not useful to arrive at the decision depending on the branches you go down.
You may not ask a question number five you may not ask this attribute those noise those redundant may not so called misled you to make a wrong decision right in the center is quite robust based on all the data if they are somehow homogeneous or consistent and you most of you get to the result even occasionally you have some noise or missing data.
Can avoid overfitting the problems if you do the pruning try not to build too many levels where you build a tree can decide I want to stop at level five right then it may avoid overfitting the problem because the more you go down the tree and then the number of sample reduced and then you most likely will overfit to the training data which is not always good because the test data may not have those kind of irregularity.
And you do not need to have the distribution of the attribute follow like Gaussian or Laplacian you do not need to make all the assumption you just based on the sample you have you can just build a tree regardless what kind of distribution they have.
And more importantly and often if you compare the result with some new name what other approach right the result is not bad and sometimes even better if you apply random for us.
Okay.
Random for us is basically an ensemble classifier which leveraged the power of multiple decision tree for making better decision.
Right.
Early on I say that you could have a thousand of features right if we use all the thousand feature to build one tree you can think of the tree is going to be very huge and very complex.
So rather than that you are not guaranteed that all the thousand features are useful.
Right.
So then you can use this so-called random for us.
One is there are different way to build it.
You build multiple trees.
But one type is each tree you only build the tree using a subset of the features random subset you just select right and thousand you select 100 of them to build the tree.
Then in our tree you then select another hundred of them or another 50 of them they can build 100 trees.
Right.
Each of them will give you a decision and then based on the majority of the decision made by the tree then you decide.
Okay.
Most likely this patient have this and this and this.
All right.
In the future you can use different sample because you could have millions of data set right.
You could use all the million data set to build a tree or you could divide all the data set each time you select 1000 of them sample build one tree.
Next time select randomly and a thousand of them.
Build another tree.
Right.
You can replicate some of the sample called the replacement you select by allowed to put back the next tree you can select the sample again.
Then you build three they call backing or bootstrap aggregating.
Then each tree you can make a decision.
Then you have multiple tree you have multiple decision then you just select out of this multiple and three that's called wisdom or crowd.
Right.
Sometimes you see those show they cannot make decision they decide to ask their friends or ask the audience.
Tell me the answer then the one with the most choices like the will be a good decision to make.
It's called wisdom or crowd.
So random forest can be more accurate than decision trees and it can handle missing data because if you have a sample that which you know have all the attribute.
But some tree would have some of the feature you have they can make decision some tree cannot make decision no output but you still have partial three can make decision.
So that means you do not need all the feature it can be.
It can handle missing data well can handle outlier well so that often that random forest is one of the popular method even today if many questions you can do.
Okay let's take a break here.
15 minutes break come back at 2.30 they will continue the rest.
Come back at 2.30.
Okay.
I
Das k Heil
Yes,
D
the nearest neighbor, SVM, Newnight work.
It's just how you can evaluate classification method.
So, of course, very often that we measure
the outcome accuracy, right?
Which is how many percent of the data
you can make correct decision, okay?
And of course, you can also just focus on the test set
or unseen data set.
And then which allow you to be more objective.
You do not really train so-called,
so-called optimize the classifier
based on your trained data.
So you want to keep the test set aside
so you can have more independent evaluation.
So let's consider two class of sample.
You certainly can extend this to multiple class,
but to make it simple,
we just look at the two class problem.
Let's say even a multiple class, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4,
you can always break this multiple class
into two group of classes, right?
Yes or no or the rest of them, okay?
So there's a two class problem.
Basically, you are going to, let's say,
decide whether a patient got COVID or not, right?
Positive or negative sample, okay?
So these are some of the so-called measure
that you can apply.
One is a true positive.
First, you look at the number first.
So let's say the number of them,
the sample have a positive sample
and you, it is correctly labeled by the classifier.
We call this true positive.
If you have a sample which has COVID
and then your classifier also says so,
then this is a true positive, right?
But if you have a sample,
it doesn't have the COVID
and then your classifier also labels so,
there is a true negative.
I mean, these true positive and true negatives
are correct classification result.
However, you could have this a false positive.
That means a sample without COVID
or without a true, but your classifier say yes,
it has a true, okay?
And you could have false negative.
That means a sample with a positive COVID,
then your classifier say it doesn't.
So it becomes a false negative.
And sometimes look at the possible cause or consequence.
Let's say if you are looking at a so-called classifier,
which decide whether a patient has cancer or not.
Apparently you want the true positive as high as possible
and because if a patient had cancer,
you better detect it so that you can so-called apply
the treatment as soon as possible, okay?
You also want the true negatives as high as possible,
but it is not as critical
because even your first diagnosed without cancer, okay?
And then you actually did not make a correction,
diagnose it as a so-called false positive.
Then later on you can verify it,
it is actually a true negative, right?
But this false negative will be serious, right?
If someone actually had cancer,
but your classifier say you do not have cancer, right?
And after a few months,
again this patient will come back to tell you
that you make a wrong decision,
you'll cause him the life, right?
And therefore the consequence may not be the same, right?
So you have to look at how you wait
the so-called cause of all these decisions, right?
So then you can kind of define a number
of these so-called measure, performance measure, right?
For example, these are the,
based on the earlier two class example,
these are the actual classes, right?
The one with certain so-called symptom
or without symptom, cancer, no cancer.
And this is what you predict, right?
If there's cancer you predict cancer,
then it's a true positive.
Cancer you predict, no cancer is a false negative.
With no cancer you predict as a cancer,
then it's a false positive
and then true negative for no and no, right?
So you can see that this is a total number of
sample that you actually,
the original sample have this so-called yes class, right?
The number of sample with no actual classes.
But this P-pram will be the number of sample
you predicted to have this a yes class, okay?
No, M-pram is no, okay?
Assuming you can see that this P plus N
equal to P-prams plus M-prams is same thing, okay?
Then the accuracy of the classifier is defined as
TP plus TN divided by P plus N.
This is total number of samples.
These are the number of sample you make correct decision.
Yes is yes, no is no, okay?
And then the error rate of the classifier
become one minus this accuracy.
So this is actually the false positive
plus false negative divided by total number of sample, right?
So that is error rate.
Okay, certainly you want the accuracy
as high as possible.
So that means the error rate is also as low as possible.
But these are not all the measure you have
and you can also look at the sensitivity, right?
Which is a true positive divided by the total number
of positive sample.
So what does that mean?
That means for all those sample with the symptom
with the cancer, how many of them
you can correctly label them so, right?
That is called sensitivity.
Whether your classifier is sensitive enough
to pick up those all those positive cases, right?
Let's say cancer example.
You certainly want your classifier to be very sensitive.
Whoever have the symptom you want to detect,
COVID-19, you don't want them to actually go back
and then continue to spread the virus, right?
You also want to have the specificity,
this you mean that true negative divided by negative.
For those without the symptom,
you also want the classifier to say so
as highly as possible.
So for cancer example, and certainly sensitivity
is more important than specificity, right?
Because for specificity, if you wrongly diagnose it,
then you can have further examination.
At the end, you may verify whether it's correct or not.
Then accuracy, if you define so,
become the weighted average of the sensitivity
plus the specificity based on total number
of true positive and negative sample.
And precision is another measure you might come across.
This happened more in the retriever.
Let's say you want to search some information
and you want the return, right?
Think about like you want to go to Google,
go to website, you want to search for some information, right?
Certainly you want the return to be as accurate as possible.
You don't want to have a lot of those website or link
which is not relevant to what you are looking for, right?
But if you are looking for, for example,
pass your exam question,
you may also want the recall to be as high as possible, right?
Whatever likely to be a pass your exam question
or even better this year exam question,
you want to be returned to you,
then you do all the practice.
You don't want to leave anyone out.
So for the cases, you may want to have
as high recall as possible.
And precision may not be so important, right?
It all depends on your application, right?
And therefore these two is a trade off.
Often that when the precision is high,
the recall is low, okay?
You likely cannot have both of them is 100%.
For example, give me an example
is I want to search for this year exam question.
I go to the internet or you want to ask a chat, GPD.
Can you find me?
What are the question that are you going to appear
in this year, six, four, eight, three final exam?
Okay, so can I have
high recall or low precision
or you want low high precision or low recall, right?
So these are the trade off, right?
Whatever you want to search from,
let's say, assuming the answer is out there
in the internet, I can always give you 100% recall
but 0% precision.
You ask me, where can I find this information?
I say, it is out there in all the internet, right?
Recall is 100%, but precision is almost zero.
That means you have to go and exam all the link, right?
Finally, you may find it, but just take a longer time.
And I can also have high precision as high as possible
but with zero recall or very low recall.
I only find the one, you give me an example,
can you find me a website or object similar to this?
I say, yeah, that is the one, that's the only one I have.
So there's 100% precision but almost zero recall
because there are many out there, I will not return to you.
So these are the trade off that you sometimes have to consider.
And for convenience, of course, sometimes two-figure,
you have to evaluate this classifier is better than not.
If you have two number, then it's hard to compare.
One is high, the other could be low, right?
Which ones do you choose?
So you can combine them by into a so-called F measure,
which is two type precision and recall,
divided by precision plus recall, right?
This F measure, you look at it carefully,
will only be a high value when both precision and recalls
are high, okay?
When any of them is low, then this F will be low, okay?
So if one is very high, the other is a meter,
then it's somewhere in between.
So but at least now they give you a one number, right?
Then two number you have to trade off.
And you can find many other F measure
with different so-called weightage
or different so-called weight to combine them together.
So here is another evaluation curve.
So early on when we talk about this,
this assume that you already have one classifier,
which always give you a fixed result.
But you could have a set of classifier,
which depend on the threshold that you set, right?
Whether you want to have weighty deliver,
I'll return or all the return,
then you can adjust the threshold.
What is the confident that you have?
Then for that, you have a method,
but there's also parameter you can adjust.
Then you want to evaluate the performer,
all the possible parameter you can set.
And that you come up with this so-called AUC.
So it's called area under curve.
So what you measure is a curve, right?
Then a number.
And this curve will operate at different force positive rate
and over this true positive rate, okay?
So true positive rate is again TP divided by P.
In general, you want this to be as high as possible.
And force positive rate,
you want this to be as low as possible.
So let me ideally you want this curve,
the area here like this.
This is the line that,
this is the perhaps the ideal line that you are looking for.
One here, then drop to zero, right?
So this area will be 100%.
You want to have the true positive rate
as high as possible,
while the force negative rate is very low.
So you can work on this region, right?
This is the area that you want your classifier to operate on.
So therefore the area will be the best.
You select the treasure.
When you change basically,
you select different so-called treasure, different computer.
So you can certainly select the one here,
which give you the highest true positive rate
and lowest false positive rate, okay?
So that means this is the best classifier.
And this is probably the worst,
meaning that 50%, 50% error, right?
You don't do anything, it's a give you 50%.
And most classifier with some parameters,
it just fall between these two extreme line here.
Therefore you measure the area under the curve.
The higher the area,
the better the performance of the classifier.
And this was early on used for so-called detecting
whether there is a aircraft coming or enemy coming.
They call receiver operating characteristic measure, right?
They try to have radar to check
whether the enemy aircraft is coming in or not.
They adjust different kind of sensitivity.
Then test the performance.
So we come with the name ROC curve.
Then here are some example
to make sure that you know how to calculate them.
So for example, in here,
we consider, okay, when I give you
so-called actual sample number,
actually for example, you can go back to
the decision tree we built earlier, right?
We have built some decision tree.
You can apply the training data
or a few test samples to apply to the decision tree
to get outcome.
So you know the actual class, right?
For your test sample, then the decision tree predict
what is a yes number or yes and no,
then you can fill in this number
based on the number or sample you have.
Then for different decision tree,
you can decide which one is better.
So in this case, we have 10,000 patient information
which try to predict whether the output
of the class is yes or no for the flu virus, right?
So basically you have 10,000 patients.
Among them, 300 has a flu virus.
Majority 9,700 do not have a flu so-called symptom.
But when you predict them, you use a tree,
you build, you predict 250 out of 300 correctly
with so-called flu virus.
And then, I mean, with virus yes,
and then those without virus.
So you predicted 250 of them have the flu virus,
but among them only 100 of them are true positive.
And another 150 of them are false positive.
That means those patients without virus,
but you incorrectly label them have virus, right?
And similarly for the majority you predict no,
but among these no, in fact,
200 of them actually have virus, okay?
Then you can compute the sensitivity
and like this sensitivity is a TP divided by P, right?
TP is 100 divided by 300, so 33% of them, right?
You actually are sensitive enough to detect
among the 300 patient with true virus,
you only pick up 33% of them, which is 100.
And this specificity is the,
this so-called TN divided by N, right?
So among the 9,700 without virus,
you can pinpoint 9,550 of them,
so there is a 98.45%.
Okay?
So let's say if you apply this for the cancer diagnosis,
it is really not very good
because you actually missed the patient
which actually have cancer, majority of them, right?
Of course, this one, 98 of them,
there will be another 12.55% of them
will be labeled as yes,
and then they will to suffer further test.
Then accuracy will be this so-called 100 plus 9,550, right?
TP plus TN divided by total number, which is 96.50.
So although you have high, rather high accuracy,
but bear in mind that your sensitivity is rather low, right?
So if you go to a hospital, the doctor tell you that,
my accuracy 96.5% or seem reliable,
you say, can I know your sensitivity?
33% okay, better not.
I don't know whether you trust your life with this person,
say you only identify one out of three
with the so-called symptoms,
because the base is huge, right?
Most people would not have that kind of symptom.
Therefore you could have very high accuracy,
but not really sensitive enough to identify your symptom.
So precision is 100 divided by 250,
so TP divided by P-prum here, okay?
Recall is 33%, right?
So F is, because one of them is low, right?
So therefore F become quite low, 36.36%.
Even, actually two of them precision and the recall are both low.
So you have to understand the meaning
of all these so-called measures and see how they apply.
Of course, beside the accuracy, sensitivity,
this so-called specificity,
you can also evaluate a classifier
based on other measures like speed, right?
You certainly want it to so-called decide as soon as possible,
just like the Chatchapiti.
At first it came out, you ask a question,
it takes a while before it can answer you, right?
Because its speed is not fast enough,
but some of the smaller so-called large location model
can give you the answer almost immediately.
Robustness, right?
You want the classifier to make correct decision,
even you have some noisy data or redundant data
or missing data, right?
If it doesn't tell you, let's say, what is the income level,
right?
It can still make correct decision.
Actually, it's not the important whether this patient
is rich or not.
It's more important whether he has a symptom or not, right?
So, scalability, you want it to be applied to a lot of data,
you may build your network based on this hospital,
but this classifier hopefully can be applied
to another hospital or another country.
You don't want it to fail.
So you want it to be able to scale,
not just to a different number of user
and also different area, different patient.
You need to be able to interpret the data, right?
Just like classifier, you can tell the patient
why I make this decision because this, this, this, right?
You have to be able to provide the insight,
provide the reason.
So here, this is another way to also evaluate
the classifier performance.
Of course, how do you test them?
Let's say if you have trained data, you have test data,
but there are many different ways you can do it.
The most common is the handout method,
which you divide your, this one we mentioned earlier,
you divide your data into two parts.
And one part, majority of them you use for training.
The rest of them, minority, you use for testing, right?
And the training set is used to learn the classifier,
and accuracy is evaluated by the test set, okay?
Hand out method, this is also known as this.
But whether it's any two-third one-third is,
depend on the number of data you have, right?
If you only have six data, right?
One-third is already two out of six.
Then the four may not be able to build
any delivery, right?
If you have a billion of so-called patients,
then you may not need one-third.
There's a lot of data, right?
You may only need one percent, which could be enough, right?
So it all depends on how many data sample you have.
And the other is called cross-varyration,
and which, assuming you have a lot of data,
rather than you test it only for one particular test set,
you can divide your data into 10 different subsets,
or V different subsets.
Each time you use the remaining,
you pick out one as a test set,
the remaining use it to do the training.
Then you build one tree, right?
To evaluate performance.
Then you can select the next subset as a test set,
and then the other remaining one as a so-called training set.
So at the end, if you're a K of them,
then you're going to have a K different so-called
evaluation, then you can take the average of them.
So that evaluates the performance capability
of the architecture of the scheme that you have
by going through different combination
of training and test data.
This is called cross-varyration.
You don't use it just once.
You can select different set of a test set,
and then apply multiple times.
In the extreme, you only have a small data set.
You can say, leave one out.
You're going to reserve one for testing.
The rest, for just now the sixth example, right?
And you just keep one,
and then use the other five to build a tree,
and then use the last one to test.
And you can repeat this six times
then to see whether the results are good enough.
This is called leave one out.
You may come across such term.
Okay?
So that is decision three.
Let's summarize it.
And we thought about the classification step,
which normally involve a training,
and then test set to predict the classes of data.
And then in terms of attributes, the feature,
there are four types of attributes,
nominal, on-in, interval, and ratio.
And not all the classifier can use
all these kind of features.
Some of them depend on the so-called
calculation involved,
and you may only use certain type of attribute
rather than all these attributes.
But certainly you want to have a classifier
that can take input like nominal, ordinal,
so-called input together with interval.
It could be text, could be image,
could be audio, could be speech, all together.
They come out in model classifier.
So decision three basically try to ask a sequence of question
and based on the answer,
if asked further question,
then derive at the decision.
So, and then when you build the decision tree,
you have to select one attribute selection measure
to select which attribute is the best
to ask a question at the level.
So this attribute measure including the information gain,
Gini gain index,
and these are the gain ratio, Gini index,
these are the measure that you can use.
Yeah, and then perform measure,
there are many more measures you can use
to assess the classifier, not just accuracy,
many other things that you have to consider,
like the speed, the cost,
and whether you allow missing data
and allow some of these so-called outlier,
and these are things that you have to be aware of.
Okay, let's go through the nearest neighbor classifier
before we end the lecture today.
And this nearest neighbor classifier,
these are the two different classifiers
that you may come across.
The nearest neighbor classifier is perhaps the simplest
that classifier can think of.
Again, this is just a recap.
These are the classification so-called definition.
For nearest neighbor classifier,
basically you try to assign each sample
the class label of the nearest training sample.
So what does it mean?
Here, if you have a training sample,
the red and the blue, right?
You know the class label of all these training samples,
the red classes and the blue classes.
So now you are given a new sample X.
You want to ask what is the label of this X?
So intuitively, you just say that,
okay, this X is most likely similar to
based on whatever feature or attribute.
You look at it, right?
Okay, it's similar to this object
and this object belong to blue class.
So therefore, this new object should belong to the blue class.
So this is called nearest neighbor, right?
So basically you check this one.
And this one, if it's closer to the blue,
you have to find a way to measure so-called the distance,
the similarity between this sample
with all the rest of the training sample, right?
Before you know the nearest neighbor,
of course you have to know to ask,
is this closer to this?
Is it closer to that?
To this, to this?
So you do a lot of checking
before you know who is your nearest neighbor.
So you can see that you do not need any training, right?
Because you just need to have all the sample,
you know the label, right?
But you need to store all these samples with the label
and then you need a lot of computation
when you come to the inference.
Given any sample you know to check,
who is your nearest neighbor, right?
It's very time consuming, right?
Assuming that you have to compare this,
let's say phase recognition, I give a phase, okay?
Who is this person?
They look, okay, he's similar to no, doesn't see, okay?
You have to compare with all the other person
in your data batch, right?
Before you can draw who this person is.
And to be robust to the noise seed sample,
sometimes your sample actually may not be noise free, right?
So for example, in this case,
you could have some training sample red and blue.
Now you have this, okay?
Now the question is who is your nearest neighbor, right?
It seems like it's equal distance to red and blue.
They cannot make decision.
Therefore you come with this K-nearest neighbor, right?
So rather than one, I say, okay,
who are my three nearest neighbor, right?
Among these three, I have two blue, one red.
So I say, okay, most likely this is a blue, right?
You seem somehow maturity vote idea
that allow you to be more robust to some outlier noise
or imperfect so-called data collection, right?
So as you can see that you need to have a way to measure
who are my K-nearest neighbor, right?
So you can use some kind of distance
which are often used to measure the dissimilarity
between two data sample or attribute.
Earlier we say the attribute could be a vector, right?
Then when you have vector,
you have those so-called number
that you can do the difference, you can do the division.
Then you can apply some of these so-called measure.
One of them is called Minkowski distance,
Minkowski distance, and between two data point
which x, y could be vector of n dimensional
vector, you can define them as summation.
This component wise, the subtract xk minus yk,
you raise the power r, you sum them up,
then you take the root of one divided by r, right?
So if this is equal to r is some kind of parameter
that you can choose, right?
It could be one, could be two, could be three,
could be even a very large number, right?
So when r equal to one,
and this Minkowski distance,
actually turning into this so-called component y distance,
which is called L1 norm, right?
Basically x1 minus y1,
take the absolute value plus x2 minus y2,
absolute value plus x-ectron under xn minus yn, okay?
And this is also known as a city block
because like New York, actually the street is very square,
right?
From here to there, you basically go through how many blocks?
Regardless, whether you go to horizontal or vertical,
you still have to go through the same number of blocks distance.
Okay?
This is called L1 norm.
And of course, something that you probably very familiar with
is called L2 norm, which is also known as equidian distance,
which is the direct measure of a two point
in the 3D Cartesian coordinate, right?
And when r become infinity,
which we call it the supremum or L infinity
or L maximum norm,
which basically just measure the maximum difference
between any corresponding attribute.
Basically, sk minus yk, if r approach infinity,
only the component with the largest xk minus yk
will be the deciding factor.
The value will be the largest difference,
regardless which direction, right?
Which dimension?
The one which is the largest at the end
will dominate all the distance, okay?
So there is a L sub-penial norm.
So let's look at the graphically, what does it mean?
It's just like the genie, the grain ratio
or the information gain, right?
They are more or less a distant measure,
just how you keep the weightage of each dimension, right?
So in this case, assuming xk,
we have two dimensional data, x1 minus one,
I call it e1, the difference, e2 is the difference.
So another x2 minus y2,
and this is the curve of the point on this,
when r equal to one,
these are all the point, e1 and e2 distant,
they have an equal distance equal to one.
They are all here, right?
e1 is here, e2 is here, then the distant r,
this is dxy equal to one.
And when the r increase,
you can see that the equal distant one,
it becomes so-called further away from the center
until r equal to infinity, right?
This one actually measure the maximum,
you have e1 and e2, right?
For this point, all the e1 equal to one,
here all the e2 equal to one,
regardless what is the other e,
then you have this one equal to maximum.
So they are all some kind of distant measure,
just how you want to give the weight
in the different so-called component differences.
You can just choose anyone,
of course, normally we will use the L2 norm, right?
Which allow you to do a lot of so-called
gradient descent, back propagation.
We also want in the Neural Network,
using L2 norm, then how do you devise
a back propagation measure to optimize the parameter?
So when r is larger equal to one,
the Minkowski distant has this useful measure.
Okay, when you measure the difference between two points,
you want that the distant from x to y
should be the same of a so-called distant
from y to x, right?
Because all the, they're called symmetric, right?
You want this property to hold.
And also because it's a distant,
you want the distance is always larger than,
or equal to zero.
They are equal to zero only if x equal to y.
This is called positivity.
And the third one is called triangle inequality.
Here, let's say you have a distant of xy,
xz and yz.
You want the xz should not be larger than yz plus xz.
You want to walk, right, in a straight way,
and you can walk two distant,
but certainly you expect that the straight direction
will be shorter than the other two, right?
If you measure distant measures satisfy
all these three properties,
then they are known as a matrix.
Matrix, there is a how, the Euclidean,
of course, when I go to two,
the Euclidean distant will satisfy the matrix.
Okay?
But there are some measures that do not satisfy
one or more of these matrix properties.
You can think about when r is less than one.
Okay?
Find out when, what measure is not satisfied.
Think about it.
If r is less than one for the Minkowski,
one of the measures,
one of these, the so-called property,
would not really satisfy.
And of course, beside the Minkowski distant,
you can also use a so-called cosine similarity, right?
And which is often used to measure
the document similarity.
Basically, let's say you want to compare the two documents,
whether they are similar or not, how do you do that?
You cannot compare word by word,
and you can rewrite the whole document
and turn out, they may look very different,
or you miss one line, the rest may be still the same,
but if you compare word by word,
everything will be different, right?
So it's not a good measure, just compare word by word,
but you can use a cosine similarity,
which you can have two different vectors,
x could be the count of those keywords in document one.
You could have, let's say, 1000 commonly used keywords.
Then in document one, you find, okay,
keyword number one appear how many times,
keyword number two appear how many times, right?
Then you can build a vector or attribute x,
then document two y.
Then you can use this cosine similarity,
which is nothing but a dot product, x dot product with y.
I assume you know how to compute a dot product
for two vector, right?
And which actually, if you heard about the transformer,
the attention model, right?
The first input is actually a dot product.
They try to decide the input sentence,
the similarity of this to itself,
self similarity, right?
By applying dot product.
So again, you should be familiar with this one.
If you cosine x and y is similar to x dot product y,
which is this, normalized by this L2 norm of x
and L2 norm of y, for example,
which is also the same as a measure
the angle between these two vector,
the cosine theta between these two vector.
When this theta equal to zero,
then it is two x and y overlap.
So cosine zero will be equal to one.
It is the highest similar, okay, possible.
When this theta is 90 degree,
then this will be equal to zero.
They mean these two vectors are perpendicular to each other.
Okay?
So question, if I distant,
if I one minus cosine xy, cosine xy similarity,
meaning when the value is high,
then the distance is small.
So one minus cosine xy will become the distant, right?
When the cosine xy equal to zero,
then the distance is maximum equal to one.
Okay?
Assuming I only look at the cosine xy,
which is a positive value.
So is this matrix,
is the cosine symmetric for few,
all the, this requirement,
is a distant positivity symmetric triangle inequality.
Satisfied?
Go and check.
And I can tell you that it doesn't meet this, right?
You could have x and y, they are on the same direction,
but x equal to two y.
Okay?
And then the distant base on cosine similarity
will be equal to zero.
Even one is longer, the other is shorter,
but because the angle between them is zero.
So cosine zero is one, one minus one is zero.
So that means you could have x not equal to y,
but the xy equal to zero.
Okay?
Yeah.
So nearest neighbor certainly is very useful,
but when you try to apply it to complex data like this,
let's say you want to use one image
to find similar images.
So this is a C-far 10 data set
that we introduced before,
which has 60,000 images, 32 by 32 pixel color images,
10 classes.
These are the 10 classes,
A-plane, car, bird, cat, deer, dog, right?
X, X, X, X, right?
So if I apply the k nearest neighbor,
I combine all the 32 by 32 pixel times three color
into a long vector.
Then I do the direct subtraction
to find which are the nearest neighbor.
So for example, you can find this one,
a truck, the nearest neighbor are this,
the 10 nearest neighbor.
You can see that even the horse becomes the most similar.
It had the same so-called structure,
but the object are different, right?
So this one is slightly better,
and you can see that some of them
is really not at the same object.
If you want to use this to retrieve the object
of the same class,
k nearest neighbor classifier would not work well.
Therefore you need a higher line
neural network to help you to build a better classifier.
You can go there to this website to try out yourself.
The k nearest neighbor classifier is not a good measure
when you apply it to such an example
to find similar images of similar content.
Okay?
So we will come back with the support vector machine
next lecture, and then after that,
I will start the neural network.
I will spend more time on neural network.
And okay, this is the orange data set.
You can go to try out yourself, right?
And go to this website.
Yeah, this is a tool that you can use to do some kind
of basic data mining or model like this.
You can do k nearest neighbor, decision tree, random.
You don't have to write any program.
You can load in a lot of data and then play around with it.
Just watch some of the YouTube video, how to do that.
For example, data, okay, you could have data here.
You can select the data and here is a Titanic data, right?
So it tell you some of this category, the feature, right?
You heard about the Titanic data or other data set, like,
iris data, right?
This one to give you a different type of flower.
So you can do in this a numeric data.
These are the feature and these are the target category, right?
So you can go in, do this.
Then you can visualize the data, for example,
it's my visualization, okay?
You can plot this, it's quite easy to link them together.
No need to write program, right?
It's free.
I think you can look at the data, you see?
You have three data type.
This is iris centosa, iris versicolor virginica,
and this is the separate length,
the length of the flower, the leaf, right?
This is the width, right?
This is a distribution of the data
and then the petal length, or this is very good
in the sense that you can differentiate this
from the other two and width, okay?
You can inspect the data.
Then you can build a classifier, let's see,
let's show you how easy it can be.
Where is my decision tree?
Model, okay, this is a decision tree, okay?
Here, I build the data here.
I perform decision tree, but I have to view the tree,
tree viewer, check the result.
Okay, this is a decision tree, now done, right?
Based on the petal length, it is cited,
you can go and examine the number of the feature.
So I tell you that you should use the petal length.
Then these are the question you ask,
and this is a decision, how many they make correctly,
how many make it wrongly, right?
You can also, this undimitted, I can set it to two level,
three level, right?
And of course you can do other more complex canes.
You have the other projector, like canes and neighbor, right?
You can also do that.
Move this canes and neighbor,
and then I can do the performer measure.
Where's my performer measure?
Okay, evaluation, okay?
You can do the confusion matrix.
Go, you have to do some kind of test and scoring, yeah.
Here, okay.
Test and scoring, and then performer measure, yeah.
Okay, confusion, call it.
Okay.
I think something is not correct,
evaluation, the result, performance, curve prediction.
Maybe prediction first.
Go and play around this data.
You can also have other NUNA network,
many other classifier, random forest, SVM,
and linear regression NUNA network.
And yeah, you can also put different
kind of performance curve, ROC, and yeah.
So quite easy to use, okay?
Download and play around.
You can load in a lot of data and to play around, okay?
So this is one of the two that hopefully you can,
I think you have a project, right?
I'm not sure whether you can use it,
at least verify the result, okay?
So I will see you next Thursday again.
Yeah, next Thursday.
Next week, I will probably send out the assignment,
homework assignment, so you have two assignments to do,
right?
Class is recess week, and after the recess week, okay?
I may send out the homework earlier,
so we can take a look at it.
Thank you.