.
Okay. So, yeah, before we start our discussions, here's a piece of information you can share
So, confirm the date and also, yeah, basically just a date because of time.
First session for undergrad, so you don't need to worry about, but the two sessions for post-grad
and the list is not available yet. They are still working on it.
But you can see, yeah, two sessions. So one starting from 10.35, another from 11.40.
Each session is 45 minutes. It's in the lab. So you will be in one of the lab, you know,
either ISL, IM workshop, or EFS, or the last one, the PCD.
So they will tell us the exact date. I mean, later we will see for each of you which location you will be put in, which session.
So we will get that list later. So as soon as I have it, I definitely will upload to the course website.
Okay. So just book your calendar. That date is fixed now.
Okay. So the date is available next Saturday.
So not this coming Saturday, but next week.
Oh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. We are in, yes, we are in week four, week six.
Okay. So it's not next. It's not this week. It's not next week. It's a week after.
Okay. Okay. So that is about the quiz, which is only my part.
And that's why it's from the week one to week five.
The first, I only have one hour in week five.
Okay. So I'll say lecture one to 13 for the first 13 hours.
Okay. So this is for your information first.
And then we can move on to our discussions.
Okay. So great. This is the last topic I need to cover.
Okay. So what we are doing today is we want to introduce the data mining,
especially the two important algorithms to us.
Okay. So this is the main focus.
So basically still symbolic face approach.
Okay. So we focus on, before we have deep learning way to do recommendation.
And how do we do the association of mining?
How to find interesting patterns or significance important patterns or kind of knowledge.
Using this knowledge to make decision or solve problems.
Okay. So this is what we are going to talk about data mining and also the related algorithm.
As well as in the end, actually the knowledge is represented by a set of the rules.
So that's why we say, actually, it's a, let's create, represent everything to show the association or correlation to see the patterns or items.
The items we are interested to see how they related to each other and how can we make sense of it.
Okay. So this rule actually presented in the way of association rule.
How the A associate with B. The A and B association, each, it can be a set of items.
Okay. So it's called item set.
So item set including, for example, Apple banana associate with cornflakes milk, for example.
Okay. So that is association.
But can be like Apple banana and also fruits, other fruits like grapes associate with just milk.
You know, so header and tell doesn't matter.
Doesn't need to be balanced.
And also the items from set to another set.
Okay. How they related.
That's final delivery.
So that is association mining, the end results.
Okay. So the key thing here is how to find out what are the patterns are interesting.
Right. What are the patterns which is significant enough.
Why you bother banana, Apple and the grape.
Why not I'm interested in tomato and the salad other things, you know, like celery.
So other things why I'm interested in these three items and related to another few items.
Right. So that is one question.
Another question is how to quickly identify these things and how to measure the importance and significance.
Of these items and how to associate them under what condition this rule is confident enough to say, okay, Apple and banana associate with milk, for example.
Right. How confident, how confident you are.
So this rule, how strong this rule is.
So this is things we want to answer.
Okay. So you can see here.
So first few minutes.
I tried to cut down the first hour about introduction to data mining.
And then we want to more talk about the actual algorithms.
Okay. So algorithm will spend more time, but we still need to know what's the difference between data information knowledge or even wisdoms.
Okay. So what, what, what is this about.
And then different type of data like the market basket data.
Okay. The association of the transaction data we want to focus on.
And then talk about what are the key functionalities or tasks we are, we are, we try to address for under the data mining.
And then we talk about the different kind of, I mean, the key tasks.
So you can see association analysis. This is the focus.
Okay. So we are going to talk more the algorithms to do that.
That is association rule mining and then associate analysis.
The others, you can see this very much like other tasks in machine learning.
Right. Like classification, prediction, clustering, regression, and some detection, you know, so summarization.
And then the others, which is under the, you know, machine learning topic.
And the other two professors were going to cover those.
Okay. So they are going to cover classification, clustering, regression, and so those are the mainly using the deep neural network or using neural network approach.
But they also touch some symbolic approach.
For example, using decision tree or using for clustering.
They also talk about k-means.
They also talk about HIN.
Oh, I'm not sure.
A heredical clustering.
Okay. So they also can be the symbolic base.
So that's why I'm only talk about association rule mining in this part.
Okay.
So first, some introduction.
Basic terminologies we are talking about.
So what is data?
Okay. So what is data in your words?
What is data?
What is data nowadays?
So easy to actually digitize everything.
Right. So those facts, figures, numbers, images, or anything possibly can be digitized.
And also stored in the computer database.
I mean, in the not necessary database.
I mean, just stored.
Okay. It can store somewhere as a file also.
Okay. So those are the things we are talking about.
We are interested about.
So collection of data objects or their attributes.
Okay. So even talk about attributes.
Attributes meaning the properties.
Right.
So this like a particular, the each role is something.
This could be the, some customer information.
You know, so you see the ID and indexing and also certain attributes and also certain credits and so on.
Each column is one attribute.
Okay. So this is the, this is the kind of typical well organized structured data.
Then we also have many unstructured or actually like image, like audio, video, those digitized things.
Right. We are interested.
So we already can store them in computer.
So that is the data or object we are interested.
Okay. So maybe not process yet.
Just a role data.
So it's a role fact we collected.
Like the temperature, you know, over the whole month, say for example, August, the whole month, the temperature in Singapore or the temperature in Shanghai or the temperature in London.
So those actually role data, we just collected every day.
Okay. So this could be the, in the text as well can be actually in the text format.
So we talk about the descriptions or summary or abstract.
So things can start.
So similarly here, just to say, okay, if it's a structure one, we can put into the roles each role of the, all of them.
Data shared the same attributes.
So they share the same columns.
So we can actually tabulate it.
Right. So it's like a table.
So you can have roles to indicate the entrance and then the column indicate the property.
Transaction data.
That is something probably not everybody see this before.
Okay. So this is actually beginning.
That's, that's the thing make the data mining very popular.
That is because we want to do the customer market, you know, market analysis and market related customer relationship management.
So we actually start to collect the transactions.
So you can see the ID here indicate each transaction ID.
Okay. And then the items indicate the customer number one.
What are the things he bought?
Okay. So for example, they bought milk, coke and bread for example, for the first customer.
Second customer bought something.
So each one is an item.
Okay. We call it each one is an item.
And then you have like you have basket and then you check out trolley.
So first one, the checkout trolley including three items.
The second one have other things they bought.
Okay. So those are the transaction data.
We record it.
And we record it because we want to find out how those items are associated one with another.
And this is important not just to provide the enough support, you know, supplies in the store room, but more importantly, they want to place the things next to each other.
Or they want to have something which is good for promotion, certain products are actually easy assessed by the customers.
If you think put next to each other, for example, you put the bread next to the milk, you probably initially you just want to buy milk.
But okay, you look at the bread also, why not buy another pack of that.
So including that kind of try to understand customer psychology or try to actually enhance their convenience and try to in a way make the sale easier.
Right. So this is the things that's why you have those transaction data.
Okay. Yeah.
Yeah. This kind of data or network or graph and now social media.
Yeah. It's a typically easily can be captured right to see how person relate to each other.
But this one is talk about also can be, you know, useful for biology or for the talk about genome sequence and so on.
You can actually generate a graph or subgraph to indicate how the molecules or the parts related to each other.
Okay. Graphical.
This is talking about, yeah, I update these slides.
It's just this year and I mean last year, but actually it's very much talk about until end of last year.
They say what are the important data, the volume, okay, the different volume they generated by all kind of people.
For example, I pay attention to this one.
Check GBT.
Okay. So this is per every minute.
Okay. They collected.
So this is how many actually prompts they submitted.
Okay. So you can see interesting like e-commerce.
Okay. Look at Amazon.
The sales.
This is per minute.
So this is the sales increase.
I mean the transaction they have and also this is the treat.
Okay. So this is really the trading.
Okay. So you see the bonds.
Also pay attention to this cyber security related.
Okay. So you see they have this attack.
They only pay attention to what type of attack.
Sorry. The video attack.
Yes. Video attack.
Okay. So that means actually they try to flood your server with all kind of fake.
I said, so you are overloaded.
So you are unable to serve your customer.
For example, we have a coffee shop and very simple server and didn't do very well cyber, you know, defense and then they flood with this attack.
Then you cannot, your real customer cannot really take order, I mean, make place order at all.
Right.
So you see this is so important.
Yeah. Do mo is a company.
They always provide the every year you can check their website.
They actually report the data, the volume and especially on those very important area.
We probably pay attention to and they generate this.
So they actually win this award this year.
Okay. So this is talking about every minute how much new data generated and available.
So we are flooded by data.
Okay. So we are starving for knowledge.
Okay. So that is not what I said.
Actually is this gentleman.
This is our future.
Future list.
Okay. So he has this very popular book called Miga trends.
So talk about future.
Okay. So he's a very, very, you know, he predict many things which is quite create a big impact to everybody.
Okay. So you can see, yeah, this is what he said.
We are drawing information.
I actually hear information probably close related to the data.
Also starving for knowledge.
Okay. So this gentleman talk about that.
And our important doctor, Dr. William Damme, actually he's a one.
He's very much talk about quality control, quality revolution.
His advisor to, you know, for all the business.
He talk about everything.
If you want to improve the business in the end, the best thing is you look at the data.
Okay. So data talks.
So you need to look into the data and then you try to find out the solution from there.
You need to conduct the thorough analysis through the data and then come up with a suggestion solution for improvement.
Okay. So that is both gentlemen talk a lot about the importance of having data also even for information.
Okay. So what's the difference between data and information?
Data, we are talking about the role facts, right?
We collected and then information is to kind of make sense.
Okay. What is this about?
So like the data, we know, okay, the reading is like a 30, 33.
You don't know what this 33 means anything to us.
Right. It's just a role data.
Then you need to take it.
Okay. So this is a temperature in Singapore on particular day.
Okay. Then this become a piece of information.
So this is after process and after you laboring it or you actually associate something, take to it.
Then this data, the role data become information.
Okay. So after you have, so, so, so, so definitely information is very important.
Right. But the data you need to collect from the role data, you have it and then you can do something to organize it, to process and organize it and probably remove the noise and do some analysis on this.
And then you can actually represent it in a way which can call it as information because it can be used for certain purpose.
Okay. So you need to process it and become something.
So this is what we are saying here.
The data actually refer to those role facts.
Can be words, can be numbers or can be text or can be image or can be photo, you know.
So can be stored and processed by computer.
Okay. So those are the things we call it.
So it's a basic building block.
Right. Basic building block for information or basically building block for knowledge.
Okay. So what about information?
Information, information we talk about, you know, the already processed it and also you know the, the, the relationship among them.
Okay. So I said that you can tag this.
So it become useful, okay, for certain purpose.
So like a temperature.
So then you can actually probably make use of temperature to decide to make something like decide, okay, today I should wear a dress or I should actually wear a winter coat.
Right.
So that is something can be useful.
And then what about knowledge?
So knowledge information can be converted into knowledge about historical pattern and future trends.
Okay. So that is something we can actually apply.
So it's a deeper level of the information.
So have information probably can help us to answer certain questions like what to do with this piece of information.
Okay. So this is another level.
So for weather, okay, weather.
So you have the raw data with the temperature, the number and then you have information.
So actually I can tag with this.
So this is a, this is a temperature in which country or which city.
Okay. So you can associate them.
And then the knowledge I probably can apply this temperature to decide.
Okay. So I'm traveling to London and I can actually work on this.
So I can figure out the, in average, what is the temperature like?
Average temperature in August, for example, they say it's the coolest summer in UK this year.
So based on that, I probably can predict, you know, in September likely what would be the temperature like?
And then how am I going to pack my travel luggage?
Right. So that is you apply the information and then you have the knowledge and then you need to make a decision.
I can make the decision for my travel plan.
Okay. So I can advise somebody, you know, they are traveling soon and what to pack, what you probably need to pack.
Not just the autumn clothes probably even consider winter clothes if it's very cold.
This summer very cold and then you predict the autumn can be very cold as well.
You know, that is a kind of knowledge.
Yeah. So it's a deeper level and a comprehensive and also insight.
You have to have experience and then add together with this information and then you can make decision.
Okay. So this is the things we are talking about.
Another level you could be wisdoms.
Okay. So then this is even high level.
Okay. So you need to like our future predict the, what's the name, the gentleman, John, John, John, John, some.
Yeah. Actually he actually can tell, you know, we are going to steal lack of knowledge.
Okay. Because the way we process information probably is not still not enough.
And then the way we identify interesting pattern probably is not there yet.
Right. So he actually can predict something which is, so this is relied on his knowledge as well as his experience as well as his ability to foresee and to actually comprehend the knowledge and then try to tell us something which is beyond the knowledge itself.
Okay. So that is the wisdom we are talking about.
Yeah. So, okay. So it's not, so wisdom is knowing not to use. Yes.
So tomato, like a tomato we know is a, it can be a vegetable or can be a fruit.
Right. So you know, you are not going to use tomato in a fruit salad.
Yeah. At that time, you know, tomato is a vegetable.
Okay. So not mixed with, but sometimes people like the color, they can mix as well. It's edible anyway.
Okay. So this is just to say, can have a subtle difference.
Okay. But those wisdom, you are able to decide, you are able to judge.
Okay. So this is a different level of the data or information or knowledge or wisdom you can actually handle.
So of course, data mining definitely involve collect raw data and then tag them.
So become information. And then after that, how to make use of information come out with the knowledge.
Okay. So that is the knowledge. Try to extract that is the most important thing.
Right. Because the knowledge will be help us to use, to address what is this about how related, you know, to answer.
Questions and make decisions. So data mining basically is about knowledge discovery.
Okay. So this is the definition. Why is data mining?
Okay. So this is our professor Han Jia.
We actually, he's the one wrote a very popular textbook for introduction to data mining.
And we know Fiat is the one. It's very important people in data mining and also the AI.
And this is another textbook written by professor Tan.
Okay. So you see they try to define different way.
Okay. So this is a professor Han focus on discovery interesting pattern.
Okay. So from, from large amount of data stored information repository.
So we are talking about the data.
Data already stored information repository.
That means already tag them. Okay.
Already have columns and the rules, for example.
And then you are able to find the interesting pattern out of it.
Okay. So that is the knowledge discovery in a way.
And then, then see a second author actually try to emphasis on is the process is not trivial.
Okay. So it's, we need to make a quite a lot effort in order to identify such kind of pattern.
Okay. So the pattern must be valid.
Okay. So it's not like a full of arrow.
Also kind of new.
Okay. So it's an interesting pattern.
Potentially very useful.
And also they want this to be understood by people.
Okay. Understandable.
This is something very important.
That's why in the end they actually put presented in a form of rules.
Right. This is something deep neural network is very hard to achieve.
Right. How to make the things understandable to people.
Okay.
Then also actually also emphasis on automation.
Okay. So this, the whole process discover the pattern need to be automated.
Yeah. Why?
Because data volume increase so much.
Right. Before probably we can manually look at this like a mini supermarket and then they have transaction data.
We can still manually work out.
Okay. The pattern now talk about large volume.
So it's not the large volume as we talk about trillions, you know, those data, but you also need to find out the pattern.
We need to have a automate, automate the whole process.
Right. So this is, so also try to highlight the automation automatically discover useful information from large report tree.
Okay. And to find out more useful pattern.
Yeah. So this is also the thing.
Also he highlight.
If don't do that, maybe this is something which is remain unknown.
Okay. So it's still there like mining the gold.
Okay. Although the gold is there, but if you don't try hard, don't mine it out.
Don't dig out.
Then it's remain unknown and not useful to others.
Right. So this is the definition.
So this is, I try to summarize this to say basically knowledge discovery from data is about extracting the interesting.
So interesting here is non-trivial.
And so we are not going to pay attention to some trivial outliers or trivial things.
Okay. And implicit.
Right. So it's not explicitly already there.
So it's not, it's kind of hidden previously unknown and potentially very useful.
This kind of pattern or knowledge from a huge amount of data.
Okay. So huge data.
We actually try to dig out these things.
Okay. So take a look.
Which one is data mining?
Which one is not?
Can divide the customer of a company according to their agenda.
Is this a data mining?
I mean, I try to say already store those data in a database, for example.
Okay. And then let's see which one is we need to try very hard to get it.
Another one is just to directly can retrieve it.
First one, then divide people by their particular gender.
So is this a data mining or is a database retrieval database retrieval.
Right. Just database and query.
And you get the answer.
Okay. Second one, sorting a database based on the ID number SQL.
Right. Sorting.
Okay. Counting number. Taking this course.
Counting.
Yeah. Again, you can use a function, right.
Directly call.
Yeah. What about this predict the future stock price using historical record?
Yes. Yeah. So this is probably a prediction.
Right. Prediction. Yeah. Extra frequency of a sound wave.
Like this.
And this data mining task.
The data information is stored there.
And you just do signal processing.
Yeah. So, yeah, we are here.
Most of you are signal processing and machine learning.
Signal processing looks very familiar.
Frequency. Yeah.
Monitoring heart rate to check whether they are abnormal or normal.
Probably have to base on the past history, a period of time and see their heart beat.
Certain pattern you identify and then can classify this patient as the normal or abnormal.
Right. So it's not a direct calculation.
You need to do observation and then you need to come out with a criteria and then you need to observe over a certain period of time.
And then check the pattern belongs to which category.
Right. So classification. Yeah.
Okay. So it's not direct signal processing.
Okay. What about searching for information from Internet?
Find the very rare kind of pokemons.
Any of you still play pokemons?
No.
Okay. So, so you want to find out where to catch those very rare ones.
They keep moving on. They keep moving so you cannot predict.
Yeah. You need to be very skillful.
I mean, a lot of randomness there, but yes, you need to have certain way to catch these things.
So it's not just an equation. You can write it.
Right. Probably you have to train the system to how to do that.
Yeah. Normal people cannot do it.
Okay. I cannot catch.
Okay. So this is, although say searching for this information, but yeah, so definitely kind of mining.
What about financial institute try to actually identify those like a very suspicious forduren transactions?
Normal transaction, fordurens transaction.
Yeah. Then fordurens transaction has certain behavior. I need to identify.
So definitely mining. Right.
Next supermarket chain want to optimize the placement, products placement from basket analysis.
Right. So likely who buy something and they will buy something together.
Then from there you try to see, okay, milk probably should put quite close to yogurt or should put close to fruit juice.
So that is all for breakfast, for example. Right. Yeah.
Okay. Next one retail. Try to improve marketing again. Yeah. Similarly marketing strategy.
So you need to do a very good analysis to customer behavior or customer, what kind of things. Yeah.
Then you can probably have a targeted marketing. Right.
So whoever buy a computer say particular very powerful server and most likely, I cannot say most likely they will play game.
Okay. Game, game, game, game server.
Then they probably likely they will play the, the, the, the, the, what's that called?
Wukong. Wukong. Okay.
So they probably play Wukong. Okay. Then, then we should targeting. Okay.
Send this kind of link Wukong where to download or buy, you know, this kind of marketing strategy.
Then probably you can easily got Wukong game. Okay. Yeah.
So these are the mining. Okay.
So this is what we are talking about in business intelligence are very useful, very useful data mining.
So it's an information discovery. And then, yeah, we definitely need to have those raw data and then we need to be processed and then also stored.
Okay. Maybe you need to integrate them, not just in one type of database.
You probably have all kinds of databases, especially now talk about cloud. Right.
So we can put everywhere. And then you need to have a way to get the visualized data or have a summary of the data statistics, patterns and reporting structure and so on.
So those are the exploring the data. Use a statistical way.
You can also easily see outliers and also some means and values and so on. For example, then from there, we need to have a more sophisticated way to identify interesting patterns.
Okay. So that is the data mining.
Then after that, we should present the results. Right.
So visualization that is a final findings and then present. Okay.
So finding, present the findings and then help our boss or decision makers to make decision. Okay.
So this is make it. That's why it's very important to make it very easily can be understood by people.
Okay. Then those high rank people, they probably don't know the, you know, the technology jungles.
So they don't need to know. They can see the rules and then they can make decision, make recommendation.
Okay. So this is a whole purpose.
And then normally typical view. So you can see from machine learning or statistics.
So you can see you have a data prep processing part and then we have a mining and then post processing, which is more for visualization come out with the rules.
Can explain the pattern. Okay.
So the data mining is a key step in discovery.
So that's why it's called KDD knowledge discovery.
Knowledge discovery. Sorry. Knowledge database discovery. I think.
Okay. So this is, we, we involve the pre processing and post processing as well.
So key tasks. Okay. So one type is actually predictive.
So you need to have a model, build a model and then you can predict.
Okay. And I predict the label.
So that means a particular category.
Okay. So that is classification or predict the value, the function value, executive value.
So that is a regression or actually you can conduct this kind of prediction for time theory related.
Or you can predict something like a temperature in the future or a cell price in the future or something like, or even predict the future train.
Okay. There are not a big category is more descriptive.
Okay. Describe the things.
So it's like a clustering.
So you based on a relationship between the objects and then try to see how close they are.
And then you describe which category they probably belong to.
Okay. And summarization is a very typical descriptive.
Right. You describe.
Okay. So for this book, what is the summary?
So you describe it. And then association rule. Right.
The rule, rule is descriptive.
So described it.
Also can be discovered as a sequence.
I mean the description can be related to time as well.
Okay. So those are the key tasks.
So we are going to more focus on this part.
Okay. Association rule.
So here just to help us to see what are the, you know, top method.
This is a bit out of date, but they stopped updating now.
I think it's mainly probably the dominant one is which one.
Probably the deep neural network.
Right. Okay. So, yeah.
So before it was like a regression.
You use a lot like a decision tree, you know, but we are, we will still introduce decision tree.
You still introduce clustering method visualization.
There are many tools available now.
They are random forest.
So this is very much rated decision tree and more like a K and N and text mining.
And those are the feature pre-processing.
Yeah. So those are the methods, you know, popular methods and five basic one in, in, uh, these few years.
Yeah. Still, still this, this, this.
Okay. But those are more conventional one.
So, but, um, the skills for data science probably, yeah, smash. Still very important.
Okay. That database.
Probably, probably also important.
Then machine learning methods.
Those are the methods.
Okay. So, uh, yes, we are talking about, you can refer to some link to get details for job wise.
Yeah. So you can see, uh, that was five years ago.
So we can see the deep, deep learning.
Yeah. It's still the very much increase a lot.
Right. The demands actually increase a lot.
And then those are the key tools and the methods we need to learn if you intend to be a data scientist.
Okay.
Uh, so for data mining, we still have those key functionalities or to address those tasks.
Right. So like a generalization, association, classification, clustering, outlier analysis.
Those are the top, uh, important areas to, to look into it.
And for data wise, yeah, relational data, uh, also the, like transaction data for association, room mining, and then more advanced database.
We support those kind of data.
Now I think nowadays most important data problem is social media data, right.
Data from social media.
So how to model these data likely is using a network or graph and then, uh, transaction data, they probably have different way to handle it now.
Okay. They, they, they try to, uh, to, to, to see they probably also looking to the graph.
Okay. Because naturally you can.
You can, you know, each item, how they relate to each other, and then how these things associate
with a particular customer.
And then you see customer behavior, which customer is a friend or which one, and then
how this friend can make inference, right?
Yeah.
Um, application, yeah, application.
So before, like, market analysis and risk analysis, those are the important things,
but also can be very useful for other data analysis.
Okay.
So this is, again, talk about the application, the areas, yeah, for data scientists.
So you can see which year and how they change.
And yeah, this is just for your information.
So basically, data science is really need people from different backgrounds work together.
Okay.
So we are trying to have this, the machine learning and AI, and also make data mining
this part.
Okay.
So it's also, you know, help to, to make sense of the data or the role, the information we
have.
Okay.
So you can also look at from the system architecture.
Most likely you have database and data warehouse or even cloud database nowadays.
And then you have knowledge base behind and then you have an engine to handle this data.
And then evaluation, visualization, graphical user interface to help the user visualize
the results and then help the decision making makers to, to, to use the system.
Okay.
So it's like this.
Uh, major issue.
Okay.
So, um, the technology, the method itself.
So it's like, how to make the method effective, efficient, and also, you know, especially
handle the large data and also different data type now.
Right.
So how to come up with the best way.
So this is a, you know, very, very diverse data type and how to do this.
And also the, the, the, the information on the internet could be a lot of noise as well.
Okay.
So, um, this is how to incorporate discovery knowledge with the existing methods, how to
feel them together.
Then the user interaction part.
How can actually use the data and with the good user interface with the interaction.
So actually how to embed human knowledge, for example, to make the whole thing more
feasible interact with them, have a different level of extraction.
And hopefully, yeah, you have a, uh, one level and you get some information and present to
the user and then user can actually have the input or select something and then feedback
and then system can refine.
So yeah, it's become like, uh, more interactive and also hopefully, uh, more interpretable.
Right.
Yeah.
So this is, uh, uh, application that was specially talked about how the association
online can be used.
Okay.
Then, um, basically based on this introduction, you can actually think about this exercise
and talk about this is how many years ago, close to 30 years ago.
Okay.
At that time, they really, when they see this information like, uh, supermarkets, they actually
look at these, um, Barbie dolls.
Okay.
They find actually it was sold very, very quickly.
So every 20 seconds that is one Barbie sold.
Okay.
And I had a 60% likelihood of buying one of the three type of candy bar.
They noticed this.
Whoever buy the Barbie, they also buy candy.
Okay.
So that noticed this.
And then the supermarkets have this information, but they don't know what to do with it.
Say, have, I don't have a clue.
So how can you help?
You know, you can think, okay, with this information and, um, what can you do to increase the market
sale or to increase, you know, things you can suggest anything you feel is, is good
for, for business.
Okay.
So you can think of something.
So that is making use of the information or knowledge.
Actually, you try to propose something, which is to address this.
Um, based on the phenomenon, try to actually do something to make the sale even better.
Right.
So this is your target.
Okay.
Then second one is also try to link this with a real world problems to see, uh, what
is the association?
What is a regression?
What is a regression different from the classification?
What is a clustering?
And you can use a real world, uh, example to explain that.
Okay.
We can discuss about this next week.
So we don't, don't talk, you can think about this first.
Okay.
So this is what we try to cover in the first 40 minutes.
So basically we want to use data mining techniques to discovery interesting patterns.
Okay.
So interesting.
That means it will create impact.
Okay.
So it's not something trivial and that is something you want to pay attention to.
So interesting pattern from very large volume of data.
Okay.
So, uh, so it's kind of steps for knowledge discovery.
So it's from the, from the knowledge, from the data to the information from information
to get this knowledge.
Okay.
And then, um, so mining can be performed most likely in a variety of information repository.
So we are talking about database, we talk about cloud database, we talk about data warehouse,
you know, so, so on.
And then functionality.
So we talk about two category, right?
So one is descriptive or actually another one is to actually get this, uh, work out
the exact value or exactly label or exactly future value.
Yeah.
Then there are many opportunities and applications and issues and challenges.
Okay.
So, uh, still unsolved problem, but still already have this have been applied it to help
many industry and, uh, have some, you know, already have some impact, but still not enough.
So still waiting for you guys to help.
Okay.
So before that, we still need to learn what are the things already exist.
Right.
So get yourself familiar with the most popular techniques and then in the future you probably
can contribute.
So for this, uh, we focus on social reminding and then we look at, okay, how to get this
interesting pattern.
Right.
So interesting pattern reflect in a way like they occur very frequently.
Okay.
So you see this pattern several times.
That is a frequent enough to actually attract our attention.
So that is a frequent item set generation.
Okay.
So there are various ways to generate this item set.
And then we use the algorithm.
Remember, we must automate the whole process.
Right.
We need to have automation.
So that's why we need to have an algorithm and then we have computer to do it for us.
Okay.
So we introduced two algorithms.
One is a apollary.
Another one is a FP growth.
Okay.
So you can see one, uh, as a working, uh, algorithm, another one is a fasting, a faster approach.
Make use of the data structure.
Um, so some terms, important terms like, uh, support, confidence, and also the lift.
Those are the measures.
Okay.
And then what is this frequent item and what is the two important algorithms we are going
to introduce.
So those are the key things.
Uh, okay.
Still talk about motivation.
So basically interesting and useful.
Okay.
So this is the pattern we want to pay attention.
It's kind of discover the knowledge and we want to make use of this in the future.
Okay.
So question we can ask ourselves like, uh, what pattern, what products have often been
purchased together?
Okay.
As I said, like a milk and also the juice, for example, why these two always purchase
together?
Uh, what are the sub, uh, sub, sub sequence purchase after buying a computer?
Okay.
So you also buy a computer, then you also buy buy one game.
Yeah.
I know it's not true for you guys.
Okay.
But some, yes.
Um, or actually you buy book club by book.
For example, you buy, uh, whoever buy the data mining book or AI book.
Likely you also buy Python programming.
You also buy database.
You know, you also buy, uh, the related book.
So in Amazon, they can recommend to you.
Okay.
Whatever you purchase AI book, they probably recommend Python programming, uh, database,
uh, also cloud computing, you know, they, they recommend that's, uh, that's a relationship.
What kind of DNA?
Yeah.
It can be very sensitive or related to particular drop type and, uh, you know, reactive.
So it's, it's good to have this information and then how to automatically classify the
documents based on their contents.
Okay.
How similar is similar.
And then you can automate the review and process.
Right.
Uh, also you want to identify someone who is anti-social.
Okay.
So you actually want to identify whether particular blog, you know, blogger did online, online
people behavior and try to identify this.
Yeah.
So very, a lot of application on no need to talk anymore.
Okay.
So, uh, try to formulate the problem.
So association when you mining is about what?
So it's about, um, finding relationship between items.
Okay.
That's a very high level.
So when I say this, I immediately think, okay, milk and the bread, for example.
Okay.
Milk and bread, how they related.
So you need to find frequent pattern association correlation and you know, how they, uh, how
they related to each other from a huge volume of a repository database, for example.
And then the pattern need to be, you know, we identify these things.
They occur very frequently.
If they only occur once or twice, this is not significant enough.
You probably don't want to find solution for this.
Right.
And then from there, after you find a frequent pattern, then you want to find out the rules.
So this rule is called association rule.
So it's like if I buy X, I'll buy Y as well.
Okay.
For example, then here X can be a set.
Y is another set.
And then inside this set, you have many items.
Okay.
Many items.
So this is a very general way to talk about this problem.
Then specifically, let's look at this.
Um, so you like to use I to indicate items in a dataset.
So you have I1, I2, so those ID.
So here like a bread, one item, coke, another item, milk, another item.
So we have many beer and also diaper, milk.
Oh, milk already have.
Yeah.
Anymore?
That's all.
Okay.
So this is how many items.
Then each one is one I there.
Okay.
So set is a capital I indicate all those items.
We are interested.
Okay.
So suppose this is transaction data.
So, um, but in our supermarket, we probably have others like, uh, just the first five
customer they haven't bought it.
Okay.
So that doesn't mean we, those are the only one.
So we can have many, many of it.
So you can have a D of it.
Okay.
And then T here, each T indicates transaction.
So this is a T1, T2, T3, each transaction, each transaction we are talking about.
Okay.
So it's a market basket data.
And then the end, the capital N is a total number of transaction.
For example, uh, NTU mini market every day probably have 5,000 transactions.
And I just, yeah, I think more than that probably.
Right.
Okay.
Just assume every day just 5,000 transactions and each transaction people bought what?
Yeah.
So that is the end.
And then, um, so each TJ here is a subset of the I, right?
Yeah.
You see?
So the transaction only three items.
So subset of the big I.
So big I, we have one, two, three, four, uh, five, only five.
Okay.
So can add like, uh, you add, uh, cookie, my banana, apple, you know, you can add in.
And then this is a subset, each transaction is a subset of it.
And then, um, contains one or number of items chosen from big I.
Okay.
So a collection of zero or more items is called, it's a termed as a item set.
It's an item set.
And then, uh, if an item set contain K items, it's called K item set.
Okay.
So what is this item set?
One.
One item set.
Okay.
So three item set, that means you have three.
You have three of them.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, uh, so, so, so you have three items that's called three item set.
Uh, empty one is now.
Okay.
So that's don't contain anything.
So probably the number six customer, yeah, didn't check out, didn't buy anything.
Then you probably also don't need to include him in the transaction table.
Okay.
Uh, item set Y is a super set of the X, uh, or equivalent X is a subset of the Y.
Uh, if all the item X are also items of Y.
Okay.
So easily.
Do we have a subset here?
Uh, not really, huh?
Any?
Uh, uh, yeah, none of it.
Right.
So suppose I have six, I have a, uh, transaction six here, just bought the diaper and milk.
Then do you see relationship?
Diper and milk.
And then this, this one is a super of the six and that one is the subset of that.
Okay.
Yeah.
So now we want to introduce you to measurements.
Okay.
One is called support.
Another one is called confidence.
Okay.
Support can always refer to the frequency or the pattern, how significant this pattern
come out.
Okay.
So it's related to the probability, how frequent.
And then the confidence is more related to the strong or not strong.
The rule related to the rule.
Okay.
Rule.
So this is the general definition.
The support also can refer to rule.
Okay.
Support can also refer to rules.
We talk about the support of the rule.
So it's a, this rule basically is also a pattern.
Right.
So how, how frequent, how, how, how, um, how, um, how do you see the, how, how, how
frequent, how, how, how, um, significant.
Okay.
So let's take a look at the details.
The transaction TJ is set to contain a subset.
Yeah.
Sorry.
It's a content item set X. If the X is a subset of the TJ.
Okay.
So this is what, um, not much new, nothing new.
And then, um, the support.
Oh, yes.
For support, actually we have two things.
Either we use a percentage.
I mean, it's a probability to, to refer to a support.
Another one is to say support count.
Okay.
So it's counting.
So it's more a number.
So we refer to how many number of the transactions contain a particular item set.
Okay.
So come to this, come to this.
What is, uh, what is, uh, support count of beer?
Number of the transactions contain the item beer.
Okay.
So how many?
One, two, three.
Okay.
Yeah.
What about the two item set?
Okay.
So what is a support count for beer and bread?
Beer and bread don't have.
Beer and bread have one.
One transaction have this.
Beer and bread don't have.
Beer and bread have.
Right.
So total?
Two.
So two out of five.
So if you use the probability, that is two out of the total.
Right.
So two out of five, that gives you the support.
But if I say support count is counting the number of the transactions contain this particular
item set.
Okay.
So that is different.
Yeah.
Sometimes actually they all mix.
They don't even call it support count.
They just call support.
But they actually give you a number.
So you know that is actually the support count.
Okay.
The, the, the, the, you can tell.
So this is, so for hours here, okay, I try to use this sigma x to indicate this is a support
count, the counting, okay, of the item set x.
Yeah.
So item set x, refer to the number of the transaction which contain this item set x.
Okay.
So it's a sigma here.
So without say sigma, you can use s to indicate support if you really like.
Okay.
But we, we actually didn't really, cannot, can, can use, but I didn't introduce the symbol.
Just don't want to confuse everyone.
Okay.
So support actually equal to support count divide by the total number of transactions.
Yeah.
So this is a definition.
This is a definition.
Support, okay.
Support has count and then not count.
Just call support.
Okay.
And association rule is a implication of the, it's actually represent in this form.
So it's a really rule.
So you have a header part which is x and then derive the y.
Okay.
So this is tail.
This is a head.
This is tail.
So both actually are referred to the transaction set.
Okay.
The story, sorry.
Item set.
Okay.
See the x and the y.
Both are item set.
Okay.
And they are, yeah, they join as MC.
So for example, diaper and milk and your idea.
Okay.
Do you think this is the real, I mean, could be real.
Whoever they buy diaper and buy milk, they also buy beer.
Oh, what's the meaning?
Okay.
Young mom also drink beer or young dad.
They like to grab a beer.
Okay.
They also help in shopping.
So they bought diaper and milk.
They also get the beer for themselves.
Okay.
So that is possible pattern.
So because of this pattern, you probably like to put the beer close to even diaper.
You know, that could be the case.
Yeah.
So the strengths of association rule can be measured in terms of their support on confidence.
Okay.
So that means the strength to how confident you are when you say this association.
So that's why we say rule can be described by two things.
One is a support.
Another one is confidence.
Okay.
Item set can only represent buy support.
Right.
There is no confidence such thing.
Yeah.
Okay.
So confidence specify how frequent items in Y appear in transaction that contain X.
That means under the condition of X.
Right.
Conditional probability.
Okay.
So do a little bit calculation here.
So we just put everything so called equations here.
You can see support is referred to the item set.
Okay.
And it's referred to the support count divided by the transaction number, total transaction
number.
So it's the probability of the X. Okay.
And then support for rule.
So these two are for rule.
These two are for rule.
So support, if you want to say support of the whole rule, that means it's a support
count of both items that merge together divided by the total number of the transactions.
Right.
Or confidence.
So it's a confidence of the rule.
Basically you can use a support count divide, I mean support count of both sides and then
divide by the header part.
Okay.
Header, header.
This is the header part.
This header part.
Support of the head.
Support count of the header.
Okay.
Yeah.
You can both, you can use a support or support count.
Right.
As long as this is a ratio.
Yeah.
So that actually indicates a confidence.
Okay.
So you can see again, I want to highlight here.
These two refer to the rule.
This one only refer to the item set.
Okay.
So now practice again.
So the X now is talking about these three things.
Okay.
We want to have beer, milk and a diaper.
So what's the support count for this X?
Bread.
No.
Beer.
This one.
Yes.
Have one.
And beer, bread and diaper.
Sorry.
Beer, milk and diaper.
Yes.
Another one.
No.
So what is this value?
Two.
Yeah.
So this is a support count.
Okay.
So what if I ask you, what is the support?
Support.
Then you need to divide by five.
Yes.
Okay.
Good.
Yeah.
So similarly, we can do this.
Okay.
Quick one.
Milk, diaper, milk, diaper, milk, diaper, one, milk, diaper, two, milk, diaper, three.
So three.
Yeah.
So these three.
Yes.
Okay.
So this is a way to calculate support as well as confidence for a rule.
For a rule.
So support of the rule.
Basically you need to have these three items.
Right?
So three items and milk, milk, diaper and beer.
Milk, diaper and beer.
This one.
So it's two.
Right?
So the support count of these three items is two.
And then we want you to calculate the support.
That's why it's divided by the total five.
Right?
So this is a number for this rule.
Okay.
What about confidence?
For this rule, is these three items together the support of it and divide by the header
part.
Okay.
Header is part.
Remember, here is a header.
Okay.
Don't not calculate the support of the tail.
It's header part.
Yeah.
Header.
Header support.
Okay.
So that's why.
Yeah.
So this is the three items.
Now we know milk, diaper and beer.
What am I doing?
Am I correct?
This is three is two.
Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
This two.
And this two is three.
Correct, huh?
The header is only this two.
This two is three.
We just calculated.
So that's why you get the confidence value.
Okay.
Everybody know how to calculate?
So this is important measure.
Important one more is about lift.
Okay.
We'll talk about lift later.
So normally the data mining is you want to find out.
Significant enough, that means you want the support to be above certain threshold.
So you have a mini support and then whatever pattern item set, they achieve the support
above that threshold that you treat them as a interesting support.
You treat them as a significant enough patterns.
Okay.
And then you try to see how they associate with each other, the rules.
Then you can actually work out.
You also have a mini confidence level and then you believe that it's a confident rule.
Okay.
So then you want to do something, make decision based on the strong, confident rules.
Try to derive something.
Okay.
Yeah.
And association rule mining, so basically it's to find out support should be greater
than a threshold.
Confidence also greater than a threshold.
So here these two thresholds is one is to indicate the minimum value of the support, minimum
value of the confidence.
Okay.
And then we actually want to find out this pattern.
So one way you can actually do the exhaustive way, right?
Like what we did for search.
Yeah.
We can actually search for all the possible combination of the item set, right?
Then you check for everyone.
You check for everyone to see whether this one is above threshold or not.
Huh?
This is the one way.
Definitely you can do it.
If you have enough time and also enough space to store all the possible item set.
Agree?
But think about nowadays the supermarket probably have millions of items.
Can you imagine you do like this?
Okay.
So probably doesn't work, right?
That's why we need the algorithm which is automate and also efficient.
So that is the purpose.
Okay.
So we say, yes, you can do exhaustive.
You can use a brute force approach to compute support and confidence for every possible
rules or every possible item set, right?
Yeah.
But this approach is very, very exhaustive, right?
Very, very computational.
Not feasible.
Especially if it's related to the rule, not just item set, but for every item set you
need to break down to the rules.
Okay.
Every item set can be a header and the rest of the remaining item set can be the tail.
Do all the possible combination that is generate all the possible rules.
And then for every rule you do the evaluation.
That is really not possible.
Okay.
I don't know how they come up with this figure.
I'm not sure.
I didn't check.
Okay.
You're very interested.
Ask Chess GBT how they work out.
Okay.
So, they are total possible rules for this content.
D items.
Okay.
So, imagine this D is talking about millions.
Items.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, even when D is six, there's already so many possible rules can be generated.
Okay.
Then you evaluate each of these that is not feasible.
So, how to do this more effectively?
That is the algorithm we are going to learn.
But before that, we want to highlight what for automation, what would be the procedure.
Okay.
So, basically two tasks.
First task is we try to get all the frequent items first.
Okay.
Those not frequent items throw away.
Don't need to evaluate.
Okay.
So, firstly, do this.
Get all the frequent items first.
Then secondly, only for those frequent items generate the rules.
And then for each rule, then we can possibly decide whether above the threshold or below
the threshold.
Okay.
So, this is things.
Then we can quickly narrow down a lot.
Right.
So, if we have a way to identify the frequent pattern, it's already a very good approach.
Then after that, actually rule, we also have a certain way to see how to prune away certain
rules.
Okay.
So, that is not the algorithm I'm going to introduce.
So, basically, the algorithm will focus on generate frequent patterns.
Okay.
Frequent item set.
Yeah.
So, just now we say the rules force way is very not feasible.
Right.
So, we still can take a look.
Okay.
What would be the search tree like?
So, this is a search tree looks like a graph.
Graph.
So, see, just now we say D equal to six is already have 600 above the different rules.
Now, we talk about five items in only in a mini market, only five items, ABCDE.
Okay.
So, how many possible combination of these five items?
Yeah.
Two to the power of five.
If you don't want to consider empty sets, then you should minus one.
Right.
So, total 31.
31, you see.
So, you don't consider this one.
Then, those are the every two combination, every three combination, then four combination,
then five.
Okay.
31 of it.
Two to the power of the D or K minus one.
So, that is a possible items.
Right.
So, those are the possible items.
Just now, another equation three to the power D or something.
That is talking about the rules.
Okay.
We are talking about item set now.
Item set is less.
Right.
It's easier.
It's two to the power of K minus one.
Okay.
So, then, we are talking about finding the frequent patterns.
Right.
So, this is all potentially can be a frequent pattern.
So, if you want to do evaluation, use of brute force kind of exhaustive search, how many
times do you need to do?
31 times.
Right.
Calculate.
For each of these, you need to calculate the support or support count.
Right.
And then, check above or below.
Yeah.
So, is there any better way to do it?
Say, for example, if this one we already know, this one is not a frequent pattern.
Okay.
So, apple and carrots.
Apple and carrots.
Okay.
Apple and carrots is not a frequent pattern.
Do you think you can prune away some other items containing these two, such as this one?
So, this one may mean apple, banana, and the carrots.
Apple and carrots are really not a frequent pattern.
Do you think this could be a frequent pattern?
Support.
Think about the definition of support, counting the number of these two, counting this number
of these three.
So, these are really lower than the minimum support.
Do you think this have a chance to be higher?
No.
No way.
Right.
But if this one is not a frequent pattern, do you need to check this one?
And this one?
No.
Can prune away.
Right.
So, is there anything we can do based on this idea?
Find the algorithms to do that.
Okay.
So, that can cut down a lot of time, right?
So, that is the idea for the apirari actually.
Okay.
But before we introduce this, I still want to tell you the time, the approach requires
how many comparisons.
So, suppose this is total number of transactions, and then this is the average number of the
items we bought, and then a list of candidates is the M of it.
So, you can see the approach actually you need to compare M multiplied with M multiplied
with W. That is a big O. Okay.
Because the M actually have the possible combination is 2 to the power k minus 1.
Right.
So, you can see this is a comparison to scan the database and then check the item and then
to check whether this is above threshold or not.
Right.
So, it's a huge lot.
That's why apirari come into play.
Okay.
So, you want to reduce this complexity.
Right.
So, this is the purpose is want to reduce number of the candidates.
Okay.
So, you want to reduce this number.
The origin number M is what?
2 to the power k minus 1.
Right.
So, you want to reduce this.
Reduce the number of comparison.
Okay.
So, reduce the number of the item set.
Candidate item set.
That means possible.
And then also because you remove, you reduce this of course you reduce the comparison.
Okay.
So, you see the principle is if item set is a frequent then all the subset must also be
frequent.
Just now we say other way around.
We say if it's a subset is not frequent then the extended is parents also superset cannot
be frequent either.
Right.
So, now if this one is not frequent then the subset, then all the subset must also be
frequent.
Otherwise it's not.
Right.
So, this is a working principle.
Okay.
So, we based on this principle can eliminate many candidates.
Candidates.
No need to check.
So, without knowing, no need to count their support counting or support evaluation.
So, comparison also a bit reduced greatly.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, similarly if this term here, this is a frequent item, then all the subset must be
frequent.
Okay.
If the subset is not frequent then it will not generate the superset which is frequent.
So, just this principle.
Okay.
Yeah.
I think in your version I put there is, I think this should be updated as a treat this
as a three item set.
Okay.
Three item set in this itself is a frequent pattern and then the subset should be the
one.
Yeah.
I think that one is forgot to correct the PDF version.
Understand the principle?
Yes.
Okay.
Then similarly, yeah.
So, we are talking about if the A B is not frequent, yeah, then the super parents.
So, just now I already show you this.
Right.
So, you can directly prune away.
Directly prune away.
So, this is talking about pruning.
So, okay.
Now, ready for the algorithm?
You can come out with your own.
Yeah.
But this is the one.
They propose to address this issue.
So, starting from K equal to 1.
Okay.
Sorry.
Here the K is not about the item.
It's about the item set, the length.
Okay.
Item set length.
So, length increase.
Not the total number of the items in the market.
Okay.
So, I'm using the same K because I use a K for the number of the items in the supermarket.
Right.
Yeah.
So, this is the K here.
It's a frequent item.
So, length equal to 1.
Okay.
Starting from 1, then 2 items there, 3 items there, 4 items there, like that.
Repeat this process.
This process.
So, we should generate candidates.
Okay.
Here is just a candidate.
The candidate may be pruned away.
Okay.
We have a way to check.
But firstly, you need to generate candidates first from, okay.
Length from 1 and then from the K item set, K item set.
And then you get the candidates of K plus 1 set.
Okay.
Increase by 1.
And then you prune the candidate K plus 1 item set.
If you notice, some of the subset is infrequent.
Okay.
So, K items are not frequent.
So, you can directly prune away, prune away.
Okay.
And then, if not pruned, that means those are remaining candidates.
Remaining candidates.
Then you should calculate the support or support count.
Okay.
Support or support count of each of these candidate items.
Item set.
Buy, scan the database and calculate.
Okay.
Calculation.
Then you can eliminate those candidates' item set.
They are infrequent.
That means their support count is lower than the minimum support count.
Or their support is lower than minimum support.
Okay.
Get it?
So, you see, you have two chance to remove.
First chance is when you generate from the K, get the K plus 1.
So, you get the whole set of candidates.
Right.
Whole set of candidates.
Then from this candidate, you should check quickly.
Any of these candidate K plus 1 candidates that have a subset, which is not frequent.
Remove.
Okay.
Then you can remove K plus 1 item set.
Then the remaining K plus 1 item set calculate the support.
Okay.
Only those support is greater than the minimum support.
Take them.
Otherwise, throw away again.
Okay.
And then, then what?
Then increase the K by 1.
Okay.
Next.
So, it's starting from one individual one item set.
And then after that, become two item set.
Okay.
For two item set, quickly check if any of the two item set is have a subset, which is
not frequent.
Remove them.
Okay.
Then calculate those item set, so-called strong candidate.
Calculate their support value.
And if the support value is still below the minimum, remove.
Then finally, only those really strong two item set will be picked as a frequent two
item set.
Okay.
And then generate, self-join to generate three item set.
Repeat.
Okay.
Get it?
That's a working principle.
That's, I mean, that's an algorithm details.
So, you need to run like this here.
Okay.
So, I may ask you to do exercise on this, or ask you to do this in the final, or in the
quiz, or not, not in the quiz.
Yeah.
You know, you can run this algorithm and then work out.
Okay.
Before you do that, we still look at the principle.
Also, so the principle is generate candidates by merging a pair of the K, two pair, a pair
of the frequent K items.
Okay.
Only if the first K item are identical, so basically merging.
Now that you get this K plus one item set generated, and then we actually put away if any of the
subset is not a frequent item.
Okay.
And then the remaining one, then you go calculate their support.
And then only take the strong one.
That's working.
So, when you merging, so how to merge?
You merge, say for example, merge these two.
How to merge?
So, you assume the first few is all identical.
Only merge the last.
Okay.
So, this is a tree here.
Indicate those are the tree item set.
Right.
Tree item set.
And this tree item set, when they merge, to form a candidate of four items set.
So, this is a way to merge for P and Q. So, first few are identical.
Only the last one is different.
Then you just, you see, these two are the same.
So, then you will have a ABCD.
Okay.
Only the last one merged together.
So, the C4 here is an ABCD.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, example.
So, you see these, those are the frequent two items.
So, you self-join with yourself.
So, check.
So, this one, any beer?
No beer.
Okay.
So, this one not merging with anybody.
This one merging with this.
Right.
Because the first two are the same.
The last one is different.
So, you can one become tree item set.
Okay.
Any more?
No more.
Right.
So, this self-join with this, you only have one candidate here.
So, one candidate.
You get this one candidate.
Then, shall we do pruning for this?
So, prune.
This is tree item set.
Right.
So, if any of the subset of this tree item set is not frequent, this can be pruned.
Meaning, we should check whether the individual is a frequent pattern.
Yes, definitely.
Because you see, this already have two items set including beer and milk, for example.
So, individual yes.
And the combination, is this a frequent item set?
Bread and diaper.
Yes.
Right.
Is this bread and milk?
Yes.
Diaper and milk?
So, no subset is not frequent pattern.
Right.
So, can we prune away?
Yes.
So, survive the pruning.
Then what?
Then calculate the support for this whole thing.
Okay.
So, have two type of prune.
Two type of prune.
So, first type prune is the candidate.
Check whether subset is not frequent pattern.
If it is, prune away.
Okay.
Any of the.
So, what I'm saying, any of it.
So, suppose.
Suppose diaper and milk is not frequent item.
Okay.
So, I remove this.
If I'm removing this.
Can this prune away?
Yes.
This will be prune away.
Okay.
Because a subset is diaper and milk.
Diaper and milk is not frequent pattern.
Then these three prune away.
No need to compute the support.
Okay.
But now, because this is not prune away.
So, this is not prune away.
So, this cannot be prune away directly.
Then we should calculate the support for this one.
Okay.
I cannot calculate because it's not here.
You can compute.
Okay.
And then see what is the support value and what is the minimum support.
So, if it is still below the minimum support.
Prune away.
Okay.
Remove.
I mean it's not.
It's a candidate.
But it's not the final.
Okay.
So, it's a candidate.
Not the final.
Okay.
That's all.
Yeah.
I think your version here something wrong and some typo right.
I think.
No.
Ah, yeah.
Yeah.
So, it should be diaper and milk.
Thanks.
Okay.
Any question?
Two pruning, different pruning.
Why the chat, the subset?
Another one is the support value enough or not.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, let's do this.
This is our table.
And we do one scan to get.
So, we get C and C indicate candidates.
Okay.
C candidate.
Here the number indicate one item set.
Okay.
One item set.
So, you see we have A, C, D.
Then we have B, E.
So, that's why we have this.
Okay.
You can sort it whatever.
Doesn't matter.
The sequence doesn't matter.
Okay.
Then we calculate.
So, we have one C. One item set listed here.
And then we second scan to get the count.
Okay.
Support count.
So, support count.
So, for A, we have one here.
A for one here.
That's why it's two.
Okay.
And then C is three.
Oh, sorry.
B is three.
One, two, three.
Yeah.
So, that's how we get it.
So, suppose our mini-minimum support count is two and above.
Okay.
Two and above.
Then what?
Then this one.
Okay.
This one.
This one will be removed.
All right.
So, this one will be pulled away.
That's how, from the candidates, we calculate the support here.
Support count.
And then we pick those, have a mini-minimum support above the threshold.
Okay.
Then we get L. L here is a final frequent item for this lens.
So, lens is one.
We get it?
Then what?
According to the algorithm, we should increase the K by one.
Right?
So, we need to do self-join.
So, here is L one.
Join with L one.
Okay.
So, we get, actually we can say get the candidates.
Candidates.
So, you see, A, B, then A, C, then A, E, then B, C, and B, E, and C, E. So, we get this.
Okay.
And then, we should scan again.
Sorry.
Actually, we don't scan again.
Suppose the first thing we need to do is, we probably should have a C2 prime, which
is really the candidate.
And then, we check any of this, any of the subset is not frequent pattern.
Okay.
So, any of the subset is not frequent pattern.
We don't have anything which is related to the D, right?
So, actually, luckily, all of them are frequent pattern.
So, that's why all of them are candidates.
And then, you can scan the database to calculate their support value.
Okay.
So, that's how you calculate A, B. So, calculate A, B. Don't have one.
That's why one here.
A, C, A, C1, A, C2.
Okay.
So, A, C2.
So, that's how we calculate it.
And then, prune away the support count less than 2.
Right?
Prune away, prune away.
So, we have this 4.
Copy over as a L2.
Okay.
Then, L2 is L2.
We get, can we get this?
We can get like this, huh?
B, C, B, E. So, we have a B, C, E. Yes?
When you're self-joined.
Yeah, we should have B, C, E, for example.
So, this one, B, C, E. Why this is not here?
Oh, sorry.
B, C, E is here.
A, C, E. Okay.
If you write C, A, and then C, E, then you can have A, C, E, right?
So, A, C, E, right?
Where's A, C, E?
I try to have a candidate.
Candidates of candidates.
Okay.
So, why this one is not here?
Actually, it can't be there.
And then, we should check subsets.
Right?
So, the subset of this, which one is not a frequent pattern?
A, E. Yeah?
We don't see A, E here.
That's why this was removed.
Okay.
What about A, B, C?
You have a C, A, C, B, right?
A, B, C, right?
A, B, C, A, B is not there.
Right?
So, pull it away, pull it away.
You see, this was pulled away.
This was pulled away.
And then, only left with this.
Okay.
Then scan to calculate the support.
And then what?
Can we continue?
Yeah, we get this.
Do we have further itself, right?
Yeah.
The line is empty set.
So, stop.
That's all.
Okay.
Get it?
So, that's how you manually run this.
Use the appareil.
You get a frequent pattern.
So, the frequent pattern is B, C, E, anymore.
So, is this?
And this?
Right.
But actually, from here, you can derive some.
Not all of them.
Not this.
Right.
Okay.
So, this is how you calculate this.
And your turn to do it.
Just a quick one.
Okay.
We'll see.
Ten minutes.
Ten minutes to try.
And the toilet break as well.
And then we come back to discuss about.
We still have to go through the F.P. growth.
That one is even more troublesome.
But more efficient.
Okay.
Yeah.
Try, try, try this one.
So, have we said anything?
Assume minimum support is 30%.
So, you can convert into the support count.
How many counts?
Two counts.
Right.
30% multiplied by six.
So, two counts.
Okay.
Let's continue our discussion.
So, for this one, just, just need to be patient and run one by one.
Okay.
So, we say the minimum support here is 30%.
So, 30% multiplied by six.
So, it's 1.8.
1.8.
That means two.
So, the support count is two.
So, if we use the apararite, we just need to select the frequent item should be two and above.
Two and above.
Yes.
Okay.
So, just do one by one.
For example, then we have the list one item set.
So, C1, sorry.
C1.
And then we have N.
We have E.
So, I don't do the sorting.
So, I have W.
And I have O.
And I have G.
Right?
And then, robot.
Okay.
Then count.
So, N, we have one, two, three, four.
So, N is four.
Then E is what?
One, two, three, three.
What about O?
O also three.
Four.
W?
One, two, three.
So, it's all there.
Right?
So, just do it one by one.
And then, seems all okay, right?
G.
Or G is one only.
Right?
So, G is one.
W is one.
Okay.
Please tell me.
Four.
O.
So, next one.
So, this C1 becomes this prune away.
So, you have L1.
L1.
So, just have N, E, W, O.
Okay?
And then you have N1 self-join with N1.
You become C2.
Or C2 have prime.
That is N, E.
And then NW.
Then you have NO.
And have EW, EO.
WO.
Okay.
And then calculate.
Then check.
If any subset is not a frequent pattern, then prune away.
Okay?
So, it looks like it's all.
I mean, before you calculate, you should check whether any of this is not frequent.
If it is, then you calculate the support.
Okay?
So, all of them become C2.
Right?
And then you calculate the N, E.
We have 1, 2, 2.
Right?
Then NW, 1, 2, 2 as well.
NO, 3.
Is that?
NW.
Ah, NW is 3.
Okay.
NO, 3.
Is that 3?
Okay.
Just do like this.
And then next is confirm the L2.
Then L2 self-join with L2.
Get the C3 candidates.
And then see any subset can be removed, prune away first.
If not, confirm all.
And then check, calculate the support.
Okay?
So, this is how you can continue.
And this is what we have.
So, this one can be prune away.
And then self-join.
So, you have NEW and NEO.
And what about NO?
Oh, no, no more.
Yeah.
So, this is three of them.
And then you work out the count.
So, these two can be prune away.
Okay.
Then this is the two.
Can stop already.
Then you can list out all the frequent items.
Okay.
So, we know how to use the appareil to get the frequent items.
Next is to have a different way to get frequent items.
Okay.
Using a different algorithm.
That is FHE growth.
FHE growth.
So, you can say that we actually spend quite some time to get the candidates.
For each, I mean, when we grow, right, when we grow, we have a K item set.
Candidates are there.
And then we need to check with the set set.
If it's not prune away, we need to scan the database again and again in order to calculate the support.
So, that is quite time consuming.
This is FHE growth.
Try to, you know, speed up.
And also try to represent the frequent items using so-called this particular database, data structure.
So, it's called FHE tree.
And then basically we will reduce a lot of time to scan the original transaction table.
Okay.
This can be very time consuming as well.
Imagine it's a huge supermarket.
Every day have millions of transactions.
So, it's very big database to scan.
Okay.
So, this is try to increase that efficiency.
And also the working principle will be very different.
Okay.
Different.
So, you don't have these candidates anymore.
You don't have the candidates idea.
So, it will directly generate the frequent items.
Okay.
So, it's a different transaction.
I have several times in common.
So, they may overlap.
So, basically we need to construct the FHE tree.
So, from the name you can tell, this is already a frequent pattern tree.
Okay.
So, only frequent pattern you construct.
You grow.
You get the tree.
And then you try to grow your tree.
Okay.
So, this is when you grow the frequent pattern, actually you are, you can do it concurrently.
For different kind of candidates.
No, sorry.
Not candidate.
You can generate concurrently produce their conditional pattern base.
Okay.
And then based on their conditional pattern base, you grow your own conditional pattern
base related FP tree.
That's the idea.
Okay.
So, you can identify the frequent pattern directly.
So, here are the key steps.
Okay.
So, firstly you need to construct the tree for the entire data set.
And then try to concurrently construct the conditional pattern base for each item in the header table.
Okay.
So, you create a header table and then create the frequent pattern tree, the big one.
And then each of the items you will link to the header table.
Then for each items in the header table, you create their conditional pattern base concurrently.
Okay.
You don't need to wait.
Not sequentially.
You can divide and conquer in that sense.
Okay.
So, you can construct your own conditional pattern tree, frequent pattern tree for each, for
each of the conditional pattern base.
Okay.
So, you recursively do this, grow your frequent pattern.
So, basically the frequent pattern is growth.
And then that's actually lists out all the possible item sets.
Okay.
So, this is the idea.
We have to go through this example to show you, okay, the key steps.
So, you see we still have these five transactions recorded.
And then each one, they bought things.
Okay.
So, the first time is, so total for this one, total now you only need to scan the whole
transaction table two times.
Two times only.
Okay.
Now only need two times.
Why?
First time you get all the, you basically build this kind of like a header table.
Okay.
Like header table.
But some actually can be removed.
So, you have the F, you have the A, you have the C, you have D, G, I, M, P. Okay.
So, each, each, each you listed, each listed here.
And then you work out.
Second time, second time you can compute a scan, a scan this database and then you calculate
the support.
Okay.
Calculate for support for each one item.
One item set.
For F, you get the value of four.
You see one F here, one, three, four.
Right?
So, four.
You put the four here.
And then A, you have one, two, three.
So, A, four.
One, two, three only.
Oh.
Oh yes, yes, three.
Okay, three.
And then C, yeah, you get four and so on.
Okay, but D, what about D?
D, you can tentatively put here.
D, you get one, one only.
Right?
Yeah, so suppose our minimum support is three.
Okay.
Our minimum support is three.
Yeah.
So, this one is not frequent pattern.
So, it should be removed.
Okay, so same thing for G, same thing for I, and same thing for L, O, you know, that's
below the minimum support so you can cancel away.
Then we need to reorganize your frequent items, frequent one item set now.
Okay.
So, that means you based on this header table.
The header table only records those frequent one items.
Okay, so not including the D and not including G, those are already removed.
So, it's not in the header table.
Header table only keep those items which are frequent.
Okay, so that's why we have this.
These two F and C have the same frequency so you, up to you, you can put the C first
or you put the F first.
Okay, so that's the sequence we have.
And then we should sort these items you bought in the transaction table accordingly.
Okay, you ordered the only frequent items.
You already throw away those infrequent one.
Okay, so that is you have F and then C in front of A, you order them because C have four,
A have three.
So, and throw away DGI already.
So, that's how you get this and how you get this.
So, you see the three columns?
Three columns.
So, the first one is ID, second one is item you actually bought.
The third one is only frequent one.
Okay, only frequent items.
And also ordered based on your header table the frequency.
Okay, you call it support count.
Okay, so that's how you ordered it.
Done?
Okay, so after that, then we should construct this.
What is this?
This is called frequent pattern tree.
Okay, that is only frequent pattern we are paying attention.
We throw away not frequent one already.
Only pay attention to frequent patterns.
So, when we construct, we basically need to go through this table second time.
Okay, so what we do is we go through this column.
So, we go through F, C, A, so this is the F, then C, then A, then M, then P.
Okay, I'll show you later.
But this is the final one.
This is actually the final FP tree.
I'll show you how to construct it later.
But suppose just accept this is the tree.
So, this is we scan the database once, find the one item, frequent one items.
Okay, then we sort based on their support count.
And you get the F list.
So, this is called F list.
Okay, so ordered.
Now we scan this to construct the tree.
To construct.
So, this is a final tree.
Okay, final tree.
So, how to construct the tree?
Basically scan this one by one.
Okay, so this is how you construct.
So, just now the first, first, okay, we just do it here.
Okay, so F, C, A, M, P, right?
So, the number here, suppose in the beginning is one.
Right, so this is only one.
So, here also one.
And then here also one.
Here also one.
That is what we have when we first branch were created after done this.
Okay.
Then do the second one.
So, F increased by one.
So, now become two.
Update, okay?
And then C become two.
And then A, two.
And then B.
So, B cannot go this way, right?
So, have to have a new branch.
So, B, one.
And then M, one.
That's how you do this.
Okay, so that, down with this.
Then third one.
F and B.
F increased by one.
Become three.
Then B, now cannot go here already.
So, B.
Okay, B first time.
So, B, one.
So, we have done this.
Number four, C, so it's not F.
So, have to new branch.
C, one.
B, one.
P, one.
Okay, so how we get this?
And then, last one.
F, C, A.
So, F, now become four.
Okay?
So, I erase.
So, and then C.
So, C was two, now become three.
Okay, A was three.
Uh, A was two, sorry.
A was, A was two, yes.
A was two.
Okay, now A three.
Okay, and then M, M increased by one.
So, M was one, now become two.
And then P, P increased by one.
So, what's one, now become two.
Okay, we are done.
That's how we construct the FP tree.
Okay, so we are finishing the construction.
And one more thing is to link the header table, okay, to each of these nodes in the FP tree.
So, F, yeah, the only node is here.
So, we point into here.
The C, point into the first one.
And then this C actually also have another C.
So, we also link them up.
Okay?
And then, uh, A.
So, A also the only A we have here.
And then B, B have one B here, have another B here.
So, oh, sorry, another B here.
And then also link to this.
Okay, so those are the B related.
And then, uh, lastly, the P.
Okay?
So, this is how you actually, yeah, M also have the M related.
That's all.
That's how we construct the FP tree.
Okay.
So, you can see FP tree only hold what?
Only hold frequent patterns.
Okay, only hold frequent patterns.
So, so this is how we have this.
Okay.
And then, next one is concurrently take the nodes in the header table to construct your own conditional pattern base.
Okay?
Conditional pattern base.
So, for example, so that means each, so that means you have a contract.
You can contract the conditional pattern base for F, for C, for A, for B, and for each of these.
Okay?
So, concurrently, you don't need to wait because each of this is independent.
So, for example, here to see the M.
So, M related to this, right?
And also this, this is only two M in this FP tree.
So, when we have this one, we track back.
So, this is two.
So, that means A can be two, C can be two, F can be two.
Okay?
So, that is this.
The conditional pattern base for M is this tree.
The value is two.
So, this is the one.
Okay?
And second one for M is here.
So, track back.
This is a branch.
Okay?
So, you have F, C, A, and B.
And the value is one.
Okay?
So, you get the M conditional pattern base.
And then, then what?
You treat this as a frequent pattern base like what you did before.
Okay?
Then you try to construct the frequent pattern tree for this conditional pattern base.
So, this is the first one.
That's why we have F, C, A, and it's two.
So, it should be two.
Okay?
So, it should be two, two, two.
Right?
Based on this.
I'm done with this.
And then, second one.
F, C, A, B.
So, F, C, A are increased by one.
So, that's why it's three.
So, become three, three, and three.
Then what about the B?
Oh, sorry.
Actually, do we need to have the B?
Okay.
Based on this pattern base, we should have the, we should work out the frequent pattern.
Okay?
So, that is F. F become two plus one.
So, three.
And C become two plus one.
Three.
A become three.
Three, three, and three.
One.
So, this is not there.
Okay?
So, that's why you construct this.
So, that is the M conditional FP3.
Frequent pattern.
B is not frequent pattern in this conditional pattern base.
Okay?
So, after you have this, a single branch already, you basically can list out all the combinations.
That means you have, you can have F with M, which is a frequent pattern.
And then, you can have F with M, which is a frequent pattern.
And then, C with M, and A with M, and then, FC with M, FC, F, A with M, CA with M, you
know, all the possible combinations.
And then, also, FC, AM, those are all possible frequent patterns.
You automatically generate it.
That's all.
How nice.
Concurrently, you can do this conditional pattern base.
Then, construct your conditional pattern FP3.
And then, recursively do this.
So, if your tree is not a single branch yet, do very much like, so you still have a header table for your
conditional pattern base, and do this again.
Okay?
Recursively.
Until you get a single branch, then you just do the all the possible elimination, and then,
you will eliminate, okay?
Then, you list out all the possible, possible combinations.
That's all.
Okay.
So, that is the details about just now, yeah, how this is constructed.
Like, AB, that's why you have AB.
Then, this is when you read the second transaction ID.
So, you have the BCD, that's why you have a BCD.
And then, B and B can connect together.
Okay?
So, that's the details about constructing the FP3.
We did it together already, right?
And this is the final layer, the constructed FP3 here, based on this transaction.
And then, create the table.
Okay?
We also did it together earlier.
The pointer in the header table, just pointing to one of it.
Okay?
And then, the related one, they should connect themselves.
Connect together.
Because this will be useful to construct your conditional pattern base.
Okay?
Get it?
So, scan once to get all the one single frequent items, and then, sort it to get the F list.
Then, from the F list, you construct, scan again to construct the FP3.
And for each, after you finish construct the FP3, you get the header table.
And then, from each of the items in elements in header table, you construct the conditional pattern base.
Okay?
Then, grow like that.
And also, yeah.
This is the one to show us how to construct conditional pattern base.
Okay?
So, just now, we say one more example to use a D, for example.
Use a D as a, we try to construct the conditional pattern base for D.
Okay?
So, D is one here.
That's why you have a A, B, C one.
Actually, for each of these is one.
Okay?
So, this is one.
And then, for second D is A and B. So, it's A and B here, the first one, the first branch,
second branch.
And then, this D is AC.
So, it's A and C. And then, this one is A only.
And then, this D, which is a B and C. Okay?
That is a pattern base, a conditional pattern base, conditional pattern base.
And then, we should apply the NP growth on this conditional pattern base.
That means we should actually get the F list.
Right?
Get their F list.
Because the A now is four.
One, two, three, four.
And B, three, C, three.
Okay?
So, all of them are available.
Right?
So, your list will be A, B, C. And then, A, B, and AC.
So, there you can construct the tree.
Okay?
So, this is your FP3 for this conditional pattern base of the D. Okay?
So, yes, ABC.
Okay?
It's one.
And then, AB.
So, A increased by B increased by one.
Okay?
Then, AC.
A increased.
So, A becomes three now.
C is the new one.
C is the first time.
So, B was two.
Yeah?
Then, AC done A. Yeah?
A becomes four.
Then, BC.
So, BC.
So, that's how you get it.
And then, you should have a header table for this tree.
Okay?
The header table here should have a C. Should have a A.
Uh, uh, uh, let's wait.
ABC.
Yes, yes.
So, you should have ABC.
You should have ABC.
Then, you can have, uh, concurrently do that for, just now, this is a D. The conditional
pattern base for D. So, you can with C and then, you track back to construct recursively.
Okay?
So, this is a D under the condition of that construct base.
So, this is finally, you can get this.
You can go back and check how to construct further from here.
So, you have a header table.
And then, this is ABC.
So, the C and B. And then, you have A. And then, A link to.
So, A should connect to here.
And then, B connect to here.
And C connect to here.
And then, you should construct that accordingly.
So, that means under the condition.
So, you will create a conditional pattern base, conditional pattern base, based on the D and
the C. Okay?
Because, because this is C, which is from the D. Okay?
So, that is how you do it.
Grow like this.
And you can also have a counting greater than two.
You can actually eventually, you get this.
Okay?
And this is actually based on the principle of what?
Fp grows actually based on this principle.
Okay?
To say, if the alpha is a frequent pattern in the original transaction database.
And then, the conditional pattern base for alpha, if you call it as a B. Okay?
So, if you call this as a B. And then, one of the items called beta in the B. Okay?
Beta in the B. So, if you want to check whether alpha together with beta is a frequent pattern
in the original database, you need to make sure this beta definitely is a frequent pattern
in the conditional pattern base of the B. So, you see, that's why you can divide on
CONQUER.
You divide into their own.
And then, each of these own construct their conditional pattern base.
And then, make sure identify all the frequent patterns in that conditional database.
Then, possibly, it can merge with your conditional pattern alpha to be a frequent pattern.
That is the working principle.
Okay?
Yeah, example.
So, if now alpha is a M, just now we have M, remember?
The M. And then, the conditional pattern base is like this, for example.
You have FCA, which is three, and B is one, and so on.
So, that is their conditional pattern base, for example.
And then, one of the things which is beta, right?
This beta actually only have one.
So, that is not a frequent pattern at all.
So, it's no way you will have M and B. Okay?
Or B and M.
So, how about this one?
Is there a chance you have FCA and M?
Yes or no?
Is this a frequent pattern in this conditional pattern base?
Yes.
So, yes.
Okay?
So, you can have FCA M.
Now, can you have FCB M?
No, right?
Because B is not a frequent pattern.
So, the combination of course not.
Remember?
If the subset is not a frequent pattern, the superset cannot be.
Right?
Yeah.
So, that's the same thing.
So, this is the whole idea.
Okay?
That's why they can divide and each one do your own.
And then, to see whether you can identify frequent pattern can combine with my parents.
Like, yeah.
That is how you grow.
Okay?
Yeah.
I think you need to go through and go through this again to see whether you can understand this fully.
So, the conclusion remark is we make good use of the tree and then the growing algorithm.
So, basically the new data structure is stored in compressed frequent patterns.
So, use a tree to store the frequent patterns.
And then, it's very compact.
So, you form this.
And then, you use the NP growth which is to use conditional pattern base.
So, can achieve this divide and conquer idea.
Okay?
So, this is a method actually proposed after you have the a priori.
So, that was Professor Han Jiawei's team.
They actually did this.
Yeah.
And, yeah, it's increased the efficiency greatly.
Okay?
But now, they have more advanced.
I mean, on top of this, they have a more progress made and also now deep learning related, right?
Deep learning which is more to do is just a final recommendation and so on.
Yeah.
So, exercise, we can only discuss it next week.
Okay?
So, the next week we will go through all exercises which haven't covered.
So, you have time to go back and work on this on your own.
Then, you probably have better idea.
So, actually, you can also use a priori to do it.
Okay?
For this, you can actually compare.
You should get identical answer.
Right?
You should get the same thing.
It's just one is more efficient than another one.
Okay?
And, do you remember so far I covered two algorithm already?
But, what is another big task we haven't achieved for association rule mining?
The rules.
Right?
So far, we only say how to identify frequent patterns but haven't touched anything about
rule generation.
Okay?
So, rule generation, a general guideline.
So, for any frequent pattern or frequent item set, why?
We can generate all the non-empty subset.
Okay?
So, non-empty subset of the Y. And then, for every non-empty subset of the X here, you
do this.
Okay?
You calculate the support of the Y divided by the header.
The header of the root.
Support of the header root.
And then, you see whether this is greater than minimum confidence.
If it is, yeah, this is a strong root.
Okay?
Otherwise, throw away.
So, that is a general guideline.
So, of course, this one is very exhaustive way to approach, right?
So, we know if the K is big, there are also a lot, a lot candidates.
Yeah.
So, this is just a general guideline for getting the rules.
But, they have some special algorithm to speed up.
Okay?
But we don't have time to do that.
So, just understand, you know, that is a systematic way we can collect the rules.
So, example, here, suppose we have Y, which is three items.
And then, each of, so we should generate the subset for each of this, for this Y, right?
So, yeah, individual is one subset, and then, combination, every two combinations.
So, you have six of this.
Yeah.
Then, for each of these, you calculate the support.
So, you can see the support of this, and then divide by the header of the support,
and then see whether it's above the minimum confidence.
Okay?
So, this is how we can pick the rules.
So, for small K, it's okay.
So, small K, we can do it systematically.
Okay?
So, that's a general idea.
If you identify the frequent pattern, then you can check out all the possible rules associated
with each of the frequent patterns.
Okay?
So, that's why, second half of the exercise, the example one is to check how to get the
rule, which is, we want the minimum confidence is 60%.
Okay?
So, just now, we had, yeah.
So, here are those frequent patterns, and then, we can just get two rules.
Okay?
For example, you can try this one.
Suppose we should have every combination, right?
I mean, every subset of, because this one, this was a frequent pattern, we identified it.
So, actually, you can have all the subset of it, and then, to be the header, the rest
would be the tail, and then, check their support count.
So, suppose, so this one, yeah, is a 66, all greater than 60%.
So, these are the two possible rules.
So, meaning, if you buy N and W, you also can buy O. So, this is confident enough to say
that.
Okay, so this is, all others, you can also list out, and then, check one by one.
Okay?
Yeah, I still want to show you a bit of the pruning, and so, previously, it was a support-based
pruning, right?
So, now, it's a confident-based pruning.
So, we are talking about, if this rule, we already know this rule is not confident.
Okay?
Then, if this rule is not confident, do you think, do you think any others can be pruned
away?
Anything else can be pruned away?
So, this is not confident already.
Do you think this will be confident?
So, you need to go back and work out.
The key thing is how you work out, how you calculate the confident value, right?
So, for calculating confidence of value of this rule, basically, it's all the items calculate
the support count of the whole four items, and divide by the header.
So, divide by the header of the support, right?
So, that is the one.
We already know this value is less than the minimum confidence.
Okay?
Then, what about this?
This also, the four of them, to work out the support count.
Then, denominator is the header, which is C and D. So, which one is bigger?
Normally, this is bigger, right?
So, this one already too small.
Do you think this one will be big?
No.
So, it can only be even less than the minimum confidence.
So, prune, prune, prune.
So, those can be pruned away.
Okay?
So, this gives you an idea.
The rule actually can be pruned away as well.
Okay?
And, this part can be pruned away.
So, this again is about how to generate the candidate's rule.
And then, if you know any of these, we can actually prune away some of the rules if they share the same.
If we know one of them is already not strong, then the combination of these two can be...
So, this one candidate rule can be pruned away as well.
Okay?
And then, the exercise 4.3 is for you to...
For us to try to see whether this can be pruned away.
And, if this is a frequent item, what are the possible candidate rules?
Okay?
So, again, discuss next week, and you can try to work out yourself first.
Last one, we want to highlight is about the lift.
Okay?
So, so far, we only say we identify frequent pattern because of the significance.
Right?
We say that they're above the some strong...
Show the strong pattern, I mean strong frequency.
So, the support count is big.
That's why we want to identify them.
Then, from them, we also want to come out with the rules.
But actually, those high...
Highly frequent occur pattern may not be interesting.
Okay?
May not be interesting.
Why?
Now, look at this table.
Okay?
So, we are talking about this association rule.
Whoever they drink tea, they also drink coffee.
Okay?
So, is this interesting rule?
We ask ourselves, is this an interesting rule?
So, in order to work out this, actually, we want to look at the confidence of this rule.
Right?
So, confidence of this rule is quite high.
Quite high.
So, the...
But the issue is, actually, the probability of this coffee itself is also very high.
So, that means, actually, whether they drink coffee is because they drink tea, then they
drink coffee, or they just drink coffee.
You know?
So, when you say this rule, probably not so interesting.
Okay?
So, that's why we use another measure called lift.
So, lift, actually, is to work out the ratio between the confidence and support of the
why.
Okay?
So, be careful on here.
Remember, the way to calculate the confidence is a header to be in the denominator.
Okay?
So, here, is a why to be in the denominator.
So, this is the confidence of the rule divides the support of the why.
Okay?
So, this is a way to work out the lift.
So, if the lift is less than one, that means it's not correlated.
So, it's a negatively correlated.
Okay?
So, it's not very interesting.
Unless it's positively correlated, it's greater than one.
That means this rule is interesting.
So, it's strong and interesting.
Okay?
We want to find out these rules.
So, this is a final example I want to show us.
I think we should stop here.
So, to summarize what we have today.
Okay?
So, we start to introduce you the association rule mining, especially introduce the measures,
actually three measures.
One is the support, one is confidence, one is the lift.
Okay?
So, those are the three.
So, we can use support to pick up those frequent items.
Okay?
So, frequent items, that means those items, they are significant enough for us to pay attention
to.
Okay?
Then, we based on that, we can work out the rules.
So, we want to only select the strong rules.
Strong rules actually indicate the association between items.
Okay?
So, we want to put strong rules.
And then, we introduce you the third measure, actually, to double confirm whether the rule
itself is a strong rule itself, is that interesting or not.
Okay?
And then, we introduce two algorithms to quickly or efficiently without using exhausted way
to actually identify frequent pattern.
That's all we covered today.
So, that is the whole summary for this topic four.
So, basically introduce those concepts and then talk about focus on association rule
mining, then the two algorithms.
And then, for rule generation, you know, after the frequent pattern is identified, then systematically
generate the rule and then pick the interesting one.
Okay?
So, this is a summary for this.
And hybrid, okay?
So, neural network actually can be applied to association rule mining.
Okay?
So, they can think of the way.
So, this is, I asked ChessGVT, okay?
Hopefully, this is the updated one.
So, they actually say you probably can have a way to embed the rule into neural network
or using the graph neural network.
Okay?
So, actually the associations, the relationship.
Actually, you can see these two are very much in apply now together with large language
model.
Okay?
Large language model together with graph neural network model.
Or, very, very hot topic in like apply the knowledge graph together with large language
model.
Okay?
To improve the performance of large language model.
But this is definitely where improve the overall recommendation system.
Okay?
So, this is purely for your information.
It's nothing to do with exam and it's beyond the scope because this class suppose it just
introduce introduction.
Okay?
So, after we have this association rule mining together with deep learning, then can apply
to many real world applications.
Okay?
And also the model like, yeah, still using the GNN graph neural network or transformer
to design these things.
And you can also think about what is the disadvantage.
Right?
Yeah?
Okay.
I think I should stop here.
Although you have the slides which is to talk about what is the maximum frequency item
set.
The way is to tell us if you just need to store, if you have a very limited space, you just
want to store some of the, you know, frequent items, then the rest can be automatically
generated.
Okay?
So, you don't need to store all.
Yeah?
So, this is one to tell us that.
And then we can, yeah, so it's a small set of the frequent items should be stored and
then the rest can derived.
Okay?
So, that is the idea.
And then the close of frequent item set, that is, if you don't want to recalculate the support,
then that is a subset.
You need to, the minimum set of the item you need to store.
Okay?
So, basically, this one, this one, actually, you still need to recalculate the support
value for your generated patterns.
Okay?
Purely for your information, yeah, it's not examinable.
So, it's totally extra information.
Just to say you don't really need to store all of the frequent items, they can be generated.
Okay?
Based on the principle, you can actually generate it.
So, if you don't want to recalculate the support value, then this is another concept related
to that.
Okay?
Yeah?
That's all.
For today, yeah, a bit, drag, a bit too long, okay, without too much stress here.
Okay?
So, hopefully you bear with me.
So, basically, I cover all the contents now.
Next week, it's just purely for cover all the discussions and exercises.
Okay?
Then, Prof Tang with Ticklebar.
Next week, he's, the last two hours, he will Ticklebar.
Okay?
So, for my part, this is a plan for next week.
And then we have the quiz.
So, I still need to keep you informed about the actual, which session, the location.
Okay?
The time, exact time you need to go.
Yeah?
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Oh, no, that is.
Okay?