Hello class, can you hear me?
All right.
Okay.
So this is our second week for this course, introduction to AI and data mining.
So this is a plan.
Hopefully we can cover all these topics today in these three hours.
That means I should finish off all the four algorithms on this uninformed search, or the
search algorithms.
And then we also move on to the topic tree, just touch a bit, which is informed search.
Okay.
So we start to talk about why it's heuristics.
We are talking about, and then some very simple idea of make use of the heuristic value.
Okay.
So this is our plan.
Hopefully we can go through this.
I understand we have exercise tool haven't covered, haven't discussed yet.
I ask you to go back and discuss it.
So we suppose you cover it later, okay, when we talk about exercises.
And let's focus on the algorithm, introduce the algorithm first.
Okay.
So that's that.
This we want to, we already introduced the state search space, right?
We talk about symbolic AI.
So we have to have the states and then specify what is the initial state, what is the goal
state you wish to find.
So then we hopefully in this, we define the operations in this, define the legal operations
in this problem solving space.
And then we specify starting states, what are the possible operation can be applied
to move to some of those other states, right, from one state to another.
And then from there, then it consists of a partial or the entire state space, right?
Then from there, we start from one of the possible states.
Then we should have a way to systematically find an answer or find one of the goal states
we want, right?
So this is the idea.
Okay.
So how to, after we have this state space, so how to systematically find the goal states?
This is what we wish to achieve.
So this is under the assumption, meaning we have a sufficient computation time.
I mean, that makes the whole thing feasible.
That means the problem can be solved within the given time.
Then another thing is we have enough memory to hold the necessary states in the memory,
right?
So then we possibly can do this.
Okay.
So that is under the assumption.
So we know, you know, either you go for data driven, that means starting from the partial
knowledge or those states, starting from there with the supporting factors.
And then you move on to the direction which leads us to the goal.
Or you go other way around.
You pick one of the goal states and then you go get the supporting goal and then supporting
states which can achieve the goal.
And then you actually move kind of backwards, right?
So this is the two direction.
And we need this way, basically we need to find the algorithm which can help us to systematically
search the entire graph or entire search space.
Right?
So this is a key thing.
Okay.
So we also highlight why we want to use graph because this is a representation we have
and also the behind the theory we may need to can use the graph theory to help us to
do the analysis.
Okay.
Then one very powerful and important algorithm is called backtracking.
So backtracking, actually that is algorithm can be applied or actually is more broad way
to search and to find the feasible solutions.
Not necessarily really just apply to the tree or graph but actually is one to find the possible
solutions or feasible solutions for those like constraints, satisfactory problem, you know,
this kind of search problem.
Okay.
So basically this is uninformed.
That means we are not using any of the heuristic value.
But of course later we can combine.
If you have a heuristic value available then you can probably also use a backtracking.
So that's why we say it's a broad kind of search algorithm.
Okay.
Compared to say that first or breadth first that kind of BFS or DFS search algorithms probably
the backtracking is a broad one.
Okay.
So let's take a look of this algorithm first.
So here we really go into like implementation level.
So we are not really using recursive algorithm.
We actually tell you use iterative way to do it.
Okay.
So we are using tree list here.
Tree list.
So you can see first list is to hold the state list.
Okay.
So it's what are the solution states.
So the state can provide a state so that is SL.
Another one is a new state or actually yeah.
So those holding those unprocessed states.
And then we have another list which holds the dead end.
So those states that is not going to give us an answer.
We already checked already.
Okay.
Then another one is the current state.
So current state actually is not really a list.
It's just can be a flag.
Okay.
Just to indicate which states we are exploring now.
So we are using this structure and then we want to go through this procedure.
So for example, we're using example to explain it first and then we go through the algorithm.
Okay.
So on the right hand side, that is a graph here.
Although it looks very much like a tree.
Okay.
Except you have some notes actually you can reach it from more than one path.
Right.
So strictly speaking, this is a graph not a tree.
But actually later you will see we will use words called game tree quite likely.
We are using game tree although it's not really a tree.
Okay.
So it's also have this more than one path can lead to the same notes.
So based on a no graph definition, this is not the tree.
It's a graph.
But you can probably look at as so we can still talk about branch.
We can still talk about siblings here because we are referring the sibling refer to the
notes.
We're actually coming from the connect to the same connector.
Okay.
So same parents.
So if that's the case, we treat them as a sibling.
Okay.
So for example, yeah.
So this is a sibling of this one because they all come from these notes.
And also this is a sibling of this one.
They come from the same notes.
So we can treat this like this.
Okay.
So for the backtracking is in a way is a depth first search.
And also we basically just need to know when we when we search, when we meet the dead end,
how should we track?
Okay.
Track back, backtrack.
Go back to the previous date to decide how to search make decision next.
Okay.
So this is a key idea.
So how to start?
Yeah.
So we're starting from the starting state.
So for here, suppose this is a starting state.
And this could be the goal state or whatever.
Okay.
We don't, we don't know yet.
So suppose one of the states is a goal state and we want to start from here.
Or actually this is a goal state we want to find.
So in the backtracking, how should we do it?
So basically branch based or depth first.
So you go all the way to the end of this branch.
Okay.
So that means you check one to see whether this is the goal you want to find.
If it is, then we can return.
That means we find the goal.
If it's not, then we check whether this state have a children.
Okay.
Is there any children related to this note?
If it is, then those children should be considered.
Okay.
So how to be considered?
We will put into this end, I mean one of the list.
Okay.
So this just now we say we have, we have three lists.
So we just need to put into the those unexplored it, unchecked list.
Okay.
And then we move on.
So we have a way to actually put this into at the, you know, dead end or actually we put
this into the solution list.
Okay.
And then we move on to next one.
And this is based on the depth first.
Okay.
So depth first, that means we probably left most branch first, for example.
Then we can go this way.
So we check this note and see if this is the solution.
If it is a goal, if it's not yet, then we check whether this have a children or not.
If no children, then we probably need to backtrack.
Okay.
Back to the previous state.
If we have children, children should put into the unexplored list.
Okay.
Then we do like this.
So until here, this is still not answered yet.
It's not the goal state yet.
And these states have no children now.
Okay.
So how to handle no children notes?
That means we should actually track back.
Okay.
And then see if these notes have any other branches.
That means if these notes have a sibling.
So if that's a sibling, then we should go to that branch.
Okay.
If no sibling, then these notes become, these notes, the children already is broadened.
And this one, no sibling, then we should actually track back, track further up previous.
Okay.
Go back to the previous parents.
So go back to the grandparents.
So this is how we do it.
Okay.
So let's say for example, this one, we actually track here.
So after that, we go back here and this have another children.
So we go to this branch and this one is not goal.
It's not no children.
So we should check back.
And check back, we find these parents is all the children already is broadened.
So this is become a dead end.
Okay.
So you should move to the dead end and backtrack.
Backtrack here.
And this branch, this, this, this notes have another branch.
So we should go this branch.
Okay.
So this is how we come here and then go back here, then come back here.
Here need to be very careful.
Should we come back here or should we go back here?
Okay.
Yes.
It's coming from these parents when they expanded this F here.
Right.
So we should come back to this parents and then from here we go.
So now this whole two bunch is already fully exploited.
So we should backtrack to here and then go this way.
And do we need to put this in?
Do we need to put the F in again when we come from the C?
No.
Yes.
We will check the algorithm.
Okay.
Yeah.
Probably no.
Okay.
Because this already appear before.
So we already explored here before.
And then we are not putting.
So only those add payment appear.
Then we actually add in.
Okay.
So we go this way and then we go back and then come here.
So this, this, this number here, they bring the sequence we are searching in this graph.
Okay.
Yeah.
So this is words to describe.
So if reach the dead end, then you should backtrack to the most recent notes on the
past and see whether that is an unexamined siblings of this dead end.
Okay.
Of that particular.
Yeah.
And then continue down to this branch.
And then actually we continue doing this.
So if you prefer to look at the algorithm in the exclusive, recursive way to look at.
So basically is you just to see the S and then check the children and then you check
the children one, children two, how many children you have for each of these.
You basically do the same thing.
And then until you find the answer or you find it's unsuccessful.
Okay.
So this is the idea.
But the algorithm we are implementing using the iterative one.
So again, you know, this is a key idea.
So we have an unprocessed notes put into the NSL and then that then put into the DE list
of notes, which is a solution or the state list, which is they are actually holding the
solution past because the solution past is useful, right?
Because we want to find which exactly from which goal, which past actually you find, you
can find the reach the goal states, right?
You can find the answer.
So it's good to keep it.
And so that is in a solution list.
And then we have another, another just a pointer, right?
To, to, to tell us current state.
Actually, you also can don't use it.
Just take the left most from, from the, you know, unexplored list, for example.
Okay.
But yes, to make it clear, this one have the current state pointer.
So here is the algorithm.
So it puts in the beginning, yeah, solution is the, the, the solution state is a starting
state and then the unexplored is also the starting state to start, right?
So it's not explored it yet.
It's not checked yet.
And that end is empty.
So we have these three lists here.
And then this is a pointer that is a current states is pointing to the very beginning
that starts date.
Okay.
So we do this while loop here.
And then the while loop is to check whether there is any notes in the NSL.
Right.
And if none of them exists already, then we should just return fail.
And otherwise we should have a solution from this SL.
Okay.
So you see, if it's not empty yet, then what we need to do.
We get, we check whether current state, the current state, whether this is a goal already.
Okay.
So it's goal, then we return SL.
We find the answer.
Then the solution state is provided in the SL.
Okay.
Go.
And if as the CS is not goal, but they have children, we should do this part.
Okay.
We should do this part.
And if have children, this is the goal.
Okay.
We should grow.
So when we grow, we put into the NSL, that means un-exploit, the un-processed, un-processed
list.
We should actually do add it in like a stack.
Okay.
So like a stack, that means last in, last in, first out.
Yes.
Okay.
So that is L-I-F-O.
So only thing is we need to be careful when we take care of the children.
We actually want to exclude those notes that already appear before.
Okay.
So in the dead end or in the SL.
So all already appear in the NSL.
So we don't need to add in anymore.
Okay.
So this is a thing.
And then we exclude them.
The rest of the children, the rest of the children should add into the NSL.
Okay.
And add in from the left-hand side.
Left.
Okay.
The first in will be the last out.
Or the last in will be the first out.
Okay.
So we add in from the left.
So this is how you add into, okay.
So here be careful.
This is add into the NSL.
Okay.
And treat the NSL as a stack.
So we add in like that.
Then after that, we should take the first element.
That means the last in one.
That means the one you want to treat.
You want to do checking.
Okay.
So that's why you set the first elements in the NSL, the updated NSL as a current state.
Then you add this current state into the solution.
Okay.
Treat this as a possible solution.
Add in first.
And then we go check again.
So that means come back to here again.
To check.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Here.
So, oh yes.
Sorry.
This is while loop.
Okay.
So we should check whether this is go.
So this is about if it's not the goal and they have children.
Okay.
We do here.
We do this one.
What if there is no children?
So this is a complicated part.
So this is a backtracking part.
Okay.
Backtracking part.
So we check SL.
If the SL is not empty and also CS is the first element of the SL.
You later you see this is important.
We have this end condition.
We wanted to have this.
Then if this is a case we should removing, removing, removing.
Okay.
So that means the parents before already become dead end.
We should remove them.
Okay.
So last children check, finish checking the last children.
Then backtrack to the parents.
Parents also should be removed.
Okay.
Until the parents, parents also if all the children already exploited then they should
satisfy this condition.
Okay.
Then you should be removed.
Repeatedly removed.
And then, and until you know you have branch then we actually add the CS to the possible
state, possible solution state and then we continue from there.
Okay.
So this is a key idea.
The details actually quite, quite detailed steps.
Okay.
So now that's how we run it.
So make sure we fully understand it.
So basically I want to put this part.
So this is the part when the current states have no children, or had children.
Sorry.
So we're having children.
So that means we should add into the NSL as a stack, you know, and then try to reset.
And this is a part CS has no children.
This is what we need to do.
Okay.
That's run it, hand run it.
So basically first thing is we check whether current states is go or not.
If it's already go, yeah, good.
Okay.
So we get something from the solution list.
So that is one.
Otherwise it's very, very much totally no then it's a fail.
Right.
If the SL is empty then fail.
Okay.
So if the CS has children then we go to this part.
If CS has no children we go here.
Okay.
Let's start.
So initial step zero.
So what we do is we set the current state, the starting state.
We set NSL, SL as a current state as well.
I mean starting state as well.
That then is empty list.
Right.
That's how we start.
And then we should run.
I wish I can have different page.
Yeah.
So we actually look at the algorithm to see check.
Does CS is go or not?
So CS suppose our goal is this one.
Okay.
So our goal is not here.
We just fully explore the space.
Yeah.
So the A, so we check the A is not a goal.
And then we check whether CS, the A has children.
Right.
So A has three children.
Yes.
So we should do this.
Yeah.
So we should remove those children which already in either dead end or the solution list or
the unprocessed state list.
Do we have?
The children actually is a BCD.
Right.
BCD.
Yeah.
So none of them in the existing one.
So that means we should add all of them into the NSL and treat them as the new unprocessed
state.
So this is how we add in.
Okay.
Adding from the left of the list.
So that is a stack process.
Okay.
So we add in.
So this is the second step.
First step checking.
Then we find no children.
And then we add in, sorry, we find they have children.
So we've added this into the list, into the NSL list.
And then what we do is here, right?
We add the first thing.
And then we take the first element in the NSL as the current state.
So that means the B will be used as the current state.
And then add the current, the new current state into the SL.
Okay.
So this is the step.
You see one.
And then two.
And then three.
So this is coming from here to here.
And then this one also add into the SL.
Okay.
So this is four steps.
So then we start from here again.
Check.
The CS.
Is this one.
Current state.
Is this a gold state?
It's not.
Right?
So we are doing the same thing.
We check the children of the B.
Is B have children?
Yes.
E and F.
Right?
Has this E and F appeared in other lists?
Not yet.
Right?
So they can be added in.
That's why they are added in here.
So this is step five.
They are added in.
And then after you add in, you actually use the first of the NSL.
That makes the E set as the current state.
And then this E also add into the SL.
Okay.
So far, all right?
So far it's quite easy.
Right?
Smooth.
Okay.
Then next.
Next.
E, check E, E is not gold.
And then E has children.
Yes.
So still have children.
So still add in.
So add in.
Okay?
So repeating.
So we add in.
Then don't look at this H cancel yet.
Okay?
So this is just H and I.
Add into the NSL as the processed state.
Okay?
And then after that, we should move this H to reset the CS.
Right?
Okay.
And then after that, the CS should put into the SL.
Yeah?
So then we check whether H is gold.
H is not the gold.
And now H have no children.
H have no children.
So we cannot use this part anymore.
We come here.
Okay.
So H have no children.
And then we see whether CS is SL.
Sorry.
The solution is that empty?
It's not empty, right?
So also whether CS and the first element of the SL is the same.
It's the same?
Yes?
So we should do this part.
Removing.
Okay?
So that means we should track back.
So we are tracking back.
So we should remove.
You see?
We should add the current CS into that end.
Yeah?
Finally, the end have one element.
Okay?
We should add the CS to that end.
That's here.
The H add into the dead end.
And then we check.
We should remove the first element from the SL.
So first element removed.
Okay?
And also remove the same elements from NSL.
So this one already processed.
Okay?
And then the first element of NSL set.
That means I should be used to set the CS.
Okay?
So now what is the, what's inside the CS?
What is inside the SL?
First element of the SL is what?
Don't look at here.
Actually they jump the steps here.
Do you notice?
After we cancel this first one based on here.
And also we reset the I into the CS.
Now what do we have?
CS equal to I and SL haven't update yet.
Right?
So SL is these three elements.
Yes?
And then the NSL, we have those.
Okay?
So is this same?
The first elements of SL same as I?
No, right?
Not the same.
So this condition is not satisfied anymore.
Okay?
So we can come out.
Yes?
So we should come here.
We should add the CS to SL.
Okay?
So that means I will add into the SL.
But next, next, you need to be careful.
Okay, we are here now.
So far we finished this and we managed to track back, right?
And then we come to here.
We come to here.
So we track back successfully.
And we come to search this one to check whether this is go or not.
Right?
So that is the I here checking whether this is a go.
So this is not go yet.
Okay?
Not go yet.
And does this note have children?
No children.
So come here again.
Right?
Come here again.
So SL is not empty.
The first elements of SL equal to CS satisfy this condition.
Correct?
Yeah.
So we should do this part.
Okay?
So what we do?
I will add into the add-and-end.
And then remove SL, remove the first elements of SL, remove the first elements of the NSL,
and reset the CS.
Okay?
So that means the I will be removed here.
And this I move to here.
And this I will be removed.
This I will be removed.
Okay, I think I should.
Okay, I just verbally say it.
I don't have a pointer to.
Well, yes, I have a pointer.
I should remove this one.
And that one already moved to here.
Right?
This is what I'm doing.
Add into the add-and-remove the first element, remove the first element of the NSL, and then the first element of the...
Okay, so that means the E should set into the...
The E should be here.
Right?
E should be set.
I mean, the current state now is the E.
Okay?
So this is what?
And now we're still in this while loop.
Okay?
So we need to check whether the SL is not empty and CS is the same element of the SL.
The CS is E.
First element of the SL is what?
E.
So do we need to...
Can we come out this loop yet?
Cannot.
Cannot come out.
You see?
It's satisfied this condition.
So meaning what?
E should add into the dead end and remove the first element of SL.
Remove the first element of NSL, reset CS.
Okay, so that means E should go.
E should go.
And this E should go to the dead end.
Okay?
We are still satisfied this condition.
No need to reset the E into...
Basically, you don't go here yet.
Okay?
This E was the previous step we got it because of eye condition.
Okay, now after you set, you find the E is exactly the same as the first element in SL.
So you still satisfy this condition.
It's not empty and this one satisfies the condition.
That's why you need to still go this way.
Okay?
Remove it.
Remove the E immediately.
Okay?
Yeah.
This is a tricky part.
Need to be careful.
Okay?
Yeah.
And then...
And then what?
And then next.
Is this still...
I mean, now it's not equal to, right?
The elements of CS is not the same as the first element because now it's a B, right?
So it's not the same.
So now we are breaking this while loop.
So we come here.
We can come to here.
That means the CS, the first elements of the CS can put into the...
Sorry.
The first elements of the SL can put into...
So that is the F.
F go here.
Okay?
So then you check the F.
So this is exactly what we want.
After we check in the eye, we backtrack to here.
We are not going to check the E anymore.
We should backtrack to the previous one.
Okay?
So that is the previous one.
Previous one was a B.
Okay?
So that's why we should go to the previous one.
Sorry.
Actually, on process...
Based on this, the on process one actually is the F.
So we should go to the F directly.
Okay?
So we have the F and then F put into the SL and then we start there again.
So any question?
So that's how we go.
Okay?
So we have the F and then the F have J.
So F have J and then after that backtrack.
Yeah?
So J is the same.
So we actually backtrack.
Backtrack F, J and then F and then even the B.
Right?
So we can remove all the three.
And then we go to the A.
Sorry.
We actually come to the...
Yeah.
Actually, basically, we come to here.
So we basically make use of the...
These three actually are already removed.
Yeah.
So we come to the C.
Okay?
So when we come to the C, the children, the F is no longer need to add in.
Because F already in the dead end list.
So F no need to add in.
Only the children G will be added.
Okay?
So for this one, actually, we go through the entire graph.
And suppose we didn't find the answer.
Okay?
The answer is not here.
So this we run this.
So please, you need to make sure you can do it.
Okay?
Not just understand the concept, but manually you can do it.
And that's exercise...
Exercise three, I think.
Exercise three.
Okay?
So look at this.
This is more complicated graph.
Right?
So we will...
I think how many of you already hand run this?
Not yet, huh?
So give you time to run.
We check the answer next week.
Okay?
And just to quickly just make sure we understand each other well.
So for example, when we come to the notes F, what are the children we should add into the NSL?
Okay, what are the children's?
L.
Can I know?
No more?
A.
Yeah.
But A, do we need to add in?
No need.
Yeah, because A appeared before.
Okay, this one thing.
Another thing, G, for example.
What are the children of the G?
Yeah, easily you identify these two, but you probably missed this one.
Yes.
Okay, so need to be careful.
So this one more like very much like a graph instead of three, right?
But we can still have definition of so-called the parents and siblings, this kind of idea.
Okay?
So go try out, use backtracking.
So we check answer next week.
So we are not doing it now.
I think, yeah, better check next week so we have more time.
And this is answer for the example today.
Okay?
Basically we go through this.
Although a bit messy, so here is a more clean version.
And do you have this one?
In your side, you have this one, right?
Okay, okay.
So you can check this one, yeah.
This is our example, okay?
It's not the exercise.
Any question?
A bit serious, but yeah, this is, okay, computer can do it very fast, but we need to fully understand this.
So that's why I give you a toy problem to hand run it.
Okay?
Just need to be careful to see children or other children.
And then when you backtrack, you know, backtrack to those parents, they already, the children already fully explore, they become a dead end as well.
Okay?
Just add in too.
Okay, so this is, so this is exercise.
We check next week.
Okay, so are you ready to move to next algorithm?
Okay, so backtracking, you see, is systematically to explore, but it's very much more probably for a graph.
Okay, so you can have this.
Our next one, next two, next three are very easy.
Okay, very easy, very easy and very easy to be applied.
So BFS, okay, BFS from the name you can tell, right?
Breath first search.
So we are going level by level.
So level by level, level by level.
Okay, so level is depends on the distance from your current state to the root.
Okay, to the root.
So that length consider as a level.
So this is, if this is level zero, then this is all level one and then level two and so on.
Okay, so only when that's no more states to be explored in the same level, given level, and then the algorithm will move to the next level.
Okay, so that is a BFS.
And so from this tree or from this, yes, this graph, what we have level by level, so level one, level zero.
And BCD, after that, the next level, EFGHIJ, then next level, and next level.
Okay, level by level, level by level.
Okay, so that is BFS.
Implementation.
Okay, so for BFS, probably we are not interested having an SL.
So basically we can use these two lists to hold the notes.
Okay, one is called open, another one is called closed.
Okay, so closed is like that then, checked already.
And open are those which is not checked yet.
Okay, so this is open, hold those which is state need to be checked, and then close is those already exempt.
So those assess states were removed from the left most.
Okay, so just check the left most is the one you want to check.
So in the open, in the open list, you take the left most, and then the new one, the successor or descendants will be add into the right.
Okay, so it's not add into the left.
So it's like a queue.
It's like forming a queue.
It's not forming a stack, it's forming a queue.
So that is the first coming, first out, right, from a queue.
So this is for the open, it's from the queue.
So we are adding into the tail, right, the tail of the queue, because we are taking from the left most.
Okay, we are taking the states to be exempt from the left most in the open list.
Okay, so this is the idea.
Yeah, so this is much simple, right.
So only two list, one is taking the state to be exempt, one is holding the states already checked.
Okay, so open, which is having those state need to be exempt.
So starting from the starting states, right, then the close will be those exams already.
And then check whether the open still have states in the open list.
If it is, then we do something.
If not, that means, yeah, you haven't find anything that means fail already.
Okay, so for the open, we take the left most, see, left most.
Left most from this open list, and suppose we put, call it X, okay, call it X.
The first elements in the open list, left most.
And then we check whether X is already a goal.
If it is, successful, okay, we find it.
Otherwise, we do this.
Otherwise, do what?
Children of the X.
Get all the children of the X, and then put the current X into the closed list.
That means X already exempt, and then throw it away.
So X gone.
And then we eliminate all the children of the X, which already appeared in the open,
or have been exempt in the closed list.
Okay, so that is the one.
So get rid of them first.
Put the remaining, put the rest of the children to the right end of the open list.
Okay, form a queue, form a queue, right end, right?
Tell of the queue.
Yeah, so this is the one.
So just, just, then you're open to check from the left most again.
Okay, then new one add into the tail.
That's all.
Yeah.
Clear?
Okay, hand run again.
Okay.
So we are using these three.
So suppose this is the goal, or actually no goal.
Okay, we just up to us how much you want to run.
So we are using a BFS to run this.
So we have two, and the queue, or first thing, first out, or you call it the last thing.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah, actually it's a queue.
And then you have open list, and also have closed list.
Okay, so when you add into, actually this one, we didn't say anything about how you want
to handle the closed list, so up to you, it's not important.
Okay, so you can add into the left, or you want to left into the right, it's up to us.
Okay, so for the open, we must have a queue, then you can actually form the branched,
the, oh sorry, the level by level, yeah, level by level, BFS.
Okay, so this is the one.
We have the A to start.
So there is a starting state, and the closed list is empty.
Okay, and then we check whether A is a goal, so A is not goal.
Is there any children?
Yes, I have three children.
So three children add into the open list, right?
Open the current X, the current X, throw into the closed, and then these three children
add into the right-hand side of the list, the open list.
But open list is empty, so left-hand side or right-hand side, it won't show much, right?
But yes, this one will show, this one show.
Yeah, so three add in, and then take the leftmost as the X, right?
So B, check the B, and then B has children, yes, E and F.
So E and F must add into the tail, okay?
Right-hand side.
Right-hand side of the open list, okay, open list.
And then put the X, the current X, into the closed list, right?
And then move on.
The leftmost becomes X, right?
So there is a C.
So C has children, yes, G and H.
G and H add into the open, and then the C will add into the closed list, and then move on.
Okay, so this is all the way until like here, okay?
So suppose if the U is a goal, yeah, until we find the U, actually we still failed.
Okay, so here I just, it's not everything show yet, we can show a few more steps, yeah?
Okay, so this one is quite straightforward, right?
Okay, next.
Oh, no, no, no, next.
So actually we are ending here for this lecture, suppose we go through the backtracking, which is more complicated,
and then the breadth BFS, okay?
So BFS is another way to implement the depth first, oh sorry, breadth BFS, okay?
So yeah, we are using two lists only.
So we just use the open and also the closed list, yeah?
And then when you're forming the, when you add in new elements into the open list, you need to form a queue, okay?
Okay, so that means add into the tail, the rightmost as a new children will be adding from there, okay?
And then you take, always take the leftmost as a state going to be exempt, yeah?
Okay, we can continue, huh?
No need to break, yeah?
Okay, so another way, okay, so algorithm is very simple.
So is there any issue with this approach?
Okay, what is the major disadvantage or what is the major could be the bottom neck of this approach?
So let's take a look of the size of the memory required, okay?
So the slightly darker blue here, yeah, it is very hard to tell.
This light blue, slightly darker light blue, actually it indicates the elements of the states inside the closed list, okay?
Closed list.
And the lighter blue, very light blue here is the elements, states inside the open list, okay?
So you can see it's a left, I mean level by level.
So when you check this, all the children will be in, and then when you check this, the other elements should be in as well, right?
So it should be added into the open.
So this is the amount of the elements, states will be hosted inside the open list, okay?
So when you check in this one, that means this already exempt, and those, those, those already throw into the closed, but there are children already add into the open.
Until here, when you exempt this, then this, this, as well as those already add into the open list, right?
So you can see the depth.
When you go, the depth grows deeper how the requirements, what is the impact to the, to the, to the size of the memory, right?
You need to host, you need to hold the, the, all the children, and the children number depends on the depth of your goal, right?
So, so depends on the depth of the tree or depth of the graph, right?
So this is the major thing.
So this is at this step, step six here, yeah, you can see those are in the close.
We have all those, the states here, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven are in the open list, okay?
So this is the requirement to the, the pressure we will have for the memory requirements, okay?
To the, for the BFS, okay?
For the BFS.
So if the branch factor is B, then the memory we require is B to the power of N, okay?
So N is the depth here.
So this is, this is just imagine, okay?
Just imagine the goal.
This is those figures I don't even, I can't imagine what's the size of this, okay?
Doesn't matter how we derive it, this is just the, the, the figure actually is about, about estimated, about this figure, okay?
Ten to the power of 360, okay?
So you can imagine one trillion is ten to the power of 12, okay?
So huge, very, very big.
So that is mission impossible, right?
Mission impossible.
That's why when we see the goal, computer can play the goal well, can beat the human being.
It was like, yeah, this is like how to achieve this.
Definitely not state-based approach, right?
Okay, so this is a major limitation or major issue with the BFS.
What is the advantage of BFS?
Level by level, yeah, simple.
Anything else?
I mean, if suppose we have the memory.
And also another thing I want to say is some state, it may repeat, okay?
In the game, game, game tree, states may repeat, right?
Because it's with a different, also depends on your opponent, how they play, and then can lead to the same state,
but different level, okay?
So if you want to find a goal state, some is here, some is there, okay?
So for BFS, which one you can find first?
Level by level, right?
So you can find this one rather than the deep down one.
So that is a kind of optimized answer, right?
That is an advantage, okay?
So if the memory can hold, you know, your memory is big enough than BFS, and also feasible time,
BFS can find probably optimal answer, okay?
Okay, enough about BFS.
Now let's move on to next BFS, depth first search.
Because we say memory is an issue, right?
So can we have something which can help us with systematic search and at the same time don't cause us so much memory?
That looks like it's an answer, right?
So we go branch by branch.
So branch by branch, that is a depth first search.
So that means we examine all the children, and that means for a state, we examine all its children and they are descendants.
And examine before they are siblings, okay?
That means they are other branches.
So deep, deep, deep, deep down, down, down, down all the way, okay?
Before examine your siblings.
So that is actually backtracking also in a way is a deep depth first, right?
Yeah, so go this way.
So from the principle, yeah, only when no further descendants of the states can be found, and then the sibling will be considered.
Okay, so this is the one.
So you go, go, go, go all the way.
So no more descendants can be found for these notes, for example.
Then, no, sorry, for these notes, no more descendants can be found.
Then you go to another branch, okay?
So that is a depth first.
So, okay.
So for this one will be the sequence, yeah?
I already color code you.
So that means we go A, B, E, K, S.
After that, yeah, L, T.
Then go back to this branch, right?
So, and so on.
Branch by branch, okay?
So backtracking, we said, it's also a depth first search.
Okay, so implementation wise, yeah, you will see another way to implement the depth first search.
We already see one which is for backtracking.
Backtracking in a way is depth first as well.
But now we have another way.
So another way, another implementation is we just use two lists, open and closed.
We don't use three plus one.
Okay, so the descendant notes will be at and then removed from the leftmost of the open to be examined.
Descendant, yeah.
Okay, so everything add into the state, open states from the left.
Okay, take also take from the left.
So that means it's a stack class, the last in first out.
Okay, and then, okay, so this is what we have.
We have the implementation two lists, one is open, one is closed.
And then the states have been exempt.
So the children would be not be exempt.
Oh, yeah, so the states which are already generally about having exempt yet to add into the open.
Okay, so similar like NSL in the backtracking.
Yeah, but then the closed basically is the dead end.
Okay, and only thing is when we add in, we add into the open list from the left.
Okay, from the left, forming a stack instead of forming a queue.
A queue is a BFS, okay.
DFS is a stack, so add from the left.
That's the key difference.
So, you see?
So open, yeah, you have the starting, then closed list is empty to start with.
If the open still have elements, then we should do this part.
We should take the first, the leftmost from the open list, we call it X.
And then we check whether X is a goal already.
If it is, then successful, funded.
Otherwise, we do this.
So that means we take the children of the X and then put the current X into the closed list.
That means the dead end.
And then also check all the children of the X and remove those they already appear before.
Okay, we don't consider them anymore.
And then put the rest into the left-hand side of the open list.
Okay, that means add them in from the left.
Yeah, so the open will act as a stack.
Okay.
Okay, so that's all for the DFS.
So, we run it.
So again, if this is a goal.
And start with the starting states, closed list is empty.
Okay, then we check whether X is already the goal.
It's not.
Then the children of the X, the BCD.
So, BCD, any of them appear before?
No.
So, all of them can be add into the open list.
And the other X already put into the closed.
So, it's empty open now.
And then these three elements add into the left.
Okay, so we cannot see add in.
Okay, and then B will be the X.
B will be checked.
And B is not.
And B is short way.
The children of the B is the EF.
So, EF add into the left-hand side and so on.
Okay.
And yeah, continue until the U is funded.
Okay, any questions?
So, easy to run this.
It's very easy to run BFS, BFS.
I mean, normally very.
So, I will test you on the backtracking.
Okay, so this is the thing.
Yeah, you need to hand run it.
Okay.
So, I say this alternative way implement the depth first.
Because we are only using this two list.
It's down.
So, yeah, let's take a look at memory requirement now.
So, remember the major issue with the breadth first search is the memory.
Like memory cost.
So, now what about this?
Yeah, so when we basically go this way.
So, this is in our close list.
Like the slightly dark curve light blue.
And then lighter light blue is here.
Okay, so that is when we having the step here, right?
Six.
Yeah.
So, this fall is inside the open.
Okay.
The other side in the closed.
We already finished this branch.
So, you see the thing in the open will be smaller.
Right?
So, the memory may not be the major issue now.
So, what would be the issue?
Imagine the answer is somewhere here.
Okay.
And then we have a huge deep, deep, deep, deep, long lane.
We have a deep down branch.
The answer is not in that branch at all.
Then we can actually waste all of time, all of life there.
Possible.
Yeah, that's the worst case.
We always talk about the worst case.
Yeah.
So, that is the issue.
Another issue is of course just now we say the level by level we will find the best,
better answer, right?
The optimal answer.
If the answer is there, we will find it first rather than the deep down one.
But for this one, it's hard to say.
It depends on the branch.
Right?
You may actually find the answer which is not optimal.
You actually have a much better answer over there.
But it's the, you know, right hand side of the branch.
Yeah.
So, you can't find it.
But major thing is you probably cannot, even the answer exists, you probably cannot find
it.
So, that is the major thing.
We waste our life to certain branch which is totally wrong, mislead branch.
Right?
So, that is a major issue with this.
Yeah.
You can take a look of this.
We try to show this, the previous using this power, right, the eight puzzle.
And so, you see, suppose our goal is sorted, the numbered tower around the, you know, so
one, two, three, four, five, six, eight, you know, the empty power is in the middle.
So, suppose this is our goal.
And so, those are the possible movement, a few steps and the answer is here, right?
So, if you use BFS, you will go like, you need to check, you get the answer.
So, you need to check 46 times.
Okay.
But if you go for depth first, this one looks like a faster.
Faster get the answer.
Okay.
But it really depends.
It really depends.
So, you can see it's just a different way to systematically find the goal, to search for
a goal.
Okay.
And some will become more efficient than another.
But the major thing for BFS is major disadvantages.
You probably, even the answer exists, you probably cannot find it.
So, if some branch like that can have a loop, you know, lead you down to the totally run
lane.
Yeah.
So, we have one slide, try to compare these two methods.
Okay.
So, for BFS, the nice thing is you can find the shortest path and then never track into
a particular blind lane, right?
So, it won't have that happen because it's level by level.
This one, but the major problem with this is very, comes to you much more memory.
That is the issue.
So, the depth first, actually less memory and it's just, you know, can be mislead.
And may not find the answer.
Yeah.
So, this is just talk about the memory console for BFS.
This is talking about the depth first issue.
Yeah.
Maybe lost in certain branch.
Okay.
Although memory wise is much better.
So, that's why we hope we can combine both.
Right.
So, that is our number four search algorithm.
Okay.
Backtracking, then BFS, DFS.
Now, we want to combine BFS and DFS together.
So, that is iterative deepening.
Okay.
I iterative deepening and using probably depth first.
So, we actually set the depth first.
And then within that given depth, we do depth first search.
Okay.
So, that is one.
So, this is firstly, yeah, deep first search in the space with depth spawn of one.
And then two and three and like that.
But every time you basically have to research, re-inituate, I mean, start the search from
beginning.
Okay.
If you find it, you find it.
If you cannot find it, you increase the depth and then you have to do DFS again from that
tree.
Okay.
So, this is, this is, yeah.
When you look at this, it's easier to understand.
Right?
So, this is the iteration one with the depth equal to one.
So, you search this way and then this way.
And this is increase the depth by two now.
So, still go branch.
So, you see this is one, two, three, four and then five and six.
So, this is how you search.
So, if you find it, then good, not, then increase by one and then go four, this way, one, two,
three, four, like this, this.
Okay.
So, depth first with that given tree.
So, this is approach.
Okay.
So, basically hopefully you can combine the advantage of both together from the, you
know, the BFS and DFS.
Okay.
Then exercise four is to go through this.
So, you can see this is a graph.
Right?
It's no arrow given, meaning what?
Bidirectional.
Yes.
It's undirected.
Right?
So, it's both directions.
Okay.
So, now I see why the children of the A, B and C.
Right?
Why the children of the C?
A is a children as well.
Right?
Although you probably no need to put in.
Yeah.
Depends.
Okay.
So, both directions.
Both directions.
That's why it's both ways.
Okay.
So, can we do this using the BFS, DFS, starting from A and then the goal is G?
Shall we do it now?
We check the answer.
It's an easy one.
Right?
Easy one.
Okay.
Should we continue our discussion?
You have tried, right?
So the best way, I can see some of you actually based on this graph and try to draw the tree.
Right?
So you try to actually draw a tree and then based on a tree, you want to do the level
by level, okay, or the branch by branch. But the best way probably is just to write, follow
the algorithm. Okay, so you just have the open list and close list. So if it's a BFS,
you go for the, you are forming, you're adding the things from the right. Okay, so that means
actually it's forming a queue. If it's a DFS, you're forming a stack. Okay, so that is a
key thing. No need to take picture. I will update the exercise answer and the exercise,
the example answer, exercise answer, I think will be available tomorrow around noon time.
Okay, after the full-time students finish their class. So those slides is already in
NTU learn. So no need to take picture. Okay, so we are starting from here and suppose G is a goal.
So this is a BFS we are talking about. So remember keywords is a queue. Okay, so the queue, forming
a queue, forming a queue, queue for the open list. Okay, open list. So starting from A and then initially
the closed list is empty. And then we check whether A is a goal is not yet. So we add in the children
of the A into the open to form the queue. So children of the A, that is a B and C. Then anyone
want to ask something here? Why I put, because the sequence of this is also important, right?
It's forming a queue. So forming a queue, why not same level, right? Why not C and B?
Yeah, so, but it's a, I mean, level by level. So same level. So why this way, not this way.
Okay, that is really hard. That's why you probably don't have a unique answer. Right? Yeah, why not
some of you probably put the C and the B. Then I will examine C first rather than B. Right?
Yeah, so actually I didn't make it very clear for this exercise. We should say for the children,
probably I want to go for alphabetical order. Then it's a unique answer. Otherwise, all correct.
All correct. Yeah, so this is just one of the possible answer. It's not the only answer. Okay,
so I'm putting the B in front of C, the two both children. I go for alphabetical order. Then the
B in front of C. And then similarly, after checking B, the children of the B, which is D F, I sorted
again, you know, alphabetical order. That's why D F H. Okay, so I think that is the only thing I need
to say about this. So similarly, if you draw the tree, then also how you, you know, which branch
you put in slightly different. Okay, D F and then check C, C, add in this and so on, so on, so on.
Okay, any question? So it's just a bit serious. Otherwise, it's okay. Right? And then only question
you can ask is about this. But they are all children. So how, which children go first? Okay,
so it's the same level, but then which one you want to check first? So suppose we go alphabetical
order. Okay, but in the actual scenario, probably that is something they have normally this is not
totally exhausted search. Okay, normally if it's a game tree, then normally come with a heuristic
value or hint, okay, which one give you a higher priority. So then you follow that or something.
Okay, anything else?
Similarly, yeah, so this is a BFS. Then what about DFS? Same graph, DFS.
So same thing here, similar here, then after that, then when you check the B,
you also have D F H, right? But D F H adding where? It's not adding from the right hand side.
It should add in from left hand side. That is the only thing. Right? Yeah, so this is the one.
See, left hand side, left hand side. Okay, so we are adding from the whole,
the whole open list, actually is a stack. Okay, so we should add in from the left.
Any questions?
So the keywords is here, left hand, left hand, left hand of the open list.
And then also the sequence probably alphabetical order. So then I put it this way. Okay.
Okay.
So for this case, it looks like DFS is faster. Seven steps to find it. This one take longer,
slightly longer. Right. Okay, anything else?
Okay. How to do this using the iterative, the deepening method? You can try.
Okay. So that is just a concept. Okay. So that's all about the lecture five. Basically,
we finish off the topic two. So we cover the exhaustive search. Okay. So we introduce the
backtracking and then the BFS, DFS and also the iterative. Okay. And then for the topic two,
in the beginning, we talk about representation. And then that's why today we start to talk about
search algorithms. Okay. Then one thing left is about the discussion for the exercise two,
which is about data driven or goal driven. Right. For the play the goal game.
Go game. Okay. Go game. Should be data driven or goal driven?
Go driven?
Data driven. Okay. How do you decide based on what?
Visibility or finding the answer. Right. We are talking about searching on the same space.
Is to check forward or backwards. Which one the actual search space is smaller?
Yeah. So like what I said before, John and Tom and John relationship. Right. So
the to check whether John is a, which one? Tom is a great, great, great parents of the John.
Right. So you, which one data driven or goal driven? Depend which direction give you a smaller
or bigger tree. That's all. Okay. So if it's a play goal, if it's a goal driven, what will happen?
Remember the, for goal, actually the branch factor is 250. Yeah. So that's why I guess you
probably want to say you want to go for goal driven, but this way the branch factor, I don't know
what is the value. I mean the front finding the goal states is also very challenging.
Many, many, many possible goal states. Right. And then after you find one, then you find the
states lead to these goal states also many, many, many possible possibilities. Right.
That is a goal driven. But if it's data driven, although it looks like a branch factor is 250,
but in actual play, that's no way you do that way. Okay. So that means actually the skill player
probably, I mean, those champion, they probably only estimate about between 10 to 20, up to 20
possible branches. Okay. And then probably also look ahead a few steps. So you, for each branch,
you probably look at likely how your opponent would play. And then you look ahead a few steps.
And then based on that, you search. So data driven seems not feasible.
Okay. So basically, okay, principle is you see data driven, what is, you know, tree size. And then
goal driven, what is the tree size? Which one is smaller? Then take that. Most likely in the
real world situation, you probably go hybrid, you meet in the middle. Okay. Yeah. Then diagnosis,
for expert diagnosis, like COVID, you know, or you actually have many data, which is to help us
to diagnosis particular disease. Right. So which way we go? Go driven or data driven?
Huh? Data driven as well? Okay. So suppose we have all the symptoms like running nose,
high temperature, you know, coughing. Those are data, right? Those are the data. And then based
on this data, we try to find what disease. Yeah. So do you think doctor will do like this?
Totally data driven? Or actually they look at your symptoms, they already assume particular disease.
And then they go this way to get the supporting evidence. Most likely they assume like, okay,
this is flu or this is COVID. And then if it's COVID and those data support or not, if not,
then you probably give up this goal. You find another goal. So likely it's this way.
Or actually it's a hybrid. Okay. So it doesn't matter. I mean, you can have a different way,
as long as you can justify well. You think, you know, which tree, which direction is smaller.
Yeah. Although in the same search space. Okay. Yeah. So no standard answer, but in a way,
the principle is this. Okay. So that is lecture five. And we move on to the last topic we want
to discuss today. Okay. So that is we move to the first section in the topic tree, which is about
heuristic search and gaming. So part A is more about heuristic search. Part B is particularly
talking about the algorithms for gaming. Okay. So you can see so far that exhausted search,
basically we don't have any hints. So we only have the search space and we want to systematically
finding the answer. Right. So that is the algorithm we learned. But what if actually that is some
hints or that is some experience plus effort and then actually can help us to give us an
evaluation function. And this evaluation function actually can lead us to, you know, quickly find
answer. So that would be better. Right. So that is hopefully we can actually improve the performance.
Because we know when the tree or the search space become very big, systematically search for answer
become not feasible. And then we need to rely on the hint. Right. The hint. So normally the hint
is come with, you know, the skills. People very skillful in this area. And then they can come up
with, they'll know some part probably is really like a pattern recognition, you know, because like
those goal player, you really don't know how they find it. They probably not really can write the rule
to tell you how exactly they find answer. They just look at the board situation. They probably can
kind of predict, you know, have a, have a, have a way to judge which, what they should do. So that
is kind of pattern recognition. Not if that is any way which is can use an equation or something
which can get the figure for you. Okay. Then actually we can come with make use of this to
have every state you can actually estimate what is how likely this will lead to the success or
lead to the goal. Then we should apply this heuristics. Okay. So this is what we are talking
about. So what is this about? And then how to design the heuristic value? Okay. So this is,
cannot answer this question actually. The heuristic value, these things, the design of this is not
like applicable for all the problems. It's very much problem driven. Okay. So it's goal, you
play goal for example, you need to find what's the best way to come out with a heuristic. If you
play chess, that's another way to do it. Okay. So it's very different. And then so we can only say
the some guideline. And then it's not enough just to have the heuristic value. Okay. Even you have
the value, but you don't have a right way to search for the answer is also will not lead to the
successful finding the goal. So search algorithm is still important. So we are going to talk about
hill climbing and their best first or greedy best first or the optimistic one, which is, you know,
finding optimal answer, which is a star. So here I will say something more about this later. Okay.
And then we talk about how to apply the heuristics in the gaming.
Okay. So first part is without talking about game. Okay. We just talk about in general how the
heuristic search can apply and what are the search algorithms we are covering. Okay. So basically
this is talking about the strategy. I'm still talking about the search strategy. So before we
talk about exhaustive search, right? We actually uninformed and then systematically search that
is so-called this blind search. Okay. So it's uninformed. And now we talk about informed. So we
know some hints. Okay. We can make use of the hints to search for answer. So that is under the strategy.
So there are a few things. Yeah. I showed these slides before is to talk about this search,
whether it's completeness. So if the answer exists, can we find it? Okay. So just now we say, for
example, the DFS cannot find, it's not complete. Okay. It's not complete. It's not satisfied
completeness because the answer can exist there, but it's in the branch and then you have one branch
which is deep down. There is no way you come out. It's trapped inside. So you cannot find the answer.
But the BFS probably is another issue is space complexity. Okay. Yeah. So these are the few
things in time and then optimal solution that is BFS can achieve, but DFS probably cannot. Okay.
Then a few things like related to the branch factor, related to the depth and relate to the
maximum space you have. Okay. And then, so these are the important things. So this is more for your
information only. Okay. I don't expect you to totally remember this or to fully justify this,
but it's good to know. Okay. So this is BFS, DFS, and then the combination of these two. So you
can see that this is depth. For DFS, it's not complete. Right. You cannot find the answer,
even the solution exists. Also cannot find the optimal solution. Yeah. So this is a major thing.
But for BFS, this is a space and time that's a main issue. Okay. And so let's start to introduce
heretics. So this word itself basically indicates, you know, personal discovery of something,
experience. Okay. So we actually hopefully, the noun here tell us is use experience and practical
efforts to find answer to questions or improve the performance. Right. Give us a hint. Give us a
hint. Yeah. So is this space search, this is formulated as a rules? So it's likely,
hopefully, can give us a lead to the answer, which is acceptable answer. Okay. May not be the
optimal. So sometimes finding sub-automome is already happy. We are already happy enough. Okay. So
that is using the heuristic help us to do. So why, yeah, basically is because not feasible
if we don't have it. Totally rely on the system as such. Probably kid cannot give us answer at all.
Okay. Within a given time and space. So that's why we have to rely on this. Also, so hopefully,
this will guide us to search along the more promising space. Okay. So space. Yeah. So we
can quickly eliminate those states, which is definitely not worth to explore. Okay. So that is
a key thing. So hopefully it can be applied to defeat those, you know, relate any question related
constraints, actually problem. We can actually find some answer. And then, yeah. So, so this is
talking about, you know, go and the chest, those have very large brand, very, very factors. So we
have to have a hint in order to use it. Limitation, of course, because this is based on human experience
and also their skills really depends. So that's why it's valuable. Okay. It's not,
cannot prove it's definitely true. Definitely work all the time. And also very likely when we
work out the heuristic value is based on our limited information. Okay. So for example, when you
calculate the H value, you probably only look ahead a few steps. And then based on that information,
you work out the hints. Okay. So it's partial information. So it's not like it's a local
information. It's not like a global information available. So that is how actually practically
how like a chess player, for example, how they estimate the value, right? Yeah. So this is limited
information. That's why definitely valuable. Sometimes doesn't work. Okay. So cannot guarantee. So
it's also, it's cannot eliminate those, you know, guarantee which one is better than the other one.
And for all the situations, it works everywhere. No.
So that's why for heuristic search, two things. One is the measurement. Another one is the search
algorithm. Okay. So still search algorithm is important. So make use of the rules to get the
acceptable solutions, combine the heuristic value we have, the measurements we have,
and then the search algorithm we follow. Okay. Okay. Then we take a look of the tic-tac-toe again.
So what is likely we can have each value, okay? Heuristic value. So that's why let's take a look
starting. And then suppose cross player and the circle player. So cross player, you have three
places to put. Actually, it's nine places to put. But we summarize one is the left corner,
one is in the middle, oh, sorry. One is the corners. Okay. So four corners. Another one is in the
middle, very center point. And then another one is in the middle of the row or columns. Okay. So
total nine. But we just show three of it to be the representative. Okay. Then after you have this
cross and then the circle player come into play. So suppose the circle player put in again in the
middle or in the corner or in the, you know, the place you can have, you can place the circle.
Okay. So this is the one. And this is the level is considered as a how many levels? Yeah. Maybe
just one level. If it's just zero, then one and two. And then you can decide where to put
for the cross. Okay. Cross player. So you can see, okay, if you already placed the cross in this
location, then the chunks are winning. It can come from this row or this column or in the diagonal.
Right. So you can say the h value equal to three. If this is counting of the possible winning
based on the current location. Okay. So if you put here, then what is the h value here?
Yeah. So one, two, three, four. Right. So this is, yeah, what about this one? Only two.
Okay. So if you want to win, where should you, you should put? Yeah. You should try to put in the
middle. Right. Yeah. So this is the one. So we are using this most win heuristic, you know,
for the first children and try to estimate together h value and then guide you to see
where to put. And then after you put, that is your opponent's turn to put next. Then after that,
you also decide how are you going next, what's your next movement. Okay. Again, you can,
based on your opponent's location, then you check what is next, where can I put. So this is a practice.
Yeah. So suppose this opponent put here. Okay. Then where should we put?
You can try. Okay. If I put here, yeah. You assume in the beginning you put in the center.
Right. So your opponent put this position. So then you decide if you put here, what's the h value?
If you put here, what's your h value? What if you put here? Okay. So you can count the h value,
how many times likely we will win. Then you pick the highest. Right. So this is a hint for us to
see, okay, how likely you can win. Now, of course, you, this h value indicates how fit you are,
a fit. So we say the h value can be a fitness or can be a cost. So if it's a cost, of course,
you want to cost as low as possible. If it's a fitness, you want to fitness as high as possible.
Right. So that is the idea. Okay. Yeah. So this is what exactly we had. So here we talk about
fitness. So for this one, actually fitness is three because one, two, three. Right. So this is
four, this is two. So opponent put here, then you are here, then you have those options. So this
one give you three, and this one give you five. So of course, you should try to put in this location.
This is h equal to five, highest h value. So if your opponent put in this, in this occasion,
but if your opponent put here, then you should evaluate accordingly. And then you probably want
to pick this one. Okay. So this is the, how the h come into play. Okay. So this is h value.
Can I can only use some very simple questions to tell us how actually you can design your h.
But since h is linked to the experience and skills, definitely is a programmer
need to decide how to design it. Okay. And it's problem based. This cannot be very general rules
to be applied. So after you have the h, then of course, just now we see, based on h value,
you should pick the maximum one for fitness and pick the lowest one for h. And is this the only
way to find the answer? Because next step is still depends on your opponent, how to move.
And then you act. Right. So is this always just to find the best only or you should have a say
search based on the best first. Okay. So it's like, you see the difference best only and best
first. This is different concept. If best only, you only keep the best one, the rest you ignore.
Okay. And then you probably stuck somewhere. You cannot find the answer. But if it's a best first,
you still have second. Okay. You can go best first and then you can still backtrack. If it
doesn't work, you can still kind of backtrack or you still have a backup. You still have backup
pool. Then you choose second best, for example. Okay. So it's different. That's why we talk about
algorithm now. Okay. So this is a heuristic based search algorithm. So suppose we go for the best
only. Okay. So he'll climbing. So you always climb the taller, you think is the best one. Okay.
And then like clay, like for example here. So suppose you're in this kind of location and then
you find the, I don't know. Okay. You probably, you're here and then you can kind of find the best
or you are somewhere, somewhere here. Then you find this one is the best. You know, depends on
local situation. And then actually best children is like for further expansion and you don't keep
any information for the siblings. Okay. So it's all up and then this is kind of greedy approach. And
you will find it won't work. Okay. So this is a limitation. So you can actually end up with
error and stuck in some local minimal. So a more informed algorithm will be, you know,
using the best first instead of best only. Okay. So don't go for best only. That's too ideal.
So go for best first. You still have second, you still have a second chance. Okay. And then
other thing we'd like to highlight is a fitness and causes. So remember if you are each function is
fitness, then you go for highest and then your best will be the highest value and you still
have a second best and so on. And then if it's a cost, then the lowest cost is the best one. Okay.
So this is the idea. Okay. So let's see for this one we want to look at whether the best only,
that means he'll climbing is this one working or not. So convince you. So we attach with a value,
don't ask me how the value we got it, but suppose this is a cost. Okay. So here the H is a cost.
So a have a cost of five, B have cost of four and so on. So suppose I go for best only. Okay.
Best only. So this is equal. I probably randomly select this one. Okay. So I select the B and
select the B. All those will be throw away. You have, you don't have the information anymore.
So I come to here and then I'm stuck here. Right. Because you expanded, you find the cost
value is higher. So you cannot feel climbing up. So I mean climbing is for best value. Okay. But
it's for the cost that means you actually go the best is, you know, lowest value. So the lowest
value here, this is higher. So I should stop here. I'm not finding the answer. Okay. So this is
talking about if I go the B. So if randomly I pick the C looks like I'm lucky I come here.
And then this is a fall. And then I expanded these two branches. And so this is lower. Right. So that
means this is better. So I can move to this. I move to this and then expanded again. I will end up
where? Best only. I will end up here. Do we find the answer? No. Not. That is a consequence.
Okay. So you can see although you have the each value, suppose each value is very correct,
but your strategy is wrong. Okay. You are using the hill climbing or the best only approach
that will not help you to find the answer. Okay. What if you are using best first?
Best first, but not only very best first. So this is the same thing. Okay. So we have
starting from A and then you have the children. And then you find the best. So best is D. So the D
will be expanded. The children of the B will be evaluated. You get each value. Actually those are
all still kept. Okay. So those are kept. So all the siblings are still kept. So those are still
in your open list. Okay. So still there. And then when this expanded, then what do you do? You look
at all the possible descendants. Okay. So you look at all of them. So can cross generation. Okay. So
that means B, C, E, F will have the same equal chance to be examined. And then see which one I
should expand next or search next. Okay. So yeah. So when you come to the D, after you expand it,
now which one you should go? Those lowest. Right. If the F is, yeah, F is a cost. So lowest. So I
should go B, right? Yeah. So the B that is expanded. Okay. So expanded you get this. So who are the
notes in the open now? It's a G, H, C, E and F. Okay. Then they compete among themselves. And then
you pick the best. So among this, which one is best? The E is best. So E is the best. And then you
get this. And there you have. Okay. So that's how possibly you can find the answer. Okay. So this
is called best first. Okay. But not best only. Okay. So that's the best first algorithm. So you
have open and also you have closed list. So this is how you evaluate. So basically pick the best
notes in the open. So you see pick the best notes in the open. That means the open list, is this a
stack or is this a queue? Doesn't matter. In a way, doesn't matter. When you add into, you can add in
any direction and then sort it. You need to sort based on their H value. Yes. And then the best one,
you pick. Okay. So you sort it. Maybe you from high to low or low to high depends on what is your H
value definition. Then you pick the best. Okay. So this is generate the assessors. And then for
each assessor, if you check, you know, whether have generate before and then evaluate into the open
and the records, the parents. So if already generate before and still in the open, you want to replace
them. Okay. Use a better H value. Replace them. Update the cost. And then if already placed in the
close, if the new pass is better than previous one, then you actually take them out and then add
into the open. So that means you can recycle. Okay. You can take out previously already exam,
but actually reach by different paths. And then if the current one is better, you add in again. Okay.
So it can be re-examined. So that is the idea. Yeah. So one more algorithm.
Okay. So this is open or closed. Okay. The only thing is now you have the H value.
You have H value. You also still checking the children. You check whether X already,
sorry, sorry. Okay. Okay. Start from here. Remove the left most. Okay. I'm talking about left most.
So I'm still using left most. That means I sorted and then our best one on the left. Okay. So left
most, put into X and then check whether X is already the goal. Yes. Then return. If not,
then get the children on the X. And then for each children, you check, check, check. Okay. So see
whether the children is not appear before. So that is very straightforward. Right. To add them.
Okay. So that means you should evaluate the value, the H value for these children and then add these
children to the open. Okay. Just add. They didn't say add from which direction. Doesn't matter. Just
add. Because after adding, yeah, the current X should be in the close. After adding, you need to
sorting, do the sorting. So that is a reordering states on the open by their heuristic merit.
Okay. So either the best lowest value or highest value depends on whether you are using the fitness
or using cost. And then the best one should be on the left most. Okay. If it's equal, then equal.
I mean up to you, random or alphabetical order or whatever if you want to have a unique answer.
Okay. Yeah. So this is the resort. Resorting. That's why here seems very casually. Just say,
just say, just say, add. Right. Yeah. Just say add this into the open. Just say add.
So this is if the children not appear before, if the children already appear in the open,
then we check whether the current one reach, is there a shorter path. That means it's a
shorter one. So we try to find the optimum. So if it's shorter one, we should update. Okay. We
should update. So similarly, if you're already in the close, but current one is shorter,
then remove the one from the, from the close and then add these children into the open again.
Okay. And then the key thing is in the end, we need to resort, sorting the open list
and then make the left most one the best one. Okay. And then go back to check. So that is
best first. Okay. Best first. Any question?
So why is a heuristic value? Now, after suppose we have a heuristic value, how to search. Okay.
Yeah. Come to this again. So check that the best first work. Okay. Heuricolumines doesn't work.
That means the best only it would not work. Best first search. Is that work? Okay. Based on the
algorithm. Yeah. We have the children here and then we sort them. So suppose B was the first
and then the expanded. So this, now we have this, this, and this, this in the open list.
Right. In the open list, then we sorted and then this one is the best. Right. So we should
expanding here. So we are having this, this edit. So we will have one, two, three, four, five in the
open. Okay. And then this is the best. So this one expanding. Right. So we will have this, this,
here, here, here, here. And then we sorted this one will be checked. No children. Then next one.
Right. We find it. Yeah. So use the best first. We can find it. Okay. Yeah. I think that's about it.
Then this is how they updated. Then, yeah, we try to find the,
and those in the close and those in the open, you know, we can still find the answer.
So we try to use a hill climbing. We can try to use depth first or breadth BFS.
Can we find it? Those are exhaustive search. Right. For this case, can we find use that DFS?
BFS. Can not. Looks like can not. Level by level. Right. I mean, if it's a BFS level by level,
if it's a BFS, then branch by branch, we can still find it. Yeah. It's just a efficiency. Right.
Okay. Okay. That's all.
I think, yeah. So we managed to cover all those algorithms from the topic tree. Those are the
topic we covered. Heuristic value concept. Okay. So, and then the search. So this is the best only,
this is the best first. This one best only. This is really just for very much introduction to
say search algorithm. Still very important. Even you have each value. Okay. And then,
so this is a topic we covered in part A in topic three. And topic B will be more about gaming.
So I would introduce the other algorithms, especially for gaming. Okay. Minimax and also the
alphabet pruning. Okay. Next week. Next week, we also go through the backtracking exercise
in detail. So please go back and try and step by step. And then we check the answer. And then
we will talk about the new things. Okay. If you want to do it here for the backtracking,
yes, I will be around if you want to check. Okay. Otherwise, I think we can stop here.
Okay. Anything else? Any quick question? Oh, yes. One thing I forgot to say. Proven already
updates the file. So already upload the file. So you can actually
fill in if you already have a team for the project. Yeah. And another thing is I think
that we can arrange probably two TA sessions just for you for question or answer session for
some related to the project. Okay. In the week 11 and 12. But I will, I haven't got the confirmation
about the venue yet, although I booked it in the tutorial room. Here it's not available. Okay. So
I will inform you again. You can form a team of three. Okay. Form a team of three. Yeah. Thank you.
I still thought you tried to make it so it's not old. Oh, we choose the old and the old is not the
goal. So we will take another one from the open. Oh, okay. So weird motion that always not so.
Oh, because the algorithm, where's the algorithm?
Now here. Yeah. So here actually we check to check whether this is a goal. You see. Oh,
so it's not goal. And then the next one will be checked, right? Because we still have things in the
open. Okay. So if it's not the OTC, so it's yeah, yeah. Thank you. Yeah. I have a question.
As you see first, A is also the children of the C. Yes. So in the deep, deep, deep, deep
process, why can't I? You don't add in anymore because A was there before.
You see the DFS and DFS, they say it was already the children, but already appeared before. You
don't put in anymore. Okay. Why the third step? The open is DFH. The order is the DFH, not the HDF.
Oh, because alphabetical, alphabetical, yeah. Alphabetical order. So ABCD, yeah.
DFH. Oh, because I think HDF is right. Yes, exactly.
But I don't know how to say it. Yeah, yeah. Actually, it's just you get the
DFS.
Thank you.