Okay, I think now we can start.
So first of all, I mean, thanks for coming and good afternoon to everyone.
I believe I'm the second instructor you have seen here, right?
So before Prof. Chen Yipui was taking care of the first part, I believe all of you finished
that part.
So original plan is that I'm going to be your third instructor, you know, I should teach
you part three, and you should see Prof. Tang Yangping actually this week, who is your
second instructor, but because he's actually very busy, he's our, you know, vice president,
so he's traveling.
So I'm going to give my first lecture in week six first, okay?
And it's totally fine, because I'm going to talk about unsupervised learning.
So you don't have to learn the network, okay?
So it's going to be like quite standalone, and also the good part for me to talk first
is that I wish to brief you about the mini projects, okay?
So I'm going to talk about that very soon, but I want to make sure all of you know that
you need to do a project, okay?
Anyone doesn't know about this, like, so for this class, the mini project was 20%, okay,
which is a decent amount of marks, okay, so you must be well prepared for it, okay?
So later, I'm going to talk about that.
So okay, so first let me introduce myself, my name is Bi Han, so you can, so my research
field is about, you know, machine learning, image processing, computer vision.
So I'm going to cover four lectures, right, mainly on, you know, unsupervised learning,
and a little bit about statistical learning theory, like how can you analyze whether your
network is working well, or something is wrong, how can you fix the problems when you train
the networks, and also I'm going to talk a little bit about, you know, some of the specific
methods relevant to, you know, unsupervised learning, okay?
So that will be basically what I'm going to cover.
So this is a plan, right, as you can see there's an interruption.
So I'm going to do this in this week, week six, about the unsupervised learning.
So mainly we're going to talk about clustering, and also regression, okay?
And after that, starting from next week, you want to see me, you know, next week, so Prof.
Tan-Yap is going to take over, and give you four other lectures, all right?
So I'm going to come back again in week 11, okay, we're going to talk about the method
for regularization and optimization for deep models.
And this is after Prof. Tan already introduced you a bunch of networks, like convolutional
neural networks, recurrent neural networks, so you have some idea how can you design or
how can you use some network, right?
So I'm going to tell you what could be wrong if you train a model, right, and how can you
fix it, okay?
So I think that's like a nice order.
And last but not least, we're going to look at the Bayesian reasoning, which is another
different approach, which you can classify, right, so it's not deterministic, something
like stochastic, all right, and also how can we do dimensionality reduction to avoid
overfitting, to deal with high-dimensional data, right?
So and last but not least, right, so week 13, that's pretty much the last week, right,
last lecture we're going to do.
So I decided to make this week not exact, okay, so in other words, I'm going to talk
about how can we do low dimensionality modeling of the model, but it's just for your interest,
all right?
So I won't give you any questions on that part.
Instead, I'm going to reserve the time for a summary, okay, I'm going to give you a summary
about my part so that you can better prepare for your final exam, and also I can take any
question regarding the mini project, okay?
So this is like the plan for my part.
Okay, another thing I want to say is that I'm not sure about other instructor, but for
my lecture, you can ask me question anytime, okay?
Feel free to interrupt me if you have any question, anything unclear, anything like
maybe I run too fast, I run too slow, you can raise your hand and let me know, okay?
I'm actually welcome that because, you know, sometimes you have questions better to ask
right now rather than waiting until the end, because if you wait, you may forget your question,
okay?
So do ask me question anytime if you want.
That's perfectly fine, and actually that's encouraged, okay?
All right, so before I move on to the actual content, like the unsupervised learning, right,
all of you should already know that we need to do a mini project.
So I do receive some questions because I think for this group of students, you are master
students, right?
How many of you are PhD?
I don't know.
Do we have any PhD students here?
All of you are master students, right?
So probably this is new to you because we do have some subjects in NTU which involve
project, right?
But if this is new to you, you better listen to what I'm going to tell you because you
need to know what you are, what we're expecting from the project, okay?
So the mini project should be made available to you already.
If you go to the folder under my name, there's a, like a folder says, you know, mini project.
So basically the due date is the last Friday of week 13, okay?
So basically it can work all the way until the last week, but I set the deadline to be
the Friday of that week, which is November 15th, okay?
So start, this is actually week six, right?
You have, how many, you have like more than several weeks.
There's also recess week, so you have eight weeks to do it, right, which should be enough.
But most importantly is that this is a group project.
So you are not supposed to do this independent, it's sort of individually, but you can group
with two other members, okay?
That's why earlier I set an announcement.
I don't know how many of you, all of you should receive the announcement, right?
So maybe I can go to that announcement I made earlier.
You go to the announcement, right?
So there was announcement before I made here, right?
So I'm saying that, well, the very first thing I need you to do before even starting a project
is about finding a group, right?
So you need to kind of team up and form a group of three to do the project.
So I offer two options.
You can either propose your group, for example, you want to work with your friends, you want
to work with some of your other members you know very well, you can then, you can actually
click this link and go to this form, right?
Okay, I should, I have to sign in.
Okay, anyway, you can sign in using your account because if I sign in, I'm going to see the
statistics I want to show you, but if you have a team in mind, you want to propose your
team, please use this form to tell me who are the members, okay?
You need to give me the name of the three member in your groups, not only the name but
also the email.
Okay, the reason is that we do have some students with the same name, okay, unfortunately or
fortunately.
So I need to know who is the person in your group.
So give me the name of your three members, the emails, and also the metric number because
these are weak, okay?
So we do, I think I have received like a 30 group, 30 something group already, if you
haven't done so, please do it at least before recess, okay?
I mean you have a week for recess to kind of work out the group, right?
But let's say that if you don't find a group, right, oh, by the way, so the other important
thing is only one of your team members do this on behalf of the whole group.
So in other words, don't submit duplicate forms, all right, so for example, if I or
two of you are working in the group, right, so one of us submit once, that's enough, okay?
So don't everybody, don't just submit like from everybody, okay, because I want to avoid
duplicates, okay?
And okay, use your true name, okay, we do have some student give me some nickname or
your English name, I have no idea who you are, okay?
Give me the name that shows up on your metric card, okay, then I can trace back who is the
guy because I need to give you the marks, okay, correspondingly, if you give me the
funny name, you end up with zero marks, okay, you take the risk, all right?
So but have to say that if you cannot find a group, which is perfectly fine, so I know
nobody, I don't know who I want to work with, and then you can use this form, okay?
So use this form to give me that, okay, who am I, and I want, I don't have a team, I want
your help to give me a team, so what I'm going to do is I will wait until the end of recess
week, which is two weeks from now, end of the recess week, I'm going to look at this
form, so for those of you, for those of you give me the name in this form, I'm going to
randomly assign you together as a group of three, okay?
So basically you can think about it, right, you want to do random teaming up with others
or you want to work with somebody you know, all right, you need to make a decision, so
no, either way, we're going to end up with a grouping after the recess, and then you
can start to do, I mean, then you should already get ready to start your mini project, all
right?
So basically I wish this can be done basically a couple days after recess week, okay, but
any question regarding this teaming, no, grouping up?
Anyone has any question, like maybe you don't understand what you're supposed to do?
So basically everybody must do, sorry, not everybody, like as a team, right, every team
must do either way, right, you either give me a team of members or you tell me if you
don't have a group, all right?
So if I see no response, I'm going to email you or maybe I just assume that you don't
have a team, okay?
Clear?
Any question?
Okay, great, so this is the grouping, right?
Yes?
Yes, yes, okay, very good question, thank you, so okay, very good point, I almost forgot
that.
So in the form I ask you to specify which option, so I'm going to tell you that we have
two options for you to do mini project, you do either one, and in the form I ask you to
indicate which option you want to proceed, right, but you can change it, you know, I'm
totally fine, you want to change it, all right?
So that's just like for me to kind of see what's the preference, like some survey, but
you can change that, no problem, you know.
So, yes?
Do we have a peer assessment?
Sorry?
Peer assessment.
You have, sorry, peer?
Oh, peer assessment, oh, peer assessment, okay, good point.
You need, yes, I'm going to get there very soon.
So in fact, in the project introduction, I say that in the end of the, sorry, in the
end when you submit the report, means like the, you know, the form report, you better
tell me who is contributing to what, okay, because I'm expecting you to, let's say, you
know, maybe one can focus on algorithm, the other one can maybe focus on survey or something,
it's perfectly fine, you can tell me who is contributing to what, or if you say both of
you are not happy about the third member, you can also tell me, basically, yeah.
So in some sense, yes, it's kind of like peer assessment, yes, very good point.
All right, any other questions?
I mean, that's great.
You know, you asked me, I share this to everybody, so all of us are synchronized, right?
Great, thank you.
Any other questions?
Okay, so if no more questions, I'm going to go back to my introduction, right?
So like I mentioned, okay, another principle, right, I forgot to mention, you can ask me
a question anytime, okay, I don't mind that, I actually encourage that, but if while I'm
talking, if you are talking, it's going to be very hard to organize, all right, because
we have a huge class here, so I really appreciate if you can like kind of keep quiet, and let's
just discuss, you know, if you ask me, that's fine, or you want to discuss with your friends,
let's do that in the break, okay?
Otherwise, it becomes like very noisy here, okay?
Appreciate that.
So we're going to work on a group of three, and for every group, you just need to prepare
one report, okay?
So later, when we create a submission portal, it's the same that you don't have to submit
a report by everybody, you just need to, one, representing the whole group to submit one
report, and of course, with the peer assessments, right?
So you clearly specify the team members in the group, okay, give me, so who are the members,
give me the name, give me the email address, or maybe even the metric number, and state
the respective contribution of each member to the project.
All right, so this is actually what I'm expecting in the end, right, as the report, okay?
Okay, now, as I mentioned, right, we have two options for you, two project options for
you, you can do either one, all right, so the, I mean, apparently the difference is
what kind of data we're dealing with, right?
So the first option, the name is like a sentiment analysis, right?
Basically, we're talking about like some kind of product review, right?
You think about you are selling something in, let's say, Taobao, or I don't know, in
Amazon, right?
You get some review from the customers, and you need to have a model to determine whether
this guy is happy, or unhappy, or he's angry, or he's positive and active.
So basically, this is definitely a natural language processing problem, but we make it
simple, right, just a binary classification, zero or one, happy or unhappy, negative or
positive, right?
So you need to come up with this binary classification method to process those, you know, kind of
text review comments and give me your prediction.
So you will have two data sets, this is same for both options, right?
You will have a training data set, which involves not only the product review, but also the
sentiment.
In other words, you also have the labels, zero or one, okay?
Can you see my, oops, wait a second, maybe I use a pointer, right, laser pointer is better.
Okay, so you will have the label, you can use them for training, you have the data,
so this is the training data set we're talking about.
So you have those, you can do whatever you like, you can separate them into validation,
training, or you're going to use all of them, it's up to you, all right?
But what I'm caring about is the testing data, right?
So you will have a set, which is for you to predict, but this testing data, we do not
offer you the ground truth.
So it's just the text, there's no label, and you need to use your model to predict the
sentiment of those texts or those reviews.
So you can perform this binary classification to give me your predicted label.
Okay, zero or one, and I have the ground truth, I'm going to evaluate your result, okay?
So of course I wish you have a better result, but let's make it clear, right?
I'm not looking for something like a state of the art.
As long as you give me the reasonable result, I'm fine, okay?
Don't give me, say, hey, random guess or something.
You give me something kind of reasonable, I'm okay with that.
I'm not looking for, say, hell, you have to be the top of the leaderboard, no, okay?
What I don't care about is other aspects, which I'm going to share with you very soon,
all right?
But you need to perform your, run your model over the testing data and submit the prediction,
okay?
So this is kind of true for both options, okay?
But the first option focuses on text, natural language processing, NLP, all right?
We do have a second option, which is more about computer vision, all right?
So this is, we call it DAWP versus CATS.
So it's also a binary classification.
I'll give you a bunch of images.
Some of them are dog images, some of them are cats images.
So again, you will have a training data, you will have a testing data.
For training data, the dogs and cats are stored in two folders separately.
So you know which images are cats, which images are dogs, okay?
You can use this for training, and you do whatever you like for the training data,
and then you need to give me a prediction result of the testing data set, right?
So you will have a bunch of images without knowing whether their cats are dogs, okay?
So you need to run your classifier and give me the predicted labels, 0 or 1, okay?
Very similar.
So basically for both objects, I'm expecting a CSV file where you will have the ID of the testing data,
which is given, and then you need to give me the corresponding prediction, the label.
So you need to change here into either 0 or 1.
All right, so this is the file you need to submit, okay?
So fill out this prediction result here, so don't change the ID.
Just keep the ID, okay, because I need to run this.
So don't just swap the order.
So keep the order of the ID and input or generate the labels your model is predicting, okay?
So submit this as part of your report.
So you need a PDF report plus this kind of CSV file as your prediction, all right?
And, well, I mean, I'm perfectly fine if some students say, I tried many times,
but somehow I couldn't get any meaningful results.
Okay, maybe not for this group of students, but for undergraduates, that's pretty common.
You know, they just try many things, but they have bugs, they have errors everywhere,
so they really cannot give me any results.
If so, still please describe what you have done, okay?
Give me something, give me partial results or showing the efforts you made towards that goal,
and hopefully I can give you some marks, okay?
If you don't give me anything, I have to give you 0.
I mean, it's very simple, right?
So try to give me something, even if you don't have meaningful results,
but you can demonstrate that you have tried something, you tried to understand the problem,
you tried to come up with the solution, and if those make sense, I can still give you some marks, right?
It can be like screenshots or part of the codes.
Yeah, so basically that's my suggestion, right?
But up to you, I mean, you can decide, right?
But it's just one suggestion.
So, again, the deadline will be the last Friday, Friday of the week 13, so keep in mind that's the deadline.
If you got late, I mean, maybe one or two days, I can give you penalty, right?
You will be deducting marks.
If it's too late, you got 0.
All right, so it's very straightforward.
Okay, any question?
Any question?
Okay, so if no question, I wish to share with you, in case you haven't checked the project details, right,
I want to share with you and highlight a few things, I mean, in case you are not aware of that.
So if you go here, okay, let me show you slowly, right?
So go to the content of your, you know, cost side, find my name here, the other name, I mean, I don't know what they have there,
but under my name, there's a folder called mini project, all right?
If you click that, you will have option one, option two, and a briefing slide, which is the same as what I showed you just now, right?
But I suggest you to read this project description, okay?
So you have a bunch of files here.
Those here are those files which, like a script for you to, let's say, get the training data, get the testing data,
something for you to start with, right?
But there's a PDF, so this is something I wish you to pay attention to.
So let me just quickly go through this.
So this PDF explains the details of the project.
I tried to give some of the description of the dataset, description of the problems.
Okay, you just read them carefully before you start to do the project.
But the most important thing I wish you to pay attention is here, is here.
So from this line, the following things stated what you need to put in your report,
because in the end of the day, you need to submit a report representing the whole group, right?
So I tried to give you all of the questions that I'm looking for answers in your reports.
So basically, it's not just you write anything in the report,
but your report is supposed to answer all of the questions I list out here, okay?
So you can find there are many.
So for this group of students, because you are master students, you are at the graduate level,
you need to do a literature survey before even starting to, say, coming up with your solution, right?
Which is quite common practice, suppose if you want to do a PhD or you want to do research,
you always need to do surveying, right?
So basically, I wish you can basically study some of the tutorial, maybe books, or maybe survey paper
that talking about this field, for example, like computer vision, image classification, right?
You want to study, say, what is the problem definition for image classification, right?
And specifically, I wish you to clarify the problem definition
and give me some kind of idea about what challenges we have to solve the problem,
like open problems, challenges, and also what are the common solution type under different settings.
So I haven't said that. Later what we're going to see, right?
Even for classification, the problem can be supervised, can be unsupervised,
or the type of class can be open set or closed set, right?
Or we're testing data with or without domain shift.
So tell me something from the survey you have done, and you don't have to come up with something new,
but I believe all of this will be discussed if you just Google, say, tutorial or survey paper on image classification.
You should find those answers in the paper, but I wish you to study them and give me some of this understanding.
And also, try to figure out some of the relevant papers.
You can actually refer to those reference pages of the tutorial paper.
They will tell you, okay, maybe these are some of the papers which are most popular
or maybe most recent, representing this field and the progress of the field.
So give me some kind of a study on the conference paper, journal paper,
relevant to this field in the most recent years.
You can quickly read them and summarize the paper in the high level,
demonstrate that you understand the field, just like a very quick reading of the papers.
And then, after that, based on your understanding, please identify, let's say,
one or two top performing or state-of-the-art papers for that problem,
and give me a more detailed summary.
You need to write a summary of these selected papers.
You don't have to be many, just one or two.
So for those things, you can read quickly for a general survey,
and then I need you to do a detailed survey for one or two top performing papers.
So this is a pretty standard practice for graduate students to do research.
So write a few things before you start to work out a solution.
And last but not least, after you finish the survey,
now is the time for you to come up with your solution for this problem,
image classification or text classification.
So let's try to explain which approach or which method,
maybe from the one you surveyed,
and you believe they are the most suitable baseline to start with.
Give me some motivation or give me some reason.
And maybe you can choose that as your baseline, and you modify on top of the baseline.
And also demonstrate and explain what improvement you need to make to,
let's say you make on top of the existing baseline,
start to propose your solution for this problem.
Just like some mini paper you are writing,
I'm not looking for a lot of novelty,
but we should understand what should be done when you write a research paper.
So these are the survey papers.
So this is unique because we don't have this for undergraduate.
For you, that's something special.
And this works 20%.
So if you're doing this well, I can give you 20%.
And of course, the following questions are really for your solution.
So the question including data processing,
including model selection, evaluation of the model,
the parameter settings, your model architecture design,
and also your prediction.
So 50% will be given to your prediction results.
Not about 100%, but 50%.
So you need to make sure your results are reasonable.
And also, you need to demonstrate some analysis.
After you get the results, maybe from your validation data,
analyze what was wrong and what was okay.
So why give me some analysis about pro and cons of your methods?
And also, you want to discuss different choices of feature maps you're using
and also why they are something in favor,
how they are going to affect your project in terms of resource consumption,
memory consumption, computational efficiency, and also accuracy.
So these are some performance analysis.
All of these are discussion about the results you have got.
Okay.
And then we actually give H and I, which are a little bit more challenging.
So H is that suppose you are doing another project,
let's say a separate project,
that you also need to do this sentiment classification,
but it's on a different dataset.
So here is like a hotel, let's say hotel reviews.
But those reviews consist of only the reviews in the text,
but doesn't really come with the rating score.
So how can you actually make use of your solution right now
and generalize to another dataset which only has the text,
but doesn't really contain the labels?
All right.
So this is like an open problem.
So you can describe how your classification algorithm will perform in this new task
and what you need to do to perform well in a new dataset.
Okay.
So try to read them and every question for certain marks.
So make sure you have a reasonable response to every kind of sub-question.
And also there's another one.
It's like if we have some noise in the annotation,
which is possible in practice,
and discuss how the method will perform in this new project,
weighs the noise in your training set, right?
And name some approaches.
Let's say there are three approaches that you can improve your algorithm
to perform even better in the new algorithm, right?
So where do we learn some of them?
For example, how can we deal with noise?
How can we prevent overfitting?
How can we deal with domain shift?
So if you cannot answer them right now,
you are more than welcome to search, find a solution,
or you can pay attention to the thing we're going to talk about in week 11.
All right?
So I suggest you to rate the description first before moving on to the solution.
And my grading criteria will be exactly following this distribution.
All right?
So basically I'm going to look at whether you answer this question well.
If yes, I give you 10 marks.
If you do this very well, I give you 10 marks.
So you need to make sure every question is well answered.
And then you should get a pretty good result.
Okay?
So I'm going to use this example.
For example, we have the same thing for the other options.
I won't really go through it, but please read it.
And if you have any questions, you can get back to me.
I'm happy to clarify.
All right?
Does the report have any limit?
Sorry?
No, we don't have any limit.
But even though we might need to write it down, we're okay.
So the whole idea is to answer all of the questions.
Okay?
So you won't be penalized, but it doesn't really help, actually.
So as long as you believe those questions are well answered, that's good enough.
Okay?
Good question.
Any other questions?
Okay?
Last call.
Any questions?
Okay.
Now I'm going to continue my lecture today, right?
Let me think.
Did I miss anything?
Oh, by the way, one more thing.
I don't know whether the prof chair announced.
So we're going to set up some office hours.
Not now, but around week 11, week 12, which means we expect some questions from you when
we're approaching to the deadline of the mini project.
So we have some TAs who are going to set up some office hours.
We can go there and talk to them.
Those TAs are our PhD students, so they should know very well about this project.
So we can talk to them.
Any questions, like questions regarding the project, questions regarding the exam, you
can ask them.
Right?
We can ask them later, but they will be around the last few weeks.
Right.
Basically, when I come back to see you again.
Week 11.
All right?
Okay.
So.
Oh, okay.
Another thing.
So we are going to have a very long lecture.
I don't need to realize.
Three hours.
So even though I don't like it, but that's how it works here.
We're going to have a break in between, by the way.
I don't know how prof chair did it.
But I will say, let's take a break around 1.45.
All right?
Something in between.
So let's take a 15-minute break.
And we'll continue.
And I'll try to finish things a little bit earlier.
Right?
Because ideally, we should have two breaks.
Let's make it one, and I can finish a little bit earlier.
I'll try my best.
All right?
So I hope that's fine for everyone.
But I have to say that if you have anything you want to go, feel free.
It's an open class.
Anyway.
Okay.
So now, back to business.
Right?
Everything about unsupervised learning for this course.
Okay?
So two main problems we're going to see.
First one is clustering.
All right.
How many of you know what is clustering?
Let's show of hands.
How many of you already know what is clustering?
Okay.
We have a few.
Right?
By the way, do you have background more like from signal processing or computer science?
How many of you have computer science background?
I just want to know.
Because this year, we have a few.
Okay?
Great.
So this is all of your signal processing background.
Right?
So from this year, we have a mixture.
For the SPML program, we have a mixture of signal processing and machine learning.
This course actually is more machine learning.
But I think I make it should be okay for those signal processing background.
Right?
Because in fact, this is the first time we offer this course for undergraduate.
Sorry.
For graduate.
It's actually an undergraduate final year course.
But have a say that for those of you who, let's say coming from signal processing background,
if you have anything you find that, oh, I don't know what you're talking about.
Or you want me to elaborate more?
You want me to slow down?
You want me to change my pace?
Let me know.
Okay.
Because I really need your feedback.
This is my first time I teach master student for this subject.
So if anything feel like not okay with you, let me know.
I'm actually welcoming any feedback we have.
All right.
Okay.
So clustering.
So basically I'm going to explain what's the definition of clustering we're talking about here.
And for any clustering method, right, it's always important to have this distance metric.
Because distance metrics give you the idea of similarity.
Later we're going to see clustering is all about grouping data with the similar nature.
All right.
So how to measure the similarity.
We need to know the metric system.
Okay.
Distance metric.
And we're going to learn two specific algorithms.
K-means and HAC, right.
Hierarchical algorithm narrative clustering.
The reason is that each of them representing one type of clustering method.
All right.
K-means is the method for partition-based clustering.
HAC is the method representing hierarchical clustering.
All right.
So there are many, many other algorithms.
In fact, this is still a very active research field.
But let's keep it simple.
Just one method for one type.
Okay.
So in the end, I'm also going to share some of the examples.
Right.
Visual examples, numerical examples so that you know how you can, how you should apply those methods and what could be wrong.
So this is roughly the outline.
And for my part, for my lectures, I always offer some questions in the beginning such that I wish you to think about it.
Right.
So you should be able to find the answer by listening to this lecture.
If you don't know the answer, we're going to see them together.
Right.
In the end.
But keep this question in mind.
For example, what is clustering?
Right.
The definition of it.
And what is the cluster?
Right.
What's the definition of cluster?
And there's a difference between clustering and the classification.
What's the difference?
And also, you need to know the limitations.
Okay.
Or in other words, what could be wrong when you do K-means?
What could be wrong when you do HAC?
So the limitation of those methods must be very clear.
Because in practice, there's no perfect solution.
Right.
Every method will always have some drawbacks.
So as a software engineer or as a researcher, you need to know what is the problem.
What's wrong with those methods?
And then that's how you can make a decision when you do a project.
Right.
So this is also very important.
Okay.
So originally, this slide is for those who have already finished proof of task part.
But anyway, we have talked about classification.
Right.
Just now, I mean, those projects are classification problems.
So classification problem is very common in computer vision, where you can, let's say,
I give an image to the algorithm.
Say, hey, tell me whether this image is a cat or not.
Right.
Do we have a cat there?
And if this algorithm give me an answer, but this answer is like a disgrace, yes or no,
with or without cat, this is actually a very standard kind of classification problems.
Right.
So if you give them a dog image, the algorithm is supposed to tell you no.
There's no cat in the image.
So this is like a classification, which is very common in computer vision.
But the problem is that for classification, I mean, for this course, for this subject,
always need training data.
Okay.
In practice, this is not true.
I mean, we do have unsupervised classification.
But for this course, all of the classification, we need the training.
Training means a data set with example images of cat, example image was dog, and the labels.
Right.
You need to tell computer what do you mean by cat, what do you mean by dog.
So the training is necessary for classification.
And that's why we call classification a supervised problem.
Okay.
But I mean, here means you have to give them images labeled as cats.
Right.
Images plus label.
This is something as a must for classification.
Now, the question is, what happens if we do not have label at all?
Right.
It's very common in practice.
You have a lot of data, but there's no label.
Nobody annotated the data.
Right.
So what can we do about these kind of images?
For example, if this is the image I have, I wish to know which pixel actually belong
to the flower.
But I have no idea what are the flower.
I have no example.
I just want the computer to tell me out of the whole image, right, which pixel are forming
the flowers.
So this kind of problem is not a supervised problem because I don't really prepare any
data set with images plus label.
But can I do it?
Well, in fact, if you want to talk about the pixel that form one object, you are making
the assumption that those pixel must be similar because all of them belong to flower.
Right.
So you are exploring not just labels, but you are exploring the data intrinsic structure,
or in other words, similarity that belong to the same group.
Here, the group is a flower.
You are exploring and say, hey, tell me which pixel are similar to each other such that
it can form the flower.
So this is actually informally called clustering because I'm giving you some of the pixels.
If you treat every pixel as a data sample, I'm trying to figure out which are the pixels
themselves are similar to each other.
And this process doesn't involve any training.
So it's going to be an unsupervised learning process.
You're still learning, but you don't have any labels.
So it's not supervised.
It's a kind of learning without supervision.
Right here, supervision means labels.
Okay.
So here, unsupervised learning is defined as some kind of self-organized learning that
helps you to find some kind of patterns.
Okay.
The patterns are unknown.
Undefined.
Right.
Not defined in training, but they have it in the data set.
You can still figure that out without pre-existing labels.
This is actually called unsupervised learning.
So for our case, we are specifically interested in clustering.
So clustering is a type of unsupervised learning problem.
Okay.
It's a one sub-category of unsupervised learning.
And the task of clustering is to, let's say, I give you a collection of data.
I want to group or organize the data such that those data in the same group will be
more similar to each other.
So the first thing is data within the group, same group, must be similar to each other.
And also the data outside the same group, say in different groups, must be dissimilar
to each other.
Right.
So you want to make sure the same group of data will be more similar than other pairs.
The data without, not in the group.
So this is the whole idea about clustering.
Similarity versus dissimilarity.
Right.
So, and in this case, the group we're talking about here is called a cluster.
So the cluster is a set of data that you want to make them similar to each other.
Right.
So this is technically called a cluster.
Okay.
So basically this is the definition of clustering.
I hope everybody's now clear.
But of course, these are just definitions.
We also want to see some examples.
All right.
So let's take the same example, the flower image.
It's unsupervised learning.
So I won't give you any label or class information.
Nothing.
Just the image.
Right.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to perform clustering to group them according to the
similarity.
Of course, here we have many, many ways to define similarity.
Right.
Later we're going to see what is the distance metric.
But let's just think about the most simple measure, the intensity of the pixel.
All right.
So this is the black and white image.
So you can measure how white or how black the pixel is.
Right.
So I plot the histogram where the vertical axis is the intensity.
I mean, the higher the wider, the lower the blacker.
Right.
The horizontal axis is the intensity.
Sorry.
This is the intensity.
You know, zero means it's completely black.
255 is completely white.
All right.
So I'm going to see how many pixels are with specific value, specific intensity.
So the bar here measures the amount of pixels that have that specific intensity.
So this is called histogram.
Right.
I believe some of you may have heard of the term histogram.
So this is one way to show the statistics of a group of data.
Right.
So after you have this histogram, you can use that to measure the similarity.
So basically here the similarity is measured in the intensity domain.
So you have two pixels that have very similar intensity.
I group them together.
Right.
So black with black, white with white.
Something like that.
And then the other group, I form them differently.
So I can use this to group them separately according to their intensity.
All right.
So in this case, I can then separate them into two parts.
And here I believe that those pixels forming the flower should be, let's say, brighter than the background.
Right.
So I make this assumption.
I group them together.
I can extract the main body of the flower, all of our image, without any labels I have.
Right.
So this is a very simple and toy example of clustering.
But I hope I kind of give you some intuition what is happening here.
Right.
So this is one example.
But of course, in practice, without predefined labels, you have no idea what does this yellow, sorry, what does this red and green box mean.
You only know they are two clusters, but you have no idea which one is flower, which one is background.
But you know they will be different.
So that's all clustering can do.
Make them separate it.
Make them different.
All right.
So this is toy example.
But you will end up with two clusters.
And those samples in the cluster will be similar to each other.
And those samples in two different clusters will be different to each other.
Right.
This is what you can get by running clustering.
Okay.
Now let's summarize.
The main difference between classification and clustering is whether or not we have supervision.
So for this class, we can assume that all of the classification methods are always supervised.
But in practice, it's not true.
Okay.
For some of you who actually do research, you know that there are a lot of unsupervised classifications.
But for this class, let's assume that classification always needs to have labels in the training.
And you have to predict the label for the testing data.
Right.
Instead, clustering is the opposite.
You don't have any labels.
You only have data.
So it's unsupervised.
And you can still understand the intrinsic structure of your underlying data by grouping according to the similarity.
Right.
So this is the difference.
Okay.
Very straightforward.
Now, let's just summarize.
Right.
Clustering, we all know that it's unsupervised.
And the basic idea is to group them together with similar data points.
So to run the clustering methods, your input is just a group of data, right, without any label.
So this will be the input you need for running clustering.
And the output will be the cluster, or in other words, the membership of your data points.
So you know which sample belongs to cluster one.
You know which sample belongs to cluster two.
So the algorithm is going to give you some membership for every sample you provided as input.
So this is basically the overall structure of the clustering method.
Any clustering method, right.
So the algorithm is different, but the input-output is always the same.
Okay.
Questions?
So far, so good.
All right.
So before I introduce the exact algorithms, one thing we haven't really talked about is that we are saying the clustering always groups the data with a similar nature.
Right.
But how can we measure the similarity?
Just like the way we do the flower image, we are saying that we measure the similarity by comparing the intensity.
So that's our measure.
That's our metric.
But in general case, how can we define similarity for a clustering algorithm?
Okay.
So we have to make sure this is clear first.
Because usually we use something called distance to measure the similarity.
So distance actually quantify the dissimilarity, but the opposite of dissimilarity.
Right.
And there are many ways to define distance, but let's just make it simple.
Let's just come up with a convention of the notation first.
Right.
So throughout my part, I'm going to always use a vector.
So here, x1, x2, xn, which I use the bold letter, I represent, the bold letter represent a vector.
Okay.
So every x, x1, x2, every x represent a data sample.
So for clustering, you will be given a set of data, not only one, but a set of data.
So I will represent the n samples as n different vectors from x1 to xn.
Right.
So these are the data we're going to cluster.
All right.
So of course, every sample can be high dimensional.
Right.
It can be d dimensional.
So we're talking about not a single number, but a vector.
All right.
So my convention is that I use bold letter as the vector.
Right.
Normal letter is just a number scalar.
Okay.
So I hope everybody's comfortable with this notation.
Right.
Anyone doesn't know what I'm talking about.
I assume everybody knows what is a vector.
Right.
I don't have to repeat what is a vector.
Okay.
Cool.
So a vector is nothing but a column.
We usually use a column vector to denote, let's say, a d dimensional vector.
Right.
So let's say a distance metric is actually a function.
Okay.
Distance is a function which have to take two vector.
This d function take two vector, two points as the input.
Always.
You cannot measure distance only one point.
It must be two points.
Right.
And the output will be a real scalar.
The output is a single number that measure the distance.
So this is actually the distance function we're talking about.
All right.
So I use d to denote the distance metric for this part.
Okay.
Now, so what are the function of d that can be qualified for distance metric?
I mean, there are many function can actually map two vector into one value.
Right.
But not every function is qualified as a distance.
So to qualify as a distance metric, they must satisfy the following three properties.
Okay.
So what are the three properties we're talking about?
So first property is that if you have a distance, let's say xi and j, larger than zero.
Okay.
So the distance function must output something that is always non-negative.
So we don't have negative distance in this course.
So all the distance must be non-negative.
All right.
And the distance equal to zero only if the two points are the same.
So if you have two different points, you cannot have zero distance.
This is true for every distance metric.
All right.
That's something we call the non-negative property.
So you can imagine that you have two points in the space.
Right.
You measure distance.
How can you get a negative distance?
No way.
Right.
If they are the same, you got zero.
All right.
So this is number one.
So we call it the non-negative property.
All right.
So number two.
This is called triangular inequality.
Right.
Some of you may know it.
So we're talking about three points right now.
Right.
So you have point xl, point xi, and point xj.
So what the property says is that the distance between ij plus the distance between l and
j, summed together, must be larger or equal to the distance that is directly measured
between i and l.
Right.
So you have to have this kind of triangle kind of inequality to qualify as a distance
metric.
I hope this is also easy to understand.
But this is a condition to say that, OK, this distance metric can be used.
OK.
So this is second one, triangle inequality.
So, I mean, also easy to understand.
Right.
Because, you know, the only equal case is that lji is in the same line, then they will
be equal.
Right.
They will be equal to right-hand side.
OK.
So last but not least, the distance metric must be due-directional.
So in other words, symmetric.
Right.
So distance between x and, sorry, i and j must be equal to the distance between j and
i.
Right.
Which is also very easy to understand.
So these three properties is always a condition to qualify a distance metric.
OK.
Not arbitrary function that mapping from two vector to one scalar can be qualified.
Right.
They can be satisfied of the following three properties.
OK.
Make sense?
So far so good.
OK.
Simple math.
I hope this is OK.
I mean, not very, very.
I tried to minimize the math for this course, by the way, but still have some math.
I hope this is fine with you.
But, OK, I'll give you some example of the distance that we could use in this course,
which is also the most commonly used distance metric.
Right.
This one is called Euclidean distance.
It's actually the most commonly used distance, which is nothing but L2 long distance.
Right.
So numerically, it means I'm going to measure the difference.
I take the square root of the, what is that?
I take the square root of the distance squared.
Right.
Something like that.
X minus xi minus xj.
And then you take the square and then sum them up.
I take the square root.
Right.
So it's something like a straight line.
I have point x and y.
I want to measure the straight line distance between the two.
So this is called Euclidean distance.
Right.
So you can check.
It definitely satisfied the three conditions, the three properties we were talking about.
But this is not the only distance we can use.
Right.
This is the square root distance, which we can also use.
And they are also qualified.
The second one is called Manhattan distance.
The only difference is that they are not measuring the square.
They are taking the absolute value between the two.
And of course, you don't have to take the square root because here there's no square.
And usually we call this L1 norm.
If you want to visualize that, the distance actually is something like you take the horizontal
distance plus the vertical distance.
Right.
You don't take the straight line, but you project the straight line into the horizontal
and the vertical axis.
You sum them up.
Right.
So this is called Manhattan distance.
It still satisfied the three properties, by the way.
You can verify if you don't believe that.
But this is also sometimes quite useful.
Right.
Especially for those image processing, you know, imposed sparsity.
That's why people love it.
Okay.
Manhattan distance.
The last but not least, some people also use so-called infinity distance, or maybe people
call it the sub-distance.
Right.
So here, it's only care about the maximum distance in certain dimension.
All right.
So it's like I have distance decomposing to x and y, or horizontal axis, but I only care
about the dimension that give me the maximum distance.
Others, I forget about it.
Right.
So it's something like, you know, for example here.
So this is the two, this is the three.
My maximum distance will only measure the three.
The two, I just forget about it.
Right.
So this is where the infinity come from.
I take the max, all of all dimensions.
Okay.
So, sunrise.
Right.
You can actually use this example to compare the three.
Euclidean distance just measure the straight line between the two points.
This is Euclidean.
Manhattan is the horizontal, sorry, the vertical plus horizontal.
So it's going to be two plus four.
Right.
And if you take the straight line, it's going to be four squared plus two squared, take
the square root.
So, sub-distance will be the maximum out of two and four.
So that's kind of the one single example if you want to memorize to differentiate the
three.
Okay.
I hope it's straightforward for this kind of comparison.
If I haven't said that, right, for this class, if I don't give you any specification in your
question, let's use Euclidean distance by default.
All right.
So if I don't say anything, you can assume that the distance is Euclidean.
But if I tell you in the question, say, hey, please do K-means by using Manhattan distance.
They have to do Manhattan distance.
All right.
So if I don't say anything, let's use Euclidean by default.
Okay.
Because it's easy.
Right.
Okay.
So this is all about distance.
So now, after we understand the measure of similarity, we can now introduce the actual
algorithms to do clustering.
All right.
So we're going to look at two kinds of algorithms.
One is called partition algorithm.
One is called hierarchical algorithm.
All right.
So I use this kind of Simpson example to illustrate.
So partition is like you just want to exclusively group the sample into, say, two groups or
three groups.
Right.
This is called partition.
Hierarchical is that you have some nested groups from causal level to the final.
So it's a different way to separate the samples.
You do progressive way or you do like partition way.
So for each of the type, we only learn one method for that.
Okay.
So let's just illustrate the difference.
So partition-based method, the key idea is that we have to group the samples into, okay,
this is important, non-overlapping clusters.
In other words, if it's a partition-based method, such as k-means, your cluster cannot
have overlap.
So they should be mutually exclusive to each other.
All right.
And this is literally what the partition means.
Right.
And also, every data sample will be always assigned to exactly one cluster, no duplicate.
You cannot say like my point, this point belong to both cluster one and cluster two.
It must be either one or two.
So every sample will be exactly in one cluster.
So these are the important thing to qualify partition algorithm.
All right.
So you can imagine that in the space, you have so many points.
I just need to make them somehow grouped such that every sample belong to exactly one cluster.
Right.
So this is partition.
Okay.
Now hierarchical is different.
Hierarchical is that, okay, I will progressively group the points.
Maybe in the first trial, I say, well, two and three are similar.
I group them first, but I leave one and four.
But later I find that, well, I don't like three cluster.
I want to do two clusters.
I will further group four together with two and three.
Right.
So the grouping will be progressively kind of merging together, but not in one shot.
So in the end, you will have a set of nested cluster organized in your hierarchical tree.
Okay.
You don't have this for partition, but for hierarchical, this is what you will have as the clustering result, membership.
All right.
So this is the difference.
Now, like I mentioned, right, for every type of algorithm, we will introduce one method.
Okay.
You only need to know the representative method for each type.
So for partition-based method, we're going to learn k-means.
For hierarchical method, we're going to learn the HAC, right, Hierarchical Agglomerative Algorithm.
So, but for those two, you need to be very clear about the algorithms, how to run them,
what could be wrong, and especially for k-means, when to stop.
All right.
Because it's an iterative method.
Okay.
So let's start by first talking about k-means.
Right.
I believe some of you may already know k-means.
And how many of you have already know what is k-means?
Okay.
You have some.
We have some already.
Maybe at least heard of it, right?
Any of you?
Okay.
Any of you have never heard of k-means?
All of you heard of it, right?
It's a very common algorithm.
Like, people love it.
It's simple.
But you better know the details, right?
Because sometimes people can get it wrong for k-means.
And k-means is a very risky method.
You can easily get it wrong.
So we use the same convention, right?
Data samples themselves are represented as a list of vectors, x1, x2, all the way to
xn.
And the question will specify a distance metric.
So you will be given some d function.
But by default, it's going to be Euclidean distance.
Okay.
So the goal of the k-means will be trying to distribute or split the data sample into
k clusters.
Okay, by the way, the k here is the parameters of the k-means.
So in other words, you have to specify what is the k, right?
Number of clusters.
So you cannot learn this k.
The k is not part of the learning.
All right?
So if you do so, each cluster will have a bunch of samples.
And it will be represented using a d-dimensional vector, mu k, which is called the centroid.
So it's like every sample will be represented as a vector.
All right?
But the cluster also can be represented as a vector.
But the vector is called the centroid of the cluster.
The dimension is the same.
All right?
So xk are the samples, mu are the centroid of the cluster.
So you will have mu1, mu2, all the way to mu k, because you have k cluster.
Every cluster will have a centroid.
All right?
So then what is the objective, right?
So you have to partition the data in any way, in arbitrary way.
But not every partition is something we like.
For k-means, the objective of class array is to make sure the summation of the distance,
all the distance, between the sample xi to the corresponding centroid mu k,
sum them together, must be minimized.
In other words, I'm trying to give you a partition such that if I measure the distance
between the sample to the centroid, I sum them up together, it must be minimized.
If I minimize the summation of distance, I'm done with my k-means.
Right?
So this is what k-means try to achieve.
Okay?
So we'll get back to it.
So this is just some kind of rough description of the objective.
Right.
But, you know, have a say there.
So k-means will need a distance metric.
It's going to be Euclidean distance by default.
Every cluster will be represented as a mu k,
which is actually the average of all the samples belonging to that cluster.
Right?
So geometrically, it's going to be the center of the cluster.
Numerically, you just take the average of all the samples belonging to that cluster.
That's going to be your mu k.
All right?
So you can compute the mu k if you know the samples belonging to it.
Right?
And your idea, your job is to split the data points
such that each data point will belong to exactly one cluster.
Only one.
Cannot be two, but only one.
All right?
So here is the actual algorithm.
Right?
Actually, k-means is very simple.
As you can see, just a few lines can explain what k-means is.
But let's go through them very slowly.
So before even running the k-means, there are two things you have to determine.
First one is the parameter k.
All right?
So you have to pick the k or maybe a question tell you what is k.
So this k is something you have to assume or you have to know beforehand.
Right?
You cannot change.
You cannot learn.
That's something fixed.
So after you know the k as the parameter of the algorithm,
you have to do something we call initialization.
Okay?
So you need to give some initial centroid which will present the clusters.
But how to pick the centroid is completely random.
I mean, you can just randomly pick some points as the center.
When we say initialization, it doesn't matter how good or bad.
Because anyway, we're going to update it later.
But you need to have this starting point.
Otherwise, you cannot proceed with the k-means.
Okay?
So in practice, it's either given by you.
So for example, in the exam, I could give you the centroid which I suggested.
So you use that as the initialization.
Right.
Or if I don't say anything, you can randomly put some points as the initialization.
But you have to do it.
All right?
And after you download the initialization, the main body of k-means just has two steps.
Okay?
Very simple.
You have to keep running the two steps many, many times until the stopping criteria is actually triggered.
So this is actually looping.
Consider a while loop.
You are doing a looping through the two steps until you reach some condition that you can stop.
So this is called iterative algorithm.
You are doing multiple iterations until stopping.
Right.
And then what are the two steps we have here?
So the first step is called like a membership assignment.
So for the step one, you need to fix the centroid.
Fix the mu k.
You don't change it because you just initialize the mu k.
Keep it, but now assign every data point to its closest cluster center.
So in other words, for every sample, I need to measure the distance to mu 1, the distance to mu 2, the distance to mu 3,
and I compare which one gives me the minimum distance.
The minimum distance will become the membership for this sample.
So for example, if my x is the closest to my mu 2, my x will be assigned to the second cluster.
So this is actually the membership assignment.
I always belong depending on the distance metric.
So it's like finding the mu k such that the distance between my sample and the corresponding mu k is minimized.
Right.
So by the end of step one, every sample will have a unique assignment to one of the cluster.
And the exact one.
So you cannot have two.
Exact one assignment.
All right.
So this is the membership assignment.
Any questions?
Make sense?
Or you think it's too easy?
If I think it's too easy, I can run faster.
All right.
Okay.
So then after you finish step one, you should do step two.
Step two is also three, four.
Now you have all the membership.
You know what other points belong to cluster one, what other points belong to cluster two.
So now is the time to fix that membership, then update the mu.
Remember the mu are just randomly assigned, so it can be run.
So now I have to use my membership and recalculate what are the mus.
And how to do it?
You just take average.
You just find all the points belong to cluster one, take average, and update my new one.
You do the same thing for cluster two, cluster three, and until you update every mu for basically all the clusters.
Then you are done with step two.
So step two is called centroid update.
Update the centroid one more time using your membership.
And then you go back to step one.
Now your centroids are changed.
You have reassigned the sample according to the new distance.
Remember, your mu key are changed, so your distance will be also different.
Then maybe some of the points will be changing its membership.
Again, once the membership are updated, you go to the centroid update.
You recompute the new centroids.
You keep doing this one, two, and one, two, all the way until you find that no more points have been changed about their membership.
So if you do like, say, two consecutive steps, you find that, oh, if I do this one more time, I don't have any change in my membership.
Then that's the signal for stopping.
You can stop.
And just output the current membership as the final update.
So that's it. That's all about k-means, just a few lines.
Okay, any questions?
Actually, this is all about k-means.
Any questions?
No?
Okay, then I will ask you some questions.
I'll see whether you understand this correctly.
So here I say that the stopping criteria will be no more points.
Assignments change.
So if you see the assignment unchanged, you can stop.
But what happens if you see that my mu's are not changed?
Let's say I run the first situation.
I get my mu, mu 1, mu 2, mu 3.
I do another one, I find that, okay, my mu are unchanged.
Can I stop?
Or how many of you think I can stop?
I'll give you a few.
Others assume that we cannot stop.
Okay.
Actually, you can stop.
Basically, if mu are not changing, membership will not change.
So it's kind of dependent to each other.
So think about it.
If your mu are not changed, how can you possibly change your membership?
Because x are the constant.
It's given data.
If your mu's are unchanged, you cannot have different distance.
So your membership will also be the same.
So it's actually either way.
You either observe the membership or you observe the mu's.
Either one seems unchanged, you can stop.
Alright, so this is actually one thing you can easily think about.
So either way, it can give you a signal.
Alright, the second question is that
just now I'm saying that we can randomly set the mu's as the starting point.
So if I give you a different mu in the beginning,
let's say I try one time, I give you a set of mu's,
you run the K-means, you get some results.
But next time I give you another set of mu's,
different points, randomly again,
will I get my same results?
So let me repeat the question.
The question is like, I will do K-means two times.
The same data, I do two times K-means.
First time I give you one set of mu's as the starting point.
Okay, maybe like a point A, point B, point C,
as my mu one, mu two, mu three, right?
I run my K-means until I converge,
I get my final output, my membership.
Now I redo the K-means, but I give you three different points.
Another three points as the mu's.
Maybe, you know, E, F, G, right, as my points.
So they'll be different.
I rerun the K-means in the exact same way,
will I get the same results as my first run?
Or how many of you think are no?
Okay, you and the others.
Or how many of you think you will get the same results?
Okay, we have some.
All right, so the answer is you may not get the same results,
which is a big problem for K-means.
I'm going to tell you why later, right?
But bear in mind that this is something
to give you different results.
So don't be surprised.
If you change your initialization,
get different results,
doesn't mean you are doing that wrong,
you're doing that correctly.
But that's the problem for K-means,
because K-means will be very sensitive to initialization,
and there's no guarantee of convergence even.
Sometimes you may be in a pretty weird shape,
but these are something you have to bear in mind.
Those are limitations of K-means.
So we will get there, but you have to think deeper, right?
So not only about the algorithm,
but what could be wrong with the algorithm.
Okay, so let's see some examples first.
So most of the examples I showed in the class
would be like two-dimensional, right?
Because two-dimensional are easy to visualize.
Our human can only match up to three-dimensional.
Two-dimensional is a plane,
but all of these methods can be wrong
for much higher dimensional,
just like you cannot visualize it.
So for visualization, we picked the two-dimensional space.
I give you, let's say, eight points here,
and I tell you that the parameter K is equal to three, right?
Now we use Euclidean distance,
and also say that I initiate my mu's as a1, b1, and c1.
Now apply K-means to estimate the final three cluster.
So this can be something quite standard,
quite possible as an exam question, right?
So in the exam question, I just give you some other points.
I tell you, well, let's try K equal to two, right?
And I give you two different mu's.
Give me the results.
So this is one thing very possible to show up in the exam.
So you need to look at what is the right approach to solve it.
How can you apply K-means to solve these kind of questions?
All right, so tell me what the step one should do,
or you should do.
I mean, if you run K-means for this question,
what's the step one you should do?
Assign the samples.
Sorry?
How?
How to assign the samples?
Like the minimize distance.
Distance.
OK, very good.
So you do step one, which is assigning the membership
for every point we have here.
And the question already tells you the initialization,
so you don't have to worry about that.
So a1 will be mu1, b1 will be mu2, and c1 will be mu3.
You just need to run step one to basically assign them
to the corresponding cluster, right?
So basically, this is how you can visualize the eight points
in the 2D space, right?
So I'm actually plotting the first dimension,
so every point will be a sample point in the 2D space, right?
So in practice, like I mentioned,
to determine the membership, you need
to compute the distance between every sample to every centroid.
In other words, here I'm showing a table,
like a pairwise distance table.
So what you need is the column with highlight,
highlight with yellow light.
Because here, my a1, b1, c1 are the centroids, right?
They are the mu1, mu2, mu3.
I need to compute the distance between every sample we have
here to those centroids.
So you need to have this yellow column
before you can determine what are the membership.
Make sense?
So numerically, you need to work out those numbers.
And then, how to find the minimum?
So here is very simple.
For a1, I have my 0, of course, is the point itself.
So 0 will be the minimum out of the three.
So I can determine that a1 goes to cluster 1, right?
And then a2, I got distance with 5, with 4.4, 3.1.
So 3.16 is the minimum out of the three.
So a2 should go to the third cluster, right?
You are comparing the number here in the same row
and find out which is the minimum.
And that corresponding centroid is the membership.
All right, so let me repeat.
When you do the question like this,
you need to work out the distance
between every sample point to every centroid.
Here, this a1, b1, c1 are the three centroids.
Every row represents a sample point.
So you need to work out all the distance
and compare the numbers in every row.
And you figure out which is the smallest number
out of the three in every row.
And that cluster is the one the point belongs to.
So you can do this for every sample.
You have to do the decision for every row.
So a goes to first cluster, a2 goes to cluster 3,
a3 goes to cluster 2, b1 goes to cluster 2.
So something like that.
Every sample makes a decision on the membership.
So you can end up with something like this.
So you can see that this is my cluster 1,
this is my cluster 2, this is my cluster 3.
So here, the blue point, red point, green point
are the new centers.
So once I do the membership assignment,
the step two will be updating the centroid.
So original centroid was a1, b1, and c1.
So these are the initial centroid.
But now I finish my step one, I can proceed to step two.
Step two is nothing but recompute the centroid.
How to recompute the centroid?
I just take all the points in the cluster, find average.
The average will be the new center.
So you can see that the center actually
shifted from b1 to here.
And the center for three shifted from c1 to here.
So that means we have to keep doing it,
because it's not finished.
You do observe a change in the centroid.
So it's not stopped.
You have to redo the first step.
How to redo the step?
Now this is actually step two.
You just compute the centroid.
The new centroid will be c1, c2, and c3.
So the new c, these are the new centers.
Now when you finish step two, you
have to redo step one, which is going to determine the membership.
But right now, the centroids are changed.
So you have to work out the new table.
So in the new table, these three will
be changed to the new center.
You have to update the table again
and re-decide which is the belongingness for every sample.
You have to redo this until you reach the stopping criteria,
which is either there's no change on membership
or no change on the centroid, either one.
Then you can stop and output the current membership
as the final output.
All right?
Questions?
Make sense?
All right, so one thing I can promise
is that in the exam, I will make this number simpler.
So you won't get a big table, which takes a lot of time.
But I will make maybe points fewer or numbers simpler.
So you won't really have a lot of time
computing the number, which doesn't make sense.
But you need to know the principle.
How can you do this thing step by step?
And I need to check your procedure.
So not only the final result, you
have to show me the step by step procedure.
When do you do step one?
When do you do step two?
When do you stop?
Every step counts.
All right, so this is important for algorithm kind of question.
OK, so this is actually one example.
So I use another example to show that how the centroid can
gradually change until we reach the stopping criteria.
So here, all of the green points are my samples.
I don't know how they belong to, but just some samples.
And I initialize the tool center as the blue cross
and the red cross.
So I run my first iteration.
I will try to assign a membership.
So I use color coding to denote the membership.
So red goes to red, blue goes to blue.
So this is the status after I finish my first step one.
And of course, you know that we need to recompute the center.
So this is how I do my first step two.
So after you finish the membership,
you take the average to update the center.
Then the center clearly change from here to here.
The blue one goes from here to here.
So you can see that they can gradually
move the center to be something more meaningful
from the initial guess.
And now I'm not finished.
You have to do one more step one.
So you really do step one using the new centers.
And the membership will be changed.
Initially, it was separating this way,
and now I'm going to separate it this way.
So the point will be re-clustered.
And now my membership updated.
I can update my centroids.
But this time, you see that the change of the center
becomes much smaller.
You don't have a huge change from here to here.
It's because the algorithm is trying to converge.
So the algorithm will most likely
converge to eventually stop.
And the phenomenon is that every time
from iteration to iteration, the change
will be smaller and smaller.
So this is the evidence showing that now I'm actually
closing to the convergence.
But still, there's something changed.
I have to redo my central update.
So this is my update.
And then I redo my membership assignment.
So from E to F, only a few points changed.
Only here changed.
But still, as long as there's a change, you have to keep doing it.
You can only stop if there's absolutely no change.
So you do one more time to update the centroid
and do one more step.
And then you do another step.
So here, if you observe no change between two
consecutive iterations, you can stop.
So this will be your final output.
So the final output will include both the centroid and also
the membership.
So this is an illustrative way to show
how the algorithm can evolve from step by step
through the iterations.
And you understand why we stop only when there's no change.
Because everything becomes so stable.
Everything converges.
Questions?
Make sense?
OK.
So here I show you one example.
Then we can take a break.
All right?
So just now, what I'm showing you are just some points,
two-dimensional, binary class.
It doesn't mean the algorithm doesn't
look like a working practice.
But I want to show you that actually clustering
can work in practice.
So just use k-means.
So suppose, for example, I have a photo like this.
I have no idea what I have in my photo.
But I want to try to separate, let's say,
the castle from the background, or maybe from the sky,
from the forest.
But I have no idea what is castle, what is the forest.
I can actually run k-means and see whether I can figure them
out.
So if I run k-means, I can use the very similar idea
as I showed you before for flower.
I use the RGB intensity as my feature.
I will first plot the diagram.
Let's say I plot the gray scale diagram as the distribution,
as a histogram.
Now I can actually try to, let's say,
put this part as my cluster one, maybe this part
as my cluster two, this part as my cluster three.
I can form clustering results.
Let's say this is k equal to 2, this is k equal to 3.
So as you can see that, actually, roughly, they
can actually capture the foreground of the castle
and maybe the forest.
Because intensity-wise, they're very close to each other.
If you increase the k, they can further
separate the mountain area or the lake behind and also
the foreground forest.
So you can see that even without labels, intrinsically,
there are some differentiable features just in the intensity
space.
But this was just like gray scale.
Gray scale means I haven't even considered the color.
I just considered how bright the pixel is.
I can do something like this.
Let's further consider the RGB.
I just take RGB into it, and every point
I have three-dimensional space, three-dimensional vector.
I run k-means.
I can actually get pretty good results.
All the forest actually has been separated.
The castle foreground will be separated and then the background.
So this is one example showing you that actually k-means
can be applied to more practical examples
rather than just poor examples.
And if you don't have labels, that
could be something not too bad for you to give a try.
So this is actually something I want to show.
But of course, just for illustration, in the exam,
I will not give you this case because it's hard to confuse.
For exam, it's always a poor example.
But I wish to let you know that they can be used in practice.
All right.
Any questions?
If not, let's take a break.
And we'll come back around 2.05.
OK, thank you.
Let's take a break.
Thank you.
Can we do a little test of the code when we put it on our data?
We need to test the code to put it on our back.
Yeah, we'd better test it.
And the reason is that, let's say
if there's something you didn't experiment with in your computer,
we can't do rock, but you make sure the code can be rock.
We give a lot of BTs.
We give a lot of bugs, but if your code can be reproducible, then you have a better path.
What's the way you would recommend Python?
I mean, we would recommend Python, but it's up to you.
We don't specify the language.
But it's because we're coming from a very diverse background.
For our undergraduates, normally they do Python because they have a Python course.
So everybody knows how to do Python.
But if you find that Python is hard to read, and you are equipped for other, for example, C or Mac apps, find the key.
I'm OK with that.
OK, thank you.
Thank you.
Oh, you just take the average of all the points.
C1, B1, B3, B2, A3, C4.
Average. Sum them together and divide by 5.
Oh, yeah.
All right.
Yeah?
OK.
Thank you.
Good.
Bye.
Thank you.
Good.
Bye.
Thank you.
Revelation sequence.
Hello, everyone.
,
All right, I think since most of us are here, we can maybe start.
Is it okay to start now?
Okay, so we start earlier, then we can finish these earlier, right, so you can go for dinner,
I don't know whether somebody else.
Okay, anyway, let's start, and let's just resume at the place we ended just now, right?
So just now I showed you some examples showing that K-means can be used not for toy example,
but also practical case, image processing, image segmentation.
But heaven say that, actually every learning method, every method we're going to talk about
for this course is based on learning, right?
So if it's a learning method, the first question you ask yourself is always, what are the methods
trying to minimize or maximize, right?
So in principle, all the learning method can be somehow formulated as an optimization problem.
So I mean, I will not test you on this, but just for information, just always say that
K-means is trying to minimize the summation of the distance between every sample to the
centroid, right?
I was saying that in words, but I didn't really formulate it in math.
So if you want to be serious about the objective function, this is what the K-means is trying
to minimize, right?
So basically, we're talking about every sample, right?
So here, it's going to sum from i equal to 1 to n.
Every sample, we care about the distance to v corresponding mean, right, the centroid.
So we want to find out the correct centroid, the correct membership.
This is a centroid, this is a membership, such that the entire summation of the distance
between the sample to the associated centroid is together minimized, right?
So mathematically, we are solving the following minimization problem to figure out what is
the best mean and what is the best membership.
And because of that, we are alternatively updating the mu and r.
That was the two steps we're talking about in K-means, right?
So all of this iterative process is coming from the fact that we're minimizing this guy
alternatively over mu and over r, all right?
So it's like we fix mu, find what's the minimum of r, we fix r, find what's the minimum of
mu, right?
So this is actually the formal formulation we're trying to minimize.
For those of you who know optimization, this is what the function looks like, right?
But of course, I'm not going to test on this, just to give you some idea, right, rigorously
what are we talking about, all right?
So just when I say that, knowing the algorithm, of course, you need to know the algorithm.
But we also wish to understand what is good about the algorithm and what is bad about
the algorithm.
So in other words, the pros and cons of every algorithm we learn.
So for K-means, people love K-means, it's because it's simple, right, as you see, just
two lines, right?
Single, but effective, we showed that they work sometimes for real business.
And it's very easy to implement, right?
So this is the reason why you always try this and see whether it works, right?
But it doesn't mean that this K-means is already a perfect algorithm, because there are lots
of drawbacks actually for K-means, I'll just name a few, right?
First one is the K. You have to know the K beforehand, because K here is the hyperparameter.
You cannot expect to learn the number, right?
But what happens if I don't know the K?
Right, so if you remember just now this example, right?
If you do K equal to 3, that sounds like a more meaningful classification.
But if K equal to 2, sorry, K equal to 2, you may not get exactly what you want, right?
So different K will get different class results, but some of them could make more sense.
So this is the problem for K-means, because this K looks like a mask for you to pick before
even running the algorithm, right?
So the K actually is something you have to tune, have to really try, but that's not the
worst part.
Actually, the worst part is that K-means have the risk of being stocked as some so-called
poor local minimum, all right?
So just now I asked you a question, like if I change my initialization of the clusters,
well, I get different results.
So the answer is yes, K-means is actually very sensitive to the initialization, and
some really terrible initialization can give you some poor local minimum.
In other words, you are stuck in some place where you are going to stop, but doesn't give
you anything meaningful, all right?
So let's see some example of what I'm talking about, right?
So think about this example where the ground truth is like that, right?
So the ground truth is like a green goes to green, red goes to red, blue goes to blue,
all right?
So if you get something like this, that's perfect.
But in practice, OK, you are looking for the optimal clustering result like this, but
if you can only do so with the right initialization, all right?
So here's one example.
So this is one example, but if you somehow get the initialization wrong or bad or inappropriate,
you could end up with something like this, all right?
So it still satisfies the definition of points in the cluster will be similar, and the point
outside the cluster will be dissimilar, but the cluster is somehow very different from
your ground truth, all right?
And all of this depends on how you initialize your clusters, right?
So here's one example, and with good initialization, for example, my cluster one is here, my cluster
two is here, my cluster three is here, all right, the black cross.
That's my initialization.
And then I run my k-means gradually from my initial points, blah, blah, blah, all the
way, I can somehow reach something quite ideal, right?
Something quite close to the ground truth.
So this is the ideal case, but nobody knows what's the right initialization, right?
So if I somehow accidentally pick this kind of initialization, which doesn't look so bad,
right?
It's still OK.
I mean, you still make the points quite close to the centroid.
But if you have those three as the centroids, if you run k-means multiple times, you're
going to stop, but stop at here, right?
You'll get something quite ridiculous.
The originally, the one cluster will be divided into two, and they still give you something
convergence, right?
So this is something we call the poor local minimum, or bad local minimum, because it's
somewhere you're stuck there, but you don't really reach the final answer, right?
So this is one of the risks of using the k-means, and the risk is picking the bad initialization,
and nobody knows what is bad, right?
That's the problem for k-means.
OK?
Another problem is the distance metric.
Remember, for every clustering method, you need a distance metric, right?
We talk about Euclidean, we talk about Manhattan, right?
So what is the good distance metric?
Still very unclear, right?
So we say that we use Euclidean, but Euclidean may not work in many cases.
So if this is my example where I want to separate the red points from the blue points, apparently
the red points close to each other, but the blue points is surrounding at the further
points, right?
But if I have to use Euclidean distance, I cannot find a clear linear decision boundary
to make the points separated, because these points are not linear separable if you use
Euclidean distance.
In other words, you cannot find the line to separate them, right?
But clearly, they are different.
So to solve that, you need to find this different distance metric.
For example, you can convert x and y into the polar coordinates, where the two coordinates
becomes the angle and the radius, right?
I hope most of you know what is polar coordinates, right?
So you can represent the points using x and y, you can also represent the point using
the angle towards the horizontal and also the distance, the radius, right?
So if you convert the x, y into polar coordinates, the blue and the red can be separable, right?
So you can find a line to separate them.
And if you use the second distance metric, you can find a meaningful k-means result.
But you cannot do that if you stick to the Euclidean distance.
Okay?
So this is one example to show that initialization matters, distance matters, k-matters, everything
actually is so sensitive.
So you can easily get it wrong with k-means if you do not pick the right choice, all right?
So those are the limitations of k-means.
If you find that your data are quite kind of risky and you don't have a good idea of
initialization, you better forget about k-means because you can get things wrong, all right?
So bear this in mind and that's the principle when you do project.
You need to tell me, for example, I give you the cannabis stock, right?
You need to decide what is the classifier.
So I want to see how you make the decision, right?
Are you going to do neural networks, are you going to do maybe random forest, right?
So you have to tell me the reason.
So here is one of the ways to identify whether the limitation of the method matters for my
dataset, right?
So this is one example which tells you how you can do analysis.
Okay, make sense?
Questions?
Any questions?
All right, great.
So, but this is all about k-means.
So so far we have learned, for example, what is k-means.
You know exactly everything.
We have seen some examples, visual examples, numerical examples, you know how to apply
them for a given point, right?
But of course, you need to know what is k, what is the initialization, and we see some
practical cases.
We also see the planned parts, right?
But this is what you need to know for k-means.
All right, but that's the method for partition-based clustering.
We also need to talk about the hierarchical clustering, right?
So hierarchical clustering will be different because we're not going to partition a sample
in one shot.
We're going to progressively merge or separate the points.
And the one algorithm we learned for this type is called HAC, hierarchical agglomerative
algorithm.
So it's going to be very, quite different from k-means because there are two approaches.
So for HAC, the idea is that you do not really partition that, but you start it by treating
every point as an individual cluster first.
The starting point is that you treat every point, every sample itself, as an individual
cluster.
And progressively, at every step, you try to merge the pair of the column two clusters.
If you find that they are the closest to each other.
So it means that, okay, I can start with, let's say I have three points, A, B, C. I
treat A as cluster one, B as cluster two, C as cluster three.
And then I look at, okay, is AB the closest, or BC the closest, or AC are the closest?
If AB are the closest, I will group AB together.
So AB becomes the first cluster, C will be the second cluster.
You progressively merge them, but every time, you only merge one pair, which has the smallest
distance out of all the choices.
So this is how you do HAC progressively.
But of course, here the question again, how to merge the pair and how to define the minimum
distance.
So this is always a question, we ask the question for k-means as well.
So here, we have to introduce the distance between not the points, but the distance between
two clusters.
So the distance measured two points will be different from the distance measured in two
clusters.
And that's unique for HAC.
k-means, you don't have to measure this, but HAC, you need to know how to measure the distance
between two clusters.
So we're going to get there.
But let me show you the outline of the HAC algorithm.
It's also a very easy single algorithm, because everything can be explained in a few lines.
Basically, you need to initialize, but the initialization is always the same.
You treat every point as an individual cluster in the beginning.
So no randomness is always the same.
So unlike k-means, k-means, you have to do random initialization, but for HAC, it's fixed.
So now, you also need to do multiple iterations.
But here, the iteration is actually by progressively grouping the clusters.
So every iteration, you are going to merge two clusters with the minimum distance.
So here, suppose I'm starting at the point where every data is a single cluster.
I'm going to group, for example, AB together.
So in step one, I'm going to group the pair of AB.
And I move on to group, say, hey, here, the DE is the second closest.
So I'm going to group DE.
And now, I realize that C and DE are the closest.
I would just group C and DE together.
So I form two clusters.
And finally, I group everything together.
So this is the four steps we need to group everything.
So the stopping criteria will be either of the two.
So it's either that all the points are merged into one.
So this is actually the scenario where you don't have anything to merge.
You only have one cluster left.
So you can stop there.
Or if the question tells you that I want to group everything into a k cluster, if they
already specify that I need k cluster, you can stop at the step where only k's cluster
remains.
So it's either way.
But actually, it doesn't matter.
Later, we can see that you can always trace back from fewer clusters to more clusters.
That's one of the good points for HAC.
But this will be all about the algorithm in a nutshell.
So because we're doing this merging progressively, after you have done with your HAC, one can
come up with a tree structure to visualize the entire merging process.
So you can read this plot from the bottom to the top where every red point is a data
sample.
So you are merging this progressively.
So eventually, you are going to form a tree structure called dendrogram.
So this diagram explains how progressively those data points are merged from more cluster
to fewer clusters.
So it's going to be a tree-like diagram, records the sequence of merging.
So this diagram, you probably find that sometimes two merges happen at the same time.
In practice, this is possible for HAC.
But for this course, only for this course, let's make it very simple.
Single merge every time.
So this won't be happening.
So for example questions, let's stick to the merging that once at a time.
Because I don't want to make it complicated.
But you should know that in practice, it's possible to merge multiple in one time.
For example, if they are the same distance, you should merge them together.
In general, you will have a tree structure like this, which records the sequence of merging.
And a good point is that if you have this diagram, I can name any k.
I can say I have three clusters, I want four clusters.
You can simply do a cut at the level that I have only k cluster remains.
So you can always trace back to any arbitrary number of clusters as the results.
So here, if I want two clusters, I just need to cut at this place.
So I will know that, well, this six will be one cluster, this three will be one cluster.
So you can do arbitrary number of k between one and the total number of samples.
You will know the exact membership.
So this is actually one thing good for HAC.
So in this case, you will know that the three will be the cluster one, the final six will
be the cluster two.
So let's see that for HAC, there will be the following advantages that k-means doesn't
have.
The first one is that you do not have to predefine the number of clusters to k.
Because like I mentioned, you can arbitrarily just do a cut.
You can always merge into one and do another kind of re-selection of the cluster without
re-running the whole algorithm.
k-means, you have to re-run.
So this is the advantages in the first place.
Really any clustering result will be obtained if you have this dendrogram, so you can cut
it anywhere.
And the result will be deterministic.
So no randomness, unlike k-means, you get different results.
For HAC, the result is always the same.
Once you determine the distance metric, same distance metric, same data, you always get
the same result.
So that's something good for HAC.
So now, when we say distance metric, we haven't really defined what is the distance metric
not between points, but between two clusters.
This is something we have to specify for HAC, which is very important.
So for this class, we're going to learn four, there are many, but we're going to learn four
different kind of distance metrics between two clusters.
So what are the four?
The first one is called a single linkage, or we call it a mean distance.
So what is the mean distance?
Well, imagine you have multiple points in single clusters, right?
I want to measure the distance between these two clusters.
I can always use the minimum distance between any pair of two samples coming from each cluster
to represent the distance between the two clusters.
So in this case, I got four points in each cluster, the yellow distance will be my mean
distance.
Make sense?
So we can specify that H, let's take the mean distance to represent a cluster distance.
They were called single linkage.
Of course, we can do the opposite, we can say, well, I want to use the maximum, right?
So the maximum distance will be the maximum out of all choices of two points from each
cluster, right?
So this will be the max distance, or we could complete linkage, either way.
All right?
Make sense?
Easy to understand, right?
And then you can do something else.
I can say, well, I want to take the average, so I try all the possible distance, okay?
You just pair up every possible pairs, right?
And I take average, which is called the average linkage.
So average is taken by all of the pairs coming from each of the cluster, which is also possible,
and this will be the average linkage.
Or you can see that, okay, I just find, I just compute a centroid for each cluster first,
and I directly measure the distance between the two centroids.
This will be the centroid distance, okay?
So we just need to learn the four, max, minimum, average, or center, right?
One of the four, well, could be appears in the exam, right?
So basically, all of the four are qualified distance metric, but which one to use, it
depends on the questions.
I will specify the distance metric, if I give you a question, like, accuracy, all right?
Okay, but let's see how we can use that, right?
So just now, I showed the algorithms, I defined the distance metric, but let's see some example,
right?
So let's start with the visual example first.
Here, if you do two-dimensional space, you can always plot them in the 2D space.
Suppose I have these five points, represented as the ABCDE, right?
So if this is my five points, I should always start it by treating every point as an individual
cluster, right?
So that's the starting point of HHC.
And now, all of all the five points, right, I should pick the pair which gave me the minimum
distance, all right?
So that's how you do merging every time, right?
So here, the minimum distance will be the AC, so AC will be the first merge I make in
my first iteration.
So A and C will be merged first, because they are the closest to each other.
And after that, I have the D, right, D is the second closest pair I have here, right?
So D will be the second merge, and then AC and B will be my third merge.
You see, it's like progressive merging, and every time you only merge a pair, right?
So you know, AC and B will be the next one.
So then, eventually, everything will become a single cluster, right?
So these will be so-called nested clusters as the progressive merging generated by HHC,
right?
So until, you can finish until only one cluster is left, or if the question specify one K
cluster, you can stop when you reach the K cluster remaining, all right?
So this is like a visual example, which we plot in 2D to show how HHC works for five
points, right?
So in the end, after you're done with HHC, you can either show this kind of a membership
diagram or a dendrogram, right?
So dendrogram will be equivalent to represent how you progressively merge the pairs of clusters,
right?
You can see the correspondence here, like the blue here is blue, red is red, yellow,
sorry, green is green.
So you can tell from the dendrogram that blue is the first merge, you know, green is
the second, red is the third, and the dashed black is the last merge, right?
So dendrogram will contain every information about this progressive merging, and once you
show it, you can do arbitrary K, right?
If you want to know the cluster result for any K, you can do a cut.
Make sense?
So far, so good?
Any questions?
Okay, great.
Now, that was the visual, right?
Let's think about if I don't, if you don't draw the diagram, but just getting some numbers
numerically, how can you do HHC, right?
So here's one example, I make it simple, just four points, but every point will have two
dimensional, right?
Every point will have feature one, X, and feature two, Y.
So our job is to do HHC for the following four points.
So what's the step one?
The step one will be figure out the first merge, right?
Because initialization is best straightforward.
Every sample is an individual cluster.
So no discussion on initialization, but step one will be determine the first merge.
So how can I determine my first merge?
Closest, yes, but how can I determine which pair is the closest pair?
Distance, yes.
So what are the distance I need to compute and make a comparison?
So all of you are right, I'm just trying to push the limit.
So now we know that we need to find the closest, we need the distance, but how many distance
we need to find?
You need every pair, basically, you need every pair of the points, right?
So which basically will give you a, oh, sorry, before that, okay, before that, remember
that we need to determine the distance metric, sorry, I forgot this.
So before you run everything, anything you need to first figure out what's the distance
metric, all right?
So I almost forgot this.
So we see that we have learned four, right?
We only learned four, which is the mean, the max, the central distance, and the average
distance, right?
So for this example, let's just pick the central distance, right?
Different distance will give you different kind of table, for sure, right?
So if it's a central distance, what you need is a distance table like this.
If it's four points, you are going to have a four by four matrix, okay?
But actually, many things are just repeating, right?
So one thing can tell is that the diagonal doesn't matter, because diagonal is always
zero, right?
From one to one, two to two, it doesn't matter.
So I don't care about the diagonal.
The other thing you figure out is that this matrix is actually symmetric, right?
So 0.14 equal to 0.14, here equal to here, because distance between two and three is
always equal to three and two, right?
So actually, the entire matrix will be symmetric, and to this end, you only need half of that,
right?
So in this case, you only need, how many, six numbers, right?
Except for the diagonal, it's called the half.
Those numbers are the distance you need, and you need to find out the minimum, make sense?
Okay, but for central distance, you can treat every point at the center, because there's
a single point in the cluster, right?
So you need to have this table.
So now, all of the six distance, you need to find out which one is the smallest, all
of the six, right?
And here, 0.14 is the minimum, right?
And if this is a minimum, that means my first merge will be one and two.
Just find the position, right?
This position is actually at the second row, first column, that means one and two must
be merged first, all right?
So my first merge will be one and two, okay?
Because it's the smallest, right?
All choices.
Okay.
Now, if it's a central distance, one thing you have to do is recompute the new center,
right?
Because when you merge things, the center will change, all right?
So you have to recompute the center.
So in this case, how to compute the center of one and two, just take average, right?
So you take average, you will get a new center, and then this will be your new center, right?
And then you can update this table, all right?
But you update the table, you probably don't need to update everything.
For example, the 0.5 will be the same, right?
Because it's still between three and four, so you need to update these two numbers.
Any distance involve the new centroid, we have to update, recompute them.
So using this distance, right?
So this will be the new table you got, and your table will be smaller because you have
fewer clusters.
So now in the second merge, you need to compare the three numbers here and figure out which
one is the smallest, all right?
So here, 0.5 is the smallest.
So you know that the second merge will be between three and four, right?
So between three and four will be the second merge, and you need to compute the new center,
which is actually here.
And now the final one is just the single merge, right?
And you just merge the remaining.
So you get the final centroid, then drop down.
You have this kind of dendrogram, right?
So this is how you can do the HAC if it is a centroid distance, all right?
Make sense?
So basically, it's like compute the distance matrix, forget about half, forget about the
diagonal line, look at the upper or lower triangle, find the minima, determine the merge,
and then update the centroid after you do the merge.
Update the table, redo everything, right?
Find the minima, determine the second merge, and do that again, right?
So this is actually the standard way of doing HAC, but the order matters.
Which one merge first?
Which one merge second?
This one matters.
You have to make sure this is correct, OK?
Now, this is actually an example for centroid distance, right?
Let's try another possibility, which is the average distance.
So if it's average distance, it's actually a little bit simpler, I would say.
So starting point is the same.
You're just treating everything as an individual cluster.
The very first step will be no change.
You still merge 0.14, all right?
So you merge that, you will get the new table.
But here the thing is that if you do the merge of 1 and 2, now we are using the average distance.
You don't have to compute the centroid, because the centroid doesn't matter, right?
What I care about is the average distance.
So what will be the new average distance between the new cluster and other points?
So for example, I want to compute the distance between the new cluster, 1 and 2, with 3, right?
So the average distance is actually the average between 1 and 3, and the average between 2 and 3.
In fact, you can directly take the average, 1, 3 is here, and 2, 3 is here.
So you can take the average of these two numbers and update the table directly.
Make sense?
Because it's no longer centroid distance, it's average distance.
So mathematically, the average distance between the new center to adding point will be the average between 1, 3 and 2, 3, right?
That's the definition.
And you can get this number from your old table.
You just need to do update without recomputing the centroid, because there's no centroid.
You don't have to use centroid, right?
So be careful about the distance metric specified by the question.
It determines the way you update the table, right?
OK, any questions here?
Make sense?
OK, average distance is defined by all the pairs, right?
If you have one cluster which is 1, 2, the other cluster is 3, you only have two pairs, right?
1, 3 and 2, 3.
So you just need to take average over 2.
You kind of figure out the new average distance, right?
So that's how you update the table, but once the table is updated, you'll find again.
Same thing for the other, right?
So if it's like 1, 2 with 4, you will be the average of 1, 4, and 2, 4, right?
Very similar.
But that's how you update the table to this one, OK?
Now, out of three numbers, again, you have to determine which is the second merge, right?
But of course, this is still here.
So the second merge is like 3 and 4.
You just need to merge 3 and 4, and then the last merge will be everything together, right?
But if you want to work out this number, you can actually do 1, 2, and 3, 4 as the average
of 1, 2, and 3, and then 1, 2, and 4.
But actually, you don't need this because the final merge will always be unique, right?
Just merge everything together, all right?
But the update of the table, you must be careful, right?
You stick to the definition of average link, and then update the table correspondingly,
right?
So this is what you need, and that's how you can figure out the final merge.
OK?
I hope these two examples help, right?
Of course, you can try the min and max.
Actually min and max are even simpler, right?
If you tried it, you will find that, you know, you don't have to take average, you take the
min, all right?
But no matter what distance metric specified by the question, I wish you can do the same
thing to complete the dendrogram and make sure the merging are in order.
OK?
All right, try it.
If you have anything unclear, you can get back to me.
I'm happy to explain this again.
All right, but this is all you need to know for HVAC.
And again, the very last thing for HVAC is understanding the pro and cons, right?
So if you compare k-means and HVAC, both of them can do clustering, OK?
Both of them are unsupervised, but if you compare the two, k-means will be simpler and
cheaper, right?
Because HVAC, we have to store all the, you know, intermediate clustering result, we have
to construct the whole dendrogram.
So comparing in terms of the efficiency, k-means is simpler.
But k-means has a lot of problems, like, you know, results, sensitive to initialization,
number of cluster must be predefined, all of them are pretty risky, right?
HVAC is the opposite.
It will be deterministic, no randomness if the distance is determined, and you don't
really care about the k.
You can actually determine the k later, right?
So it's the exact opposite of k-means.
But, of course, it's going to be more expensive, right, because there's no free lunch.
If you want to enjoy something, you have to pay the price.
The price is that it's going to be more expensive in terms of memory, in terms of computation,
compared to k-means, right?
So it's going to trade-off between how much you want to pay and how much you want to enjoy,
right?
So you have to understand the trade-off between the two methods, OK?
So this is actually the comparison, and also the pro and cons for HVAC, right?
So but that's all.
For clustering, you only need to know the two, right?
k-means, HVAC, and you need to make sure you understand what is the definition, right?
And what is the distance metric?
How do you apply k-means and HVAC?
What's the goal?
And what are you expecting at the end, right?
So these are the takeaway for unsupervised learning, all right?
So remember we have some questions in the beginning, right?
Now we should be able to answer, right?
So cluster.
What is cluster?
What is clustering?
So the difference between clustering and classification, main difference is supervised versus unsupervised,
right?
And k-means, clearly, you know that picking up the k, initialization of the cluster, all
of them need a metric.
All of them will be something undetermined, right, which depends on your heuristics.
And HVAC, the problem is actually the expensive cost.
In terms of memory, in terms of commutational, both of them are more expensive than k-means.
All right?
Okay, so that's all for unsupervised learning.
Sorry, that's all for clustering.
Any question before I move on to the very last topic, regression, which we're going
to cover today?
Everybody's clear?
Okay, good.
Now, we have 20 minutes, or maybe 25 minutes, I'm going to finish the regression.
So regression, well, some people can treat that as the supervised learning problem, right?
If you want to predict, say, the labels using the variables, but if you are treating this
as a line-feeding problem, or you want to feed a point with some kind of model, right?
This one is actually unsupervised, so it depends on how you view that.
So let's first talk about the concept.
One is regression, and I'm going to introduce you to the most simple regression, like linear
regression, and see how we can do it, and then some examples.
And I'm also going to, if I have time, I'm also going to show you the derivation of linear
regression, but this part is for interest, right?
So I won't test it on that, but I want to show you that linear regression and learning
is very simple.
You don't have to do a gradient descent.
There's a closed form solution for linear regression, all right?
So concept-wise, you need to understand the difference, again, between regression and
the classification, okay?
And then for training the regressor, what is the training loss, or in other words, what
are the objectives we are minimizing here?
So these are the two important things to understand the linear regression.
So let's recap on the classification, right?
We say that classification is nothing but let the computer decide whether the image
is capable, right?
The simple example.
But one thing you realize is that it's always a mapping from data to discrete labels.
Discrete means yes or no, class one, class two, class three, right?
Every output is either one or two, either zero or one.
So that's like discrete labels.
But sometimes we want to do something final, right?
We want to do something, say, well, I'm not interested in whether it's a cat, but I wish
to know what's the likelihood the image is a cat, right?
How likely is this cat, how likely is the dog?
So what I need is a percentage, or it's a likelihood, which is represented not as a
discrete label, but as some percentage, some kind of real number, right?
So this is also needed in practice.
But if you are looking for a likelihood which is a continuous quantity, this problem is
no longer a classification problem, all right?
So the difference is that classification output is always discrete.
Now if you're looking for a continuous quantity as the output, it's going to be a regression
problem, all right?
So the difference here is that classification always predicts a discrete label.
Regression is going to predict a continuous quantity, all right?
That's the major difference.
So of course, in some sense, right, you can actually also form or maybe formulate a classification
indirectly as a regression.
For example, I can say that, well, I can determine the class based on, let's say, the probability
for a discrete label, right, which is also something we do in practice, but the intermediate
result doesn't matter.
Whether it's a classification or regression depends on the final result.
So finally if I need a label, discrete label, that's a classification.
Finally if I need a continuous quantity, that's going to be regression, no matter what I do
in middle, right?
So this is the principle.
And the way we evaluate the effectiveness for classification for regression is also
different, all right?
So if you're doing a classification, normally we use like, say, accuracy to quantify or
to evaluate whether my results are good or bad, right?
So the personage can be, the accuracy can be the person page of the correctly identified
sample out of all predictions, right?
So this is also something you need for your mini-project, right?
So when you have some results, when you have some validation result, you need to tell me
what's the accuracy, right?
So accuracy will be the measurement for classification, all right?
But for regression, it's different.
Regression because you are outputting something continuous.
You cannot say this is true or false, right or wrong, right?
Because the only way you can measure is like, how close my prediction is comparing to the
ground truth.
So you need also a continuous quantity to evaluate the correctness.
So the commonly used accuracy is something like root mean square error, right?
Something like the L2 long distance between my prediction and the ground truth.
Of course, it's the smaller the better, right?
But it won't be person page.
It will be some quantity that measures the deviation from your output and ground truth.
So you can see that because the output is different, the way we evaluate the results
also different.
So be careful when you do the project, right?
Make sure you are reporting the right metric to evaluate you more.
Depends on what problem you're solving, okay?
So this is one of the difference.
So then what is the regression problem look like?
Well, for regression, we are predicting a scalar, right?
So basically, I want to output some kind of quantity continuous.
So the output will be a number that something like a real number.
So the output will be the scalar.
The input may not be a scalar.
The input can be a vector, right?
So just now we say that you can talk about d-dimensional vector.
So your sample will have d numbers, okay?
But the output will always be a scalar.
The input can be either a scalar or a vector.
Depends on your data dimension, right?
So a linear regression, so we only learn linear regression, by the way.
There could be other more complicated regression, right?
But if it's a linear regression, the way we predict the output is by using a linear
function, something like this.
We use a linear function to multiply my w, which is the weights of the linear regressor,
with my x plus the offset or bias term, right?
So this is how you can formulate a regressor to predict my y.
So here, the w is also a d-dimensional vector, okay?
So I hope all of you know what is this t, superscript t, right?
It's called transpose, okay?
So if you do w transpose x, it's like inner product of the two, okay?
So all of you know what is inner product, like you have two vectors.
You want to do inner product, how do you do that?
It's like you do w1 times x1 plus w2 times x2 plus w3 times x3, right?
You sum together, the output will be a scalar, okay?
So do you know this?
If you don't know this, I can explain, but I just want you to know that, are you familiar
with the notation here?
t stands for transpose, means that I'm going to make my column vector to a row vector,
right?
And because of that, the output of the w transpose x will be a scalar, okay?
So w transpose x is equal to w inner product x, it's the same thing, right, but I use this
as a proper notation to represent a linear regression, okay?
So by doing so, I'm going to get a scalar plus a scalar that will make the y also a
scalar, right?
This is the linear regression form, all right?
But of course, we do not know exactly in the beginning what is w and b, right?
w and b will be the parameter of my model, my kind of linear regressor.
So there will be a training process to determine what is w and what is b, okay?
So the training process basically is to find the best w based on the training data.
So here the training data means you will have n points, where you use x, sorry, x,
y, x2, all the way to xn, where is the label y, y1, y2, and y, yn, right?
So this is actually what we need for training, or we need to do fitting of the line, right?
But later I can show you that, in fact, if you treat y together with x, right, this can
be formulated as unsupervised learning, because you can form the data as the, how should I
say, you can represent data as the merge of both x and y, right?
So there are two ways to view the regression, right?
Okay, but basically the training process refers to the process which we determine the w, or
we learn the w, right?
So here's like a few kind of progress showing that how we can do the training, right?
So like I said, every training process is always about minimize something, or maximize
something to find the right parameter, okay?
So here's the same thing, I want to find the parameter of w and b by minimizing the following
mean square error, right?
So what is this error?
This error is called the mean square error, which is between the ground truth y and the
predicted y, okay?
Just like we said that linear regression is going to predict the y using this linear function,
okay?
But what I want to do is that I want to find the best w and b such that my prediction is
very close to the ground truth.
That's why here you can see that the term here is exactly measuring the distance between
the prediction, this is my prediction, and the ground truth, okay?
I take the square, it still measures the distance, right, the L2 distance, I sum them up at the
average, right?
So this is why they call it mean, mean means the average.
Square error means the error is somehow squared, right?
So this is where the name comes from.
So basically, I want to minimize the overall error, all the samples, overall error, comparing
the prediction and the ground truth, I want to minimize it by finding the best w and b,
right?
So this is basically what linear regression learning is happening, right?
Why, what we're going to do, what we're going to minimize.
This is actually the mean square error we're going to minimize.
All right, so let's make it clear.
For exam purpose, what you need to know is that if I ask you, say, hey, what is the loss
we're using for linear regression?
You need to tell me, okay, the loss is mean square error, okay?
This is actually the form we're trying to minimize, and what are we learning?
We're learning the w and b, but that's it, okay?
How are we learning the w and b?
I'm going to talk about it, but that's not something we're going to test you, all right?
But you are more than welcome to learn because it's very interesting, I would say, all right?
So but before that, let's see one example, right?
What is actually happening when we do linear regression in the visual, visual example?
So consider the following data, right?
So this is actually the data we have.
We only consider x, y, two-dimensional, okay?
So every row here represents a data point.
So the data 1 is like 1, 1, data 2 is 2, 2, data 3 is 3, 1.3.
So every sample has one-dimensional x and one-dimensional y, okay?
Now I want to do linear regression over these data.
So like I mentioned, right, if it's two-dimensional data, I can plot that in a 2D space.
So now I plot these five points in the x, y plane, right?
The horizontal is actually the x, vertical is the y.
Every point will be plotted here, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, right?
So this is my five points.
Now if I run linear regression to find a regressor for that, what I'm doing here is actually,
okay, of course, I need to first define, right?
I'm minimizing my mean square arrow and find a line such that the mean square arrow is
somehow minimized.
So here what I'm doing here is actually finding a line, the black one, which is fully determined
by w and b, okay?
Why?
Because in this case, w will be one-dimensional, it's a single number.
b is also a single number, right?
So the w will be the slope of an ingredient of this line, b will be the offset here of
the line.
So two numbers can uniquely determine a line in the plane, right?
So basically, I need to find the w and b such that I determine this line and this line should
minimize the mean square arrow, which are denoted as the distance, color distance in
the space.
Okay, so here's one thing very, very critical, this distance is not the distance between
the point and the line, but it's the distance vertically.
Okay, very important because later, I mean, not later, I mean, in week 12, okay, actually
very, very late, week 12, we're going to learn PCA, okay?
PCA, you will see something very similar, like reducing dimensionality.
We also want to minimize the distance, but that distance is different from this one because
that distance is the perpendicular distance.
I want to minimize the projection.
So here, the distance is only on y, that's why the distance is vertical, okay?
I wish to highlight this and that's the only, that's the major difference between regression
and also principle component analysis, all right?
Okay, so then the question is why, why it's vertical, why not perpendicular?
We have to go back to the loss function, right?
Remember, this is our loss function, okay?
What is this loss function?
The loss function is the difference between the predicted y and the ground truth y, okay?
Both sides are y, nothing to do with x, are y's.
That means the distance here are measured in the y domain, y-axis, okay?
And vertical is actually the y-axis.
That's why here the entire distance is defined as the vertical distance.
So in other words, in this plot, right, this y value is the ground truth y for my point
5, okay, because this is actually my point 5, right?
The line intersection here, this is the predicted y using my linear regressor, okay?
In other words, this point is my w times x5 plus b, this is my wi-fi.
So the distance between my wi-fi and w times x5 plus b, that's the distance we're talking
about, vertical distance.
So be very clear about that and I could give you some tricky question and if you get it
wrong then, you know, you have to think about this example, all right?
This is going to tell you that, you know, what is the distance, what is the right distance
to visualize in the 2D space, okay?
Think about it and, you know, convince yourself and then later we can talk about another case,
which is the PCA, all right?
Okay, but this is important and this is the only thing I need to know, okay?
You do have to think about the derivation, but I'm going to tell you the derivation of
linear regression.
Okay, so, okay, this is like, this point is actually w times xi plus b.
In this case, it's x5, right?
And this is the point which is yi, same for every point.
So this is my y4 and this will be w times x4 plus b, right?
And this is my y3.
So all of the arrows are arrowing y, that's why all of the distance are vertical, okay?
All right, so that's all for the things that could be tested, all right?
So from now on, the things are just for your knowledge.
So I won't really give you anything exammable, all right?
So I'm going to show you how one can derive the w and b, right?
So just now we see that if we train the regressor, we will know w and b.
But we haven't talked about how exactly we can obtain the w and b, right?
So in practice, there's an easy way, I mean, not so easy, but like a reasonably easy way
to obtain the w and b by using some simple linear algebra, all right?
No gradient descent, just linear algebra, we'll do it.
So here's actually the starting point, right?
We're talking about having a group of data, which is the x and y.
We want to obtain the w and b, right?
So this is actually the linear regressor we have, all right?
But for making things simpler, we can do one possible simplification.
That is writing the w transpose x plus b as the expanded vector.
Okay, how I expand it?
I'm cascading the w with b.
Okay, here's what I mean, right?
So maybe I just draw things a little bit.
So suppose my, let's say my w is, I don't know, let's say 1 and 2, all right?
So my w and b is equal to 3.
So in this case, I can do w transpose x plus b.
I can also make it as 1, 2, 3 multiplied by x1.
Make sense?
Because if you do vector-vector multiplication, right, this is equal to 1, 2 times x plus 3 times 1.
So it's the same thing, right?
What I'm doing here is I'm just making it simpler, making two terms into one term.
But nothing changes, it's an equivalent change, everything is the same.
I just make the notation simpler by merging the b into my w.
Because anyway, I'm going to learn both, right?
So I don't want to differentiate them, I make them the same, into one vector.
All right, okay?
So I hope this explains the small trick here, erase, all right.
So after that, I can simplify my notation by calling the entire vector as w.
I'm actually abusing the notation here.
I want to redefine the w as the cascading concatenation of the old w with b together.
It's still a vector, but vector is one more dimension with b appended there, right?
So in this case, I also update my x with my old x plus one more 1, right?
I'm going to expand my x with one more dimension, but the number is 1.
The reason is that I want to simplify the linear regression as simply a w times x.
But the things are still the same.
All of the parameters are embedded in the new dimension, in the new notation.
But the dimension is upgrading from d-dimensional to d plus 1-dimensional.
Same for w, right?
Upgrading from d-dimensional to d plus 1-dimensional.
It's a simple algebra, but it's going to make the notation simpler.
All right, so now I reformulated the problem.
I just now remembered we have this mean square error, right?
The mean square error is actually between w times x plus b minus y, remember?
That was the old mean square error.
After I do this upgrading, the mean square error will become simply w times x minus y.
But here, the x and w are updated, all right?
It's the same thing, but I changed the notation a little bit, OK?
The reason for doing that is I can simplify this matrix form into a simple L2 norm.
OK, L2 norm is actually the Euclidean distance measuring between x, w minus y.
So here, I do a change of the notation where every x1, x2, x3 are vectors, remember?
Every sample is a vector.
But I have entirely d numbers, right?
Sorry, d points.
Oh, sorry, n points.
I have n samples.
So I'm going to have x1, x2, x3, all the way to xn, right?
But instead of writing a summation, I can define a matrix, right?
The matrix means it's going to be like a height and width, right?
So here, every row of the big matrix will be a specific xi.
Basically means my x1 is the first row, my x2 is the second row, my x3 is the third row.
So you are going to concatenate in all of x one by one to form this big matrix x, uppercase x, right?
So in this case, the mean square error can be written as uppercase x times w and minus y.
Because this multiplication will give you the predicted y, but all of them together.
So this will be my y1, y2, y3, all the way to yn.
Still, nothing changed.
I just simplified the notation, upgrading the summation to a matrix vector multiplication, right?
So this is what I'm doing.
But by doing so, I can use this form to denote the mean square error I'm trying to minimize, all right?
So now what happened?
This is the thing I'm going to minimize.
I know all of the x.
I also know all of the y.
I want to find what is w.
So w here is the variable I want to figure out, right?
Remember, w includes the old w plus the b.
Now, how can you solve the minimization problem?
Many ways, but one way to do it, you can find the gradient, right?
You can take the gradient with respect to w and make the gradient equal to zero, right?
That's the first order solution.
Sorry, second order solution for a linear equation, right?
So if you do so, you can find the gradient of this linear term,
and the gradient will be something like 2 transpose x times w minus 2 times x transpose y.
You can break the bracket.
Now, if this guy equal to zero, which means this term should equal to the second term.
So this term will be equal.
All right, now I can inverse the x transpose x,
make it to the right-hand side, now only have w on the left-hand side.
Now, this is the closed formula for my w.
And the w can be written as the matrix inverse of x transpose x multiplied by x transpose y.
So just in the one line, if you know the entire x and y,
you can use this one line equation to compute the entire w.
Which is the parameter of your linear regression.
OK, so this is like some, how should I say,
least square solution for linear regression.
This is only true if the loss function is mean square error, right?
Other error function may end up with different solutions,
but if it's a mean square error, we will use the b square term solution,
which can find easily the parameters of your linear regression.
OK, one thing to keep in mind is that if you want to find,
let's say, a d-dimensional linear regression,
you have to have at least d sample points in the space.
OK, in other words, you want to have five unknowns.
You want to determine, you need to have five equations, right?
This is very simple, solve linear equation, right?
The reason is that only when you have d rows in your x matrix,
this matrix inverse will exist.
Otherwise, you cannot invert a matrix.
But for most of linear regression, you can assume that this one exists.
But if not, this w may not be unique.
You can have infinitely many solutions for your w.
OK, that makes sense?
Just like you want to determine a line, you need two points, right?
Two points can determine a line.
One point, you have many, many lines, which can fit the points.
OK, so this is actually the co-sponsor.
But I'm not going to pass on this, but I want to give you some idea.
When we say training the linear regressor, how are we training?
The training is actually using the following way.
You can figure out the matrix, do the inversion, and work out the w.
And those w will determine the regressor you're talking about.
So this is one way to do it.
And of course, you feel free to try this for your project.
But you won't see the question asking about deriving it in the exam.
So don't worry about it if you feel like it's hard to read.
OK, so like I mentioned, we are minimizing the mean square error.
So this closed form is called a least square estimator of the linear regression.
OK, so also I explained to you that, well, if you visualize a point in 2D,
we are basically fitting a point with a line.
Right?
You want to minimize the vertical distance,
such that you minimize the vertical distance to find the line fitting all the points.
But you see, sometimes you can find a good fit.
But there could be a case that maybe your points are not distributing so closely.
So you may fail to find a good line fitting them, which is possible.
Practice is possible.
So what should we do?
I mean, what should one deal with the regression problem
with those points are quite kind of sparsely distributed.
So I have two options.
The first option is that, well, maybe I don't have to use a line, right?
I can use a polynomial to fit the points.
So for example, here, I want to fit the points.
Instead of using a line, which is the red line, you can use a polynomial,
like high order polynomial to fit the points.
In this case, as you can see, the arrow here is the vertical distance.
Comparing the line with the polynomial, polynomial is actually much better, right?
You fit the points in a much better way.
But do you think this is a good choice for regression?
No?
Why?
Exactly, overfitting.
So some of you may notice, right?
So in fact, if you look at the literature in regression,
very few people talk about polynomial fitting, right?
Even though they fit very well, the question is that,
you only fit well for those kind of points you know, right?
But those kind of training samples may have noise.
Nobody knows whether the points themselves are very clean
and coming from the actual distribution.
So use polynomial to fit the points will give you smaller error,
but you won't be able to generalize that to future data,
because the future data won't really be exactly the same as your training data, right?
So that's why even though linear regressor will give you some error in the training,
people still love it, because the structure of the line
will help you to overcome overfitting recognition, right?
So we're going to get to that in week 11, unfortunately.
But in 11, we're going to talk about what is overfitting or even underfitting
and how to overcome them if you observe that, right?
What's the way we can maybe constrain our model
or change the way we train to prevent overfitting, right?
But this is one example that overfitting is a problem,
and you should not just minimize the error.
You should also consider the generalization to testing data, right?
So the answer is no.
Nobody wants to do the polynomial fitting due to overfitting.
People still love linear regression, all right?
But instead, another way people are trying to do
if you find a really bad fit is by replacing x with some better feature.
So we don't have to do fitting the original xy domain.
We can actually do the fitting maybe in a better domain.
So this is actually all about this kind of feature embedding and also deep learning, right?
Deep learning is nothing but getting the right feature and we do a fitting again, right?
So possibly learning the feature will help you to fit the data better
even if you still use linear regression, right?
This is actually the better solution in practice
rather than upgrading the linear to polynomial, all right?
OK, so I think that's pretty much the end I will talk about.
So just summarize, right?
For regression part, you need to know the difference between regression and classification.
The major difference is what are you predicting, right?
Regression is going to be continuous quantity.
Classification is always discrete.
So it depends on the finger prediction will make a difference
whether it's classification or regression.
So for linear regression, you need to know what is the training loss, OK?
The training loss in our course will be mean square error
between the prediction and the ground truth.
And also I wish to understand why visually we are minimizing the vertical distance
rather than the perpendicular distance.
The reason is actually at the loss function.
This is the loss in the y domain.
Nothing to do with x.
That's why we are always talking about minimizing the vertical offset, OK?
So these are something kind of takeaway for regression part.
So with that, that's the end for today.
And I hope I will see you again like after several weeks, so week 11.
All right, so don't forget the grouping, right?
I hope to see the response by everyone.
Either you find a group or not by the end of recess, OK?
So by the end of recess, I'm going to help those who cannot find a group.
I'm going to announce the grouping.
Then you can proceed to the project.
All right, OK, thank you so much.
And see you in week 11.
Thank you so much.
Yes, yes.
No, no, this is n.
Yeah, yeah, x, I mean, the weight is like 80 plus 1, 100 plus 1, yes.
1, yes, it's not a matrix.
Either way, but I need to see a reason.
For example, you want to propose your own.
What's wrong with the existing one, right?
Or you want to use something at the baseline y.
Why this one specifically?
Why not other baseline?
So that's why you need to do a summary first and show me a clear kind of a thinking.
So how you end up with your choice.
Can we select about three to four models based on the model that you just told me to propose
with final notion of this?
Yeah, I mean, that's something you can do.
But I wish to remind you that, OK, you're talking about numerical verification.
You say, hey, I have five.
I want to numerically test how well they work in the empirical experiment.
But that will only verify the performance over a specific set.
I also wish to know the reason if you find A is better than B as a fact.
But why do you think that's possibly what kind of generate this kind of result?
Yeah, so like to explain.
Yes, yes.
Or at least give you some intuition.
I know for deep learning, maybe it's hard to theoretically justify.
But it's always better to give me some of the heuristics.
For example, maybe to do is the complexity of the method.
Maybe something to do is like overfitting.
Something to do is optimizer.
Right.
So that was your understanding.
You know how they are actually formulating.
Oh, OK.
OK, good.
So no more questions, right?
OK.
Bye-bye.