Hey, no, it's not.
All right.
I think we can get started.
Welcome back.
I hope you had a great public holiday yesterday.
Also, I believe a protest already introduced various methods on
neural networks, supervised learning, and now we are coming
back to maybe have a better understanding of those learning.
But since the last time I met you was like four weeks ago,
or five weeks ago, so week six, I just want to, before I start
my own lecture today, I just want to have a quick recap on things
I cover on week six, make sure you still have a good memory
of those things.
And as usual, for my part, through through the ask question.
You can ask a question anytime you want, so you don't need to
wait until the end, so just raise your hand.
I'm happy to clarify any question you have.
All right, so I hope you still remember, in week six, we talk
about several methods on supervised learning.
We talk about clustering methods.
We also talk about linear regression.
And I say that for clustering, you need to know the two
methodologies that we covered, and those are the only two,
which represents the partition-based method and also the
hierarchical clustering methods.
So the first one is K-means, right?
I hope you still remember what is K-means.
A few key points for K-means method are, you need to know
that K-means, of course, is very different from the SVM or
neural networks you just learned from Prof. Tan.
It's unsupervised.
In other words, you will not need labels in the training.
That's a major difference between supervised and unsupervised
methods.
And the K-means also need a parameter, which is the K.
You need to know the number of clusters before using them.
And also, you also need to specify the distance metric.
So in most cases, in this subject, we're going to use Euclidean
distance, unless we specify in the question.
And one important thing for K-means is that you have to
care about how you initialize the algorithm.
And you do need an initialization.
That's the very first step before running into the iterative
steps.
And usually, by saying initialization, we're talking
about initializing the centers.
So for example, you have K clusters.
You need to initialize what are the starting point of those K
centroids.
So they must be specified.
And different initialization will affect your final results.
Because we know that K-means is very sensitive to the
initialization.
And remember the output of your K-means method.
Suppose you see one question in the exam.
And the exam asks you what is the output.
You need to specify two things.
So one is the membership for every data sample you have.
So for every data you have in the question, there must be
associated to a specific cluster and only one, all right?
Exact one cluster.
And you also need to tell us what are the learned centroids
for every cluster.
So both of them you need to specify.
And that's the full, complete answers.
And also make sure you specify when you stop.
Give us the stopping criteria.
So these are basically the key points you need to know.
In order to make sure you get the answer properly addressed in
your final exam.
And another thing we learned is HAC.
So HAC is another different approach compared to K-means,
but it's also for clustering.
And a few highlights or differences compared to K-means is
that first, it doesn't need any initialization.
It's kind of deterministic.
The algorithm always give you the same answer if data samples
are fixed.
I mean, other things are similar.
For example, you also need, because this is an unsupervised
method, so you need a collection of data, but you do not need
labels.
So it's like data without labels.
And you also need to specify distance metric.
But this distance metric is slightly different.
So when we talk about HAC, you need a distance metric, not just
between samples, but between clusters.
Because later we'll see some examples.
But we basically learned for kind of distance, like inter-cluster
distance, the centroid, max, min, and average.
So make sure you know what they are.
You can tell the difference.
And for any of them giving the question, you know how to update
your distance table, how to come up with the cluster updates.
And, well, this distance metric well-determined how you merge
the clusters.
So make sure you know, you can decide how to merge the cluster
from the distance table.
So we say that from distance table, you can tell which pair of
clusters, the one with the minimum distance, and how to
visualize them.
We talk about visualization, but of course, with only two
dimensional data, or maybe one dimensional data, you can
visualize them.
And a very unique thing for HAC is that you can always come up
with a dendrogram.
So the dendrogram, well, trace or kind of track all of this
merging process right in the beginning and all the way until,
let's say, only one cluster remains.
So if you have this dendrogram, you can actually get the result
for any number of cluster you like.
So make sure you know how to interpret the dendrogram, and
also you can kind of plot the dendrogram from your
clustering process.
So again, stopping criteria.
But stopping criteria for HAC is quite simple.
You just need to stop either when you only have one cluster
left, or if the question say, well, I need two clusters, then
you stop at two clusters.
So these are some of the things you just want to use them to
refresh your memories and make sure you know what I'm talking
about.
Every key point, those are something quite important when you
answer the question.
You have to make sure they are covered in your answer.
So these are some recap.
So I actually give some examples, if you remember, in week
six.
This is actually the four data sample example I gave.
And I show you how to do the HAC using the central distance and
average link.
Remember?
Though I give these two examples in the lecture slides in week
six, because they are actually more complicated.
The reason I show these two is because actually using central
distance and average linkage actually is more complicated
because you have updated the central, it's calculating
average.
And I didn't show the mean and the max distance because they
are relatively simpler.
But I still receive some questions where people ask how can
we do with the first two.
So I will use the same example.
I show you in week six.
But let's try using the single linkage and also complete
linkage.
In other words, mean distance and max distance.
Let's see how they are different.
So in the beginning, any distance metric, as long as you are
doing HAC, the very first step is always the same.
No difference.
You have to come up with this distance table.
Of course, you only need, let's say, a lower triangle or
upper triangle because it's actually symmetric.
But you need to calculate the point-wise distance in this
table.
So basically, if you have four points, you will need a four
by four matrix, but only the lower triangle, all of this value
to be calculated by comparing the distance between every two
samples you have.
That's the same.
That's always the same, no matter what inter cluster distance
you choose.
Now starting from this table, you can make a decision, say,
whichever give you the smallest distance, that's going to be
the pair of points you're going to merge.
So in this case, by comparing all of these non-zero numbers,
you can tell that the first merge is always 1 and 2.
That's kind of the same, no matter what distance you use.
Now starting from step two, this step makes a difference.
Depends on what inter-class distance you are using.
The procedure of making the second move will be different.
So if you remember, we talk about centroid distance.
If you are using centroid distance, you need to update the
centroids of this new cluster by merging 1 and 2.
So basically, you need to compute the new center and
recalculate the distance.
Now if it's not centroid distance, if it's average, mean,
and max, you don't have to explicitly compute the new center,
which makes the things easier.
But you just need to update the distance table accordingly.
But how to update the distance table?
I hope you still remember for the average case, what we did is
that if we want to know the distance between, let's say,
1, 2, and 3, if we want to know the new distance between 1, 2,
and 3, the way we do that is by taking the average of distance
1, 3, which is here.
You can read from the first table.
This is your first distance table in step one.
You can extract or calculate this new distance directly from
the first table by simply taking the average of distance 1,
3, which is here, and the distance between 2, 3, which is here.
So you just simply take the average of these two numbers.
That's how you get the 0.79, which is the distance between 3 and 1, 2.
So you just need to take the average, but you don't have to
recalculate or update the new center.
The new center is not needed.
Make sense?
This is the recap.
I got the same thing in week six.
It's a recap.
And then you can do the same thing for distance between 1, 2, and 4.
So between 1, 2, and 4, similarly, you take the average over 1, 4, and 2, 4.
You take the average of these two numbers.
That gives you the 1.24.
So this is your average distance.
The average distance, let's say, between x, y, and z.
x plus y and z is equal to the average between x and z and y and z.
Very simple.
Make sense?
So make sure you know how to do it.
Next time, it may not be 1 and 2.
Next time, it may be 2 and 3.
But the principle is very similar.
Now, how about the other two distance metric?
So how about, let's say, well, this is average.
So basically, this is the average.
I already showed you.
You take the average of these two.
You can get the output here.
Now, if we're talking about not average, but the mean, we say that
another way to calculate the inter-cluster distance is by looking
at what is the minimum.
What's the minimum pair of points between the two clusters?
Now, if we are using the minimum distance, it's even simpler.
Remember, previously, we're taking the average.
Now, if it's a mean, you don't need to take average, but you take the mean.
So if it's a mean distance between 1, 2, and 3, it will be the
mean of distance 1, 3, and distance 2, 3.
So just compare the two, whichever give you the smaller
distance, that's become the final distance.
So now you have this 0.72 coming directly from the previous
distance between 1 and 3.
Make sense?
Then similarly, the other pairs, you can just take the
minimum of these two guys, whichever is smaller, make them
the distance between your new cluster and then 4.
So basically, you need to identify what are the two numbers you need,
then depends on the inter-cluster distance.
Either you take average or you take the mean, or another way
is that you can take the max.
If you take the max, similarly, you just pick the bigger one,
all of the two.
So that's how you can do the mean distance and max distance.
It's even simpler, but all of the average, mean, and max,
they are actually simpler because you don't have to calculate
the centroid.
You can directly derive the new distance from the distance
table in your step 1.
Is it clear?
Because some people ask me, so I think it's better to clarify here.
So same principle, but you have to be very clear about what distance
you are talking about.
Make that distance correspondingly and don't confuse yourself.
You cannot just change the distance.
It must be the same, specified by the question.
OK, great.
Again, you will be very likely to see one question, at least,
in clustering, so make sure these two, k-means, h-a-c, you are familiar with.
This is the only thing I can tell you.
You will have one question about that point.
Now, another thing we talk about in week six is the linear regression.
So linear regression is kind of a different problem.
It's not about labels.
It's about the continuous value.
You want to predict what is the, say, underlying y using the parameters
x to predict it.
And then if you assume that the model itself is linear, in other words,
you are having a line defined by the vector w and b,
you can actually predict the y by using a simple linear combination,
right?
x times y, sorry, x times w plus b.
And so if we need to have a training process to obtain this w,
and we say that to do so, usually you need to have a training data set,
like a list of x and a list of y.
And the way you train the w is by solving a mean square,
sorry, least square problem.
In other words, you are trying to minimize the mean square arrow
between your prediction, remember your linear regression,
the prediction is always w multiplied by x, basically it's
like inner product of the two plus b and distance between that
with the underlying yi, right?
You make the difference, you take the square, and then you want
to make sure that w you have is going to minimize this arrow
over the entire data set, the training data set, right?
And that's how you can catch a w, right?
And well, remember that we show a figure, right, in the plot,
if we are using the two-dimensional data, you can plot all of this
x and y in the 2D space, and we say that the actual arrow we are
minimizing, in fact, is the vertical arrow, right?
Remember we say that?
So make sure you don't confuse it with the PCA
that we're going to see maybe next week, all right?
So the reason is these arrows are entirely in the y-dimension.
So vertical offset means the arrow in the y-direction, okay?
So in fact, all of these arrow are minimizing, it's the actual
point, the distance vertically from the point itself to the
projection onto the y, right?
Sorry, not projection, I mean the vertical axis.
If you draw a vertical line, intersection with the linear
regression, that's the distance we have, okay?
And we also quickly describe how you can derive this w.
I mean, this is optional.
I will not give you any questions specifically on
deriving the w, but for those who want to know this, right,
we say that there's actually a closed form solution to come up
with the optimal line, right, the w, is by first simplifying
this linear regression formulation by absorbing the wang
into the x, and now if you do so, you can formulate this matrix
vector multiplication, you know, linear kind of a, linear
algebra kind of regression, and now solving this problem is
nothing but finding a gradient and then making a gradient
equal to zero, right?
So if you do so, you can do a simply a matrix inversion of
the x transpose x.
Of course, this x is the data matrix by concoilating all of
the x you have, and then as long as this x transpose x does
have an inverse, right, matrix inverse exists, your w will be
equal to nothing but the pseudo inverse of x multiplied by y,
right, so that's going to be the closed form solution of your
linear regression.
So suppose you want to use them for your project, you can
basically try this formula, right, it's very simple.
You don't even need to do any kind of gradient descent, right?
But, okay, again, this is not going to be tested, but good
for you to know, and I also got one question from the student
asking, well, can you give some example, right, like how
exact is this so-called linear, sorry, least square solution
can be calculated?
I give you like a quick example, right, so maybe you can
get a feel like how this formula can be applied, right?
So suppose we have, let's say, three data samples, right, just
three, and every data sample will have a corresponding
near x and y, so suppose this is my data one, data two, and
data three, I got three data samples, so how can I use the
three data samples to construct my w, which is my linear
regressor, how can I use this formula?
Well, you need to do actually three steps, all right, the
first step is to form a, you know, modify the x to incorporate
all of the samples, and what we're talking about is to
incorporate x and y together, right, remember, this is
what we did here, we have to concoinate the x with the
extra one here to incorporate it, so what we do here is by
incorporating the original x, right, zero one two with the
one adding to it, right, that's the step one, you make sure
the x is augmented with the extra offset, right, the
biostern, and step two is to formulate this data matrix x
and data vector y, so the matrix x will be nothing but
concatenating your x one, x two, and x three, right, this is
how you form this three by two matrix, now y vector is even
simpler, you just concatenate all of the label y, right,
your y one, y two, y three together as a vector, now the
only thing left is by applying the pseudo inverse, right, you
just need to calculate what is x transpose times x, this is
how you get your x transpose x, and you do an inversion, right,
you do an inversion of it, and then multiply by x transpose,
all right, and doing so, this becomes your w, right, the w is
very simple, this is nothing but just, you know, a vector one
one, right, that's how you can get your linear line, which is
exactly 45 degrees, right, so it's just one example for those
of you who are interested in giving a try, but again, i won't
give you any question like this, but this is some kind of example
to tell you that what really this closed form solution means,
right, okay, just for your curiosity, all right, and you
can see that all of these calculations are very simple, except
for this matrix inverse, right, so matrix inverse may take
a lot of time, but there's many solvers for getting the inverse,
okay, but sometimes the inverse may not exist, right, especially
when your matrix becomes super large, you need to make sure the matrix
itself has full rank, right, you cannot have any row or column
which is dependent, right, all of them must be independent, okay, so
I think that's all i want to recap for our week six, again if you
have any questions, feel free to ask me, we're going to have a break later,
or maybe in the class, so you can raise your hand, i'm happy to answer any question.
Now, moving forward, starting from this week, i hope
i can cover most of them, but maybe not, so we're going to continue next week,
it's about, you know, how we can get the training
done right, all right, so you have learned
like SVM training neural networks like bag propagation,
i believe with neural networks with proptan, right, you have learned all of this,
and you know that one can actually train a neural network
by having a bunch of data, right, you can do BP, you can calculate
the gradients, you can update the weights to come up with a learned model,
okay, so everything seems to be pretty well defined, but
the next question is that how do we know the
learned model is working properly, okay, so in the project
you also have this kind of question, right, you come up with some, you know,
neural network with several layers, and many people even
ask me, say, hey, is it four-layer enough, right, is it like a three-channel
enough, so in the end you need to have the knowledge
to tell the answer, right, you cannot ask me, right, so this week
i'm going to tell you what's the tool, or what's the way to analyze
whether your model learned is working properly, or in other words
have you done, have you do it right when you learn the model, and how can you tell
it, and how can you quantify the amount of error
you get from your models, okay, so this is
what i mean by optimize the training model you have, and how to regularize the training
process to prevent some question from happening, okay, so these are
the main topics i'm going to do starting from this week,
so here's the outer line, right, so we're going to first kind of
formally define the pipeline of supervised training,
okay, because all of this thing i'm talking about is mainly for supervised training,
okay, supervised training means all the things you learn with pro 10, like
SVM, in your networks, but not something to do with what i teach
in week six, right, so what i did in week six is all unsupervised,
okay, this is supervised, so we're going to formally define it, and also even
mathematically define it, and then we're going to look at the two major
part of the error you will have, right, so whatever model
you get, if the model is not doing well, means that there's some error
in your prediction, the error comes from these two parts,
it's either the bios or the variance, okay, so remember
bios and variance are the two major components of your model
error, right, so later we're going to see what are they and where they come
from, and then due to the fact that these
errors may play a role in your model, right, your model could suffer
either from underfeeding or overfeeding, okay, you may
have heard of this term many times, that people use the term overfeeding, underfeeding to
characterize, okay, what is wrong with the model, right, so what is wrong with
the training process, so these two are the main phenomenon
you probably will observe, maybe in your project, in your other kind of
practice, practical training, and we're going to see where they come from, and
how can we make a call, right, how can we know this is overfeeding or
underfeeding, I'm going to introduce a very
introductory level of this theoretical analysis about
formally defined bios and variance, so I'm going to use some
simple tool of statistical learning, but it's optional, okay, so I
don't ask everybody to know it, and I won't give any question on that, but it's really
good for you to understand, you know, formally
what do I mean by bios and variance, okay, I would say very useful, but
because it involves some math, so I don't really, I won't really test on it,
okay, but so I put them as optional, so last but not least, we're going to
use all of this knowledge we learn to see that in practice
if you observe something in your training, model training, or maybe
your model behavior, right, during the training, how can we do
model diagnosis, in other words, how can we tell that this training is wrong
or something happened, alright, and correspondingly
how can we make it correct, what should we do to improve it,
or maybe to get it done correctly, alright, so this will be
the topic I'm going to do this week and also next week, okay,
so here are some questions, as usual, I wish
you to keep in mind, and also we should be able to answer by the
end of the lecture, right, so including what are the types of supervision,
so in total I'm going to introduce four types, okay, and
how to measure the degree of overfitting, so in other words,
how can we quantify the amount of overfitting the model is suffering from,
okay, and last but not least, if we know there's overfitting,
what is the method to prevent overfitting, or at least to alleviate overfitting,
alright, so these are some of the questions, let's answer together, right, after the
lecture, okay, so I will start by introducing
or review the supervised learning framework,
so from what we learned so far, right, my part, prof10's part, you should know that,
for example, the classification you learned, let's say
using SVM or neural network is supervised, and
the symbol for that is you always need a training
data with predefined labels in the training,
I mean that's the common thing, no matter you're doing SVM or neural network, you have to
have a data set with many, many samples involving
both the sample themselves and the underlying labels,
okay, that's the common thing, whereas the clustering
method we just recap, like HAC or K-Means,
is unsupervised, in other words, we won't have any preexisting
label, we don't need them, we just need the sample points, and we can
do them for training, right, that's the main difference, so now
I'm going to focus on the first category, so in other words, I'm going to
focus on supervised training for the entire analysis I'm talking about,
in other words, we are at this
side, so if I'm going to use this dimension to summarize
those kind of type of supervision, unsupervised learning is like
the least restrictive things, you don't need
any label on the left-hand side of this axis,
the supervised training is on the right-hand side of this axis, in other words, you need
a complete training label for the tasks you want to do,
alright, so we have covered both of them, some of the
examples we have talked about, but we also have something in between,
I wish you to be aware of that, so in between there could be some
cases, for example, you may have labels, but you only have the label
for a small portion of your training data, suppose
you have 1000 samples in your training data, you only know the labels, maybe for
200, sorry, maybe 50 of them, like a small portion,
majority of them are unlabeled, so if you are training over
these kind of set, we call it a semi-supervised training,
so there's another kind of something between, it's called semi-supervised
means that the labels are partially available, only a few
of them are available, there's another category we call the weekly
supervised, I believe you heard of this term, like frequently, but the definition
for weekly supervised means you have a label for
all of the samples you got in the training, but those labels
could be noisy, in other words, the label could be right or could be wrong,
and the label could
be not exactly for the tasks you are interested, it could be
labeled for some other tasks but relevant, so these kind of
scenarios we call it the weekly supervised, alright, so all of these are not
quite ideal but you still have something, so
that's kind of the four scenarios if you read the literatures,
so basically these are the four most commonly seen scenarios
of supervision, but just wish to know that the
supervised training is actually the best scenario or the most ideal
scenario, everything is clean and you have all the labels, but we still
have two things in between, so you can actually memorize this using this one-dimensional
axis, alright, but now talking about
completely supervised training, so let's just recap what
we learned from prof10, we're talking about
have input, so for example if we are using the image classification as an example,
the pipeline is always taking the image as input
and the output will be the corresponding label, predicted label
of that image, so this is like a very classic supervised
image classification problem setting, you give the image
as input, the model predicts the desired output as a label
but to do so, to come up with the model
doing that, we always need a stage, we call it the training,
so you heard of this term training many times, and the
training in the supervised setting will be the following,
so we're talking about using a sample, the
images, not the label, we use the images, we will represent them using
whatever models we have, and we're trying to compare
with the training labels, I mean the ground-truth label we have,
we want to make them similar, like minimizing some errors or minimizing some
loss, such that we find the best model
that can represent all of these samples, and also the best model
to make the decision, think about SVM, your decision
boundary, that's something you want to learn, so bear in mind that
for the training process, you well know the label, so the training process
do not need to create any labels, the labels are given,
the purpose of training is to finalize
the model you learned, the purpose or the output
of the training is the learned model, so that's the major difference,
and then we use the model for testing,
the next thing is the testing stage, the testing stage
is fix the model you get from the training, you don't touch
the model, and you use the learned model to generate
the label prediction, so let's make them very clear,
training step, no need to worry about the labels, the labels will be given,
our purpose is to create or generate the learned model, and the testing
is talking about using the model you learned in the training, create
the prediction you have in the testing data set, so this
is like the general pipeline for all of the supervised training we talk about,
in this subject at least, and this is like the
illustration, I'm illustrating this using the
flow chart, now let's try to make it a little bit mathematics,
so instead of doing this hand-waving description
of training and testing, mathematically we
can represent the model we are talking about as a function, f,
here the function f, we use a function
f to represent the model we are talking about, I mean this f
can be very different from using different models, like SVM, this f will
be your support vector machine for predicting the label,
and it depends on your model, the neural network, f will be
your multilayer neural network taking the input and generating the output,
and all of this model we are talking about in machine
learning, they will be parameterized,
in other words they will involve some parameters that you can
set or you can learn, so we use the symbol
theta to denote the actual model parameters,
so think about this theta as your neuron,
weights or bios term, these are characterized
as the theta, so f theta denotes the
actual model you are using, and of course you can use your input
as x, denotes output as y, so the entire
classification process can be described
using this one line equation, mathematically,
now what is the training, the training process is
nothing but given a training set of label sample, in other words
I will give you a, let's say n pairs of x and y,
x1, y1, x2, y2, all the way to x and yn,
and the purpose of training is nothing
but estimating the theta by
making the right prediction over this
pairs, so remember the purpose of training here
mathematically is to determine the theta, that's the purpose of
training, so you don't touch x and y, x and y are given
you want to determine the theta, once the theta is finalized you are done with
the training, now testing or sometimes we
call it inference is to apply the learned f theta
nothing changed there, it's fixed, now we want
to apply them to some new samples or unseen samples
x, and now predict the corresponding y
for those x in the testing, so this is what we
refer as testing, the testing means fix f theta, apply them
to the x, generate the y for the testing data set
so let's make it very clear, and then
this is nothing but the mathematical description of the previous
pipeline we are talking about, and we summarize them, so here the f can be anything
all of the model we have learned, depends on what they are, they will have corresponding form
and then they will have corresponding different parameters of theta, but in general
this will be the mathematical description of the supervised training process
so I will using this notation for many of the
analysis I'm going to do, so let's just keep this in mind, and this is the
convention, now we know that we have now
described the learning process, and we
can actually learn the theta using the specific methods for specific
models, but like I mentioned, we are
not very sure, sometimes the model you learn could work very well
sometimes the model you get may not work so properly, and
here what we want to understand is that what are the potential problems
when you learn the theta from the training
samples, x and y, so what could be wrong, or what
could be the possible problems that you encounter during the training
so welcome to see a few, the first one we call
this overfilling, and overfilling happens when you
don't have sufficient data for a specific model, in other words
for a specific f and theta, you may not have sufficient
x, so illustratively
the case is that well, you only have a few samples, and it
depends on how you decide to feed them, you can feed them
into a very restrictive way, or you can make them like a
quite funny way, so this kind of problem that because you
don't have enough data, somehow you feed the model in a very
funny way, that's usually referred as overfilling, so this is
like the intuitive way, we're going to define them later
formally, but overfilling is one of the major issues, or major
problems when you don't have sufficient data for a specific
model, that's the number one, number two is the opposite,
the opposite is that your data may be enough, or maybe
sufficient, but your model
themselves may not be rich enough, in other words the model
could be too simple sometimes, so here's one example, you
have some data samples, and the data sample themselves
underline model of them will be like a second order, let's say
polynomial, but because you insist to learn
a linear regression over the sample, so no matter how
much you adjust this line, this line cannot feed the
sample very accurately, it's due to the fact that you are
limiting your model complexity to just a line,
and using a too simple or not rich enough
model to solve the problem, that's the issue we call
underfilling, so these are the two major things we may
encounter in practice, so now we're going to see
we should understand what really happened, so basically we need to know the mechanism
causing these two problems when you do learning,
that's the purpose of what we do today, so let's see first
where does this error come from, so we know that due to these two facts
there could be something wrong, there could be some errors, let's see where this error comes from in the first place, now
in practice there are two main challenges
preventing us to get the correct model or accurate model,
so number one, the challenge is that in practice
if we are given a bunch of data without prior knowledge, we will
never know the exact model, meaning the true model, really mapping from
x to y, because there could be some mechanism, but we have
no idea, we just have the data, we have no idea what is the underlying true model
that exact mapping from x to y, we have to guess, so
that's actually one of the limitations that we always encounter
in practice, the second challenge we encounter is that
we will never know the true distribution of the data,
in other words I give you a bunch of samples, we only know the measure
we have over those lesser few, but what exactly is the true distribution
of the model, based on the limited measurement we have no idea
about it, so these are two fundamental limitations that
physically impossible to know them exactly,
now what happens, so for example if we have the first challenge
what we do in practice, we have to do something to overcome them
so what we do in practice to overcome the
first challenge is by always making certain assumption of our
model, because we don't know exactly the true model, so we have to assume something
for example you may usually assume that your
classifier is let's say linear, or your classifier itself is
like a two level neural network, so this is the assumption
you make, you believe your assumption is right, but your assumption
will be deviate or maybe deviate from the exact model
so these assumptions, we will make assumption, we need to make
assumption to determine the model architecture, but we have to bear in
mind that this is assumption, this is not the truth, so that's the
gap one, from what you do in practice and what really
happened in practice, that's the assumption one, now what
we do for the second challenge is that we, it says we do not
know the actual distribution of the data, remember all of this loss function
we use in the training are usually just based on
the average over the training data we have, remember
we talk about this linear regression, we say that linear regression is nothing but the
mean square error, while minimizing the mean square error, average over all the
sample we have, so we usually just minimize
the error that is average over the training sample, in other words
every sample you have share the same weights, we simply want to
make sure the average error is minimized, so this is something we call
empirical minimization or empirical risk minimization, but
bear in mind that this is different from directly
measure the distribution difference, because distribution
in terms of distribution some of the sample may appear more likely, some of the sample may
appear less frequently, we do not know this information so we have to treat
them equally, okay now these two
will solve the problem but they will introduce some
gap, in other words some deviation from your assumption
compared to what actually happens in the sample, now
each of them, right so we have challenge number one because the model
we do not know for sure, challenge two we do not know exact data distribution, we only know
the limited measurements, they will be corresponding
or the approximation you make will be corresponding to the
two major errors that we usually talk about in machine learning,
alright so the first error we call it a bias
so one thing I want to make sure is that you use the term
bias in let's say neural network, I hope it's different
so here the bias and variance are not about
the data, okay all of these bias and variance I'm talking about is
about the model, the parameter the theta, we talk about the f theta
okay so let's don't confuse yourself, we use the term
bias and variance sometimes for data, let's say I have a bunch of data I can calculate the variance
it's not the same, okay so here the bias is
the error that we learn from the training, means the theta we
get through the training, okay so this error is
caused by the wrong assumption you made during the training
or you made in the model you have, okay
so I'll give you one example, just now I mentioned that
if let's say I know my x and y are actually following the
second order, let's say polynomial, right I know that my y equal to
maybe x squared plus x plus some constant but I always
use a linear regression to fit them, so no matter how much you fit
there will always be some fundamental error due to the single assumption you have
and this will contribute to the bias part of
the model, okay so again bias is part of the
error you well get in the model and it's due to the fact that your model is too simple
okay now the second error, variance
is due to the fact that we always use the empirical
risk minimization, we do not know the actual distribution, so
sometimes when you have this few number of training data in practice
they could have some small fluctuations, okay
so due to the fact that you have some noise, could because when you sample the measures
you could have some very unlikely sample to generate it from
the training data, right so this small fluctuation could
drive your model to be wrong or to be deviate from the
optimal model, right so for example when I learn them
somehow my training label have some noise and then
when you fit the model to the training sample the model could fit to the noise rather than
the sample itself, right so these kind of
errors due to the sensitivity to some small fluctuation
in the training sample, this is called variance, okay
in other words for the same data distribution I could, let's say the first time
I sample 1000 samples over it but next time I randomly get another
1000, you will get different models that you learn, these difference
is the variance we're talking about, alright now
so until then, well contributed to the total
error we care about, means what the model you
get deviate from the true model and overall error we
care about is called the expected error, right so you
will hear the term later, so expected error
talking about the, for the future testing case, for
example a sample that is randomly drawn from the same distribution
what is the likelihood that we expect it to be misclassified
by the learned model, right this is the true error we care about
or the total error we will need to analyze, right we call it
expected error and in practice like how can we estimate
or measure the expected error because we don't know the distribution
right so the practical way to do it is by setting
another data set without the labels and see how the model
predicts for them, so in our subject or in most of the cases
we will use testing error or sometimes validation
error to measure the expected error, right so you
will see that in some questions, people use expected error and the
testing error interchangeably so don't be surprised because both of them represent
let's say I have unseen cases, right where I apply my model, how much
possibility that I will get it wrong, okay so this is
what we really care about, now haven't say that
if you plot let's say your expected
error as the function of the model you have, okay so here
the expected error again is the error that
I apply my model to a future data in a testing set
right how much likelihood I will get my sample wrong
right so basically the smaller the better, the larger the worse
the better, right that's the expected error I will have, now I can plot this curve
as a function of model complexity so what is this
model complexity means, it basically, I mean informally
means how flexible your model is, can it be like very free or
very limited, right so basically the larger the complexity
the more free your model is but you can think about the complexity
informally as how many free parameters in your
SVM or neural network, the amount of free
parameters is like more you will get higher model
complexity, right you can think about this informally as the amount of
free parameters you have, right so in other words I can plot
my expected error as a function of number of free
parameters, okay so for example if I have a neural network
right the complexity is usually referred to the
number of hidden neurons, means the more hidden neuron I have
the higher complexity I will have for my model, right so now you can actually
plot your expected error as a function of model
complexity, right to see what is the right complexity I should get
because we want to minimize this error, right now we see that
the expected error will have two major components
alright one is bias, one is variance, okay now
the bias as part of the error will
refer to the type of error that due to the wrong or inaccurate
assumption you made for your model choice
okay it's part of it but it's contributing to the entire error we have
and the bias term different from expected error
will be always decreased when your model
complexity increases, okay so this is very important
even though the total error will change, you know sometimes increase
sometimes decrease but the bias part of it
which is major portion of the error you will get will be
monotonically decreased as your model complexity increases
okay why, you know why this is true
because you know if you still remember the definition of bias
the bias is due to the wrong assumption you make in the model
in other words if your model is more free
you are not limiting your model to some specific set
in other words you let the model to be more free, right so the freer
the model is means that the chance you get the model assumed to
be wrong is lower, right you don't really have this strong assumption
on the model, okay so in other words you can think about this like the
smaller, sorry the more restrictive the model is the chance
that the bias increase is higher because you could limit yourself
from getting the really the underline model, right for example
if your model is second order somehow you limit your model to be linear function
you may miss the chance to find the right fit, right so to this
end we see that the bias term is always decreased
or actually monotonically decreased as we increase the model
complexity, alright so you can represent it using this
red curve here, okay and we see that the bias is high
when the model is too simple, right so for example here
these are the region that corresponding to very high bias, okay if you
have a really high bias that means your model is too simple, right you don't
have a free enough model to feed through the data set you have
okay, make sense so i pose a little bit if you have any
questions you can ask me, right because this is really important so make sure
you understand the following things first what we care about
when we say we want to analyze the model is good or bad what we really care about
is the expected error because you are going to use the model
some way for future data, right so the expected error here
is defined as the likelihood that you will get the answer wrong
when you apply the model to future data, right so this is what we care about
we want to have a model that minimize the expected error, right that's number one
and number two is that the total error will be contributed from two parts
one part is called bias, one part is called variance, okay
bias and variance are the two major components that form the total error
okay so these are two parts and we say that they are driven by different
source, right different kind of source of error, bias is driven by the wrong
assumption or too restrictive assumption you make on the model
for example your parameter is too few that's the wrong assumption
right your model must be linear that's the wrong assumption it's not flexible enough
now variance is due to the fact that your model is like
too free such that when you learn the model there could be
too sensitive to a small or some small fluctuation in the set
and this so-called small fluctuation could due to the fact that
there could be some noise, right there could be some noise in the sample you get
and fitting to the noise will cause the model to be wrong
okay so the two things bias and variance are the two major components
of the total error you care about and now we are saying that
how these two contribute to the total error, right so we know that one of them
the bias term will be a function that is monotonically
decrease over the model complexity
which is highlighted in the red curve here
that's the bias, right the bias for sure is going to decrease
as the model complexity increase because
well normally the bias high scenario is here
referred to the fact that your model is too simple or too restrictive
alright so make sure you understand where the
phenomenon come from the phenomenon of monotonically
decrease of the bias is that the bias is reflecting how restrictive
your model is, how simple your model is, alright
okay good now the other part right remember
there are two parts the other part which is called the variance
now the variance is the opposite the variance will always increase
monotonically as the model complexity increases
okay because like I mentioned the variance is due to the fact that
there could be some wrong feeling to the
data that is caused by the small fluctuation
because you will only have a few number of samples from the distribution
and those samples could be corrupted with noise now when I'm
training my model I'm feeding to the limited measure you have and when I'm feeding them
I could feed to the sample themselves or I could accidentally feed to the noise
so if your model is too flexible
instead of feeding to the sample sometimes you are feeding running
to the small fluctuation maybe caused by noise and that feeding
will cause your model to be wrong or deviate from the
optimal model right and to that end the variance
will always become higher when the model is more free
or in other words you have higher model complexity so it's also a
monotonic function but this time is increased as the
complexity increases okay
so always variance increases with the model complexity
right so together these two
if you sum the two up like the red line red curve
plus the blue curve and of course there could be some other like
small perturbation which is not a major fact together
they can be used to formulate the expected error of your classifier
so this summation is what we care about
we want to make sure this summation is minimized
okay so that's why
if you are given any curve for example expected error here
you have to keep in mind that this curve is contributed by
bias plus variance and the bias and variance
behavior are exact opposite right one is increasing
one is decreasing and the summation of them is the
true error that we care about right is so-called expected error
and in practice the expected error will be always
approximated by the testing error or validation error so if you see next time
I give you a plot where the vertical axis become testing error
and that's the price that just means expected error right
or validation error it's the same because we can never know the true expectation
so we always use a unseen data set to approximate the
expected error right this is what we usually do in practice
okay it makes sense so far
any question so far so good
okay great now if you are given a table like this
you can put a plot like this and sometimes
I ask you say hey if I have a model with certain complexity
right can you determine whether this model I have
is like too simple or too complex now how to make a
judgment so the very first thing you do is first
trying to find the minimum point okay maybe I didn't draw this line right but
the very first thing you want to do is find a good tradeoff the good
tradeoff point which is exactly at the location
which minimizes the total error okay remember what we care about is the
total error right so you need to find a line that is indicating the
minimum of the total error and if your model
is on the left hand side of the minimum error point
okay that's something we call the simple model
because you can further increase the model complexity to
decrease your total error right so if you find a given model
which is at the left hand side of your minimum error point
you call this a simple model and this simple model will have
like a high bias and low variance
okay because here the red curve is still pretty high the blue
curve is pretty low okay so the whatever region
on the left hand side of this cutoff bar you will call it a simple model
on the right hand side of it correspondingly we will have a
complex model right which means this model suffers from very low bias
but relative high variance it's the opposite but
both of them means your parameters is not optimized
you can further make it better by either decreasing or increasing
the number of parameters or the freedom or complexity of your model
right and how to decide it is to first find this cutoff line
and see which side is your model where is your model right on the left
on the right you can make a decision whether you should increase or
decrease the model complexity okay makes sense
so make sure you know how to draw this line this line is nothing to do with
this line will be the point which corresponding to
the minimum expected error and also it's going to be the intersection
of the two lines so either way they will always be the same okay make sure
you can find it and compare that point ways and in given model
you have right and then you can make a decision
alright now here is the illustration right
so we know that when you choose the model parameters
you will have this tradeoff between bias and variance
what you really want is to try to minimize the summation of the
two okay but what really happened
is if you have let's say a complex model or simple model
so I use this we call it a bow
eye plot to visualize it so let me first explain what
I'm plotting here okay so all of these red dots
or red cross here they are representing
a specific model okay so you can consider all of this point
like the cross here are referring to a specific model I have
and this point will be determined by the parameter theta
so let's say I have the same neural network but
depends on the parameter I have the model will be different
so what I'm visualizing here is how the parameter is plotted in the space
okay so imagine you have only two parameters right X and Y
you can plot the parameters in the 2D space right this is what I'm plotting here
so every red dots representing a specific model
okay now the entire plane represents all the possible
model you can have right all the possible model parameter space
is this 2D space now we know that the true model
in other words the best optimal model is the bow eye
in the center right you want to make sure your model is close
to the center as much as possible right but very likely you cannot
get it so we're going to see what happened if your bias
and variance varies okay so the first plot
is the case where you have high bias and low
variance okay so what is high bias and low variance
it basically means here right simple model remember
if you have a simple model you have high bias and low variance now
if your model is like too simple you have high bias and low variance
what you will have let's say I learn the same model let's say
you learn it multiple times or maybe here how much time we have
eight times right you will get different models but all of them
will be deviate from your bow eye in a similar way
in other words there could be something shifted to one direction
and this uniform shifting is called a bias
because for example your limit to your model to be linear
right so no matter how much you learn it it will always deviate from the second order
polynomial right and high bias means no matter how
many times you learn it they will be always shifted from the bow eye in a uniform way
alright so this is how you visualize high bias and no variance
and now you can see where the term bias come from because you will have
this consistent deviation from the model themselves
to the optimal model right okay now
the second case is that maybe I can try to
even increase my variance right so
if both my variance and bias are high I will have
a universal shift from my optimal model
plus the model I learn themself will be very different from
time to time remember every time when you sample differently
you will get different noise right and those different noise could affect your model
in a different way so high variance basically means
if you learn the model let's say 10 times with different kind of sampling
I will have all the learned model to be different from each other
on top of a universal shift
so this is what if you visualize the high variance case that's what
you will have alright now another
of course we want to have the best case which is low bias and low variance
if you have low bias and no variance that means all of the sample will be concentrated very closely
at the bow eye and themselves will be very similar
so this is like low bias and low variance case now if you
have a complex model means here that's the case
where you have low bias but high variance now in this case
all of this learned model even though they are concentrating
very close to the center but due to the fact that they will be very
easily affected by the noise themselves will be quite separate
from each other so that means you will have certain
variance if you sample your training data differently
so these cover the four scenarios if you want to visualize them in this 2D plot
and hope they give you some idea like first where does the bias
and variance come from secondly if you want to visualize them
how do they look like in the 2D space
alright so think about it let's take a 15 minutes break
and come back with the following up content
if you have questions I'm happy to take answers during the break
come back around 10.50
.