Hello class. Okay, so we are in week three now. So this is our finalized class size,
I guess. Okay, so from this week, this is the things we want to cover. Okay, so basically
we are removed into the third week now. So we want to further discuss about the heuristics
to design heuristics with an example. Of course, we cannot really, probably we can only get
a very, very basic idea of setting evaluation or actually based on the information we are
given and then try our best to come up with the embedded our skills and the experience
and then try to set the ideal, I mean the best we can make the kind of estimations or
actually evaluations for each of the states. And then with that heuristics, we can actually
hopefully can help us to find the answer, find the goal state within the effort, I mean
within the efficiency given efficiency time and memory possible consumptions. Okay, so
those are the things we want to finish off. So that means under the informed search, we
look into the heuristics again and then also we look at is there any other way? I mean,
we know the heuristics most likely is a kind of indicator or come up with a rule of functions
and try to see based on the current state, any of the current state end, how to get the
figure or get the value to indicate how much effort or how what's the cost or what's the
fitness to reach one of the goal. Okay, so how to evaluate that value, right? So that
is suppose that rule or that kind of function or that kind of indicator can be applied it
to every state in this search space. Okay, so this is the things we are talking about. So
it's talking about from current state end to one of the goal. Okay, so that is a value. But
what about from the starting state, right from the starting state to the current state? Is
there anything we can do? So of course, one simple thing we can do is we can actually
consider the depth, right? Consider how far away from the starting state. So that is the
depth. Okay, so that is the things we want to take that into consideration. So that actually
introduce a kind of thing which is we so far we don't see in the even backtrack or in the
depth first, whatever is also search actually we are best first search. We never really
mentioned about actually the state can repeat, right? We actually say we did mention in the
best first search we already said if now reaching the same state from a different pass, say
better shorter pass, then probably we can reconsider that state again, right? So that is
something we want to take that into consideration. That's why we talk about the GN. Okay, so
that is the try to evaluate the pass from starting state to each of the current state end. You
can call X or whatever. Yeah, that is each of the states. So that's why we want to have these
two parts. One is to measure the pass from the starting state to the current state. Then
another heuristic value is to talk about from current state to the goal state. Okay, so
we add these two together called FN or FX for each of the states end. So that is the
thing we can have. And then we can distinguish the best first search with or without the
G. Okay, so then we say, okay, one is called greedy, another one is called best first search.
So the greedy one probably you don't consider the G. Okay, then you, the actual best first,
you probably consider the G. Okay, and then best first search. And then also we have another
one is a A star. Okay, so that is another search algorithm. So again, impose a condition
to the H. Okay, so if the H satisfies certain condition, then we say this is a A star search.
Okay, so that is something we want to finish off. And then the last two lectures, we want
to cover the gaming, the algorithm, which is more suitable for game, not just for search
for answer. Okay, so the difference is search for answer seems the answer is always there.
You just try to find the answer. But the game is also depends on the opponent. Okay, so
it depends on how you play and also depends on how your opponents respond. Right, then
based on that, you develop a probably different kind of subspace. So how to actually find
answer from there. So that's the algorithm we want to introduce. Actually, we basically
just introduce one, which is a mini max, but alpha, the alpha beta pruning actually is
a better version of the mini max. So basically, it's just we don't want to exhaustive search
the entire tree, the game tree. Okay, so hopefully we can actually cut off certain branches.
So those branches, we can no need to explore at all. So we can cut off. Okay, so that is
two algorithm we are going to go through. And then of course, we will support with examples.
And then we will have exercises. Okay, so for this exercise, I think we cannot cover
today in the class. So again, we do it next week. Okay, oh, sorry, actually even not next
week, because next week we have to focus on discussion about data mining. Okay, so I will
use the last lecture in the week five, one hour only for me. Okay, then I will discuss
exercises. Okay, so this is the arrangement. Any quick question? Okay, I know you are probably
asking have we fixed the date for the quiz yet? Not yet. Okay, yeah, so one thing is
most likely, most likely that's no chance for us to squeeze in week five. Okay, so that
is a good news for many of you probably because week five, I heard some of you actually have
another quiz. So the good thing is most likely will be in week six Saturday. Okay, but I
still cannot get the confirmation yet because we have very big class and then venue and
then invigilator and that is all need to be settled. Okay, so likely, likely week six
is not week five anymore. It's week six Saturday. Okay, but still waiting, still waiting.
Just before come here, I actually chat with the team again with the OISIS team. They still
no answer. Okay, so but likely, yeah, so week five schedule can be updated. Okay, so it's
week six likely. And also the grouping, I think you don't know the project now, but
what project you're going to do or whatever that is. Okay, but just you can informally
have a group first and then later when the information available, then you can quickly
share on the Google documents. Okay, so we still want to ask ourselves why we need to
have heuristics. Okay, so although it's a bit silly question, but we still want to say,
okay, so basically we only have a very limited information. So definitely one heuristic could
be better than another one. Okay, in a way it's like better informed or actually it's
like a better embedded our skills or with limited information. Okay, so that's why sometimes
you have many ways to design your heuristics and then some can lead to failure or some
actually can work and some can be more efficient and so on. So that is hopefully we have a
way to do it and then we can make use of this score or this rule or this kind of indicator
and then try to apply like best first search or eight star search. This is a key idea.
Okay, so we have a little bit of discussion about different heuristics for the same problem.
Okay, so same this game that we can see. Okay, so this is a puzzle again. So we want to,
suppose starting from here, this is our goal state. Okay, so this is a goal state. So it's
sorted number the tau in this around the site. Okay, so the empty tau is in the middle.
So that's how to actually, I mean, there are various ways to come up with a heuristic value.
Okay, so this is the way we try to see. Okay, so example here, we show you three ways to
work out the heuristic, I mean to be used as a heuristic indicator. Like the first one
is the, okay, I put it here actually. Okay, so the first one is to count the tau out of
place, okay, out of the space. So it looks like that is our each one. Okay, each two
is a second heuristic design is to count the total sum. Okay, so it's a sum of distances
out of space. Okay, so here is a distance, distance measure. Okay, you can use Euclidean
distance or you can use the Hermetin distance or any distance. Okay, so suppose we are using
this way to calculate distance, then that is the each two we are talking about. Okay,
then each three is to have a heuristic set like this. Say we use two, multiply with a
number of the direct tau reverse. Okay, this is a reversed order. If we can reverse it,
become, they are in the order that that means that's done. Okay, that is considered as one
and then we can multiply by two and count this total. Okay, so this is the each three.
So, so, so this, let's look at this example. So we have this starting from here. So this
is our goal state and let's look at if we use each one, so that is a counter number
of tau which is outer place. So the one actually supposed to be here. Right, so it's outer
place, right, because one is here now. So one is out place, two, two is out place as
well, two is here, two supposed to be here. So two is out place. Three in the right place,
four right place, five right place, six. Okay, oh sorry, sorry, six outer place, right, seven
outer place, eight outer place. Okay, so that's why that's how we get the five based on the
first heuristic. Okay, based on the second one, heuristic actually use Manhattan distance.
So that means you work out the difference between x and difference between y and x together.
Right, so let's look at the one actually the x is one away, right, the, oh sorry, x is
the same, yeah, it's in the same x and then y is one away. So that means it's a zero
plus one, right, so that's why it's one. So we have one for the number, the tau number
one, for the number two, yeah, it's also one, right, yeah, one away, you see, this is,
suppose the position is here, okay, so three, okay, four, okay, five, okay, six, one away,
yes, seven, one away, yeah, eight, two, yeah, this way, this way, okay, so that's why you
get six. So this is a calculation, I mean, indicator you can use, so you see, different
age, different heuristic, I mean, different rules give you a different value and then
this value later will be used to make decision, right, so which one actually give you a better
way to guide us to find the answer, definitely the heuristic value is very important, right,
so probably more skilled player, you have a better way to design this and to feel which
is better, okay, the third one, yeah, let's go through the third one, so the third one,
yeah, we want to multiply, the two, multiply the number, get directly flipped, okay, so
one and two, can we directly flip, it's not in the position, you can flip but it's still
not in the right place, right, for both, yeah, so two also, yeah, one and two, and three,
nothing, no change, and six, okay, six and seven can flip and six will be in the right
place but seven is not, right, so eight also, no, so zero, nothing multiplied by two, so
that's why it's still zero, okay, so this is what we want to show you, with a different
way, actually, that is a careful design of the heuristic is very important, okay, yeah,
so in order to show you something, I just create something like this, so suppose we
have the seven and the six like this, so you flip this one, and, oh sorry, one and two,
you flip, yeah, so reverse it, then you have the right position, one, two in the right
position, all the rest is still not, so this one give us some value, okay, but yeah, this
can be updated if I arrange it this way, right, correct, one will be out of place, two will
be out of place, three, four, five, six, seven out of place, eight out of place, so it's
four, right, so this is four for each one, and then this is five, we can work out based
on the head and the distance, right, okay, so this is an example to show us of that,
so the key point is to design this is not trivial at all, right, to design the heuristics
for each of the problem, also very, very much problem dependent, I need a lot of skills
and experience and then a plan, and basically you need to reinvent it, okay, it's not like
somebody just tell you, okay, and nothing like, okay, this can be applied for everything
at all, right, so probably need to reinvent it based on the problem, invent it accordingly,
okay, so that's why we are saying the conventional symbolic AI, the designer is very, very important,
right, okay, so that is the most important thing and also to say something about how challenging
it is, so basically only limited information available and also hopefully this single rule
or single formula or single describer or discriminator that can be applied to every state, right,
so help us to make an intelligent selection and then can lead us to find a goal, right,
so this is very much skill-based, experience-based and empirical problem and depends on the
problem, depends on the skills, depends on the information available, depends on the
memory size, for example, yeah, because especially for those game tree you can look ahead many
steps if you have a very huge memory, can hold those states, then your information's relatively
rich compared to somebody which only can say, you can only look ahead two levels, compared
to another person you can look ahead 20 steps, right, so then your heuristic value probably
the way you design heuristics will be very different, so hopefully they will lead you
more successful rather than failure, so that's what we are talking about, okay, so just now
we said, yeah, other than the heuristic value, another important thing is to see how much,
how far away from the starting state, right, so we want to take that into consideration,
so that is the GN we are talking about, that is to say the cost we spend to take this path
to this particular state, so taking this path that means starting from the starting state
to reach this current state if you have more than one way, right, because it's a game graph
actually, it's not really a tree, right, actually it's a graph, so the graph you, we are talking
about you can reach the same states from different passes, more than one passes, right, so then
which path is shorter, which path is longer, we should take that cost into consideration
as well, okay, so that's the back counting, take that into consideration, so the evaluation
function, actually we are not just purely talking about the hint to guide us from current state
to the goal, but also we talk about overall cost, overall evaluation, that is taking the
GN into consideration as well, okay, starting state to the current state, so that is the
path cost, so that is the cost from initial state to the current state, or measure the
actual length of the path, okay, so that is the depth count, and then the H is still from
the current state to the goal state, okay, so this is knowledge, hopefully the skills
we have, we can evaluate that, so we add these two together, and then become our overall
evaluation function, then whatever best first search, or eight star search, okay, since we
talk about best first search, and then eight star search, actually here is the only thing
different from the others, is this H, the Hersey value here is always admissible, okay,
so meaning, what is the meaning of it, meaning this value is always less than or equal to
the actual cost from the current state to the goal state, okay, so you always underestimate
the cost, okay, so in a way it's like you always underestimate, so for example, for example,
compared to just now, this H1, H2, H3, which one you think is underestimate? H3, can you
say H3? It needs to be true for every state, okay, so that's not just true for some state,
but not true for other states, these have to be applied for every end, every state's end,
okay, so H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3, H3,
okay, so H1, yeah, H1, why? Yeah, actually the cost is underestimate, right, because we are talking
about, we only consider as 1, 1, you see, tau out of place, so you only count 1, but how
other place can be very far away from the actual place, at least is 1, right, at least
1, at least 1 away, or in x direction, or 1 away from y direction, or actually it's far
away, right, so you only count 1, so isn't it underestimate, right, underestimate the cost,
so if t is, then this is called the H, actually the H, the way we estimate the cost is called
admissible, okay, so this is, so it's not larger than the actual real cost, so if that is how
you design your H, then actually that can make the best first search, find the answer
with the optimal answer, if you can find it, okay, so this is a good thing, that's why
we call it A star, okay, so that is a concept, and so here I want to revisit about the best
first search, okay, so now best first before, now we didn't emphasis so much about the evaluation
function, actually it consists of two parts, right, we just go through the algorithm, but
in the algorithm we say, okay, if this is reach this state, if reach this state, the current
line, we reach this state by a shorter path, then we can actually update the open, right,
update the open list, or even we dig out the list, the states, in the closed list already
we dig them out and put into the open, remember, yeah, why, because this part, okay, because
this part, so actually the best first search we introduce the algorithm already take this
into consideration, okay, we say we revisit the state, if it's already appear before,
but before let's go through a longer path, reach that, then we should revisit it, if
the current one is shorter path, okay, remember that is the one, okay, and then so basically
that's a key thing, so if we don't consider the G, don't consider the cost from very beginning
state to the current state, then probably we call it greedy, a bit greedy, we miss out
some information basically, okay, so that is what we are saying, okay, greedy best first
search, so basically use heuristics close to the target as a key guide, okay, we don't
really consider the cost from starting state to the current state, okay, then you can call
it greedy, and then the A star, okay, so basically very similar, it's just a slightly constrained,
okay, the difference is a subtle difference, so we take this into consideration, that means
actually we want to get, if there is an answer, we try to have the answer which is close to
the starting state, as close to the starting state as possible, right, so as close to the
starting state as possible, that means actually we are doing the BFS rather than DFS, right,
we want this to be close to the starting state, so that's the thing, and also we know the
H here, so if the H is always under SMA, then it's the A star, okay, so it's a combination
of these two, actually very much like a best first search, I mean close related to the
best first search, it's all about evaluation, then from the evaluation, then how do you pick
the best, and then from the best, you also keep the other candidates, you don't throw
them away, and then you can expand the open and the closed, you know, checking, okay,
so this is A star, so this is more details about the A star, so the H and here need to
be admissible, okay, so that means this, for each of this H, each of the H and all, that
means all of the N, all of the states in this state space, you satisfy this condition,
the H star here actually indicate the actual true cost, the actual true cost, okay, so
we always less or equal to the true cost, so if that's the case, then that is, you can
get the optimal answer, okay, so this is the condition, you need to be careful about this,
this is admissible, and then we actually have to stick to that, when we try, when we design
the heuristic value, we try our function or formula, we try to do that, and then that
will guide us to find the optimal answer if we can find it, okay, okay, now let's look
at the example, so we still use this A puzzle, and then, so the GN, this is starting state,
so that's why the GN is level zero, right, so it's zero, and then the next one is one
step away from the starting state, and then two steps starting from the starting state,
then it's a GN equal to two and so on, okay, so here, now the evaluation function actually
we can consider both, so this is value, so the original one, we can count, like here,
probably we use which one, are we using the first each one, let's see, so one out of
space, two out of space, three, four, five, six out of space, seven out of space, eight
out of space, so it's five, five plus this G, so that's why the value is six, right,
so this is how you get it, how you get it, yeah, so the overall actually is F now, so
F is two components, one is G, one is H, okay, so let's see, yeah, so the first one is
we have the H value, sorry, we have the G value listed here, so this is how far away from
the starting state, so zero, then one, then two, and so on, and then we have, this is
our starting, and the goal state is still the same, we actually have the tiles around
the site, so then we can actually have the value, then we add this G, so this is become
six, okay, so can we quick check, one out of space, two out of space, then six, seven,
eight, right, five, plus one, that's why F here, F is six, okay, similarly you do this
calculation, so yeah, then even the C, do we have something exactly same, but the G
is different, then we can, do we see anything which is exactly same state, but with the
G we have a different value, not really here, huh, okay, so you can see based on the, based
on the value, then we actually choose the best first, right, we are using the best first
search, so you can see this is, the option we have is six, four, and six, right, so which
one we are taking, this is the cost, so the lower the better, right, so we sort it, and
then this is the best, so we get this one, and then expand the children, so this is not
a goal yet, so their children will be evaluated, I mean those are the children generated, and
then you get the F value for each of these, so this is a five, five, and six, okay, so
we need to sort it, what are the, in the open now, what are the states in the open list
now, are you able to run, this one, this one, this one, this one, this one, this one, this
one, this, this, this, and this, yes, in the open, yeah, then you choose the best, we should
start, and then the best one on the left most, right, so you have a six, five, five, six,
six, and then the five is the best, so you get this one, so then you, it's the children
of this one, so children of this one, because we only have these two, and then the six was
there, five was there, six was there, six was there, five and seven, right, in the open,
so then you choose the best, so you move here, yes, and then five, then expand, so among
all, this is a five, seven, six, and six, six, and five, right, so, so you get the best,
ah, so we actually can select this five, but suppose we select this five, is there any
reason I can select this five, not really, so suppose it's just lucky, we select this
one, because they are identical, and even I say alphabetical could be here, right, because
this is F, E, right, this is I, okay, so actually I can end up this side, but suppose I'm
ending random, take one of it, you know, out of the, with the same value, I take the same
one, I randomly pick one, so I'm lucky I took this one, and then I have these two, expand
it, so then you have a five, seven, seven, six, six, six, and five there, so I'm lucky
again, take this five, then I find the answer, yeah, so this is, this is the high, this is
how we make use of the evaluation function, with the best first search, we actually find
the goal, with how many steps are, with this path, okay, that is exactly the number, the
states we evaluated, do you still remember how to do this with the best first search,
or that first search, BFS, DFS, how many steps we actually had to go through, this picture,
oh, sorry, this is something we just run it, okay, so yeah, in the beginning, remember
the best first search, we have open and closed list, so starting state put in, so that is
our A4, and then the children, so these three, BCD, now BCD with the value, we don't care
insert into the open from which side, but we sort it, right, so sorting, that's why
we get the C4, and then C4 was evaluated, so it's not the goal yet, then you have to
expand the children of the C4, that's why we have an EFG there, and EFGH add-in, and
it's happened to be, yeah, then I actually checked the E, oh, I checked the E, okay,
oh, actually I did check the E, okay, I did check the E, so those children actually also
in the open, okay, so it's the children, the H and J was added as well, yeah, was added,
H and L, right, yeah, so they were added, so these are how we actually go through, okay,
so total just the seven steps, we find the answer, let's see how that was a memory used,
right, so this is the first one, then those, the light blue, see the light blue, light
blue, light blue here, those are the things in the closed list, sorry, in the open list,
this is the darker one, this is lighter one, okay, darker one was those actually in the
closed list, when we actually finished checking this few, these three, okay, so that's how
we get the answer, and that was the one, we use BFS, oh, sorry, this is the one we actually
get the answer, right, yeah, so in the end, this is how we reach these states, okay,
so I put the three together, so this is 46 steps using the BFS, BFS, 31, and this one,
7, right, so of course heuristic definitely will help, that's why we need to have a heuristic
in the search, we cannot do the exhaustive search, right, but the how to design with
the idea, how to actually have a very good way to estimate the cost that is challenging
and problem dependent, okay, okay, do you have any quick questions regarding this part?
Then another example, okay, because the first example so far I just showed you, I just showed
you, with the help of heuristics, actually we can find the answer much quicker, right,
so that is critical if you have limited time and also limited memory space, if you want
to find the answer, especially for those very challenging games like Go, right, so even the
toy problem we can see the difference, then what about just now we say the A star, okay,
the A star or just greedy best first search, how this can be applied for this finding,
you know, the past, okay, so let's look at this map and together with some information
about the distance of their actual mileage or actual road you need to drive, okay, to
reach one place to another, so this is the number you indicate on the map is actually
that I would say just actual probably the road, the distance, okay, and then we have
this information here is the heuristic value, this is the straight line distance, okay,
so from each of the city here like A, like B to the goal, goal probably is their capital,
so this is the Budapest, Buda rest, okay, so this is the B, so of course itself to itself
is zero and then from the arat to this place is the km miles, okay, and then so we are
using greedy best first search that means we don't consider the G, okay, actually we
starting from this place, they are right and then we want to reach the bug rest, okay,
so from the A to the B, okay, so the red line is I just added to help us visualize this
value here, okay, so you see this is not the distance we add up from one place to go through
some places to go through some cities and to reach this goal state, okay, so it's a suppose
that is a direct line, although that is probably don't have such road, right, it's just in the
map measure a direct distance, so that is the one provided here, so it just indicate one
for us so we know the like from C to the distance of, I mean C to B is 160, so C where is C,
okay, from here, so the direct distance is this, okay, although probably that's no, it's
a mountain there so it's no way for you to drive through, okay, but this is what we have
here, okay, so now let's use this map together with this very ideal hn, okay, and then we
are going to use a greedy best search, best first search to find the path from A to B,
okay, so how should we start? Starting from starting states, right, A, yes, from here,
then what about the branches of A? Go states is here, huh, yeah, so what are the possible
next moves? How many? Three, yeah, so one is this one, this one, this one, yeah, so we
have Z, then we have S, then we have T, right, so you can have the three branches and then
we can label them with the distance, okay, so that is the one, we expanding, that's a
legal one, right, we have, it's possible, we can move to expand to here, expand to this
city, expand to this city, and then what is this value here?
How do we get this value? From, we only use h, right, did we use g? No, that's why we
get directly from here, so yeah, confirm S, S where is S, yeah, this is S, right, yeah,
so this is the value, h value, h value, h value, okay, so then best first search, which
one we should pick? This is a cost, so the lowest, lowest is the best, right, okay, so
lowest, yes, that's why we should expand this one, so expand this one, then we draw, what
are the things, next one for this, after you reach this place for the S, then we can
have O, then we have F, then we have RV, right, yeah, so another tree expanded, and then for
each of these, look for that h value, then we can label the, that is our h value, and
based on that, we sort it again, then see which city to be expanded again, right, okay,
so that's what we did, the 1234 actually, and then, oh yeah, this one, don't forget,
we can actually go back, all right, now we are here, so this is both direction, so you
can actually have another way back to here, yeah, so that is, and then we choose the best,
okay, because this value now is, we updated from this table, right, so it's not, you
can still appear, you see, exactly same, but have a different h value, then this one,
expanded, and so on, okay, I think you get it, so this is, get it, expanded, so we are
here, oh sorry, we are here, and then we have this way, or you are all the way to reach
the goal, and so, so we find it, okay, so then where's the total distance from the a to
b, since we actually, we go this way, this way, and this way, is that, so we add up,
this is 450, okay, then what about if we, so I highlighted by this yellow color, that
is the path we actually can reach from a to b, then what if we go, we are using the,
we are using the both, okay, we are using the best first, not great, but we are using
the best first, okay, we are using the best first, and then we actually still want to use
this, okay, also, that is a straight line, and then this one, I'm not sure whether this
is really a, probably safer to say, is a distance, okay, because I'm not sure, okay,
whether this is really a straight line, they didn't say anything about that really,
yeah, so I feel probably safer to say the distance, because that is only indicate the level,
so from the starting state, okay, so, yeah, so very much the same thing we want to apply,
but it's just an evaluation function now, you have two values, okay, so we need to take
the gn into consideration as well, okay, so that is how do we do it, yeah, so basically,
previously we only use this h, now we need to have the gn as well, okay, so for the
gn, we know from here, we know from here to this, this is a distance, right, distance,
so we just add this into that, to be the total value for this note, that is an evaluation
value for this, and this, and this, how we get it, okay, then based on this, the best
value is still this one, right, so this one should be expanded, yeah, so this is a full
value, similarly, we know how we get it, how do we get it, 280 here, gn, gn, from starting
state to this particular state, so starting state to this state is from here to here,
then here, right, so 1,4,0 plus 1,4,0, okay, so that's how we get it, okay, so remember,
the definition is from starting state to the current state, okay, so that's why it's
two times, because starting state come to here, then reach the current state, right,
so it's two times, so that's how we get it, okay, so yeah, also look at this, how you
get it, and we know how to expand, and this is how we expand it, so this is how we actually
get the answer, looks like, yeah, we go several different places, we expand this one, then
we get this, and then we actually come to this side, and then, because, best first, but
not, the other candidate is still there, right, so we can still find the best after, I mean,
after we expand, we find this is not the right one, then we go this branch, and then we expand,
and then we go here, and then we find this is a shelter, oh, sorry, initially go there,
yeah, then we come here, so we find this is better, okay, so this is the actual venture,
so now, this give us a total distance, this is the one, okay, so it's better than using
the greedy best first search, why, why this is better, one thing is we take the G into
consideration, then the most important one is the HN, right, the HN actually is the direct
distance, so the direct distance can be, the actual cost can be, the actual cost can be,
higher, yeah, than the direct value, right, yeah, that's why, okay, so that's all for
this part, I think we are done with this, for, to highlight the difference between like
use greedy or versus the A star, or just actually sometimes it's, people also call it A star,
but the A star is without the H become the admissible, okay, so if it is, then we can
find the optimal answer, otherwise cannot, okay, but you can see the still, the big issue
is, can run out the memory, right, so the memory requirement, time requirement is still very,
very high, so, so, although even you have a good heuristic value, but you don't have
the space to hold, all the candidates, right, and also you have problem to wait for so long,
so that is a thing, so it's still not very practical for very large scale problem, okay,
so that is the main issue, okay, so yeah, I think your turn to have, to do something,
okay, so the exercise, we went through the example already, so now you try the exercises,
okay, then we hand run this, it's a very small problem, very simple one, exercise, so one
is to run this, then two is to have, it's something about the concept, okay, so sometimes
there's no evaluation function available, okay, for a particular problem, but that's
a good comparison method, can be applied, okay, so in a way it's a ruler, so a way to
tell if a note is better than another, so you can compare, okay, without actually assign
their numerical values, so is this good enough to do best for search, okay, so that's the
concept, then lastly, yeah, just to, starting from this state, so this is a goal state,
okay, so you see the A puzzle problem, we are not sorting around the site, but we actually
are sorting line by line, okay, a row by row, so that's a goal state, so we want you to
have two H to work out, what is the value for it, okay, so yeah, very, very simple question,
okay, so spend some time on this, and then we can quickly check answer, or you can have
a toilet break now, so maybe 10 minutes, 10 minutes, enough for this exercise, okay,
work on this first, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of
10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes,
okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay,
so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so
we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we
have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have
a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total
of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10
minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes,
okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay,
so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so
we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we
have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so we
have a total of 10 minutes, okay, so let's go through this together, so you see,
because the two things we need to pay attention to from the question, this set is
So that is a hand run.
And then we are using the greedy best first search.
Starting notes is A. Goal states is O.
So we want to reach here.
We want to reach here.
Starting from A. And then the H value was attached.
Do we need to consider the G for greedy?
No, right.
So we don't care about the level.
That means we don't care how far from the starting states.
So we just use this.
But we do notice that actually more than one pass
can lead to one note.
So that is something.
If we are hand run this for best first search
or greedy best first search or A star or whatever.
Although just now I showed you the example,
try to, especially about the map,
actually we try to base on the map
to see how the tree is spanned.
But it's actually good to have.
Actually it's good to just look at the open and closed list.
What's wrong with this side?
22.
OK, so let's look at this.
We have open and then closed list.
And then step zero is a starting state.
Closed have nobody.
And then we check the A is not the goal.
So the children put in.
OK, then together with the H value.
So after you add into the list, then we sort it.
We're sorting.
And then the best one on the left most.
Because this is cost, so the lower the better.
That's why B is the first element.
And then sort the rest.
Then we take the left most.
Evaluate this one.
So B, to check whether B is the goal.
B is not goal yet.
Then children of the B. So children of the B,
these other children of the B, should be added.
So this is the F, M, G, H will be added.
And then we sort it.
So we're sorting with everybody here in the list.
So we have M, the best on the left.
OK, so basically we just do like this.
And then followed by next one is children of the.
So M is not the goal yet.
Then the children is the N. So the N should be added
into the open.
And then children have the one, value one.
So N will be the next.
I cannot.
I have to do like this.
OK, I know my I just cancel this.
Cover all the way.
So you see the N coming.
Then the rest is still from the previous one, the sorted there.
N was checked.
N is not the goal yet.
N have no children.
Then N throw into the closed.
Then H. OK, then H also.
Any children for H?
Yes, H have N, but N already appear before.
Although we are reaching the N in the same path, same length.
But we are not adding anymore.
So based on the best first search actually.
No need to add.
So the rest, and then H was checked.
Then G was checked.
F had children.
F children L, M. Then M was reached before,
was shorter than current.
So M shouldn't add in.
And then the L was added.
L then sorted.
So this is sorting.
And then we go.
So this is how we reach the answer.
OK, so this is a hand run of this best first search.
Any question?
Then of course, slightly more comprehensive would be,
I give you a heuristic value.
I mean, I give you an evaluation function.
And I ask you to do it together with,
either greedy or not greedy.
The best first search.
Consider the G as well.
And then you need to every step evaluate it.
The F function, F value.
And then apply the best first search accordingly.
Also can run manually for toy problem, for example.
Can do it?
Or as you, yeah, either greedy, that means no G.
If it's not greedy, then have the G.
And this will be your extra exercise.
Extra homework later.
Oh, have you done the extra exercise for last week?
I forgot to mention to your group,
HAI makes that available last week, Friday.
So you have extra exercise for extra homework one.
But it's not really assessive.
No need to be assessed.
And also no discussion about that.
The solution will be available.
Have I made the available already?
I forgot.
It's until you learn the course website.
So just check that.
So for my part, actually, you do have extra exercise,
just for your practice only.
It's not for CA components.
But be careful.
Prof loan and Prof time part, they are homework
will be assessed.
OK.
OK, so this one, any question?
So this is exercise one in this topic.
Exercise two, assess this one.
So is that OK?
Do we always have FX function and how to evaluate the H,
for example?
Is this H have to be calculated?
Have to have a formula or some specific rule?
Or can we just have a comparison?
Is that OK to do the best first search?
OK.
Why is it OK?
Yeah.
We only need to know best.
We only need to know the rank.
So as long as we can rank them, we know how to pick the best.
And from the pick the best, then we know the children.
And the children also can rank them
with all their siblings, or their uncles,
grandparents, grand uncles, basically can rank.
So as long as you can rank them, then we can decide which one.
OK, so the question two is easy.
Question three, what is the value?
So this is the current state.
This is the goal state.
So we are using H1.
First heuristic function is to work out
number of the misplaced tiles.
So what's the value?
This is the current one.
This is the goal state.
One out of space.
One is here.
One should be here.
One out of place.
Two out of place.
No.
Two is here.
So in the right place.
Three out of space.
Three out of the place.
Three.
OK, three.
Four.
Five.
Out.
Six.
Six, OK.
Seven.
Out.
Eight.
So we get the value.
OK.
Then another one is use Manhattan distance.
You know how to calculate, right?
OK, great.
So that's all.
So this is what we are saying, the second one.
And yeah, so we just, oh, yeah, for this one,
we need to calculate now.
So Manhattan distance.
So the one is here.
So basically, we have to go one, two, three, four.
So that's why four.
Then two.
Two is OK.
Two is zero.
Three.
Three is here.
Three is one, two, three.
So three.
For four, for five, for six.
Six, OK.
Yeah, then seven, eight.
So you get 14.
That's for second one.
First one is equal to six.
Correct?
Yeah, no need to take picture.
This exercise solution will be provided.
It's available tomorrow.
Tomorrow after the undergrad course.
OK, so we are done with this part A. Part A is about use
heuristics to search.
OK, so we go through the best first search algorithm.
And then also introduce the idea of the greedy.
OK, greedy best first.
Basically, we are not taking the G into consideration.
And then if we take both, also the H
have some special constraint that make the H always
underestimate the cost.
Then that is a very good one that
is can find the optimum answer.
Then we will call this special best first as A star.
So this is admittable the meaning of it.
So that must be always for each of the states.
Cannot be for all of each of the states.
The heuristic value is always less than or equal
to the actual cost.
So if that's the case.
OK, that's all for this.
Then we can move on to the second half
of this topic, which is about heuristics, which
is about the gaming.
So we already know, OK, for setting heuristics,
it's really a big effort plus experience, plus skills.
And then try to come up with discrimination,
rules, equations to evaluate the best possibility
of reaching the goal.
We can actually successfully reach the goal.
So to find the question, find the answer,
and then improve the performance.
So for the gaming, as we said, we have opponents.
So it's an adversary.
So we need to have consider how the opponents play.
And then we will play accordingly.
So that's why we not just totally search passively,
search for answer.
So that's an important thing.
So for the game tree, then we have
to use this minimizer, which tries to minimize the cost.
So select the most lowest possible value to move towards.
And then maximizer is always put, select the best value
out of his children.
So that is a different strategy.
So we go for this minimax search and the pruning.
So the difference between just passively search for answer
and the one is a game.
So as we said, the key thing is we have opponents.
Also the time constraint.
Most likely, you cannot go forward many steps
in order to predict what your opponents will do,
how you react, then how your opponent do again
until you reach the final stage.
So it's very hard with a given time.
So that's why the time limit and also the depends
on your opponent's reaction.
So that's why it's really kind of we
can only based on the limited information
and try to find the best possible approximation
and the best optimal and suboptimal answer, for example.
And also the game is like although we know the rules,
we know how to play, but not everybody can play well.
So that is kind of intelligent activity.
We are not talking about carry out some routine job.
Just follow the rules.
Everything will be done successfully.
It's not talk about that.
It's a challenging issue.
Although we know the rule, but every minute,
you probably have decision making.
You have to make decision.
You have to decide which pass you are going to follow.
So you see those play, goal play.
You have so many options.
So which pass you are going to follow.
So this is if we can ignore the code, the program,
or the agent with the ability of such kind
of intelligent decision making and movement,
that means actually they have the intelligence.
So that is actually if you have this ability, that means,
especially if the ability is so powerful
and they can actually win or beat human,
that indicates the intelligent level they will have.
So that's why design game is interesting
to show artificial intelligence.
Artificial, because we actually try to,
the kind of intelligence is given by the designer
to the agent, and then hopefully agent
can make best use of this and try to achieve
some activities or tasks which needs
a so-called intelligence.
Okay, so the game, that's why we are talking about,
for the player, for example, if here is a maximizer player,
that means actually he want to choose the best value
from his candidates.
The try to get the best out of this.
Like for example, you are looking for a job
and then you have many options, offers for you,
and then you probably choose the best offer.
So you are a maximizer, maximized the best opportunity,
like the highest salary, you take that offer.
But what about your company, what about the employer?
Okay, so they have many candidates.
So they try to offer the lowest value,
as lowest salary as possible for the profit.
So you see the difference, so maximizer, minimizer.
So you are the maximizer, you try to get the opportunity
out of those offers, and then your employer
will be trying to actually try to give as little,
they want to have the best profits as possible,
so they want to cut salary.
So this is get the minimum out of it.
Okay, so then it's your turn to make decision again.
So it's like this.
Okay, so it's not totally like a game,
but it's in a way you try to maximize the opportunity,
you can win, and then your opponents try to minimize
the opportunity you can win.
So then he can actually have a chance.
So this is what we are talking about.
Okay, so if this game, we can really hold the whole thing.
So we have plenty space to hold all the possible states
like this, so this is if this is an entire game tree.
This is an entire game tree or game space we are having.
Then isn't it easy?
You know, we already have, this is winning
the final goal state already.
Each of these have a value attached with it,
like the particular cost or profits you have.
And then you say who the parents is this maximizer
or minimizer, so you just take the value accordingly.
Okay, so if I have a utility value or a evaluation value
already attached to each of these notes, terminal notes,
okay, then I just backwards, right?
So depends my parents, is this a maximizer?
If it's a maximizer, I will select the best
out of these children, right?
Then I have the utility value accordingly for this level.
Then for the next level, they will take,
this is a minimizer, so I will select the minimum value
out of my parents, out of my children, right?
So in that way, you can all the way feedback to here,
then you know what to do, which path to go, right?
So easy, problem can be solved.
But what's the issue?
Space and time, right?
So we don't have the space to hold all the possible branches,
all the possible states.
So this is the ideal case, but far away from reality, right?
So that is the issue.
So is there any alternative idea?
Okay, before we ask ourselves whether it's an alternative
idea, but we can think, okay, how to make use of this
mini max to play with a given depth, for example, okay?
Cannot entire until everything went, but we can actually
look ahead two or three steps.
And then based on that, we consider that is a terminal
node, sorry, and then we can actually use evaluation function
to evaluate what's the value, and then we backwards
to see what's the best path you can go.
At least we can do that.
Okay, so that is a mini max.
Let's take a look at this.
We are talking about Tic-Tac-Toe again here.
Okay, so yeah, starting from the empty box,
and then we have nine possible way as a cross player.
Okay, so you have, you put every possible place.
And then the minimizer, I don't know, suppose you are,
whatever I would call it, minimize or maximize,
depends which one you are the one.
And then, so after the cross player finish,
there is a, sorry, this, yes, this is a cross player,
so he plays everything.
And then is a circle player's turn, right?
So he can actually place his circle
with a given box, right?
So many, many place again.
So nine and then eight and so on, right?
So we know that.
Yeah, so this is how they can get the value.
Then this is end, you see?
This is already winning, right?
Who win?
Circle's win, right?
Okay, so circle's already win.
This one, do we have winning?
No winning, right?
So this is a draw, or this is no, no, no, yeah.
So this is a draw case.
And then this one, yeah, diagonal.
So it's a cross win, right?
Okay, so I'm a cross here.
I'm cross here, cross player here,
and then I suppose I'm a maximizer.
So then your utility value, you should set is the best value.
So maximizer one.
You can, if you are winning, then you put the plus one.
If you lose, then you put the minus one.
Or minus one would be the case for minimizer.
Minimizer is a minus one.
And then draw case is zero.
So you can put the utility value like this
to the terminal notes, or terminal states.
Okay, to the terminal states.
So this is what we can show you.
And the H value here probably can be the fitness,
or can be the cost, okay?
So for this case, we probably want to decide
how to decide the evaluation,
how to decide the H fitness.
So basically, game related,
if we treat the game as a search problem,
that means we always have a starting state,
initial state, and we have a goal state,
the terminal state.
And then we have operation, that means a legal movement.
The same thing, this is the same thing as we had
for state space problem solving.
And then we have a utility function.
So that is the one to apply to the terminal states,
the final terminal states.
And then return numerical score to see how well it performs.
So for example, the chess of Tic Tac Toe,
we can use, if the maximizer is a player,
then wing will be plus, minus one is a loss, and so on.
So this can be the one we try to put in this way,
from left to right.
And then you can see those circle one,
is already a terminal state, right?
You see, we have a winning case here,
we have a winning case, we have a winning case, yeah?
You see?
Okay, and then for those terminal states,
you can actually attach with the utility value, for example.
So for cross, yeah, so for example,
this one cross wing, right?
So I should have a plus one here, okay?
And this is a plus one as well.
And we have one which is circle wing.
Here is all cross wing, okay?
So it's not, not, not, not, yeah, it's not.
Okay, so basically that is a terminal state,
then we have how to assign the value.
Okay, so the minimax of working principle
is a bit like exhaustive search on the graph.
Okay, so two person play,
and then the whole movement sometimes is unpredictable,
depends on opponent's movement and actions.
So we assume both players follow the exact same knowledge,
we have the same knowledge and the rules we apply,
and then the minimizer always take the minimal value
out of the children, maximizer always take the maximum
value out of the children.
So that is operation, and then under this assumption,
so we can actually refer this as searching strategy,
is to find sequence of move lead to the terminal state
by apply, you know, minimizer always get the maximum,
oh sorry, minimizer always get the maximum,
if we have the entire space available,
this is a search, you can exhaustive search,
like you can find the answer, okay?
So let's take a look of example.
So this is the subtraction game, okay,
so N-I-M, NIM, okay, so this is,
I think we all played before,
but maybe not using matches,
we probably use even a pile of sand,
you know, try to get the,
get the one, each take turn to play,
and you try to get the sand,
or you try to get the match,
the number of the match, the whole pile of it,
and then you get, and then you try to break, okay,
break into two, you cannot break equally,
the two pile cannot be exactly the same,
have to be different, okay,
so this is, in the end, if none of you can move,
can break further, that means you lose,
so that is the game, right?
Divide a pile of the matches into two,
non-empty and different piles, okay,
so this is the game.
So suppose we starting with seven matches, okay,
so what are the options?
Divide into two, and these two cannot be the same,
so of course easily you can think it's four and three,
right, three or four, four and three,
and then another way, five and two, or six and one, right?
Different divide into two, and cannot be the same,
and also, so those are the possible three way to divide them.
Okay, then next one, next one you can,
can we actually break this one?
No, then we can break this pile, right,
so six can be divided into five and one,
or four and two, can we divide into three, three?
Yeah, not allowed, okay, have to be different,
not empty and not equal, okay,
so three, three is not allowed, you cannot have three, three,
so you cannot have another circle,
and then another state which is a three, three, one, no?
Okay, then this one, similarly,
five can divide into four and one, four and one,
and then two remain as it is, right,
and then another way is five divided into three and two,
yeah, and two remain, so we are doing like this, okay,
and then you see if I reach this state,
can we move further, can we divide further?
Yeah, two, none of the two can be divided into
two not equal piles, right, yeah,
so we have to stop here, so this is one of the gold states,
terminal state, another one, another one, right,
so that's how we reach this state, okay,
so this is a state space we are having, okay,
then suppose we have a way to decide, oh, okay,
okay, I still need to talk about the minimax algorithm first,
so I already said many times, okay, just two players,
one is a minimizer, another one is a maximizer,
so just they share same knowledge
and share the same principle, okay,
so they work together, so if the parent is a maximizer
or max node, then they should give the maximum value
of his children, okay, if the parent is a minimizer
or MIN node, then they should take the minimum value
of his children, so that is the rule they should apply,
and then the value that assign to such states
indicate the value of the best states
the player can hope to achieve, okay,
so in this way they derive the value
and choose among the possible movement,
so that's all the idea, so we are saying just through
this sequence of movement and lead to the terminal states,
okay, yeah, so again, if we put, if no time limit,
no space limit, then this can be achieved,
operate on the entire tree, down all the way to the terminal,
and then we have a way to calculate the utility value
for terminal states, basically assess the utility,
and then determine the best utility of the parents,
so depends on parents, maximizer,
then you take the maximum value among the children,
if the minimizer take the minimum value among the children,
and repeat this process until they reach the root, okay,
so that is the algorithm, so basically then after that,
we select the best move from the beginning to the end,
so that is the ideal case, ideal case,
if no time limit, no space limit, this is what we can do,
in reality, yeah, so it's not possible, right,
so only possibility is we set the depth,
and then based on the depth, we do something like this, okay,
so similarly about this one, this one actually,
we can see the entire space, right,
we can see entire space, but it's just,
it's just to double check again,
so we use this as example to see even with a stand,
we have the whole space,
then how are we going to use a minimax to do this, okay,
so we already see this, how we get this,
and yeah, for example, can you have a link to lead to here,
this one, is that possible, why not possible,
yeah, I'm dividing two, dividing four into two, two, right,
so it's illegal, yeah, is this possible,
similarly, yeah, three, three is not possible,
although I can also, if possible,
I can all draw the link to these states, right,
but it's not allowed, because six cannot divide
into the equal, same size of the two paths,
so this is not possible, okay,
so we know we can lead to this,
and is that possible to have this, not possible, yeah,
two cannot divide to one, one, right,
similarly, this one cannot, okay,
so we have those terminal states,
so now, terminal states we set, okay, do this,
the utility value is very simple,
if max win, we put one, if a mini win, we put zero,
or you like to put the minus, it's also okay,
or if it's a draw, but this one, no way to draw, right,
it's always one of them win, so that's why we can say mini,
we just say zero, it's a mini win,
one is max win, okay, so you see why this one is zero here,
terminal and terminal, we only have three terminal states,
right, so why here put a zero,
look at the top, this is minimizer, maximizer,
minimizer, maximizer, minimizer, maximizer,
so maximizer's turn to play, can he play?
Stuck already, so he lose, right, so who win?
Minimizer win, so should be zero, right,
okay, so you know how to get this zero,
don't ask me about zero yet, this one,
how you get this zero yet, we set the utility value
for the terminal nodes first, okay,
this is not the terminal nodes, right,
this have a children, so this one is a terminal nodes,
this is a terminal nodes, this is a terminal nodes,
none of the others are, okay, only these three,
so we know how to set zero, do we know how to set one,
why this is one here, why this is one,
because, yeah, minimizer's turn, minimizer,
can they play, cannot play, so he lose,
so maximizer win, maximizer win, that means one, right,
okay, so similarly you get zero here,
who win this one, minimizer win, yeah,
because it's a maximizer's turn, maximizer get stuck,
so minimizer win, so that's why we get these three value,
okay, we get these three value,
everybody know how we get it, yes,
okay, now let's do midi max algorithm, okay,
so how to do this, remember the algorithm, here,
okay, so basically create the entire tree
all the way down to the terminal, right,
we did, and then calculate utility, we did, right,
we did for the terminal states first,
and then we had the utility for each of terminal,
we did the first one, then determine the best utility
of the parents from the terminal, okay,
so that means this is the parents of this terminal, right,
and then how to decide this value, why this is zero,
based on the algorithm it said for minimizer,
yes, for minimizer, mini player,
they should select the minimum value among the children,
if the max player, they should select
the maximum value among the player,
so this is what player, minimizer, right,
mini player, mini player, they should select
the minimum value from the children,
how many children he has, only one, right,
so not much choice, he has to choose this is zero,
so if here suppose I suppose I suppose I here,
I have a one, then he should choose one
or select the zero, still select zero, right,
minimum value, okay, that's how he get this value, yes,
okay, then that's how he get zero,
because maximizer select maximum value,
so not much choice, just one, okay,
and this one, that's how we get it,
then what about this one, why this one is zero,
so we do this layer by layer,
we have all the terminal done, then we parents
and parents, grandparents and so on, okay,
so this one, why this one is zero,
this is a minimizer or maximizer, mini, right,
so mini, they should select the minimum value,
what are the options, one is zero, one is one, right,
that's why minimum value is zero,
okay, yeah, so similar layer, do we have another one,
have more than one, okay, so that's why we get one,
yeah, here no option, so this one,
and here you have another option, right, zero and one,
zero and one, this is a maximizer,
that's why you should select the maximum value,
that's how you get one, okay,
and the amount of this children, they are equal to one,
so that's for minimizer, no choice, just get one,
if that is the value here is zero,
then you will get a zero, right, hmm,
okay, get it, so now every note get the utility value,
yes, now after that what to do, you follow the best,
okay, so for this one, I happen to be all one,
so any of it would do, you basically,
you can either choose this one or choose this one,
or choose this one, so suppose I go this way,
and then left, I go, I move to this one,
I decide to choose this one,
and then my opponent, which one I should choose,
should I go this way or should I go this way,
this is the maximizer, maximizer meaning one,
choose the best offer, right, yeah,
so the children one is give you zero,
another one give you one, so of course,
I should go this bunch,
so I should come to this branch,
and then minimize this one, again,
I know choice one branch and then one branch,
and still have a possibility of winning it,
for maximum, maximizer, isn't it,
okay, so what if I come to this way,
then I will go this way, yeah,
so still have possibility of winning,
if I come here, then I also have two,
equally, now take any of it,
so if I come here, then also lead to this way,
okay, so this is basically how,
this example, not very good because
you have a same kind of branch,
you have equal chance to go into one of it,
another example will have better way,
but this one is a complete game tree,
and then we can see how to set
the terminal utility value and then backwards,
to get the utility value for every node,
and then based on that,
you can decide which branch to move to,
okay, so that's a key idea to explain
the mini max algorithm,
okay, ready for another example,
so this one, we want to see the take that toll again,
and now the evaluation function is different,
so the evaluation function here is to use
the possible wing, or the possible fitness,
of the cross player minus the fitness
of the circle player, okay,
so you see, this is my evaluation function,
is m, n minus o, n, m,
stand for the total of my possible wing lines, okay,
then o refer to the opponent's possible wing lines, okay,
so you see the cross is myself,
and o is the opponent's,
and so for example, if you are here,
then how many possibility line of wing,
so one possible two, then three,
then four, then five, then six, right, cross, yeah,
so that's why I have six possible wings,
and then my opponent's, you work out,
it's like one, and two, and three, and four, and five,
right, so five, that's why six minus five,
so if I'm in this stage, my evaluation value
is equal to one, okay, so that is how you evaluate,
so similarly, go check this, this, okay,
so basically, look at this,
so this is utility, if now, if say for example,
if now reach this state,
then I use this function to evaluate my utility value,
okay, done, but probably for, even for Dictato,
we probably cannot hold the entire,
all the states in this memory, okay,
probably no, no, very small memory,
we have very small computer, very low end computer,
we cannot hold all of them,
so we can only see like two depths of down the road,
okay, so if that's the case,
then you treat that one as a terminal note,
and then you work out the utility value,
and then you're backward to decide
which direction you are going to move,
that's how you can make use of the minimax
to play the game, okay, so this is an example,
yeah, looks very messy, oh, okay,
so we start from here, this is starting states,
and then we look to ply, okay,
so that means to ply two steps ahead, okay,
so one step come to here, right,
one step you put the circle,
you put the cross in the corner,
in this middle, or in the center, okay,
so I may use this tree,
and don't work out the utility value based on this,
because this is not my terminal notes yet, right,
I say two steps, two play, two ply, two ply,
so that means the depth equal to two,
so this is only one, one, one,
and then next level is the next level, right,
depth equal to two, so this is two,
so if I put here, then my opponent's supposed to put here,
here, here, here, you know, all the possible places,
and that's it, we stop there, okay,
no more play, no more the maximizer come play again, no,
we stop here, we stop here,
we treat this as a terminal notes now,
okay, then you use the evaluate function
to work out the utility value, okay,
so you see that is five, six minus five,
if you have this position, and then I get one,
so this is a one, five minus one,
five minus five get zero, and so on, okay,
so the red color here indicates the E value
of each of these, utility value for each of these
terminal notes, okay, get it,
so similarly here, here, here, here,
so you see even have minus two here, okay,
then what, then apply minimax,
because suppose our memory is only so small,
we can only do two steps ahead,
and then we do evaluation,
based on this evaluation, minimax, okay,
so remember how to do minimax backwards, right,
so this is a max, this next level,
so if you are max, your opponent definitely mini,
and then you are max again, right,
if I'm a mini, your opponent will be max,
it's like that, okay, so now max,
that's why the next one is mini,
then this is a max, right, okay,
so amount your utility value,
what value you should choose, huh,
you should one, zero, one, zero minus one,
this is what player, mini player, right,
that's why choose what,
minimum value among the children, right,
minimum, that's why you get minus one, okay,
so this minus one is not really work out,
it's based on your children,
based on your children's utility value,
then I get this, okay,
but this value is really your utility value,
it's really based on evaluation function we work out, okay,
that's how you get minus two,
because minus two, zero, minus one, zero, minus one,
so you need to select the minimum value,
that's why you get minus two, yeah,
and minus one, oh no, no, sorry,
one and two, minimizer, take one, right,
and then this is only one level up, right,
so the amount of minus one, minus two, and one,
what value are we getting,
we are the minimizer or maximizer, max,
we should choose among the minus one,
minus two, and one, the maximum value,
so that's why we get the one, okay,
so what's the indication, that's it, we are done,
we are done with the utility value backwards,
we get everything, then which one decide the movement,
yes, from the player, right,
so you are maximizer, of course, you choose a maximum,
the branch give you the maximum value,
so you go this way, I should go this way, right,
then this is a minimizer, I should go this way, right,
by right, by right, if you follow this,
but you also know this value is only based on my two plies,
right, so it's not getting this whole,
based on the entire search, entire game tree,
so this may not be accurate,
so you see this minimizer, he decide, not go here,
he want to go this way, possible, right,
then he take this way, he take this way,
he put his circle here, yeah,
then let's see what's next,
so we are expanding from here, okay, next page,
we are expanding from here, then we have the options,
oh sorry, sorry, we are expanding from where,
oh yes, yes, from here, okay, then go for this,
these, those are the possible four branches,
and then again, two ply, okay, so two steps,
two steps, so one level, and then next level,
for each of this, and then these,
those are the terminal already, terminal,
so apply the terminal evaluation function,
get the actual value, get actual value,
so all those actual value are here,
so then we know this is a maximizer,
so the minimizer should select the minimum value out of this,
so that's why it's all either zero or one or two, right,
so you should choose zero, the minimum,
similarly among those, then I choose that one, and so on,
and then backwards, okay, so then from one,
from zero, from one, zero, so I choose maximizer,
so I choose one, so I choose one,
I can either go this direction or this direction,
so suppose I come to here, and I come to here,
okay, so this is how they move based on limited information,
and then suppose minimizer take this way,
then we can expand, look at the next step,
so very similar, we can do two steps ahead,
and then get the evaluation function for the terminal,
and backwards, we get the value,
then decide which branch we are moving, yeah.
That's all, so as we said, if the entire graph is available,
then this is possible, right,
but the thing is still probably cannot explore,
okay, the efficiency is still a crucial issue,
that's why we need another thing
which can help you to chop up, you know,
certain branch, for example, probably certain branch,
we just totally no need to care about it,
just chop up, so prune away,
that's why we have this pruning come into play,
that's the alpha beta pruning algorithm,
but it's actually based on a minimax idea,
okay, so before we do introduce you the last algorithm
in the game search, exercise, okay,
exercise four, just a quick one,
because this is very simple,
I hope you get the basic idea of the minimax idea, okay.
You see the value, a number attached to the bottom,
or to the terminal nodes, yeah,
so those are the, don't ask anyhow,
they come up with the evaluation function already,
they give you the number, okay,
so suppose the number is available,
then how to make use of the minimax
to get the value for the starting nodes,
and then to tell us which branch you should choose,
okay, can we do that, just five minutes?
Okay, so we're gonna do the same thing,
we're gonna do the same thing,
we're gonna do the same thing.
I think most of you have done that,
ahh, done that correctly.
So just quick check.
Okay,
so we are having
a very simple mini max tree,
and then
probably have a very good
evaluation function,
so the utility value
already being around
$2,000,
$1,000,
So the utility value already evaluated and attached to each of the terminal nodes.
Right?
So the terminal node, that means there's no children after that.
So we already have this value attached to it.
And then for minimax algorithm, it's always played with a game tree, and then they always
layer by layer.
So if the first layer is a maximizer, the next definitely is a minimizer.
Okay?
Maximizer again.
It's take turn, take turn.
And then if the first one is mini, then next is max.
Okay?
So it's always like this.
So suppose here, in the beginning, this is the maximizer, then next one will be mini,
next is max, and this way.
Okay?
So for this, can we get the utility value for i?
We need to check.
This is what player, right?
So this is mini, m, i, n.
Yeah, mini player, then what value he should choose?
Yeah, zero.
So that's why we get the zero.
So we get zero.
Okay, we get the, I didn't choose.
Okay, I have a zero here.
Zero.
Okay, then f.
Okay, this level no more, no need to decide because all the rest, actually, are the terminal
already.
So for f, f is a maximizer.
So what value we should have?
Five.
Eight.
Okay, then this is a minimizer.
That's why we have four.
This is a minimizer.
Yeah, three.
Then we have four value.
Four.
This is a maximizer.
Yeah.
So meaning what?
Maximizer by right should go which branch?
And move to which branch?
Go this way.
Yeah, so what is the indication?
What's the meaning of it?
Yeah, if you come to this branch, high chance of way.
If our utility value are very well-designed, then based on this algorithm, if he moved
to this, likely, no chance.
Especially if this number indicates certain probability, for example, then he definitely
should go higher priority.
But of course, after he moved to here, up to his opponents, his opponents maybe not
really play as we thought.
He'd probably not go this way.
He'd probably go another direction.
Then we need to adjust accordingly.
But it's just like the first movement indicates whatever.
We guide by this.
OK.
So that's all.
Everybody know how to use minimax?
OK.
Then yes, that's very nice if the space can be fully stored or exploded in the computer
and then stored there.
We can also have a very good utility function to evaluate.
Then we can apply this.
But we probably don't have such kind of luck.
That's why we probably have to come up with another more efficient method on top of the
minimax.
So that's alpha beta pruning.
OK.
So this is the last algorithm I'm going to talk about it before end of this session.
So we still use exactly the minimax tree or graph.
And then the end results should be exactly the same.
OK.
Meaning, for example, if I decide this is a max and should go this branch, if you use
pruning, non-pruning should give us the same answer.
That's ideal.
Otherwise, it's not the efficient model.
It's not improved version, improved algorithm.
And then the good thing is actually they can enable us to prune out certain amount of the
states or significant amounts, say 50%, that would be nice.
You can totally abandon them.
You don't need to go into those branches.
That's a key idea.
OK.
Anything I can say?
So it's an advanced minimax by pruning, OK, by good pruning strategy and pruning without
losing any information.
OK.
So that is the alpha beta pruning.
Two kind of pruning.
One is called alpha pruning.
The other one is beta pruning.
But pruning is a cutoff certain branch.
OK.
So how to cut?
They attach a value to maximizer or minimizer.
OK.
The value you attach on the symbol we like to attach to a maximizer, we use alpha.
Alpha to relate it to the maximizer.
Beta related to the minimizer.
OK.
So alpha, beta.
Then this is one pruning here.
So if the grandparents here is the minimizer, OK, mini.
So you have a value called beta attached to it, right?
And then you have the children.
So this children, because you are the mini, the children definitely is a max, right?
So the children have max.
So alpha attached to max.
So now you compare the relationship between the alpha and beta.
OK.
So if the alpha value actually is greater than the beta value in the parents or in the
sisters, then you can prune away those branches below the alpha nodes.
That's a pruning.
So that is a relationship between the, OK, if you say these are the kids, then this is
a parent, then this is a grandparents, right?
So if based on one of the children, you already can set the value for your parents as an alpha
value, tentative alpha value, then this alpha value already greater than your grandparents
beta value.
So if under this condition, you don't need to care what is your sibling's value.
Prune away.
No need to visit.
OK.
I'll show you why later, but just remember this.
This is a relationship.
So you have children, parents, grandparents.
OK.
So these three, three pairs, two.
Is that considered as two or three?
So you have n, n plus one, n plus two there.
OK.
And this is a relationship.
So this is alpha greater than beta.
Beta is a minimizer.
OK.
What if the grandparents is alpha?
It's a maximizer.
OK.
So if your grandparents is a maximizer, parents is a minimizer.
If your children already give the parents a tentative beta value, which already show
the beta value less than the grandparents alpha value, that means don't care.
You don't need to evaluate your siblings.
OK.
So this is the idea.
So I try to use, draw the graph to help us to understand these words here about this
cutting, OK, about this cutting.
So this is called alpha cut.
Previously called beta cut.
OK.
Because this beta here, but doesn't matter you call it what cut, but just know it's cut.
But the relationship is important.
If this is a max, this is mini, your current value already show greater than the mini,
you see the mini meaning they will choose a minimum value.
Right.
So your tentative value already show this whole branch have a tendency of greater than
the mini value in the parent, in the grandparents.
OK.
Your parents already show their value, the alpha value already greater than their grandparents
mini value.
Do you think you still have chance to be visited?
This branch is totally will be ignored.
Right.
So that is why, that is why no point to check what's the value here.
That's the whole thing.
OK.
Because you see mini, mini meaning they want to choose a branch with a minimum value.
So your tentative value already show you are too big.
You are a little big.
This branch already too big.
They will not come to here.
So why bother these things?
Right.
That's the idea.
OK.
So if you are a little bit smaller, if it's a max and your value already show you are
so small, you see your beta value already very small than your parent's alpha value.
So they will not come to this branch.
They will move to other branch which have a high potential.
They are taking the maximum value.
So you are too small.
This branch is too small.
That's why no chance.
No water.
No need to bother.
OK.
That's a key principle.
Need to remember.
Have this picture in your mind.
You know, that's the relationship.
OK.
That's all.
I think we can put together.
We are just now separate.
But I put together in one slide so it helps us to visualize it.
Also, this is talking about, you know, we have basically have to have n, n plus 1, n plus
2, at least have three layers.
Then you can actually see the relationship among them.
OK.
Now let's do it.
Apply this rule.
Do you have this version?
I already show you the cut.
Your slides.
Do you see your slides have this cut or not?
Already have.
OK.
They are online.
You don't know which one cut.
OK.
Let's do it.
So for minimax, we go all the way to the terminal and then we go one level up and backwards
to get the utility value.
For this alpha beta pruning, we can say we want to go for the steps first, DFS.
OK.
Either from left, most left to the right, or right to left.
You can specify.
OK.
This will not give you the same answer, but you can have preference.
So let's start from left to right.
OK.
DFS from left to right.
So if we don't say anything, normally it's left to right.
So we left to right.
DFS, DFS.
OK.
So that first.
So I go.
OK.
I need to.
I probably should say the initial value of the initial value.
Or for the alpha, we should all set as a minus infinity.
OK.
Because the alpha value can only increase.
Where is my?
OK.
Good.
So this is the alpha player, right?
This is the alpha.
Where is my pen?
OK.
I cannot see it on my screen.
I can only see from here.
OK.
So this is the alpha player.
This is the beta value.
And then alpha value and beta value.
And then initially, all the alpha should start from very, very small.
Then all the beta should be very, very big.
Because beta always have to be decreased.
Alpha value always need to be increased.
OK.
So this is the minus infinity.
So that means for all this level, all the nodes.
OK.
And then we go left to right and DFS.
So we hit this terminal.
And this is value two.
And that means we should update the alpha value.
So the alpha value from minus would be two now.
OK.
Then we can compare these two to this beta value.
Because we have the alpha value.
This is our beta value.
So beta value, are we too big?
Are we too big?
So ignore these three.
Initial value is a positive infinity.
Are we too big?
Are we bigger than positive infinity?
No.
Right?
Meaning what?
Meaning we should continue checking this branch.
OK.
So we should check this branch.
This branch is value is three.
So three.
We are alpha.
At moments alpha value equal to two.
Now it's three.
Should we update?
Yes.
Update.
Now we get three.
OK.
We get three.
And now this whole branch, is that done?
We are done.
That means these three can be used to update this value.
OK.
Before was positive infinity.
So now become three.
OK.
So this is just tentative three.
This is tentative.
Then we can compare these three with the beta value.
Oh, sorry.
Alpha value.
Because this is the beta value.
OK.
Are we, what's the relationship between beta and alpha?
Are we too small?
This is negative.
This is three.
Are we too small?
No.
So meaning what?
Can we prune this away?
Cannot.
We must do checking.
OK.
So we go that first branch base.
So this way we get five.
This used to be negative infinity.
Right?
To start, every, every, every notes here is negative infinity.
So now it's five.
So we should update it.
So now this is five.
OK.
My.
So it was negative.
Now update become five.
OK.
Now watch.
Now we need to decide whether we can prune away or we should check in.
Right?
OK.
So what we need to do is we need to compare these five, the value here with the beta value
here.
What is the beta value now?
Three.
What is my value now?
Five.
Am I too big?
Yes.
Yeah.
No chance to come to this branch because I'm five already.
This is only three.
So definitely go other branch.
So do I need to check this one?
No.
Prune.
OK.
Prune away this branch.
You don't care what is the new value here.
That's the alpha beta pruning we are talking about.
We finally prune away something.
OK.
And then these five now we are done with this.
So these five values should be used to update this one.
OK.
So this is a mini.
This is five.
This is three.
Any update?
No need.
Right?
Because I'm five.
I'm too big.
So you just keep us three.
So now this whole branch is done.
So we should propagate this value to the top.
So the three will be used to update this negative infinity.
So now it's three.
Actually it's this three here.
OK.
Then come to this branch.
Come to this branch.
Zero, then zero, then zero.
Then zero here.
Zero one.
This is the beta value.
This is the alpha value.
Am I too small?
Too small.
Prune.
OK.
This branch no need to check.
And then this is zero.
So zero.
This is three.
And this is alpha.
So no update.
Right?
Because so keep us three.
Then I go another branch.
That's how we do it.
So this branch and then you have two.
So you have two.
Previously was negative infinity.
Then we update to become two.
And then we can compare with this value.
This value was positive infinity.
So I'm not too big.
Right?
So I cannot.
I cannot prune away.
So I need to check.
So I'm checking this one and then update.
Then they update this alpha player.
I mean maximizer.
So you cannot update.
This is two.
So this one.
So keep the two.
Then back.
So this whole branch finish already.
Then you can update.
OK.
So that's why this become two.
You get two.
And then compare two with this top.
So this is a beta value and alpha value.
Am I too small?
You are too small.
Cut.
OK.
Done.
So this is how we do it.
So you see, neither we prune away how many nodes are.
We prune away this whole branch and then this whole branch and this branch.
Not bad.
OK.
Although it's a very tiny tree.
But imagine it's a big tree.
It will be very useful.
Right?
OK.
That's all.
That's prune this one.
And then the name.
Call alpha or call beta.
And then I draw this for you.
So it's just basically, you know, suppose I already have an alpha here.
So this I need to check, you know, whether my value is too small.
So if it's too small, then I prune away.
You know, if here, then this value, the relationship between this value and this value.
So if I'm too big, then prune away.
OK.
So visualization.
Drawing.
And then that is a detailed algorithm.
OK.
Read it.
So basically just say something like this.
OK.
Exactly what we are doing.
Search can be stopped below.
We're using MIDI notes having a beta value less than or equal to the alpha value of his max ancestor.
OK.
So that is draw.
Try to draw this out.
OK.
So similarly, these two are the key thing.
The pruning.
OK.
And also, yeah, I think we can have one more example before I stop.
Again, this one I already set the initial value as we said.
All the alpha set the minus negative and all the beta set positive infinity.
OK.
And then we have this right.
Left to right.
And then that DFS.
So three.
Then a whole branch gets.
So I'm canceling this value away and I get three.
Right.
So this is compared with this negative.
I'm not too, what?
Too small.
Yeah.
So I can, I should continue this.
OK.
So I get this.
And this is 12.
I back, go back to 12.
But this is three.
And this is a minimizer.
So no need to take the 12.
Keep us three.
Right.
Then next branch, eight.
Also too big.
I mean, this is three.
So we should keep the three.
OK.
Now the three can be used to update here.
Right.
So I get my first three for the eight.
I'm done with this branch.
Nothing pruned it here.
OK.
Then second branch, I get two.
Yeah.
So the two will be used for this C. And then two compared to this.
Huh.
Am I too small?
Too small.
What?
The mini under this beta value pruned.
Right.
Pruned away.
No need to check.
OK.
So then these two should be back to update this part.
Right.
But this is a max.
So two is smaller than three.
So keep the three.
OK.
So we are done with this branch.
Then come here.
So we get 14.
So we have 14.
So we have 14 first.
OK.
Then 14 compared to the three.
Am I too small?
No.
I'm big actually.
So this cannot be pruned away.
So I need to check.
So this is five.
So five.
I'm a minimizer.
So I should update.
Become five.
Smaller.
Right.
And then five.
Is that still too small?
Am I too small?
No.
So that means third one.
OK.
I get two.
So I get two.
Oops.
That's how I get two here.
OK.
So if no green pattern, the version you have, then we are done.
So these two.
And then this is maximizer.
So we just keep it.
Yes.
Suppose I'm adding another branch.
I'm adding another branch here.
It's the D4 with utility value one.
So this is two here.
Should I prune here?
Yes or no?
Yes.
Because my value now is two.
Two is small.
So this one should be pruned away.
Right.
Yeah.
OK.
So then these two should be used to update this.
But this is a maximizer.
So don't take my two.
So I'm done.
OK.
Done.
So actually another way to represent this is they are using a range.
They have alpha beta both from negative to positive infinity and then keep updating both.
But I personally feel prefer to have a single value that is quite clear to me.
OK.
So you can also look at this way to see how they updated.
Exactly the same thing.
OK.
But it's just for each alpha beta value they have a range from negative to positive and
then update half of it or both of it.
OK.
So this is a detailed description provided.
You can read this at home.
But this is an important slide.
OK.
So we just now, OK, we just say, oh, OK.
We visually, we actually visualize how this prune is going on.
So why can we prove mathematically this is not a fact anything?
Yeah.
So this is a good example.
OK.
So just now we have this A and BCD, right?
There's three branches and no external and no nothing added here.
OK.
So you can see the value.
The A is a maximizer.
And BCD is a minimizer.
Right?
So we can write equation like this from the root.
We have a max because the A is a max.
Right?
And then max among all the three.
Yes?
So then each of the three is a minimizer.
So minimizer among the actual value, the terminal value.
Right?
Three, 12 and 8.
And then C is among these two.
And then you don't care what is the value here because those actually was pruned away.
Why we can prune away?
So you can use the x, y here.
And then the B with this utility value is a minimizer.
Right?
OK.
Then next we just replace.
So among these we know the minimizer value is three.
Among these we know we can take the z.
Suppose z is actually less than or equal to two.
Right?
We will take because the minimum value.
Minimum value.
Yeah?
So it has to be less or equal to two.
Then we take the z.
And then this side we take the value which is minimum value two.
And then we need to select the maximum.
So the maximum, the z actually is less or equal to two.
Then why we care about this?
Right?
Definitely we will take the other value which is.
So let's show us, we prune away this will not affect performance at all.
We are not losing information.
OK?
That's a whole working principle behind the alpha beta pruning.
So, yeah, you can imagine this is something like this maximizer.
Yeah.
So your minimizer, although you just show you are too small.
So it will not come to this branch at all.
So let's go other branch.
That is exactly the working principle.
Yeah.
Can go home with this exercise.
And then we will discuss the exercise in the last lecture, OK, in week five.
So you still have a bit time.
I think this one take a while to digest.
Although, although it looks very simple, just two rules that you need to, you need to run it here.
OK?
I think with, you know, alpha beta concept, then you also need to see the initial value
and how to update.
And remember you only update when the whole branch finish, then you can update the parents.
OK?
Also keep that in mind.
And then when you check the parents relationship, the alpha beta is always checked with your
grandparents, OK?
Not your immediate parents.
OK?
So this is about everything.
And then, yeah, the property is just try to say, actually, this can cut down the complexity
a lot, but still not good enough.
OK?
So like game like a goal, still not feasible.
That's why this is purely for your information.
OK?
Definitely I'm not going into this at all.
And, but this is how, actually, previously, the symbolic AI tried to address.
Actually, it can have a hybrid system.
And either they totally rely on statistics or actually they rely on combination.
OK?
Use neural network to train some data.
Now, after that, they give you the statistical value and then attach with the value as a
terminal evaluation value and decide what to do.
OK?
So that is a Monte Carlo tree search method.
And that is the whole purpose.
I say maybe you can still consider this traditional method with deep neural network.
Design a hybrid system.
OK?
Yeah.
So this is a summary, quick summary.
So Minimax and alpha beta pruning.
So you have something like this in your mind, OK?
The alpha beta relationship.
Hopefully that will help.
OK.
So that's all.
Oh, OK.
Still have extra exercise or extra homework for you.
OK?
So that is, I already show you exercise one.
And then heuristics game tree, I will give you another one, maybe end of this week.
And then the quiz, as I said, this is still need to be confirmed.
OK, no need to take picture because I hope it's not delayed further.
OK?
But most likely, definitely will not be in week five, looks like.
So it will be week six, week six.
And the time don't have idea yet, about 45 minutes.
OK?
Record a lecture.
I think our class is OK.
But for another group Friday, they said they have issues.
Always have a black screen for a while or something.
Is that?
OK.
So I'm reporting to CSIT already.
I don't know why.
OK.
I think they have some setting, time out setting probably in the computer.
And then this is the one for the project later, mini project.
OK.
So this is for your information.
See you next week for the data mining.
Thank you.
Where is?
Off.