.
OK, let's start.
Yeah, let's continue with the mapping between S-plane and Z-plane.
Yeah, the mapping is based on this transformation, as mentioned last week.
So, S-domain has variable S, Z-domain has variable Z, so they have this relationship.
Now, we consider the case when the frequency is constant.
So, in S-domain, the imaginary part denotes the frequency.
So, if the frequency is constant, that means omega is constant.
And the sigma can be any value between negative infinity and positive infinity.
OK, based on this relationship, as mentioned here, we can find that the angle of Z is t omega.
That's this part here.
So, if omega is a constant with t as the sampling period, then the angle will be fixed.
But the magnitude of Z is changing because sigma is in the range between negative infinity and positive infinity.
However, it is bigger than or equal to zero.
Yeah, when sigma is negative infinity, it's zero.
So, we have this mapping here.
Yeah, this is the S-domain graph of constant frequency Lucy.
For example, if your omega is equal to omega one, that means this is a constant.
The angle is straight line parallel to the real axis here.
Then, the angle corresponding to this straight line will be this, omega one t.
So, this is the image of j omega one in the Z-plane.
Yeah, as I said, this magnitude is changing from zero to infinity.
So, you have this straight line as the mapping of j omega one in the Z-plane.
Similarly, if you have another straight line like negative j omega one, the angle will be negative omega one t.
So, this is the angle and the straight line would be like this.
For omega equals omega two, then you have this range.
Okay, remember we have the concept of primary strip.
So, those omegas should be in the range between negative half omega s and positive half omega s.
In fact, based on sampling theorem, you have this situation also.
Your sampling frequency, omega s is the sampling frequency, should be at least twice of the bandwidth of the signal.
So, that means the range of all the frequencies of the signal considered should be in this range.
Okay, so that's the case when we have constant frequency.
Now, let's look at an example.
In this example, we are looking for the mapping of this region in the S-plane to the Z-plane.
So, for this region, it's bounded by four straight lines.
Theta equals negative theta one, theta equals negative theta two, and below is negative j omega two, above is j omega one.
Okay, so we found the boundary of these four lines, and then found their mapping in the Z-plane.
For omega equals omega one, what's the image?
Just now we talked about the image of this horizontal line, it will be this straight line.
Okay, so if your region is below omega one, yeah, below this straight line, j omega one, then that should be on the right side of this.
So, it's this part of the region in the Z-plane as the image below j omega one.
Okay, for this horizontal line, negative j omega two, you have this image.
Then, for the region above this horizontal line, it should be on the right side of this line also.
The angle should be bigger than this negative j, negative omega two t, so it's on the right side also.
And now we have two vertical lines.
For this left vertical line, the image will be a circle with the radius e to the power of negative sigma one t.
That's this circle, centered at the origin.
So, for the region on the left side of this negative sigma one, it should be inside the circle of this, yeah, this big circle.
Now, for this sigma equals negative sigma two, it's also a circle with the radius e to the power of negative sigma two t.
So, the radius is smaller, but this region is on the right side of this vertical line, so the image should be outside this circle.
Okay, so you consider all the overlapping of the images of all the regions concerned.
We have this shaded area in the z-plane as the image of this shaded area inside the rectangle.
Okay, so that's how you find the region in the z-plane.
So, basically you find the boundary images and then find the overlapping regions to get the answer.
Okay, next, we consider constant damping ratio Lucy.
What does this mean?
Yeah, in this case, we have a constant damping ratio.
Actually, damping ratio is an important concept in control system.
So, if you consider secant order system, which means the denominator of the transfer function is secant order.
Yeah, I just considered the denominator.
It will be s squared plus two zeta omega n s plus omega n squared.
Okay, we have the parameters zeta and omega n.
This zeta is called damping ratio of the system.
Omega n is called the natural frequency of the system.
Okay, if you find the pole of the system, it will be this.
You have two poles.
When our damping ratio is between zero and one.
Yeah, between zero and one, you have this two complex poles in the complex plane.
Yeah, you can saw this complex poles.
So, one is here, for example.
Then the other one is a conjugate of this pole.
So, if you saw a line from the pole to this origin,
and saw this vertical line and this horizontal line,
this is the real part, which is negative zeta omega n.
And the imaginary part is this.
J omega n square root one minus zeta squared.
And you can denote omega d as this.
Just a notation for this part.
So, actually this is omega d.
The imaginary part of the pole is omega d.
For this case.
Okay, you can see that the angle here,
if it's alpha, then your cosine alpha is equal to zeta.
Okay?
Yeah, you can find this easily.
Actually, the cosine alpha equals this distance divided by this distance.
This distance is zeta omega n, this distance is omega n.
So, the ratio will be zeta.
If zeta is constant, it implies alpha is constant.
So, in the S-plane, yeah, we are considering S-plane,
for constant damping ratio, it is a straight line, like this.
Okay?
So, this straight line will give you a constant damping ratio.
Yeah, of course, you have a different real part and the imaginary part.
So, if you treat omega d as a variable,
then, if your imaginary part is changing,
then your pole will change along this straight line.
So, we are looking for the image of this red line in the Z-plane.
So, that's the objective of this subsection.
Okay, so now, we are looking for this image with constant damping ratio.
That is, we are looking for the image of this red line.
Yeah, this is the relationship between S and Z.
Now, our S is equal to that.
You just substitute negative zeta omega n plus minus j omega d t.
Yeah, times t, you get this.
Okay, so you do some simplification.
As I said, we are going to consider omega d as a variable.
So, in this case, we do some manipulation here.
This t is equal to 2 pi divided by omega s.
Okay, that's t.
Yeah, because omega s is the sampling frequency in radians per second.
So, that's t will be equal to 2 pi divided by this.
And this omega n, based on this definition,
it will be equal to omega d divided by square root 1 minus zeta squared.
So, this omega d divided by that is our omega n.
Of course, we have this zeta here.
So, that's the real part of your S.
Now, for the imaginary part, you also change t to 2 pi divided by omega s.
Okay, so this is our manipulation.
Now, based on this, our magnitude of z will be equal to part of this real part.
And the imaginary part, no, the angle will be this part here.
So, it's e to the power of j 2 pi omega d over omega s.
From this part, you get this angle.
Okay, so 2 pi omega d divided by omega s is the angle.
Okay, now we have this magnitude and angle.
Now, as I said, I will choose omega d over omega s as a variable.
That is, we consider omega d is changing.
So, if you look at the result here, as this increases,
as omega d over omega s increases,
the magnitude decreases exponentially, but the angle will increase linearly.
Okay, so we have this image for the red line.
So, at the beginning, this red line is the positive half of the two poles.
So, at the beginning, it's this point.
This point has an image at this position.
Then, as this omega d increases, the angle will increase linearly,
but the magnitude will decrease exponentially.
So, we can see that you get this logarithm spiral, like this.
Yeah, we can see a few important points.
For example, one omega d over omega s is 0.25.
That means omega d is just one quarter of omega s.
You can compute this angle.
Yeah, this is one quarter, so it's half pi.
Half pi, then, yeah, this angle will be half pi.
If omega d over omega s is a quarter, that's this point.
So, this angle is half pi, but the magnitude is much smaller than this.
It decreases exponentially.
And the one omega d over omega s increases further to half here.
Then, yeah, to half. Actually, it's this, at this point.
Then, your angle here will be, yeah, if this is half, then that will be pi. That's this.
Then, you increase further, you get this.
Eventually, it will converge to zero, because the magnitude converges to zero.
Okay? Yeah, let's look at the case.
If we have zeta as 0.3, yeah, I already mentioned.
One omega d, yeah, if zeta is 0.3, you can compute the angle corresponding to this value.
That is omega d over omega s.
That's the angle is half pi, as I just mentioned.
But the magnitude with this zeta value is 0.61.
So, that's 0.61.
And if you have, yeah, omega d over omega s is half,
the magnitude is further reduced to this.
So that's this. You have this magnitude, but the angle is pi.
Okay?
Okay, so that's the image of this red line in the z-plane.
However, we should focus our omega in the primary strip.
Which means our omega should be in this range.
Okay?
So, if your omega is in this range, that is between zero and the half omega s,
then you just have this image up to here.
This part above the real axis.
Yeah, because omega s has an image here.
Okay, so this is the image of this part.
As I just mentioned, if you have a complex pole, you will have another pole.
What's the other pole? It's the conjugate of this.
So, we have another branch, in fact.
This branch is symmetric to this with respect to the real axis.
So, it's something like this.
So, how do we get the image of this?
Yeah, we have obtained the image of this upper half plane.
That's this shape, like this.
Then, how about this?
Yeah, you just do a reflection.
Because these two are symmetric with respect to the real axis.
Their image will be also symmetric.
So, overall, for the upper half, it's something like this.
Okay?
Then, for the lower half, you just find them by doing a symmetric mapping.
So, you do a symmetric mapping, you will get something like this.
Okay?
Yeah.
Okay, actually, last week, we considered an example.
I have not finished the example.
Yeah, we are looking for the, if you recall this example, here.
We have two requirements.
One is the settling time should be less than equal to four seconds with the two percent error tolerance.
The other is that the dimension ratio should be in this range, between 0.707 and 1.
So, we have this situation.
The dimension ratio is bigger than some value, like this, bigger than 0.707, but less than one.
So, how do we find this image?
Yeah, that's the result here.
So, you have a boundary, zeta equals zeta one.
That's the positive omega side.
For the conjugate, we have this boundary.
So, for damping ratio bigger than equal to zeta one, it will be the shaded region in S-plane.
Okay, so now, we found the image of the boundary.
So, for this zeta equals zeta one, the image will be like this.
For the lower half, you have this image, as I just mentioned.
You find this by symmetric image of that.
Okay, so damping ratio bigger than zeta one will be inside the hot shaped region.
So, that's how we get the image of this zeta bigger than zeta one.
Therefore, for this case, you just find the boundary with zeta one as 0.707.
So, you do some calculation, then you have this image as the boundary.
Okay?
Yeah, for zeta bigger than 0.707, it will be the region inside this hot shaped area.
We have the case when zeta equals one.
What does this mean?
If zeta equals one, our pole will be...
Yeah, if you look at the transfer function.
If zeta equals one, you have two repeated poles.
Both are on the real axis.
I mean, in the s domain.
So, that means, in this case, your pole...
Yeah, two repeated poles will be here.
Yeah, that's the case when zeta equals one.
Okay?
So, we have two repeated poles here.
Then, what's the image of the...
Yeah, in that case, you have to consider the image of the negative real axis.
What's the image of the negative real axis?
It will be this.
Yeah, because at this point, the image is here.
When the real part tends to negative infinity, the magnitude will go to zero.
So, the image is just inside the hot shaped region.
That's zeta equals one.
So, to meet the second condition.
Yeah, this condition.
Zeta is bigger than 0.707, less than or equal to one.
Our image will be inside the hot shaped region,
because zeta equals one is already inside, including the boundary here,
because it equals 0.707.
Last week, we said to meet the first condition,
that is the settling time requirement.
We need our pole inside the unit circle.
No unit circle.
Inside this circle, with the readers, calculated as e to the power of...
Yeah, this is the readers, calculated here.
So, you consider the intersection of the two regions, you get this.
So, that's the required pole locations in the z domain.
So, this completes the solution of the example.
Now, let's consider another example.
You have to specify the region in the z-plane that corresponds to a desirable region,
shaded in the s-plane here.
So, this region is bounded by two horizontal lines,
and also two straight lines, which corresponds to zeta equals zeta one.
Okay, so this is formed by considering the bound first.
So, for this bound, omega equals omega one, we have this image.
For omega equals negative omega one, we have this image.
So, for this zeta equals zeta one, we have this heart-shaped figure.
Then, for this region, it will be inside this.
Yeah, and the left of this straight line, and also this straight line,
and the inside this heart-shaped region.
Oh, so we have another bound, zeta equals zeta one.
That means this is negative zeta one here.
Then, the circle is the image of this zeta equals negative zeta one.
So, you consider all these intersections, you get this region.
Okay, so that's how we found the image of the regions in the s-plane.
Okay, so that's the first topic of this chapter.
Next, we consider stability analysis of a closed loop system in the z-plane.
Yeah, stability is an essential requirement.
When you design your controller, the first thing is to ensure you have a stable system.
In linear system, for stability, you have this condition.
That is, you find the closed loop transfer function first.
Then, the stability is determined by the poles of the system.
That is the roots of the characteristic equation found from this.
You make the denominator zero, you solve the equation, you get the poles.
So, how do we ensure stability?
You have to ensure all the poles are inside the unit circle.
Okay, so that's the stability.
In fact, this is also considered as the region of convergence.
Actually, for stability, you don't allow your signal to go to infinity.
Yeah, so that's ensured if all the poles are inside the unit circle.
If you have one pole outside the unit circle, then if you take an inverse Z-transform,
the term corresponding to that pole will diverge.
Okay, so to be stable, all roots of the characteristic equation must be inside the unit circle.
Roots outside the unit circle will give you instability.
How about those poles and the unit circle?
We have some special cases.
If we have a sample pole at the point Z equals one, then you have critical stability.
That means your signal does not go to infinity, but does not converge.
It will stay at the unit, yeah, because this is corresponding to the unit step input, so it's a constant.
And if you have a single pair of complex conjugate poles and the unit circle, it's also critical stability.
The signal will oscillate.
Yeah, if you take an inverse Z-transform corresponding to this pair, then you have sine functions.
Yeah, so you have oscillation.
So it's also critical stability because the signal does not go to infinity.
However, if you have multiple poles at the unit circle, you will have an unstable system.
For example, you have two poles at Z equals one.
The corresponding signal will diverge.
In our case, we just focus on strict stability.
We have to ensure all the poles inside the unit circle because for critical stability,
if we have some uncertainty or disturbance or some perturbation, the system will be likely to be unstable.
So in that case, we don't wish to have such a control system.
Okay, how about the zeros of the transfer function?
Just now, we mentioned the closed loop transfer function is this, right?
This is how you calculate the closed loop transfer function.
So if you simplify that, you have a numerator.
The numerator will give you zeros.
The zeros does not affect stability.
So you don't worry about zeros when you talk about stability.
However, zeros will affect your response.
Okay?
So that will affect your trial and response and also steady state performance.
But does not affect stability.
Even if your system is stable, maybe the performance is not good.
So in that case, you have to consider zeros.
Okay, so how do we check stability?
Yeah, one straightforward method is to solve the equation.
Yeah, you solve this equation to find the poles.
If all the solutions are inside the unit circle, your system is stable.
However, if you want to solve the equation, especially high-order equations,
it's very tedious. Sometimes, maybe cannot be solved manually.
So in some cases, we don't have to solve the equation to determine stability.
Because we just need to know whether the poles are inside the unit circle or not.
You don't need to know the exact location.
So we will have a method called jury stability test to check stability.
In this case, you don't solve the equation.
Okay? So how do we do that?
Let's consider this nth order polynomial.
Suppose this is the denominator of the transfer function.
So we are just considering the denominator.
Don't worry about the numerator.
Assume this is the denominator and we know the coefficients of the polynomial.
This denominator is a polynomial.
We know the coefficient will be a0, a1, up to an.
So these are known.
Assume a0 is positive.
Then we are going to check stability of the system.
Before we study the criteria, we talk about jury table.
Jury table is formed in this way.
So I show you the jury table.
How do we form the jury table?
We have some procedures.
Okay, for the first row, if you look at the first row of this table,
it's an up to a0.
So that's the coefficient of pz in the ascending motor of power z.
So an is the constant up to a0, so you put it in the first row.
How about second row?
Second row, you just reverse the order.
Okay?
So second row is the reverse of the first row.
Actually, for the remaining rows, we also obtain the even rows in the same way.
So now we just want to obtain the outnumbered rows.
For example, the third row.
How do we get third row?
This is the method.
Yeah, the third row contains b values.
So we have to compute b0, b1, up to bn-1.
How do we obtain these values?
For example, when k is 0, how do we get b0?
So in this case, you form two by two matrix.
The first column is a and a0.
That is a and a0.
That's the first column of the first two rows.
So that's fixed.
Then the second column, yeah, when k is 0, what do you have here?
It's am-1 and the a1.
Where do we get am-1 and a1?
Yeah, when k is 0, so it's am-1.
That's a1.
So you look at the table here.
It will be this.
Oh, sorry.
It's this.
These two numbers, am-1 and a1.
Yeah, when k is 0.
So based on these two by two matrix, you completely determine it.
That will give you b0.
So for b1, you change the second column to this two number.
Yeah, in this case, it's am-2 and a2, if you look at the formula here.
So you have this.
Yeah, this first column is fixed.
The second column is changed to this.
Then you compute the determinant, you get b1.
Then for next one, you have this column as your second column.
So you just shift the second column in this way.
And finally, for this element, when k is am-1,
when k is am-1, then this will be a0.
And this is, yeah, k is m-1.
Then m-1 plus 1 is an.
So that's this period.
Okay?
So that's how you form the two by two matrix.
Yeah, maybe for easy to remember, we compute this one first.
You just use this as the first column, this as the second column.
Then you compute the determinant, you get this.
Then for this, you just change these two values to this.
Yeah, you have to replace the second column by the previous column here.
Then compute determinant until you have this to get this b0.
Okay?
So you just, to compute this, use this pair.
This one, you use this pair.
This one, you use the second pair here.
So that's how we get b.
Once you get b, then you reverse the order.
Yeah, you just reverse the order to get the fourth row.
Okay, for the fifth row, you have to use the previous two rows to do computation.
This time, you use the same rule.
For example, for this Cm minus two, you also have to use the two by two matrix,
which is formed by this column and this column.
Then you compute the determinant of this two by two matrix, you get this.
Then for this value, you replace this column by this column here.
Then compute this until C0 here.
C0, then this will be the second column.
So you can compute the determinant to get C0.
Once you get this C0, you have finished the fifth column.
Then you reverse the order to get the sixth column.
Then you can stop at this here.
You have a second order in this case.
Yeah, you have three values.
So that's how you get the jury table.
Okay, so this is to form the jury table.
Now, let's consider the stability criteria by jury test.
We have four conditions for stability of this polynomial.
First, the magnitude of An, that is the absolute value of this An should be less than A0.
Remember, we put A0 as positive.
Second condition, you compute P1, that is you let Z be one, you compute P1,
which is A0 plus A1 up to An. This should be bigger than zero.
Third condition, you compute the P negative one.
Okay, if n is even number, this value should be bigger than zero.
If n is odd number, yeah, odd integer, for example three, five, then this value should be negative.
And finally, you will use the jury table.
Okay, for the jury table, you have to compare the absolute value of Bn minus one, which is this value,
the absolute value of this term, and also the absolute value of B0, the last one.
This absolute value should be bigger than the absolute value of B0,
and also for other first common values, until Q2, yeah, this Q2,
the absolute value should be bigger than the absolute value of Q0.
So, if all the four conditions are satisfied, this polynomial will have all the poles,
all its roots inside the unit circle.
Okay, you don't have to find the exact location.
Based on this, you know all the roots of Pz should be inside the unit circle.
Now, we have a special case.
For second order system, you only need the first three conditions.
You don't have to form jury table.
So, in that case, you save lots of calculation.
Okay, let's look at some examples.
Yeah, this is a general fourth order polynomial.
Then, you can have these four conditions found.
Yeah, because that's the first condition.
This is P1, and that's P-1.
This should be bigger than zero, because n is a given number.
And also from the jury table, you have these two conditions.
Okay, yeah, in this case, you have a fourth order.
So, you have to form until the fifth row here.
The middle one is not required.
So, you don't have to compute the C1.
Okay, this is how you form the matrix to compute the determinant,
so that B3, B2, B1, B0 can be found.
And this is how you form the two by two matrices to compute the C2, C1, and C0.
I said you don't have to compute C1.
Okay, that's for the case when you have a fourth order polynomial.
And let's look at the numerical example.
So, this is a fourth order polynomial.
You check the first condition.
A0 is actually one, and this A4 is negative 0.08.
So, its opposite value is 0.08, which is less than one.
So, first condition is satisfied.
Yeah, maybe I put this condition here for easy reference.
Okay, so first condition satisfied.
Now, you compute P1.
Just let Z be one, you do a calculation, that's positive.
So, second condition satisfied.
You compute P is negative one, so Z is negative one.
Negative one, that will be positive.
This will also be negative.
Yeah, that's negative.
Then you compute this value.
That's bigger than zero.
So, third condition satisfied.
And finally, you form a jury table to compute the B values and also C values.
This is how you can compute the B values and the C values.
You just form the two by two matrix, find the determinant to get the B3,
and this give you B2, this will give you B1.
Then, from the B values, you can get your C2, C1, and C0.
You don't have to compute C1, in fact.
Okay?
So, all the four conditions are satisfied.
Therefore, this polynomial is a stable polynomial.
In fact, you can check that the four poles are at 0.8, 0.5, negative 0.5, and 0.4.
Yeah.
Now, let's look at the third order polynomial.
Yeah, in this case, A0 is 1, A1 is negative 1.1, A2 is negative 0.1, A3 is 0.2.
So, based on these four conditions, we check the jury test, check the stability.
First, condition satisfied.
That's okay.
Second condition, you compute P1.
That's zero.
What does this mean?
If this is zero, it means one is a solution.
Yeah, because P1 equals zero, that means one satisfies this equation.
So, one is the solution.
So, you have a pole at z equals one, in this case.
Then you compute P1, and this is negative.
So, this condition is satisfied.
And you also have to check the fourth condition.
To check the fourth condition, you have to form the jury table.
So, this is the first row.
You reverse the order to get the second row.
Compute P2.
That's the first P value.
Use this first column and last column.
Compute the determinant.
Get this P2.
Then replace this column by the second last column here.
Compute the determinant.
Get this.
And this is the P0.
In fact, you don't have to compute P1,
because you just need to compare the opposite value of P2
and also the opposite value of P0.
And you can see this condition is also satisfied.
So, what's the conclusion?
Our system is critically stable.
You just have one pole at z equals one.
Two other poles are inside the unit circle.
Okay, now let's consider more examples.
This is a third-order polynomial.
We check the four conditions.
First condition, satisfied.
Second condition, you compute P1.
When z equals one, you do a calculation,
and the answer is negative,
which means this condition is not true.
So what can we say that?
System is unstable.
Then you don't have to proceed.
Yes, you can stop here,
because this second condition is not satisfied.
Then you say this system is unstable.
So when you are using jury criteria to check stability,
you don't form the table.
Like this, you don't have to form the table.
You just check the conditions one by one here.
First condition, second condition, third condition.
If all these conditions are satisfied,
then you form the jury table
and check the fourth condition.
If one of the conditions like this is not satisfied,
then you can stop here.
then you can stop here
to give your answer about the system stability.
Okay, now let's consider a control system.
Just now, we mentioned this closed-loop system.
Okay, assume the sampling period is one second,
and the open-loop pulse transfer function is this.
Yeah, that is gz equals this value, where k is a constant.
What's our h in this case?
Actually, h is one.
How do we know it's one?
Because it says unit feedback.
Nothing means the feedback here is unit feedback.
So h is equal to one.
Okay, now we have to determine the range of k for stability.
Okay, so now we compute the closed-loop pulse transfer function
using this formula, which is g divided by one plus gh.
I said h is equal to one.
So you just substitute this g into here with h as one.
After simplification, you get this.
So that's a second-order system
because the denominator is a second-order.
And in fact, your a0 is equal to one.
a1 equals this.
That's the coefficient of z.
a2 is the constant term.
We don't have to check the force condition
because our system is second-order.
So you don't have to form the jury table.
You just need to consider the first three conditions for this system.
Okay, so we have this first condition.
a2 magnitude should be less than a0.
a0 is one, in fact.
What is a2? a2 is this.
So this observed value should be less than one.
p1 should be bigger than zero according to this.
p-1 also should be bigger than zero
because n is two, which is even.
Okay, so now based on these three conditions,
we will have three inequalities.
Yeah, these are the three conditions to be checked.
Now, for the first condition,
this observed value should be less than one
because a0 is one.
Then you solve this inequality.
Yeah, I believe you know how to solve this inequality.
It has this solution.
Yeah, basically you have to remove the absolute sign.
So that means this term should be bigger than negative one
but less than one.
So you get this solution for k.
Now p1 should be bigger than zero.
And our p1, yeah, you do a calculation.
What is p1?
When z equals one, you can find that it's this value.
Actually, it is just this plus this.
This implies your k should be positive.
Third condition, p-1, you compute p-1.
So you replace z by negative one, negative one.
Then you do a calculation, you get this.
That should be positive.
Less than this.
Your k should satisfy the three conditions simultaneously.
So what's your final result?
You find the overlapping regions.
That's this.
So for stability, your k should be bigger than zero
but less than this.
So you cannot choose your k obviously.
That's why when you design your controller,
you have to be careful about the choice of k.
Actually, when k equals this boundary,
the system becomes critically stable.
In this case, the two, yeah, actually,
this is a second order polynomial.
You have two poles.
These two poles will be on the unit circle
and the pair of, yeah, you solve this equation,
you get this pair of complex conjugate poles.
With the sampling period of one second,
you can find the oscillation frequency from 4.2.
Yeah, 4.2 is the one we're considering
constant damping ratio.
Remember, we have the definition
of constant damping ratio, omega d here.
Yeah.
This.
And omega d is the imaginary part.
Here.
Okay?
So that's the frequency of oscillation.
So omega d
over omega, yeah, omega d times t.
T is one.
So the angle of z is your omega d.
So if you want to find the angle,
you have to use these two terms.
You know how to find the angle?
It's the inverse tangent of the imaginary part
divided by the real part.
Okay?
So it's this.
So that's the frequency of oscillation in this case.
Yeah, if your case is this value,
the feedback system we are considering here
is not,
the output is not convergent.
It will oscillate.
And the frequency of oscillation is this.
Okay, so that's about stability
using jury criteria.
We have another method to check stability.
That is to use the
Rouse array approach.
If you study classical continuous time control system,
you know what is the Rouse array.
If you have not studied,
maybe you don't know this method.
Yeah, basically we will transform our z to w.
Yeah, we define z as this.
Then based on that, w will be equal to this.
Then this transformation
will map the inside of the unit circle in the z-plane
into the left half-plane,
yeah, left side of the w-plane.
You can prove this.
Assume w has a real part and the imaginary part.
The real part is sigma, imaginary part is omega.
Then you compute
the magnitude of z.
Yeah, because later on,
inside the unit circle means the magnitude of z
should be less than one.
Okay, z equals that.
Then you do a calculation
with w changed to that.
Okay, so you compute the magnitude of this
and this should be less than one.
Actually, here,
this condition is equivalent to that
because this is magnitude less than one.
If we take the square
of the magnitude, it's also less than one.
Then the square of the magnitude is equal to this
divided by this, right?
Yeah, the numerator magnitude square
will be sigma plus one squared
plus omega squared.
Yeah, that's how you find the magnitude
of a complex number.
For the denominator,
the real part is sigma minus one.
So the magnitude is sigma minus one squared
plus omega squared.
So if z magnitude is less than one,
it implies this is also less than one.
Actually, if this is less than one,
our z magnitude is also less than one.
So that's sufficient and necessary condition
for these two cases,
these two substitutions.
Now, we consider this part
where you multiply the denominator and both sides.
This inequality becomes that.
Because the denominator is positive,
so you don't reverse the sign here.
So this is the result.
Now you solve this.
Inequality is sigma less than zero.
Based on this proof,
we can see that z magnitude less than one
is equivalent to sigma less than one.
That is, if you have the unit circle in the z-plane,
the inside of this unit circle is equivalent
to the left side of the w-plane.
So based on this,
we can do bilinear transformation
and then use Routh's stability criteria.
What do we do?
Just now, we have a polynomial of z.
So you have Pz.
Then you replace z by this, w plus one over w minus one.
You do a substitution.
So you replace your z by this.
What we have is a rational function in this case,
because this is a rational function here.
So you substitute this into the polynomial Pz.
Then you get a rational function.
Then you consider the numerator of the rational function.
So this numerator is P prime w.
Then, using this P prime w,
you can check the stability of the original Pz
using the continuous Routh's stability criteria.
That is, we have to ensure the roots of P prime w
on the left half-plane,
because we have used this transformation.
So let's look at an example.
Suppose we have this fourth order polynomial
studied earlier in example 4.5.
So now you just replace this z by w plus one over w minus one.
Then you have lots of calculations involved.
You have to compute the fourth power of this,
the third power of this, squared, and this.
Then you do subtraction, addition, and so on.
After simplification, you get this numerator.
Based on this numerator coefficient,
you can form a Routh's array like this.
You should know what is the method of Routh's array
based on the classical continuous control system.
So you form the first row
with the coefficient of the highest power.
You jump one term and jump one.
You get one, 59.78, 21.
For the second row here, that's the second term,
and then jump one, you get this.
Then based on these two rows,
you have the row corresponding to w squared,
and from this you get w1 and w0.
Then you look at the first corner here.
As you can see, there is no change in the sign.
So you have zero root on the right half plane.
The number of changes in the sign in the first column
corresponding to the number of roots of your p prime w
on the right half plane.
If there is no sign change,
you have zero root on the right half plane.
So this is a stable system.
This is a method using our classical control.
For the two methods, we have some remarks.
Our jury table or jury test
does not give you the number of roots
outside the unit circle,
but the Routh's test will give you the number of roots
on the right half plane.
That is the number of unstable roots.
However, the jury table is easier in calculation
than our bilinear transformation.
For example, the case for the fourth order example,
you have to substitute this to the polynomial
and do lots of calculation.
So this is a very tedious computation.
This is not required in our examination
because lots of calculation.
But jury test is definitely required.
Stability has nothing to do with the system's performance.
That is, how the output tracks the input is not discussed.
Stability is to check whether you have a signal
that goes to unbounded.
So now if we want to consider system performance,
we have two analyses,
quadrant and steady state analyses.
For quadrant analysis, it is very difficult.
For second order, it is possible to do analysis manually.
But for high order system
and also for advanced control systems,
normally you will use computational tools such as Matlab.
We did this previously.
We are using Matlab to find the output response.
But here I just gave you some definitions
on the quadrant response.
The response over a time period from zero to settling time
is called quadrant response.
You have overshoot, you have rise time,
you have settling time like this.
Just previous week, we studied the settling time requirement.
So this is quadrant response.
You are using computational tool to find such results.
So here we don't consider our calculation manually.
I will study steady state response
because we can use final value theorem
to determine our steady state value.
Steady state means your time goes to infinity.
So we have steady state error analysis
as our last part of these four weeks.
Okay, so how do we study steady state error analysis?
We will use some typical input signals.
They are called test signals.
The typical signals are step input, ramp input,
and the acceleration input.
Also, we have to recall one important concept.
For continuous time system,
you have this open loop transfer function.
Open loop means, for example, you have this feedback system.
That's closed loop.
That's closed.
Open loop means you've broken the loop.
So in this case, it's open.
Then you have open loop transfer function.
For continuous time system, it's Gs times Hs.
So if the open loop transfer function is like this,
the number of integrators in the open loop transfer function,
N, is called the type of system.
Okay, we have this concept.
Now, for discrete time system,
if we have this open loop transfer function,
that is, this is open,
then the open loop is G times H.
Yeah, that's this part here.
Then, if this open loop transfer function is denoted as this,
we have integrator 1 over Z minus 1 to power N.
So that means you have also an integrator here.
This is called the type of discrete time system,
similar to the continuous time system.
Of course, in this situation,
your Pz and Az shouldn't have the factor of Z minus 1.
Yeah, if your Pz has a factor of this,
that will cancel out this.
If your Az has such a factor,
it should combine with this.
So that's the definition of the type of system.
Okay, now we consider this system
Yeah, this is a typical discrete time control system.
We have this actual 18-a-root, E t,
which is R t minus B t.
Yeah, actually this E t is a continuous time signal.
Of course, you can take Z transform
to obtain E z equal to R z minus B z.
Yeah, for continuous time signal, you have Z transform,
as I mentioned before.
Okay, so we are looking for the steady state error
of E t or E kt.
So based on final value theorem,
the steady state error will be equal to E kt,
when k tends to infinity.
That's the definition of steady state error.
Based on final value theorem,
this is the same as this.
Of course, assume the system is stable.
Yeah, if your system is unstable,
then you have divergence.
Okay, so this E z is this E z here.
Then you have 1 minus Z inverse times this Z transform of E.
And then take an limit of Z tends to one,
you get the answer.
Okay, so that's how we find the steady state error.
Okay, now let's consider a few typical case.
Yeah, first, with the input.
With this input.
Yeah, okay.
Okay.
Yeah, here actually we do some analysis.
E z equals R z minus B z, as I just mentioned.
Here.
Yeah, that's E z.
So you do some analysis.
And this B z equals G H z times E z.
From the block diagram.
Yeah, that's B t.
So you have B z here.
This is the pulse transfer function, you can find out.
Then times E z here.
Okay, G H z times E z.
And how do we find the G H z for this system?
Yeah, we have a zero-order hold.
So you have to use the zero-order hold formula,
which has this factor, 1 minus Z inverse.
Then times Z transform of G p times H s over s.
Basically, you multiply G p with H, and then divide by s.
Then you find the corresponding Z transform,
then multiply with that.
You get this pulse transfer function.
So B z will be equal to this pulse transfer function times E z.
Okay?
Yeah, we did this in week three.
Okay, so based on that, you can find G z equals this.
Yeah, you substitute this.
Yeah, you consider this equation.
You move the term here to the left and factorize E z out.
Then you find E z to be this.
Right?
So you move this here.
You have coefficient 1 plus G H z as the coefficient of E z.
So E z equals that.
Okay, so we are using this E z to find the steady state.
Yeah, based on final value theorem.
So it's 1 minus Z inverse times E z when Z turns to 1.
Okay?
So this analysis is possible for us to do.
Okay, now let's consider a few typical case.
When the input is unit step,
yeah, when this is unit step,
then we do steady state analysis.
If this is unit step, R z will be equal to this.
Then we substitute this R z to the formula we just obtained.
Yeah, this is the formula we just obtained.
Yeah, you have this R z.
Then this one times this.
This cancel out.
So you just have this term.
And this limit is equal to that.
So based on this, we can have a definition.
Called position error constant, K P.
That is this term.
Then the steady state error will be 1 over 1 plus K P.
Okay, this K P, what depends on the type of the system?
Yeah, just now I have a definition of the type of the system.
Here.
Yeah, this is the open loop transfer function, G H Z.
Yeah, that's G H Z.
So if you have zero integrator, what do you have here?
When Z tends to 1, you get B1 divided by A1.
Yeah, if this N is zero, you don't have this part.
So you just have B1 divided by A1.
So this K P is just a constant.
Then you have a non-zero error in this case.
Because 1 over 1 plus K P, K P is a constant.
So in this case, you cannot find the zero steady state error
to track this constant input.
However, if your open loop transfer function here has an integrator,
for example, N equals 1, what do you have?
When Z equals 1, that is when Z tends to 1,
this will go to infinity, right?
Yeah, because 1 divided by 0, that's infinity.
If N is 1, what's bigger than 1?
Then this is a constant.
So this is infinity, K P can be infinity,
then this 1 divided by infinity will be zero.
So if you want to have zero steady state error,
your open loop transfer function should have at least one integrator.
Okay, so that's the case when we consider unit step input.
Now, if your input here is a ramp,
yeah, ramp, what's the,
yeah, if this R T here is the ramp,
in this case, your R Z will be equal to this.
Yeah, you can find this Z transform from the table.
So, you use the formula we just have,
then you substitute this R Z to here,
and do some calculation.
Actually, here, you have a square,
so any cancel out one factor,
so you have 1 minus Z inverse lift in the denominator here.
So this multiply the denominator here,
you have these two terms, okay?
Then when Z go to one, this will go to zero,
that will go to one.
So you have this, yeah, this T in the numerator,
that go to zero, so you have this part,
and you divide T again, you get this.
So we have a definition of velocity error constant K V.
For this case,
you see this error will be one divided by K V, right?
This is the definition.
Actually, K V also depends on the number of integrators.
Yeah, if this N is zero, what is K V?
If this N is zero, you don't have this.
Then when Z go to one, this term will go to constant.
So that means this is a constant.
Then this will go to zero.
So K V is zero, then that will be infinity.
In this case, if you have no integrator,
your speed is error will go to infinity
if your input is ramped.
However, if your system has one integrator,
this will cancel out with this.
Yeah, one under the inverse will cancel out this,
then you have a constant.
So you have a non-zero state error,
but not go to infinity.
Okay?
Similarly, you can analyze acceleration input.
In this case, you have this R Z,
then you do some calculation by substituting this R Z to here.
Yeah, you get this.
You have cube, so you have square left in the denominator.
After you take limit, you get this.
And you can put this square in the denominator.
And we have the definition of acceleration error constant, K A.
So that's the definition.
Again, steady state error will be one over K A.
Okay, so these are the definitions of three error constants.
And based on the error constants,
we have those steady state error summarized in this table.
Just now, I already considered,
if you have a step input and your system types zero,
you have non-zero steady state error.
Because K P is a constant.
And if your system type one, that means
if you have one integrator, that will go to zero.
Two integrator, that will go to zero.
For ramp input, yeah, this is the input to the system.
Type zero, that error will go to infinity.
I already analyzed that.
For type one, that's a constant.
For type two, that will be zero.
And so on, you have this situation.
Okay, so that's the steady state error analysis.
Yeah, this analysis just applies to our system here.
Because our transfer function is obtained
based on this system.
And also, actually, the error I mentioned
is not steady state tracking error.
It's a steady state actuating error here.
You see, it's the error between R T and B T.
If H is one, then it's tracking error.
Okay?
If you have other configurations,
you can do similar analysis.
Yeah, you have some other configuration here.
Maybe as exercise, you can define
the position error constant, velocity error constant,
acceleration constant, or coordinate
for each of the configuration in the system.
Okay, finally, we consider our response to disturbance.
Yeah, just now we considered input R T here.
And we found the output.
Now, if we have disturbance, for example here,
you have disturbance entering the system.
Then, how do we find the output?
You can use superposition, because this is a linear system.
So, in other words, the total output C Z
will be equal to the output when R is zero
and N is non-zero, plus when N is zero, R is non-zero.
So, you find the response of your output
respectively to R and N.
Previously, we already considered response to R.
So, now we focus on response to disturbance.
So, we want to find the output in response to N.
To do this, we find the transfer function from N to C.
Okay, we do a transformation of the block diagram.
I think you should know how to do block diagram transformation.
So, that's N.
Then, after this, you have this G.
Yeah, that's G.
Yeah, this is a summation, but here is a subtraction.
So, this sign is moved to here.
So, N applied to this, you have G.
Then, that's output C.
C is feedback through, yeah, GD.
So, here, C is feedback through GD.
This negative sign is moved to here.
Okay?
So, you have feedback pass.
Okay, based on this diagram,
you can find the transfer function
from N to output C.
And then, you find the error.
Actually, we also consider error analysis.
Okay?
Yeah.
So, our R is zero in this case.
What's the error for this situation?
The error is actual 18 error.
If we have unit feedback,
yeah, actually, this diagram is unit feedback.
Then, the error is same as tracking error.
So, it's R minus C.
Yeah, that's always the definition of error G.
And R is zero, so that's negative C, right?
Yeah, we assume R is zero,
because we try to use superposition.
So, this is the transfer function
from N to C.
It's G divided by one plus G times GD.
But, in front, you have negative,
and the input here is N.
So, that's how you find this C.
C is equal to this G divided by that times N.
Okay?
Okay.
If the denominator here is much bigger than one,
then you can, I mean, the magnitude,
yeah, is much bigger than one,
then you can ignore this one.
If you ignore that,
then this becomes this, approximately.
Okay?
So, this G comes out with this G.
You have negative one over GD N.
So, based on this 4.11,
if this GD has very large magnitude for all Z,
the error is small.
In fact, we want this error to be small.
That means, if this is small,
the effect of disturbance is small.
Okay?
Now, let's consider a special case.
That is, if this N is a constant disturbance,
yeah, just now we considered general case.
If N is constant,
and this GD includes a pure integrator,
which means GD has a pole at Z equals one.
Yeah, this GD is designed by us.
So, you can include an integrator in your GD.
And we also assume this GZ.
That's the transfer function of the plant.
Yeah, GD is a controller.
GZ is the transfer function of the plant.
So, GZ has no zero at Z equals one.
If we have zero, then this integrator pole
will be cancelled out by this zero.
Then, under this saturation,
this error due to a constant disturbance is zero.
Yeah, the K word here is steady state error.
So, that means one time go to infinity.
Even if you have a non-zero value here,
the error will be eliminated by the integrator.
Of course, during the transition period,
you cannot eliminate.
Okay, now let's do a proof.
Assume this GD equals that.
Because GD has an integrator,
so the denominator should have this factor.
And the remaining part is just G hat D, Z.
Of course, this is non-polynomial.
It's actually a transfer function.
Yeah, we just factorized Z minus one out.
So, based on this, you can also do this manipulation.
And this part has no zero at Z equals one.
Because if you have zero,
then the integrator has no meaning.
It's cancelled out.
Now, we assume the constant disturbance is C.
The value is C.
So, the disturbance Z transform is C divided by this.
This is the Z transform of a constant value.
Okay, now let's use 4.10 to do calculation.
4.10 is here.
Now, of course, you have to substitute this GD into here.
And the GZ, yeah, this GZ has no zero at Z equals one.
NZ, NZ equals that.
So, we substitute NZ and the GD to this 4.10.
And also consider the final value theorem.
You get this.
This G is this G.
Yeah, that's your controller part.
That's NZ.
Okay, so NZ equals that.
Just now, we get this NZ.
And we have this just copied here.
Okay, so you do a calculation.
You multiply one minus Z inverse.
Inside the denominator, you have these two terms.
Yeah, one times that, you get this.
This one minus Z inverse comes out with this.
So, you have GD hat Z, Z inverse times G.
Then one minus Z inverse combined with G and C, you get this.
Okay, you take a limit.
This goes to zero because G has no zero at Z equals one.
So, this will go to constant.
C is a constant.
So, a constant times zero is zero.
This will go to zero, but this is non-zero.
That's not equal to one.
That's G one.
G one is non-zero because you don't have zero at the...
Yeah, GZ has no zero at Z equals one.
So, this is zero.
Okay?
So, we proved our disturbance has no effect.
And your arrow at the speed state.
That means this disturbance effect is eliminated by a controller,
including integrator.
If your controller has integrator, so at the speed state,
if this is a constant, it has no effect.
But it has effect during transition period.
Okay, so that's the first part of my course.
I will come back in week nine.
Yeah, but before that, we have a quiz today.
Okay.
Its
so when the paper distribute to you don't turned it over we will start at the same time
yeah otherwise some people were early.
You didn't like a paper then stardate that's not fair.
Okay.
So we were start at the eight 45.
At the same time all the students
Don't turn it over, just put the paper on the table.
Don't turn it over.
Don't write.
Hello?
Excuse me.
Hello.
Don't turn it over.
We will start the quiz at the same time.
Just put the paper on the table.
Wait until 845.
Also, when you submit the answers, you have to submit to the invagilator.
The invagilator will make a tick to take your attendance, okay?
Yeah, I think it's enough.
The space will be enough.
Okay.
Yeah, we see one page.
Two, three.
Yeah.
Any way for their draft.
They prepare their own.
They want to prepare their own?
Do they have their own?
Their draft.
Do they prepare their own?
No.
They can also write off to here.
Yeah.
Okay, please don't turn the paper over until we ask you to do so.
Okay.
No.
Just use this.
You don't have to use your own rough paper.
Just write your draft.
I think we have enough space.
Okay.
You can use the back side.
Yeah, we should be uniform.
So just use the paper.
Yeah.
The space will be taken when you submit your answers, okay?
So later, yeah, group one, submit to her.
Yeah, you can stand here, right?
Yeah.
Group two, submit to him.
Group three, to her.
Group four, to her.
And to him.
Group five, to her.
Group six, to her.
Group seven, to her.
Group eight, to her.
Group nine, to her.
Group 10, to her.
Group 11, to her.
Group 12, to her.
Group 13, to her.
Group 14, to her.
Group 15, to her.
Group 16, to her.
Group 17, to her.
Group 18, to her.
Group 19, to her.
Group 20, to her.
Group 21, to her.
Group 22, to her.
Group 23, to her.
Group 24, to her.
Group 25, to her.