.
I believe you started container design based on status-based model.
Now we will consider container design based on transfer functions.
So we have three approaches.
Basically, in this chapter, we will study how to design digital containers for this system.
We have a few approaches.
Before I show you the approaches, let's consider the block diagram shown here.
In this block diagram, we have a plan to be controlled.
This plan is given to you.
For example, you want to control DC motor.
This plan is DC motor.
If you are going to control a car, the motion of the car, then this is the car.
So that should be given.
So this is the system to be controlled.
Then when we implement digital control, we should have sampling and the zero-order hood, as we discussed during the third chapter.
So this is a block diagram of the control system.
Basically, we are going to design a digital controller for this plant, such that this output follows the required trajectory.
To do the design, we have to model the system.
So in our third chapter, we studied how to find the model or the transfer function for the plant together with the zero-order hood.
So this transfer function is represented as GZAS.
Z means zero-order hood.
AS means analog system.
That is the plant.
So we have GZAS Z.
That's the transfer function of these two blocks.
Okay, for the controller, we have this transfer function CZ.
So in the design, this is given.
Of course, you must make sure the system meets some requirements.
For example, stability.
That's the essential requirement.
Also, you have to ensure the overall system to meet the given specifications, which include the transient performance and the steady-state performance.
So based on such requirements under the transfer function, GZAS Z, you have to find CZ.
So our purpose is to find the CZ.
That is the controller design.
So we are going to consider how to find the CZ with the following three approaches.
First, we design our analog controller for the system.
And then we approximate the analog controller by a digital transfer function.
So this is the first approach.
Second approach is called direct Z-domain digital controller design based on frequency response approach.
So you have to use the results in the classical control.
In classical control, you know how to design a compensator based on the continuous transfer function in the frequency domain.
So this is the second approach.
Third approach is called direct control design based on pulse transfer function.
We have three approaches to find this CZ.
Let's consider the first approach.
That is digital implementation of analog controller design.
This is actually indirect approach.
Why is it indirect?
Because you design continuous controller based on the given transfer function of the plant.
Then you convert the continuous controller to a digital controller.
So that's the idea.
So the approach is based on design analog controller for the analog plant.
And then you obtain an equivalent digital controller and use it to do the implementation.
So that's the idea.
We have two steps.
For the first step, you just design a controller CS.
CS means continuous controller for the analog subsystem.
To meet the desired design specification.
As mentioned, our plant is given.
So you know the model of this plant.
Of course, that's the transfer function in continuous time domain.
And also the desired specifications are given.
So based on those given information, you have to find a continuous controller.
Use your method studied in the classical control course.
There are a number of approaches to find out CS.
So I don't have to repeat it here.
I assume you know the classical methods to design continuous time control.
Actually, later on, when we consider the second approach, which is based on frequency domain,
we will review how to design continuous controller from the frequency domain.
Okay, once you have done this, that means CS has been found.
You just map the analog controller CS to the digital controller GD.
That is to find this.
Or that is the CZ in this figure.
So that is you have to convert this CS to CZ using a suitable transformation.
Later on, we will study a few approaches or a few transformations to do this conversion.
Once you have this done, that means you get the CZ.
Then you have to check the response of your digital control system.
That means you have this GZ-AS available.
You have found this CZ.
So you can use your computational tool, such as MATLAB, to find out the response of the closed-loop system
based on some test input signals, such as step input, ramp input, and so on.
So you have to check the time response of the system after you get your CZ.
If your time response satisfies the given specification, then you can stop.
Then you just use this CZ for implementation.
Otherwise, you have to repeat the procedure in one or two.
That means you may have to do some modification in your design to meet the requirement.
So this is a kind of iterative trial and error process to find our CZ.
So that's the procedure.
We have three steps to design our CZ based on the continuous controller CS.
This is a block diagram showing how this is done.
So this is GS. That's given.
Yeah, that's the transformation of the plant.
So you just use the continuous approach to find CS, as I just mentioned.
You have a number of approaches to find CS to meet the requirement.
After you have found CS, you convert this to CZ with a suitable transformation.
Yeah, that is the conversion.
But when you do the implementation, you have to have a sampling and a zero-order hood.
That is like here.
You have a sampler, that's this, and you have a zero-order hood.
Yeah, this is the plant GS.
Okay, this approach works very well if the sampling period T is sufficiently small.
That means when you do this approximation using CZ to replace CS, this T cannot be very big.
If it's very big, you have a big approximation error.
Okay, so this is a graphic illustration of our design approach.
Okay, how we obtain CS from GS, as I said, I don't have to repeat it here.
Then we just consider the second step.
That is to, yeah, our focus here is the second step.
That is how we find CZ to approximate CS.
Okay, so that's the focus of today's lecture.
Yeah, for this step, we need to have the following requirements.
A stable analog filter.
Actually, our consumer is just a filter.
Okay, so that is our stable controller.
Must be transformed to a stable controller also in the digital version.
Stable means if we have poles in the left half plane for your CS,
then the poles in the digital controller should be within the unit circle.
The frequency response of the digital controller must closely resemble
the frequency response of the analog controller in the range from zero to half omega S hertz,
where omega S is the sampling frequency.
Yeah, we require our omega S to satisfy some conditions to avoid the anti-annoying effect.
That is, we have to follow the Nyquist sampling theorem.
Over this range, we need the frequency response of the digital controller
to be closely following the frequency response of the original analog filter.
In fact, in our chapter four, when we talk about the mapping between S plane and Z plane,
we have a primary strip.
So this from zero to half omega S is the primary strip of the S plane.
So this will be considered in the frequency response.
So we have these two requirements when you do the mapping.
Okay, now let's consider some methods which transform our CS to CZ.
Maybe hair rotation is GS to GDZ. The idea is the same.
So to show the approach, we consider this simple first order controller.
First order means the relationship between the input and output is modeled
by this first order differential equation here.
So this is equivalent to this, dy dt equals this.
And this transfer function for this is given as YS over XS.
Yeah, because X is the input, Y is the output.
So from that, you can see this transfer function will be A divided by S plus A.
Yeah, I believe you can find this transfer function easily based on this differential equation.
You just take a non-prol transform on both sides, then find this ratio. You get this answer.
Okay, so now we consider this equation.
Yeah, because we are going to convert this transfer function to discrete time transfer function.
So we consider the integration of this equation on both sides from K minus one T to KT.
Yeah, we have this result. You integrate both sides.
Okay, now we are going to...
Yeah, for this integral it's easy. What's the result? It's Y.
The integral of the derivative of Y is just Y.
Of course, this is a definite integral.
So you have to compute the different integral with Y, with lower limit K minus one T, upper limit KT.
For the right side, we will do approximation.
Yeah, because we are going to approximate this transfer function.
That is, we are going to find what is S to be changed to.
So we consider the approximation of the integral on this right side.
So we have three approaches to do the approximation.
Okay, I put this here. So we are going to consider the approximation of this term and this term.
So first is backward difference of approximation method.
So basically, for example, for this Y.
Suppose your Y is something like this. Yeah, this is your Y.
That's T. So the integral is taken from K minus one T to KT, like this.
So exactly the integral is the area below this, correct?
Yeah, below this curve, from this point to this point.
Now, we just approximate this area by the area of this triangle.
So you have a rectangle like this.
The length of one side will be this, Y KT.
And the length of the other side is just the sampling period T. That's this.
So this area will be Y KT times T.
So this integral, that means this term, can be approximated by this.
And in the same way, the second term, this term, can be approximated by X KT times T with the same idea.
Therefore, our equation, 5.3 here, can be changed to this.
Yeah, this is the integral on the left side.
As I said, this integral is just YT, so you compute the definite integral.
It will be Y KT minus YK minus one T.
On the right side, we have these two approximations.
This term here is changed to negative A times this area.
And this second term, it will be A times this area.
OK, this is a difference equation.
So you take a Z transform on both sides.
Of course, you move this term to the left.
So move this term to the right.
So the left side will be YZ.
Yeah, the Z transform of Y KT will be YZ.
For this term, you apply the shifting value theorem.
It will be Z inverse because this is delayed by one sample.
So Z inverse YZ.
For this, you have a common factor, A times capital T.
So that's YZ minus this XZ.
Therefore, from this, our discrete time transfer function will be equal to...
Yeah, you just use this.
So from this, you find the ratio, YZ divided by XZ.
It will be this.
OK, so that's the Z transfer function.
So this first order transfer function in 5.2 is converted to this Z transfer function.
Yeah, from this, you can note your S.
Yeah, this S is changed to one under Z inverse divided by T.
Yeah, you just replace this S by that.
For stable digital transfer function here, we should have this to be less than zero also.
OK, so this is called forward method.
Oh, sorry, backward difference method.
So we just replace our S by this one under Z inverse divided by T or Z minus one divided by TZ.
OK, so that's the first approach.
Now, for the second approach, just now, we have backward difference method.
So next is forward difference method.
Why here is backward?
Because we approximate this line by this horizontal line.
Yeah, this is backward because this is YK minus one.
So you backward one step here.
Now forward.
Forward, you are going to use this value to obtain a rectangle.
So here, the area below this curve is approximated by this rectangle, the area of this rectangle.
Yeah, this part.
So that's called forward difference method.
So in this case, our integral, the area below this curve is approximated by this area, which is YK minus one T.
Because at this point, the function value is YK minus one T.
OK, so you are using this as the length of one side, then times T.
T is the length of the rectangle of the other side.
OK, so similarly, the second term can also be approximated by this.
Then this equation, yeah, this equation here, 503.
We'll change to this.
Yeah, left side has no approximation.
And the right side, yeah, this left side is exactly equal to this.
For the right side here, you have these two approximations.
Then you take Z transform.
You have this equation.
Then you find the ratio of YZ over XZ.
So you get this answer.
Therefore, you change your S to this.
You get the Z transfer function.
Yeah, you get this Z transfer function.
OK, so that's the second approximation method.
Now we have the third one.
Third one, we don't consider rectangle.
We will consider a trapezium.
So you have this base.
This is another base.
So this trapezium is this.
So what's the area of this trapezium?
It will be equal to half times this length plus this length,
then multiplied by this height.
So that's the third method called the bilinear transformation method.
Basically, we have this approximation.
So it will be this length plus this length divided by 2.
That's this times T.
So that's the area of the trapezium here.
Similarly, for the second term, you have this approximation.
So in this case, our equation here, 5.3, will be changed to this.
The left side is YKT minus YK minus 1T.
On the right side, we have these two approximations.
So you have this difference equation.
Then you take a Z-transform on both sides,
and then to some simplification, you have this result.
Yeah, this is YZ.
This move to the right, you have Z inverse YZ.
For this term, it will be YZ plus Z inverse YZ times AT divided by 2.
Yeah, for this, you also have the same as this.
Okay, you take the ratio.
Basically, you have to find the ratio of YZ over XZ.
So you get this discrete time transfer function.
Okay, compare this transfer function with our Laplace transfer function here.
We can see that S is replaced by this term.
2 over T, 1 minus Z inverse divided by 1 plus Z inverse.
Or equivalently, you have this approximation.
Okay, so this is the third transformation method
called bilinear transformation method.
Yeah, this method is frequently used
because you can see the approximation error is smaller
than the other two methods.
Okay, this is to approximate the integral.
Now we have another approximation method
called the pole-zero matching.
Yeah, so you can see based on the title here,
pole-zero means you are going to consider the pole and the zero
of your transfer function.
Yeah, so this is the transfer function of the analog controller.
Yeah, that is the controller we obtained.
Here, I use the notation GAS.
Actually, at the beginning, it's the CS.
So this is represented in pole-zero form.
Yeah, that means you have to factorize your numerator
and the denominator into a number of factors.
Of course, in front, we have again, K.
So that's the transfer function we obtained in the first step.
That is, you obtain your CS from the analog design method.
Okay, so we are going to convert this to a digital controller.
So based on pole-zero matching.
Yeah, the idea is this.
We use this relationship, z equals e to the power st,
to do the matching.
So based on this, all the poles for the analog transfer function
in the poles are bi.
So bi is converted to e to the power bit
based on this relationship.
If you have m poles, all the m poles are converted in this form.
So it's the product of z minus e to the power bit.
Okay, that's the mapping of poles.
Now, we have zeros.
In this case, we have m zeros.
Yeah, so each zero ai is mapped to this e ai t.
So you have m zero here.
Okay, when we consider pole-zero matching, that's not enough.
Because based on this transfer function,
we have order difference, which is m minus m.
Okay, m minus m.
You have m poles, m zeros.
This actually means
there are m minus m zeros at infinity
for this transfer function.
So those zeros should be considered
when you do the pole-zero matching.
So you have to add either m minus m
or m minus m minus one zeros
in the transfer function gz.
These zeros are at negative one.
Yeah, that is the zeros at infinity
is corresponding to negative one in the z domain.
Basically, we are going to set this,
yeah, this omega t should be equal to pi
because we have to have an upper bound
for the mapping from the continuous frequency
to the digital frequency.
Yeah, this is to follow the Nyquist sampling theorem.
So basically, the frequency at the infinity
is corresponding to half omega s.
So if you substitute the half omega s to here,
yeah, that is when omega equals to half omega s,
then omega t is pi.
Yeah, because half omega s times t,
yeah, you do a calculation, half omega s times t.
That is equal to, what is omega s times t?
It's two pi, right?
Then this divided by two, so it's pi.
Yeah, omega, you have to note,
basically, our t is,
yeah, this t is just the one over f, correct?
But omega s is two pi f.
So that's why omega s times t will be two pi.
So two pi divided by two is pi.
So that's why at this frequency,
the corresponding location in the z domain is negative one.
Okay?
So the continuous time in the s domain,
the frequency at the infinity,
the zero at the infinity corresponding
to our frequency in the infinity in the s domain,
this should be corresponding to the boundary
of half omega s when you do the matching
by following the Nyquist sampling theorem.
So all those zeros should be mapped to negative one.
That's why we either have z plus one,
two power of m minus m,
or z plus one, two power of m minus one.
This will be sufficient.
So these are the pole-zero matching.
Now, how about the gain?
So we have to consider the gain also.
So here, we don't know this alpha.
So we don't know the gain in gz.
We just put the alpha.
So we have to select our frequency to find our alpha.
So this frequency maybe is a critical frequency
to be considered.
For example, for no-pulse filter,
alpha is selected to match the dc gain.
At dc gain, for this case,
in the s domain, dc gain means ga zero.
In the z domain, dc gain means g one.
So based on this condition, you can find your alpha.
Okay?
So that's the method of using pole-zero approach
to convert gas to gz.
So basically, we have four steps.
First, you convert all the poles, bi,
to e to the power of bit,
where t is the sampling period.
Second step, you convert zero ai to e to the power of ait.
You have m zeros.
You have to do this m times.
And the third step, you have to consider the zero at infinity.
Yeah, either you added this z plus one to the power of m
plus m, or m minus m,
or z plus one to the power of m minus m minus one.
Both are okay.
And finally, the fourth step is to find a constant alpha
to match the gain of gas and gz at a critical frequency.
Yeah.
As I said, normally, it's at the zero frequency.
dc gain is zero frequency.
Zero frequency in s domain, that means it changes s to zero.
In z domain, you change z to one.
Yeah, because when s is zero, if you use this, z will be one.
Okay?
So we have four steps to do this.
Yeah, that is this relationship here to find alpha.
Okay, let's look at the example.
Suppose we have found a transfer function, gas.
We need to use a pole-zero matching method
to find the corresponding discrete time transfer function.
Okay, so for this transfer function,
we have the following data given.
The damping ratio is equal to 0.5.
Yeah, that is this zeta.
This zeta is our damping ratio.
That's 0.5.
So I maybe write this here.
So this is our zeta.
Under the undamped natural frequency, that is omega n.
Yeah, this omega n is five radians per second.
If the sampling period, t, is 0.1 second,
you have to find the corresponding
digital controller transfer function.
Then you can use the frequency response
of the obtained digital filter
to check the accuracy of your approximation.
Okay, so based on these three data
and also the transfer function,
you can use the pole-zero approximation to find the gz.
So here, for the given transfer function here,
our n is two, m is zero, correct?
Yeah, so this n should be two, this m is zero.
So we have two poles.
And you can find these two poles at negative zeta omega n
plus minus j omega d, where omega d is equal to that.
Okay, how do we get this?
You just solve the equation by making the denominator zero.
You can find these two solutions.
Two solutions.
Okay, now gz, yeah, based on this result,
for the first step, you have to map the two poles
to the product of these two factors.
Yeah, one is e to the power of negative zeta omega n
plus j omega d.
The other is, yeah, and the map of the other one
is e to the power of negative zeta omega n minus j omega d.
Actually, if you do some simple calculation of this product,
yeah, you have two factors here.
If you multiply the two factors,
you get this answer in the denominator.
Yeah, you can see that the multiplication will be this.
You just have, yeah, for the denominator,
one pole is this, another pole is this, s2, s1, s2, okay?
So if you do multiplication, this will be z squared for,
yeah, this z times z is z squared for this.
The coefficient of this z, it will be negative
this times one plus this times one,
so it's this summation times z.
Then for the constant term, this one times this,
you get this.
Okay, when you do this addition,
yeah, consider this addition, it will be this.
Yeah, the s1 is negative zeta omega nt
plus j omega dt, as you can see,
from there.
So when you do this exponential,
it will be separate into the product of these two terms.
For the second term, it will be this.
Then you can factorize this out.
Yeah, you get the zeta omega nt,
then you have this left in the first term,
you have this left in the second term.
Okay, this plus this is two times cosine omega nt.
Dt, right?
Yeah, this plus this will be twice of cosine omega dt
based on the OE norm formula.
Okay, so that's why we have this.
Negative two times e to our negative zeta omega nt
times this times z.
Yeah, that's the coefficient of z.
Now for this product, yeah,
you can also do multiplication,
e to our s1t times e to our s2t will be equal to this.
And s1 plus s2, the imaginary part will be cancel out.
The real part is just negative twice zeta omega nt.
Okay?
As you can see here.
So, the constant term will be just equal to this here.
Okay, so that's the denominator.
Yeah, based on this mapping,
our denominator is equal to this.
For the numerator, because we don't have zero,
so we don't have this part,
we only have to consider one zero at negative one.
So we have z plus one, two power of two minus one minus one,
which is one here.
Okay, in front, we have a constant alpha.
So you have to determine this alpha
from our given transfer function here.
Yeah, from this given gas.
Okay, so you have to do some calculation.
Yeah, here, you have to compute this omega d.
Yeah, omega d is given here,
omega n times square root one minus zeta square.
This omega n is five, and this zeta is zero point five.
So your calculation is this.
So you get omega d, then later you have to time zero point one
to get this omega dt.
So, you get this answer here.
Yeah.
You have to calculate this also,
zeta omega nt, that's zero point five,
and this is five, then times zero point one,
then take the exponential of g to the power of negative time,
and you get this.
Okay, so now, to get alpha, how do we get alpha?
Yeah, you choose...
When s is zero, then this is one, right?
So gas, when s is zero, that's one.
So here, you also use the condition.
Yeah, that is, when z...
Yeah, you have to get this alpha.
When z equals one, yeah, when z equals one,
then you have two alpha here,
then you have to compute the,
you have to compute the denominator also.
Yeah, we have to get these values,
then from that, you get this value for the alpha.
So that's the gz in the discrete time domain.
And we also can plot the frequency response
of our gas, yeah, that is this transfer function,
and also the obtained gz here.
So you can plot this, the frequency response
of these two transfer functions.
So this is the magnitude of gz,
and this is the magnitude of gs.
This is the phase.
You can see that for the frequency range
from up to this,
this is 10, 20, 30, here.
You have good approximation.
Okay?
Yeah, let's have, let's consider another example.
Yeah, this time, we have this transfer function,
and the damping ratio is 0.88.
Omega n is 1.15.
Actually similar to this.
So if you choose sampling period as 0.02 second,
you follow the approach same as we did earlier.
We have this transfer function to approximate this here.
Yeah, by using the pole-zero matching.
Now let's consider a design example.
In this example,
we consider the,
a car.
Yeah, we are going to control this car.
The weight of this car is 1000 kilogram.
Assume the average friction coefficient B is 100.
We have to design a cruise control system
such that the car can reach this speed,
which is 100 kilometer per hour from stationary
in eight seconds, with overshoot less than 20%.
Okay, so based on the approach I just mentioned,
first, we have to design a controller
for the continuous system.
Yeah, this is a continuous plant.
The plant is a car, okay?
So this is the plant.
That's the car here.
So we have to design our CS.
Yeah, based on the,
based on this idea here,
we have to find the transfer function for this also.
Yeah, later on, we need to find this transfer function
for this system.
Yeah, to find the transfer function, what's the input?
What's the output?
Yeah, the output is easy.
It's speed, right?
The output of the car.
Yeah, maybe for this example,
this is the car.
So the output is a speed, V.
What's the input?
Input is the force, okay?
Yeah, you can find the force to drive the car.
So this U here, actually this U here is the force.
How do we find this model for the car?
In other words, how do we find this GS?
Yeah, you can use Newton's second law.
So what's the total force applied to the car?
This is the driving force.
So it's U, then minus the friction.
Yeah, what's the friction?
You have a friction coefficient 100.
Yeah, this friction force is proportional to the speed, BV.
So this should be equal to M, which is the mass,
times acceleration.
The acceleration is V dot here.
Okay, so that's how you find this equation for the car.
Then we are looking for GS.
So you move this B to the right side.
You have MV dot plus BV.
Then take a Laplace transform on both sides.
You have US on the left.
Then this, yeah, what's a Laplace transform?
A Laplace transform of V dot is S times VS, okay?
So this is M times SVS.
Yeah, that's the property of a Laplace transform.
Yeah, this is the derivative.
Then plus BVS.
So our transfer function GS for this car will be
output, yeah, our output is VS divided by input US.
That will be one over MS plus B.
Okay, so that's the transfer function for this car.
So we are going to design this U
to achieve the requirement here.
The specification has,
yeah, this is a transient requirement,
transient response requirement.
The overshoot should be less than 20%.
And the set, yeah, this is like settling time.
So from zero to a second.
You're set to, from zero to this speed
is like settling time.
Yeah, actually here should be,
the input should be 100 kilometer per hour.
Yeah, it's no unit step.
It's 100 kilometer per hour.
And the hours,
so this performance can be converted
to this transfer function.
Yeah, that's the closed loop transfer function.
In other words, this overwork system,
this overwork closed loop system
should have this transfer function.
Okay, in this case,
based on the given specification,
we can find omega N and zeta.
Now for this overshoot 20%,
yeah, less than 20% requirement,
our damping ratio should be bigger than
or equal to 0.46.
Yeah, for second order system,
there is a relationship between overshoot
and the damping ratio.
Yeah, that was covered in the classical control design.
Yeah, you have a formula to compute overshoot
for a given damping ratio.
So from that, you can find your damping ratio zeta
based on this information.
So we choose zeta as 0.7.
And we also note our settling time.
Yeah, I think we studied settling time in chapter four.
We have a few definitions.
You have 2% settling time,
5% settling time,
and here we have 1%.
So if you still remember for 5% settling time,
Ts,
yeah, this settling time will be
three divided by zeta omega N.
Right?
And the 2%
is, this settling time is four over zeta omega N.
Yeah, you take a longer time
because you require more accurate
tracking error.
So now, if we consider 1%,
your settling time is 4.6 divided by zeta omega N.
Okay, so now our settling time is choosing as 8 seconds.
So 8 equals 4.6 divided by 0.7 times omega N.
So from this, you can get your omega N.
Okay?
So basically, we can convert
this specification of overshoot
and the settling time to this
closed loop transfer function.
And this closed loop transfer function
has a gain of one in DC.
Yeah, DC gain is one.
Yeah, you can see that when S is zero, this is one.
That's why we put omega N squared is the numerator
so that this divided by this is one.
Okay?
Yeah, you want this output to follow the reference input.
So this DC gain should be one.
Okay, so that's the conversion of specification
to a closed loop transfer function.
That means this closed loop system
should have this transfer function.
Now, we have found this Gs.
We can compute Cs.
To obtain this closed loop transfer function.
Okay?
Yeah, this is the desired closed loop transfer function.
Just now, I will issue that our Gs.
Yeah, this Gs equals this transfer function.
So we are going to find the Cs to beat our requirement.
So the input is 100.
We want the speed of the car to follow this reference.
And it should reach this reference input in eight seconds.
Okay, there are many possible controllers
to achieve this purpose.
Here, we just try a PI controller.
Yeah, I believe you know what is a PI controller.
You have two terms, Kp and Ki.
So to find the Cs, you just need to find the Kp and Ki.
Once Kp, Ki are found, then get your Cs.
Okay, so with this Cs,
you can compute the closed loop transfer function,
which is Gc divided by one plus Gc.
So you substitute our given values of M and B
and also this transfer function.
You get this result.
Yeah, our M and C are given.
So you get this answer as the closed loop transfer function.
Then we have to equate
this denominator to this, okay?
So you do a comparison of the two denominators.
So this should be same as this.
That means zero point one plus zero point zero one Kp
should be one point one five, should be equal to that.
Zero point zero zero one Ki should be zero point six seven.
Then you can find out your Kp and Ki
from these two equations.
So we have designed the Pi container.
Okay, so that means this Cs has been formed.
That is the first step in our design procedure.
That is, from the given transfer function
and also the specification, we can find out Pi container.
Okay, now we have to convert this Pi container
to discrete time container.
So that's our second step.
To do the conversion, you have to choose a sampling period.
Okay, how do we choose a sampling period?
One way is to consider the bandwidth
of this closed loop system.
Yeah, so you consider the closed loop transfer function.
That is this transfer function.
And the plot, because now our Kp and Ki have been formed.
So we can plot the frequency response
of this transfer function using MATLAB.
This is the magnitude response.
So based on this, you can see the bandwidth
is about zero point three hertz.
Yeah, because this is the DC gain.
This part is DC gain, which is zero dB, that's one.
Then this frequency is one, that's two, that's three.
Okay?
Okay, actually our bandwidth should be around here.
Zero point three.
Yeah, which was this?
And this is equivalent to one point eight.
Sorry.
It's one point eight.
Actually, this is true.
So one point here is around here.
So that's the one point eight radians per second.
Yeah, that is negative three dB.
Yeah, I believe you know how to define the bandwidth.
The bandwidth is negative.
Yeah, because the DC gain here is zero dB.
So you look at the negative three dB position.
Yeah, this is about negative three dB.
So because here is negative five.
So negative three, the corresponding frequency
is about one point eight radians per second.
This is equivalent to zero point three hertz.
So that's the bandwidth of this closed loop system.
Okay, from this bandwidth you can choose
your sampling frequency.
Yeah, normally you can choose at least ten times
of the bandwidth as your frequency.
The minimum is two times.
Yeah, but two times is not good enough.
So in the solution here, we choose 30 times.
So with this 30 times of the bandwidth,
then the sampling period is one over this.
Yeah, that is the sampling frequency.
The sampling frequency is 30 times of the bandwidth.
Yeah, the sampling frequency should be at least twice.
But as I said, this is not good enough.
So we choose 30 times.
Then from this sampling frequency,
you get the sampling period.
Okay, using this sampling period,
you can convert this PI controller
to digital transfer function, CZ,
with this bilinear transformation.
Yeah, earlier we have discussed
the bilinear transformation with two over T
times Z minus one over Z plus one.
So this T is zero point one.
Then you can do a calculation.
You get this digital controller.
So that's the second step,
which is to find the discrete time transfer function.
Okay, so how about next step?
Next step is to do verification.
Yeah, so the third step is to verify
whether our digital controller
can achieve the required performance or not.
That's the plan.
Yeah, just now I already mentioned
the transfer function of the plant is obtained here.
Our mass is 1,000 kg and the B is 100.
So we have this transfer function.
When you consider digital controller,
you must have a zero order hold.
So we put a zero order hold here.
And this sampling period is also chosen by us.
And this is the digital controller obtained from CES.
So you do a simulation for this closed loop system.
Yeah, that's the input and this should be the output.
So the red curve shows the output.
And you can see that in about eight seconds,
the output reaches 100 km per hour,
reaches the speed, and the overshoot is less than 20%.
So the performance is satisfied.
Okay, so this is the first approach
we used to design our controller.
Yeah, this diagram shows, summarizes the approaches.
So we have this example.
Illustrating this approach.
So you have to find the GS from the given information.
And you have to find the CS to beat the required performance.
Yeah, there is more than one approach to find the CS.
Just now, based on our example,
we used this closed loop transfer function
and this PI controller to get the result.
And after you get this CS,
you have to convert to CZ.
Then in implementation, you should have zero order hold included here.
For the third step, you have to do verification.
Okay, so we have a break of 20 minutes.
Thank you.
The second approach.
You are also given a plant.
But
you need to obtain
the transfer function for
both the plant and the zero
of the hole.
To get this.
So from this
and the desired frequency
we are going to find
CZ.
So that, yeah direct
domain means we directly use this
to find CZ.
But this is
from the frequency response
approach.
Okay.
Yeah, just now the first approach
involves
approximation.
That is you find
your CZ by
approximating CS.
So
if the sampling period is
big then
there is a
significant
error.
Yeah, approximation
error if the sampling period is big.
So now the
method may not work well
when the sampling period
is big.
Okay, so
now let's look at the frequency approach.
Again, this
is also iterative trying the
error method.
And we are going to
use Bode plots.
Yeah, I believe you know what is Bode plots.
We have two plots.
One is the magnitude
and the other is the phase.
Okay,
two Bode plots
of discrete time transfer function.
Yeah, this is given.
So you have to change
this Z
to e to the power
j omega t.
So that's the frequency
response of the
given
transfer function.
As you can see here
this
is a function of
e to the power j omega t.
So it is not a
rational function of j omega.
It's a rational function of
this e to the power j omega t.
So it's not
a rational function of j omega.
Yeah, in
classical controller design
based on Bode plots
you just change
your S to j omega.
Then you have a rational function
of j omega.
So you can plot
the Bode plot easily.
Here, because it's a function
of e to the power j omega t
so
to plot the Bode plots
is very hard.
Okay, so we also
consider binomial
transformation in this case
to solve the problem.
The binomial transformation
is to convert
our GZAS
Z
to a W
plane.
Yeah, Z plane changes to W plane.
W plane is similar to the
S plane.
So
we apply the W
transformation
which is this
to change
this transfer function
to a function of W.
And this t
is the sampling period.
Of course, W
is a complex number.
Okay, if you
walk out, this W
is
from this transformation
you can find your W
which is equal to two over t
z minus one, z plus one.
So that's the binomial transformation
we used earlier.
Yeah, this one
this mapping
will map the inside
of unit circle in the Z plane
into the entire left
half plane in the W plane.
So we have two planes.
One is Z plane
which is
to consider
the Z transfer function.
Now if we convert
your
Z transfer function
to a function of
W, then
you have a W plane.
Okay,
why do we do this? Because
with this W
plane, you can
find out
the frequency response.
Yeah.
Because the imaginary part
of W is negative j omega
xe, so that's the
frequency response.
So now, I'll show
our gz, yeah, this
transfer function has been
converted to gw
through
the transformation
that is
this transformation,
5.9.
Then, you have a transfer function
in terms of
W.
Then you change W to jv.
You have, yeah, this v is
the
fictitious
frequency in the W plane.
Yeah,
fictitious frequency here.
And you have a magnitude,
you have the phase.
Then you have the body plots
for this gw.
Yeah, maybe this look at an example.
Suppose,
yeah, just now we
considered the cruise control system.
Yeah, of course,
in our transfer
function earlier, we have
different parameters in front,
the mass and the
friction. Yeah, here
is a simple
first order transfer function,
1 over s plus 1.
So you can
obtain the,
yeah, that means
if you look at the block diagram,
nothing means this
plant here
has this transfer function.
So we need to
obtain the
pulse transfer
function for both
the zero order hold and the
plant. So how do we do that?
We can
use
the
formula
studied before.
Yeah, maybe I
write the formula here for you.
Yeah, for the zero
order hold
together, yeah, you have
zero order hold.
The transfer
function is
1 minus
u2 prime negative
ts over
s, correct?
So
together with gs
and this
zero order hold, you have
this transfer function,
which is this
gzas.
That is
obtained as
1 minus z inverse
times the
z transform
corresponding to
gs over s,
okay?
Yeah, I believe you still remember
this formula.
So based on this formula,
you just
substitute this transfer function here,
you get 1 over s
plus 1 divided by s.
Then
you get a z transfer function,
the z transform
corresponding to this part, then multiply
with that.
And you have
this answer.
When the sampling period is
0.1 secant.
Okay?
You can verify this
by doing some
calculation. Yeah, calculate
this.
Then you can apply
our
transformation
5.9.
Yeah, that is this transformation.
5.9 here.
You can have
this
transfer function
in term of w.
Yeah, basically
with this t,
which is 0.1
secant,
you just replace this z
by this.
After simplification,
you get this.
Now if t is 0.01
secant, yeah, you have
another case,
0.01
secant.
We have this
pulse
transfer function
with this
formula.
And you change this z
to this
with t as
0.01 secant,
you have this result.
So that's the
g1w, g2w
to
convert
our pulse
transfer function.
Clearly, both g1w
and g2w
and also the original
gs
have the same pole
as the negative one
you can see here.
But for g1w,
g2w, you have 0
involved.
Okay?
The original gs
does not have 0.
So
when we do this
mapping,
gs will convert
to this.
Then you have 0
introduced.
And you can also
plot the
frequency response
to see the effect
of the 0 here.
Yeah, this is the
frequency response.
You can see that
this is
the original gs
this is the
phase.
And this is g1w
this is g2w
that's the phase
of g1w
phase of g2w.
Yeah, g1w
has
based on this response
you can tell
our
influence
of 0 and the system dynamics.
So if we have
a larger sampling period
which is the first case
0.1 sec
then this
0 has more
significant effect.
Okay?
If you see the
result here.
Yeah,
g2w is
closer to gs here.
Okay,
now let's come back to our
design procedure.
First,
you have to
choose a
sampling period
and obtain a transfer function
gzas.
Yeah, that is
based on the
same plant
you need to
find gzas
for
which is the pulse transfer function
for both 0 order hold
under the plant.
So that's the first step.
Then you have to
convert gzas
into gw
using our
5.9 here.
Yeah, this
conversion
yeah, that is you need to
consider this
yeah, we have obtained this transfer function
and you replace
the
z variable in this transfer
function with this
expression
here.
Then you get this
gw.
Okay,
third step,
you have to draw the body plots
of
this gw.
That is you change
w to jv.
That is the frequency response
of gw.
And they use the
analog frequency response methods
to design a controller
cw
or gdw
here.
This is
if you use cz, then we have
cw here.
Or digital controller, sometimes you use
gdw.
So you design this cw
that satisfies the
required frequency
domain specifications.
Yeah, these specifications
are given to you.
So we have
cw, you have to
transform the controller back
to the z plane
by using
5.10, which is this.
Yeah, because here
you get this
cw, so you just replace
this w by this
transfer, 2 over t
times z minus 1 over
z plus 1. Then you get
this transfer
function, cz.
Yeah, so that's how
we get the cz
using frequency domain
method. So you get this
cz.
Yeah, after you get the cz
you have to verify
the performance.
And check if the
performance is satisfied or not.
If not, you have to do
redesign.
So that's why it's an iterative
try and error method.
So we have these four
steps.
Okay, here
for the first two steps
they are quite
standard. Yeah, you know
how to find
gzas and you know how
to convert this
gzas to gw.
You just use 5.9.
Our focus here
is step 3
to
find cw
based on frequency response.
Okay, so we will consider
this in our design.
So to consider this
we need to make some revisions
about
compensators.
Yeah, we have phase lead
compensator.
I hope you still
remember this
phase lead compensator.
You can include
PD controller as
a special case.
For such compensator
it can improve
stability margin. That is
make your closed
loop system more stable.
You can
also increase system
bandwidth. Therefore
you have a faster
response.
Of course there
is an issue. That is
such a
system is sensitive to
noise because
the bandwidth of the system
is increased. Your noise
is normally high frequency
noise. So
in this case the high
frequency noise will be
taking
effect if you have
your system has a higher
bandwidth.
Okay, so to overcome
this drawback
we have phase lead compensator.
In this case
PI controller can
be considered as a special case.
Yeah, basically it reduces
system gain
at high frequency.
Yeah, that is
to overcome this
issue
of high frequency
noise here.
Yeah, if you
reduce high frequency gain
then the noise is not
so sensitive because
noise is high frequency
components.
So you reduce system
bandwidth in this case. Of course
that will reduce your
system response which
means you have larger
rise time
in this case.
Of course
you can
improve
speed state accuracy
because low frequency
gain
increased
especially for the special case.
At low frequency
for PI controller
at zero frequency
the gain is infinity.
Yeah.
So for
PI controller you have two terms
KP plus KI over
S. If
S tends to zero
this gain
tends to infinity. So that's why
you have
very high frequency gain
at a low frequency.
Okay, so
phase lead, phase lag
compensators have
their own advantage
or disadvantage.
You can combine these two together
to get phase lag lead
compensator.
In this case PID controller
is a special case.
So for such controllers
it increase low frequency
gain and also
increase bandwidth
and stability margin.
Okay,
since we are going to
consider frequency design
so I make a revision
about
such design approach.
If you have not studied
frequency design
compensator design
before I
just go through this part.
Yeah, in fact
this can also be used
to get our CS
in the first approach.
Yeah.
Okay, so you are given
GS. Yeah, this is a continuous system
different from here now.
So I just make a revision
so this is not
discrete time system.
It's just GS
yeah, you are given GS
we are looking for CS.
So our
objectives to design CS
such that the closed
loop system has
the desired performance.
Okay, in frequency domain
and the time domain
you have
some
different specifications.
For example
in time domain
we have
price time, settling time
maximum overshoot
yeah, these are
transcendent responses.
Transcendent response
specifications. We also have
steady state errors.
So
these are time domain specifications.
Now for frequency domain
specification
they are
given as bandwidth
yeah, sometimes
you are given the bandwidth of the system
you have to design your controller
to achieve this bandwidth.
Or gain crossover frequency
yeah, both bandwidth and
gain crossover frequency
will be an indication
of speed of response.
If you have larger bandwidth
or higher gain
crossover frequency, you have
faster response.
You have phase margin,
gain margin
yeah, this rough estimate
of the damping ratio
just now we have a
second order transfer function
I mentioned the damping ratio
so this is an indication
of the overshoot
for the damping ratio.
So if you have larger
phase margin or gain margin
that means your system is more
stable.
So you have less overshoot.
And
of course you have a steady state error also.
Yeah, I just mentioned
phase margin is close
related to damping ratio
and the gain crossover frequency
or bandwidth is related
to rise time
steady state error can be
determined by the low frequency gain.
So this
started
in classical
control design course.
Okay, for frequency
domain design
it is basically
reshape the frequency response.
When we
talk about the frequency response
we normally consider the
Bode plot
which has two plots
magnitude plot
and phase plots.
Nothing means
this
yeah, if you just have this
Gs here
the frequency response
may not meet the requirement.
So you have to add
Cs
then Cs together with the Gs
you will reshape
the overall frequency response
to meet
the required frequency
domain specifications.
Okay, when we plot the
frequency Bode plots
here
we plot the open loop
transfer function Bode plots
not the closed loop.
So we will consider
the product
G times C
that's the open loop.
So before we design C
we just plot the G.
So this G
may not meet this requirement
so that's why you have to use
C to reshape
the frequency response.
Okay, we have some definitions
here
for the
open loop transfer function
if we don't have C we just have
G. Yeah, H is one here.
H is normally
the feedback
transfer function.
So
if we want to find the gain margin
without C
you just plot
Bode plots of G
here.
Yeah, later on if you
finish your design of the controller
you have to plot
the Bode plots
of G times C.
But for both cases we have
such definitions.
We have the definition of
gain cross over frequency.
So you look at the Bode plots
yeah
that is the magnitude plot.
So for this
red curve
because
this is in terms
of dB. You know dB is defined
as 20 N
times the magnitude of the
transfer function. Of course
for the frequency X
is similar to paper
here. So
this frequency
is the frequency
when the magnitude
cross the
frequency X.
So that's 0 dB.
At the 0 dB
the corresponding frequency is
called gain cross over frequency.
At this frequency
you look at the phase
value.
So this is the phase.
Then phase margin
is just equal
the phase angle
which is this
value
minus
negative 180 degree.
This line is negative 180 degree.
So this is the difference.
So this is our
phase margin.
If this phase margin is bigger
than 0 then
the system is
stable.
Yeah.
This is 1
here. Then
H is 1. So
with this G then
the system will be stable
if this phase margin is bigger
than 0.
Later on when we
plot the transfer function
G times C
if you have positive phase margin
that means this feedback
system will be stable.
So when you plot the
both the plots you just use
open loop transfer function.
Now we also have the
definition of gain margin.
For the gain margin you have to consider the phase
cross over frequency.
Here you look at the phase curve.
And
the phase cross over frequency
is the frequency that
the phase
cross negative
180 degree line.
So at this frequency
you look at the magnitude.
This amount of the
gain is called the gain margin.
So actually is the
difference between 0 dB
and the gain
of the
transfer function.
So it's 0
minus this
log magnitude
of GH omega
5. So 0 minus that
will be negative 20. If this
answer is positive then you have
positive gain margin.
Then your system will be
stable.
So that's the definition of
gain margin and phase margin.
And this is
one of the
one or two of the
specifications of the
system.
Now let's consider the
design of
lead compensator.
Just now I mentioned
lead compensator are used
to improve transit performance.
So this C
will be our lead compensator.
The idea is
to increase the
phase margin of the system
without changing
much the steady state accuracy.
So that means the
frequency response
will be modified at the
high frequency part.
At the low frequency part
there is
there is no much change.
Okay
what is the transfer function of lead
compensator? It is
in this form.
So you have
constant K
yeah that's the gain
of the lead
compensator. C0
should have this form
TS plus one
divided by alpha TS plus one.
Where alpha
is positive constant
less than one.
So
to find this CS
you just need to find K
T and alpha.
If you find these three values
your design is finished.
Okay
now because our design
is based on frequency domain
we need to plot the
frequency
response
of CS.
So you can see from this
transfer function we have two
basic factors.
This is a term used
in classical control.
So for the zero this is
a basic factor TS plus one.
Yeah basic factor means
your gain should be one.
Okay
so you see here is one
for the denominator
this is also one.
The coefficient of
S may not be one.
So here we have
two basic factors for
this compensator TS
plus one that's the zero
and alpha TS plus
one that's the pole
of this transfer function.
For the zero
you have a corner
frequency which is one
divided by T. Yeah T is here.
For the pole
the corner frequency is one
over alpha T.
Because alpha is
less than one
so this value one over alpha T
will be bigger than
one over T.
Okay
so that is the corner frequency
for the pole is bigger than
that of the zero.
Okay
now let's look at the
frequency response
of this part.
Yeah because this K is a
constant it will be determined
based on this error
requirement.
So for the frequency
specifications
we consider this portion.
Actually for this portion
the DC gain is one.
Because when S is zero
then this gain is one.
Okay the corresponding
frequency response for this part
is obtained
by changing your S
to J omega.
Yeah you get this.
So you can get this
yeah you plot the
frequency response of this
you get this plot here.
For the, yeah I said
you have two parts. You have a
magnitude and the
phase. This is the magnitude.
Yeah that is the
magnitude of this. You can
see when omega
is very small. Yeah that is
when omega tends to zero that's one.
Right?
One is zero dB.
So that's why at the beginning
the magnitude
is almost
zero dB. Now when
the omega is
almost one
over T. Yeah it's close
to one over T.
Then
actually when omega equals one
over T this is one. The numerator
is one. So it's J
one plus one.
And the denominator
because alpha is smaller
than one so you can still
ignore this term. So the
denominator is still one
here. So you plot this
zero and you have
this corner frequency called
one over T. Yeah that's why
we have this one over
T here. So that's the corner
frequency. That will change
the slope of this straight line.
So
the slope will be
20 dB
per decade.
Yeah.
So
you get this red curve
when
omega is
bigger than one over T
you get this. Then
when omega is approached
to one
over alpha T so you have the
corner frequency of
the pole.
Then this will take effect.
When this
pole is in
effect the slope will
be changed
from positive 20 dB
to zero
zero dB per decade.
That means
this
is positive 20 then
minus 20 dB per decade
it will be zero.
Okay I
believe you should know how to
plot such
body diagrams.
Okay so that's the
amplitude
of this transfer
function. Yeah.
Now for phase.
Phase angle
it is computed
by this formula. So it's the
phase of the numerator
minus the phase angle
of the denominator.
The phase angle of the numerator is
inverse tangent
omega T divided by one.
That's the first term.
The
phase angle of the denominator is
inverse tangent alpha T omega
over one.
So it's this.
And
this is always positive.
In fact for this
function
if you take derivative with respect
omega and make it zero
you can find the maximum value.
So that's the phase
curve.
That's the angle of this.
And this angle is always positive
for this 90 degree.
Okay
so this maximum
occurs at
this frequency.
You just
solve this equation you can get omega
n.
Okay.
Okay so now
for this compensator
we will use this
maximum
phase
to increase our phase margin
of the
feedback control system.
So
as
just now defined
phase margin is
defined at the
gain crossover frequency.
So we will choose
this omega m
as the
new gain crossover
frequency.
Later on we will consider
that.
And this phase
phi
can be computed
as this maximum
phase.
This is the frequency that gives you the maximum
phase and this maximum
can be computed also
by using this formula.
You just substitute this omega m
to here to the calculation.
It will be equal to
inverse sine one minus
alpha over one plus alpha.
Which means sine phi equals this.
Okay from this equation
you can get your alpha.
So that's how you design your
alpha.
So this formula
is used to calculate
our alpha. Of course
you have to decide
what's the value of phi.
Yeah phi
will be dependent on the
specification. Which is
phase margin. Later on
I will show you how to get
the phi.
Okay so once
you get this phi you can compute alpha.
Then
we want
this frequency to be
the new gain crossover
frequency. So
we should have this
amplitude computed.
Yeah
You just substitute
this value
of omega
to the magnitude.
Yeah you compute this magnitude.
You find that
it is negative ten
over alpha. Yeah that is this
amount here.
Okay this is
from the
compensator C.
C zero.
Okay so this is
C zero
J omega.
So at this
frequency you have this magnitude.
Okay
so
after we
review this concept
this is just about
the
compensator body plots.
Now let's consider our design
of phase need
compensator. So first
step you have to determine
this K value. Yeah
we have
as I said we have this K
here
in the need compensator. We have to
design this K first.
How do we design K?
You just use the
steady state error requirement.
For example
the
steady state error is one
over one plus KP
where KP is the
position error constant.
If this is given
this
can be computed
based on the
open loop transfer function
KC zero times the G.
Yeah this K times G.
You can compute this.
Yeah because when S go to zero
this is one. So the open loop
transfer function
which is
C times G
when you take this limit
it's just K times
G
when S tends to zero. So
from this and this
requirement you can find your
KP. From this KP
you can get your K.
Okay anyway
later on we have an example
to compute such
a value.
Okay so you are using
the steady state error requirement
to find this K.
Once you get this K
you can solve the body plot
of KGS. Because
GS is given
so you can
plot KGS now if K
is determined.
Okay so for example
we have this
yeah I put this diagram
here for
reference. Yeah this is
the slice.
Now I go to the diagram.
Yeah this
is the diagram.
We have plot
this KGS
which is this blue curve
ah blue line.
This is KGS
that's the magnitude. Yeah
this is just an example
KGS and this is the angle
K of KGS.
Yeah because K is a constant
so the angle of KG
is same as the angle of G.
Okay.
So this is the
yeah that is the
body plot of KGS.
The blue
blue line here.
Now based on this blue line
you can find the gain cross over frequency
omega G.
Yeah that is the gain cross over
frequency without C0.
Yeah later
we are going to find the C0. So this
is the gain cross
over frequency without C0.
From this
you can find this current
phase margin phi 0.
This phi 0 means
if you don't have C0
then you have this amount of phase
margin.
Okay. That's the
existing phase margin
without our C0.
Without this part.
So we just have
K times G plotted here.
Okay so
that's phi 0.
Now
you have to decide
your phi.
How do we decide the phi?
This is the
idea.
So we have
found the phi 0 just now.
And this phase margin is
given specification.
So you are required
to
design your controller
to achieve this phase margin.
So that's given, that's
specification. And this is the
current phase margin.
So this
required one
minus the current one.
And
you have to plus
some additional degree.
Then you get
this phi. Why do we
add this additional degree?
5 to 10 degree? It's because
currently
our phase margin
our gain cross over frequencies
are here. But later on
we have to
move this gain cross over
over frequency to a higher
frequency. Yeah because
you have to include
the C0 magnitude
response and this should be the
new gain cross over frequency.
And this frequency is higher
than omega G.
At this frequency
the angle
of G
is reduced
a bit.
So this
if you consider
this increasing of the gain cross over
frequency there is a few degree
difference. So this
phi 0
prime is maybe 5 to
10 degree less than the red one.
So that's why we add
this 5 to 10 degrees
to compensate
this difference.
So this is how
we get this phi.
Once we get this phi we can
compute our alpha.
Just now we have this formula
to compute alpha which is
1 minus sine phi divided by
1 plus sine phi.
So that's how we
get our alpha.
This alpha has been found.
So k has been found earlier
alpha is found. Now let's
find the t.
How do we find the t?
As I said
our new gain
cross over frequency will be here.
So we have to
use this to find our t.
So for this to be our new
gain cross over frequency
this green
magnitude should be
same as
this magnitude.
This blue one
at this
frequency has this
amount of
gain margin. But later on
due to this C0
you have an increase
of magnitude.
So this increase plus
this amount
should be zero.
So that this is
a new gain cross over
frequency.
So that's the idea
of doing this.
So we have
this alpha then you can compute
negative 10 over alpha.
Once you have this
negative 10 over alpha
computed then
you look at this
magnitude
and find out the value
of 10 over alpha.
The
corresponding frequency will be your
new gain cross over frequency.
So that's how you
find the new gain cross over
frequency omega m.
So omega
m should be this.
Now
you rate
yeah this is
10 over alpha we have found this
so you rate your curve
k g j omega prime
that this omega
g prime should satisfy
this equation you solve this
equation you get this.
Okay.
So
you get the omega g prime.
Then omega g prime
is same as this omega m
so from this you get your t.
So that's how you get t.
Yeah.
In
summary
this step you get alpha.
So from this
you can compute
negative
10 over alpha.
So this is
negative 10
over alpha.
Then from
the given
transfer function g and
obtain the k
you have this equation
20 log magnitude
k g j omega prime
equals this 10
because this plus that
should be zero so that's why
your
original
magnitude curve
should
have the same magnitude as
this by opposite sign here.
So you solve this equation
you get omega g prime.
And this omega g prime
is the same
as our omega m.
So you have this equation
then you solve this equation
you get t.
Once
you get t then you have this compensator.
Okay.
After you get this
you have to do verification.
Yeah.
So the verification
is
to
plot this curve again.
Yeah, you just
plot.
plot
this.
Yeah, this is g times
c. It will be like
this.
And this is the angle.
So now that's the new
gain cross over frequency
which is ensured
by our design.
And from this
you can calculate
you can find the fixed margin here.
Yeah, that's the fixed margin.
You have to verify if this fixed
margin meet our requirement
or not.
Okay, so that's the
design.
Yeah, I already mentioned
this. Need compensator
can improve the fixed margin
and therefore
turn in the performance.
The gain cross over frequency is increased
as you can see from
the plot.
Yeah, that's the new
gain cross over frequency.
So
that is bigger than
the
one without
c zero. So this
is increased.
You have larger bandwidth
so the speed of the
response will be improved.
Yeah,
as I said, for such
system
such a design system is
more sensitive to high frequency
noise.
Because you have
larger
gain cross over frequency.
Yeah, that's the amplitude response.
Okay, so this is
a revision of
compensator design.
Now, let's look
at the example in our
second
approach. So here
we are going to control this
plant. Yeah, this
is the plant
transfer function. We have
zero order hold. And
this is the controller to be designed.
Okay, we have to design
this controller
such that the overall
system has
phase margin
of 50 degrees.
So this is a given
specification.
And also the gain margin
is at least 10 dB.
10 dB.
The static
velocity error constant
kV is 2 sec
per sec.
2 per sec.
And the sampling period
is 0.2 sec.
Okay, here
we have to design
lead compensator
to achieve this.
This k
actually
for this k, it should be our
k here. So in
the example, they put the k in
the plant.
In fact, we are going to determine
this k in
our first step.
So in this
case, for our lead
compensator
in the design, we have
unit
DC gain because
k has been moved through here.
We have this
requirement. We will use
this requirement to find the k.
Okay.
So
let's see the solution.
We follow the design procedure.
As I said, we have
four steps.
Yeah, here are the
Yeah, first step, you have
to, yeah, in this case,
we have sampling period given
and you have to obtain
a transfer function.
For the plant
here. So this is how you
obtain the transfer function
of the plant.
Because our
plant
has this transfer function,
that's zero, the hole.
So you just use
the formula,
you can find this
pulse transfer function.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's one minus z inverse times
the z transform of this
Laplace transform.
Actually, you can find this
z transform
directly from the table.
Yeah, you see in the table
here,
you have
this term and
this Laplace transform function.
Our k is
a constant, so
you just move this k out,
then you have one over s squared
times s plus one.
So this a is one, in fact.
Then you have this transfer function.
T is given, then you do a calculation.
It's this.
Yeah, after you multiply that,
you get this.
So that's how we get
this.
Okay, so that's
the first step.
Yeah, step one.
You select
you have
to find this gzas.
Now,
second step, you have to transform
this transfer function
to gw
using our
bininear transformation,
which is this.
So z equals
one plus wt
divided by two over one minus
wt divided by two.
So t is given
to be zero point
two secant,
as you can see here.
That's zero point two.
So you substitute this
into
this transformation.
You will have this
z. So you substitute
this z into here.
Yeah, you have three z
in the result. So you have
two calculations.
You get this.
Okay, so
that's gzas.
Yeah, which is about that.
So that's the second step.
Transform this
into gw.
G
w here.
Okay?
Okay, next step.
That's the key part.
So you have to draw the body
diagram of this transfer function.
Yeah.
Before we saw that, we also
considered
the lead compensator.
As I just mentioned,
we should have
a constant
in the compensator here.
But
in our example,
that constant is moved
through here.
So in this case, our
lead compensator has a
unit gain
here.
So this k
has been moved to the plant.
Okay, we are going to determine
this k also. So basically,
we are going to
determine alpha t
to get gd.
And we also have to find the k.
Okay, to find the k,
you have to use the position
error constant. That's given here.
So you have
to know the definition
of a position error constant.
That's the
Yeah, you find the open loop transfer function,
which is gd
w times
this transfer function.
Then you take a limit
of w
times this transfer function
when w turns to zero.
Yeah, if you
do a calculation
of this limit,
yeah, this
is the gdw
times gz s w. That's this
part. Then multiply w.
This w is cancelled out.
Then you take a limit,
w turns to zero.
Then this will
be one. This is k.
So this is also
one. That's also one.
Yeah, this w has been cancelled out
by this w here.
So
our
velocity error constant will be k.
And this
k should be equal to two
because your kv
is required
to be two.
Yeah, that's the
specification of
the
design.
So this kv
is two.
And we're using our
open loop transfer function.
We found kv is equal to k.
So this k should be two.
So we have found this k.
Okay, now let's plot
the
body
plots of two. Yeah, because
k has been found. Two times
gz as.
Yeah, earlier we have this
gz as found.
Yeah, this has been
found
in the second step. So here
is two now.
So you have that.
Then you plot this body diagram.
Yeah,
this body diagram
is showing here.
Okay, this is the body diagram.
Yeah,
that's the
dash nine here
for the magnitude
response.
So you can see this will
be the present
gain
crossover frequency.
Yeah, that's cross
the zero db here.
And you find
the corresponding
phase margin.
Yeah, this
is the
current phase margin, which is
30 degrees.
Yeah, you just look at the
graph.
Yeah, that's the
okay.
So this is the
magnitude
and this dash nine is the
of
this transfer function.
Okay, so
from this, the phase
margin is 30 degrees, as
I just mentioned here.
This is the phase margin.
And
our desired phase margin
is 50 degrees.
Okay,
so we need
20 more degrees
from the compensator.
And also
by considering the
effect of
increasing gain
crossover frequency, we
add 8 more degrees.
So totally we need
28 degrees from the
phase
lead compensator.
Yeah, you see why we need this
extra because later on
you have the new gain
crossover frequency here
at the higher position. So
this
at this
frequency, the
phase margin
or the phase is here.
So you have a decrease. This
decreasing is about 8 degrees.
Yeah, this amount.
You just draw a horizontal
line from here.
You can see you have this decreasing.
So you have to add this
reduction, which is about 8 degrees.
So you have 28 degrees.
So that's how you get your phi.
From this phi,
you can compute alpha.
Yeah, the formula has been derived
earlier. So you just
use this formula, you get this
alpha. So we have found
alpha.
After we find alpha,
we have to find t.
Yeah, because
because our
phase
lead compensator
is this. So alpha has been found
from the
additional phase you did
here.
Okay, so we have to find t.
How do we find t?
Yeah, you look at the gain crossover frequency.
So currently,
with
this 10
log alpha, you have this alpha
found just now,
which is
this value.
So you substitute this alpha
to compute
10 log alpha.
And this 10 log alpha
is negative 4.425
dB. So that
means you look at
the
magnitude or you can compute
your
dual gain
crossover frequency, omega g prime.
You have two ways
to find this Vg prime.
One is by
checking
the
diagram.
So you have this
magnitude curve.
You just look at this curve
and find out
negative 4.425 dB.
Yes,
maybe it's here.
So you find this amount
is negative
4.425 dB.
Then this corresponding
frequency
is our
dual gain
crossover frequency here.
You can also do computation.
Basically, you can solve the equation.
Yeah, because
because
this
is known.
So
you've taken
20 log of this.
The answer should be
the
10 log alpha.
Yeah, so
that means
you
have 20 log of this
equals negative 4
.425.
Then you solve that
equation. You can get this
on Vg prime.
So you have two ways
to obtain this
value.
One is by using the graph.
The other is by calculation.
Okay.
So once you get this
you can
use this formula because this
omega g prime should be
same as our omega m.
Omega m is one over square
alpha t.
So this is 1.7
then
from this equation you get a t.
Once you get t, you get the compensator.
So
you just substitute this t
to here and also alpha
t you get this. So that's
how we obtain gd.
Okay, now you have
to do verification.
Yeah, you plot
gd, g
yeah, this gd times g.
That's the solid curve.
Yeah, that's this part for the
magnitude.
That's the phase.
Yeah, this is gd times g.
Times g.
So based on this
you can see the
new
gain margin here.
Phase margin.
This is the gain crossover frequency.
So that's about 50 degrees.
Yeah, that's the phase.
So this is 50 degrees.
This is the requirement.
You can also check the gain crossover frequency.
Yeah, that's this.
This is the phase crossover frequency.
Then look at the gain.
So that's about 14 dV.
So this
meets the requirement.
Yeah,
we have to get this gd w
you have to convert this
gd w to z.
Transfer function.
So now
you go to the fourth
step.
Yeah, so
you do this conversion
you get gd.
So this is w
change to 2 over
t, z minus 1, z plus 1.
Then you do this calculation
you get this answer.
So that's the final controller.
Okay.
And you can also do
verification about the
step response.
So you have
this unit
step response
obtained by using MATLAB
simulation.
The input is unit step
for the closed loop system.
Okay,
so this is the design
procedure.
And we have used
our example to
illustrate this five step
procedure. Okay, so
that's the lecture today.
We come back next week.
Yeah.
Okay.