Okay, let's start, yeah first I would like to make this announcement, yeah it's about
the third quiz for this course, yeah it will be conducted on the 11th November, so that's
two weeks to go, okay, yeah we will start the quiz at 7.30 and finish at 8.15, so you
need to come here to be seated by 7.25, so that we can start our quiz on time and finish
on time.
Okay for this quiz we have two AOTs, one is here, AOT26, the other is the next door, so
is more convenient than quiz one, so it's AOT27, yeah our quiz will be 45 minutes, same
as the first two quizzes, third quiz also no MCQ type, so you have to show your workings
in detail and clearly.
Also the quiz is a closed book quiz, so you cannot bring any unauthorised material, yeah
you can use your calculator, but you cannot use your mobile phone and other unauthorised
materials.
If you are caught, it will be a serious issue, so yeah we have actually eight student helpers
to invigorate the quiz, so there will be a round to oversee you, so you should be careful,
so just do the quiz without using your mobile phone and also unauthorised materials.
Okay the topic involved will be lectures in week 4, week 10, yeah actually this is week
11 and week 12, yeah week 4 means the week in the last lecture I delivered, including
the stability using jury's test, yeah that chapter, week 11, yeah week 10 is last week's
lecture, week 11 today's, yeah we have one more next week.
Okay this quiz will be 15% of the course, for the grouping it's the same as quiz one
and also quiz two, so you can find out the grouping in the information folder, yeah in
the information folder of the course.
Okay for group one to group four, you will be here in this L.T. with the same seating
arrangement as we did for quiz one and quiz two, but for groups five and six, it will
be just next door in L.T. 27, yeah you can check the grouping showing in the information
folder.
So when you arrive at the assigned AOT, you just sit in the respective group area assigned
to you, so that attendance can be taken by the student helpers and also in the end they
will collect your answer sheet and then take attendance when you submit your answer sheet
as we did in the first quiz.
Okay as I said you can bring your own calculator, we will provide necessary transform tables,
yeah necessary transform pairs and you cannot use mobile phone as I just mentioned, yeah
to take attendance you have to show this student helper your matriculation card, yeah.
If your student is absent from the quiz without a valid reason, such as without showing the
NC then zero mark will be given, however if you have a valid reason you should email me
after the quiz, yeah I mean by 5 p.m. 11th 2024, that is, oh sorry 12th, no 11th, okay,
yeah 12th, yeah the next day after the quiz, the quiz is on the 11th, so there are two
corrections here, yeah, yeah this one and this one here, okay so that's the announcement.
Now let's consider our design of controllers, yeah as we said when we design our controller
the plant is given and in my part the plant together with the zero order hold can be represented
by this transfer function, okay so this is given, if it's not given you sometimes have
to find out by yourself, for example you have to model the plant like what we did last week
for the controlling of the car, so you have to find the model or transfer function for
the plant then you have to find this transfer function and also the overall specification
for your control system should be given, so based on such given information you have to
find this controller, yeah that's what we try to do in this chapter, yeah as mentioned
we have three approaches, one is digital implementation of analog controller design
and make a summary on this procedure, so we have three steps in this case, first you have
to design a controller CS for the analog subsystem to meet the required specification, so you
can use whatever method you have studied to design this CS, once you design this CS you
can map this CS to the digital domain to obtain CZ based on shootable transformation, we started
a few approach transformations, for example binomial transformation and also pole zero
matching, yeah these two methods are important to do the transformation and the third step
is to check the sample time response of the digital control system, yeah you have obtained
this CZ and also you have the given transfer function GZS here, so you can find out the
response of this overall system by using some computational tool such as Matlab to check
the performance, if the performance is satisfied then the design CZ is acceptable otherwise
you may have to do design again, so that's the first method which is digital implementation
of analog controller design, the second method is direct Z domain digital controller design
by using frequency response approach, yeah we also have procedure for this approach,
yeah in this approach we have five steps here, first step is to obtain the transfer function
GZAS of the discretized process, yeah this means you are given the plant, yeah you are
given the plant then you find this, yeah that's the same, that was just mentioned also, now
for this transfer function you have to do transformation to obtain GW, yeah basically
you can use the binary transformation to get this, then based on this GW you put the body
plot of G JV, then based on the body plot and the required frequency domain specifications
you can design controller CW, once you get this CW you can convert back to CZ by using
the binary transformation again, of course you also need to verify the performance obtained
based on the obtained CZ and also this, yeah this last step is the same as we did for the
first approach, okay now today we will consider the third approach which is direct control design
approach, yeah in this approach we have to obtain the closed loop transfer function based
on the given specifications, yeah just now for our control system we have this Z domain
representation, so this is obtained, now you can obtain the closed loop transfer function based
on the required specification, okay, then we can find CZ from the closed loop transfer function
and also this GZAS, so that's the approach or that's the idea, of course when you use this
method you have to ensure the obtained controller CZ is realizable, that means your CZ should
satisfy some conditions, okay so now let's look at the detail, yeah this diagram is same as this,
so as I just mentioned the closed loop transfer function for this system can be obtained as this,
I believe you know how to obtain this transfer function, right that's quite standard,
so in this case GZ is obtained, that is known or is given from the specifications and the GZAS is
also obtained, therefore we just want to find CZ, then solve this equation, you get this solution
for CZ, so that's the controller we obtain, so it's very easy, okay so the issue here is how to
obtain the closed loop transfer function from the given specification and also to meet the condition
that the controller is realizable, so this is important here, so you have to ensure they obtain
CZ to be realizable, yeah you can compute your CZ here, but whether this is realizable that
will depend on how you choose your GZ here, so now let's look at some conditions for the choice
of this closed loop transfer function, yeah basically for the controller to be realizable
it must be causal, so that's the realizable condition and also when you implement the
controller you have to ensure the asymptotic stability of the closed loop control system,
yeah here our control system is this, for you to ensure the closed loop asymptotic stability
is not only the transfer function from the input to the output, you also have to consider some
internal signals in the system, for example this U, yeah you have to also ensure this U is not
divergent, yeah based on the closed loop transfer function you get the relationship between the
input and output, in certain case if you have poor zero cancellation between the controller
and the GZAS, if this cancellation is unstable poor zero cancellation maybe the internal signal
is unbounded, so we have to consider this case, yeah not only just this overall transfer function
but also some internal signals should be considered, just like in state space you have some
state variables, you also have to ensure the state variables to be bounded, that is without
divergence, now how do we ensure our controller is causal with the given formula here, yeah we
are going to use, later on we will use this formula to find this CZ, so with this formula
how can we ensure this CZ is causal, so that depends on your choice of the GCA,
this GCA that is the closed loop transfer function, what's the meaning of causal,
causal means if you have a controller CZ here, yeah in the end you get a rational function,
so you have a numerator and a denominator, so maybe in the end you get for example NCZ and the
DCZ here, causal means the order of the numerator should be less than or equal to the order of the
denominator, okay and in other words there is no time advance, okay we have this condition,
yeah if the order of the denominator is higher than the order of the numerator or equal to the
order of the numerator that implies the number of poles of the transfer function of this CZ is not
less than the zeroes, or less than the number of zeroes, yeah maybe to be more precise I think
you actually have to put the number of poles, not less than the number of zeroes, okay, also there
should be no time advance, that means the output of the system does not depend on the future of
your input, okay to ensure this, to ensure this CZ to be causal, to ensure this CZ to be causal,
the relative degree of GCAO must not be less than the relative degree of the planned transfer
function, maybe I have to explain what's the meaning of relative degree, yeah I also give
a proof of this condition, so this is actually a condition for you to choose your GCAO, okay,
so this is a condition we need to consider when you choose your GCAO, yeah this is given,
you cannot choose this, but this is chosen by us, so you have a freedom to choose this GCAO,
this one is not possible to be, so what is the relative degree, yeah I said this,
yeah I do a calculation, first I have to define relative degree, for example for this given GZS,
transfer function, it is a rational transfer function, maybe I can write this as BZ over AZ,
so for physical system the order of the numerator should be less than or equal to the order of the
denominator, and the relative degree is defined as this, yeah maybe I use R to denote the relative
degree, so this relative degree is the degree of denominator, which is A in this case, minus the
degree of B, yeah or B here, okay, so that's the definition of relative degree, so now how do we
show this condition should be satisfied, yeah this condition here, okay so now I will use the
formula here, yeah this formula is important, yeah you have to remember this formula in fact,
in order to compute this CZ, okay so we also denote this GCAO as a rational function,
maybe just N, yeah numerator CL divided by DCL, so in this case we compute C, yeah this is C,
yeah you just substitute this GZS and the GCL to this formula, you can compute the C,
that will be one over that, one over this is just the inverse of this, so it's A divided by B,
right when you do this inverse, that's this part, then GCAO is NCAO divided by DCL, then this is a
one minus NCAO divided by DCL, okay, so that's how we compute this C based on this formula here,
okay now let's do a simplification, now there will be A divided by B times, yeah you multiply
DCAO in both numerator and denominator, this will be NCAO, this is DCAO minus NCAO, correct,
yeah, okay now let's compute the relative degree of C, yeah, relative degree of C,
based on this calculation, it will be the degree of the denominator minus the degree
of the numerator, so that is the degree of B times this part, yeah actually this is,
when you consider the degree of the denominator is just a degree of B plus the degree of DCAO,
okay, because for this part the order of DCAO should be larger than or equal to NCAO,
so this degree is the degree of NCAO, okay that's the denominator, then minus the degree
of numerator, that's degree of A, yeah that's this, also minus degree of NCAO, correct, okay
you can see that when you do this calculation, this minus this, that's the relative degree of
GCAO, correct, then this minus this, that's the negative of the relative degree of the given
transfer function, so minus R GAAS, okay, so we have this, okay so that's the relative degree of
the controller, now for your controller to be causal, this should be bigger than equal to 0,
yeah that is a relative degree should be bigger than equal to 0, which means the order of the
denominator should be bigger than or equal to the order of the numerator, so we have R GCAO
bigger than or equal to R GAAS, okay, yeah that's this here, the relative degree of GCAO must not
be less than that of GCAAS, which means this, okay, so that is the choice of the relative degree
for your closed loop transfer function, so that's the causal condition, next we consider the second
condition here, we have to ensure the overall closed loop control system is asymptotically
stable, so to ensure this, you should avoid unstable port zero cancellation, otherwise,
even if your system is input output stable, but not asymptotically stable, because you have some
internal signals involved, okay, so this is to ensure this asymptotically stability, which is
equivalent to this, you should avoid unstable port zero cancellation, okay, how do we choose,
how do we ensure this, okay, the set of zeros of GCAO must include all the zeros of GCAAS that are
outside the unit circle, what does this mean, this means if your GCAAS, yeah, this is R GCAAS,
maybe you have some unstable zeros, yeah maybe I put this as B stable zeros,
and you have some unstable zeros, yeah, then maybe for the pole you can also put that A stable
and A unstable, so this means this B unstable here, this factor should be part
of the numerator of GCAO, yeah, that is your GCAO should include BU inside, when you choose your GCAO,
of course, if you don't have unstable zeros, then you don't worry about this condition,
how is this condition valid, you also use this formula to do the proof, okay,
so now I also use the same calculation, yeah, actually we have this computation for the
controller, as I said, I will separate or factorize the numerator as BS BU, so this means
you have BS BU here, yeah, at this stage for the A, I don't, I just use this because A does not
give any condition on the zeros of GCAO, so this should be true, and this is also BS BU, okay,
yeah, of course, this NCAO is our numerator of the closed loop transfer function,
if your NCAO has BU as a factor, yeah, that means NCAO can be written as BU times maybe NCAO,
the remaining part, put NCAO here, then with this, you can cancel out this BU, right,
therefore, in your controller C, yeah, this is the controller C you obtain,
you don't have BU involved, because when you do this calculation, this BU has been cancelled out,
therefore, when you look at the control system, yeah, this is the control system,
yeah, as I said, this GZAS has stable zero and the unstable zero factor, then this is A,
so in this case, if your C, yeah, this C does not have BU, then you don't have port
zero cancellation for the BU part, that means the unstable BU has no cancellation
involved, because in your C, you don't have this BU,
so we have avoid unstable port zero cancellation in this case, if your BU is included in your NCAO,
otherwise, if your NCAO does not include BU, that means maybe just the NCAO without BU here,
so in this case, your BU will be part of the denominator in your C, so if you substitute here,
you have BU in the denominator, that will cancel out with this BU, then you have unstable
port zero cancellation with this BU and this BU in your controller, okay,
so if you include your unstable zero
inside your NCAO, this is, this port zero, unstable port zero cancellation is avoided,
yeah, if you have stable zero, then it's okay for cancellation,
but you cannot cancel out unstable ones, okay, so that's the first condition,
for the second condition of asymptotic stability,
your zeros of this transfer function, which is one minor GCU,
should include all the unstable ports of the plant, yeah, that means in this case,
you have unstable ports in your GZAS, so that's, this should be included as the zeros of
one minor GCAOZ, you can also do the same calculation, yeah, you see,
yeah, here, for example, we just consider this A is written as
our A S AU, so stable one and the unstable one, so if this part, yeah, actually this part here
is one minor GCU, correct, yeah, if you look at the formula, the denominator here is one minor GCU,
so if this denominator contains AU as the zero, that means the numerator of this
has AU, so the, yeah, this actually is a rational function also, so the numerator
has AU, that means here in the denominator of this part, you have AU, then this is cancel out,
therefore in your controller C, you don't have AU here, then when you consider the
original block diagram, if this A is A S and AU, now you don't have this AU here, so this AU,
yeah, this AU cannot be cancel out because there is no AU in your controller, otherwise
if this AU is not cancel out, if this AU is not cancel out, then you have this factor
in the controller, then that means this AU in the controller numerator will be cancel out
with this AU, so in this case, you also have pole zero cancelation, yeah, you can use this approach
to verify this is required to avoid AU as part of the numerator of your C,
okay, yeah, there is another possible way to show this condition,
suppose the process has a zero outside the unit circle, yeah, this is not zero,
has an unstable pole at the Z bar with a magnitude of Z bar bigger than one,
so we can factorise this Z minus Z bar out from this overall transfer function to get this form,
that is you can write GZ ES as G1 divided by this, so this is an unstable pole,
then you can compute this, yeah, this form, one minus GZU actually is equal to this,
is one divided by one plus C times this, yeah, this can be from here, you can see this
GCO is that, so if you just calculate one minus this, then you get this result,
okay, then you do some manipulation with this, so this is zero of that
one minus GCO, yeah, this is zero, if your C does not have Z minus Z bar as a factor,
if your Z has a factor Z minus Z bar, then that will be taken out, then this will be cancelled
out, anyway, I think it is better to understand from this calculation here, because if you don't
have this unstable AU in the denominator here, then AU in the controller is not cancelled out,
then when you do the implementation, this AU will be cancelled out with this AU in the plant,
so in that case, you have unstable pole zero cancellation, okay?
Okay, so that's the requirement on asymptotic stability, now in many cases,
you also need zero status error due to a unit step input,
yeah, how do we meet this requirement from your GCO? Yeah, you have to choose your GCO,
so how do we meet this requirement? Yeah, you can also see from this diagram, yeah, in this case,
RZ is a step input, so once the Z transform, it will be one over one minus Z inverse,
yeah, RZ, when the input is a unit step, so our output YZ will be GCO Z times RZ, correct?
Yeah, this is the general case, now, when the input is this unit step, it will be GCO Z times
one over one minus Z inverse, yeah, because the overall system is ensured to be stable,
so we can apply the final value theorem, so how do we apply the final value theorem to get the limit,
so that means limit K tends to infinity YKT will be equal to limit Z tends to one,
one minus Z inverse times YZ, correct? So this is the final value theorem,
then when you substitute this YZ to here, you can see this is cancel out, then you have GCO lift,
so that is same as a limit GCO Z when Z tends to one, so this is just the GCO one,
so this should be equal to one, because you want the output to be the same as the input,
when time tends to infinity, yeah, you see this input is always one unit step,
so we have this condition here, GCO one should be one in this case,
right? Yeah, because when K tends to infinity, the output should be one, same as the input,
so this is the steady state error requirement. Okay, in summary, we have the following
considerations when we choose our GCO. First, the relative degree of GCO must
satisfy the condition just derived, that is the relative degree of GCO should be bigger than or
equal to the relative degree of GZAS, yeah, this is given, so you know the relative degree,
so when you choose the transfer function, the difference between the degree of the numerator
and denominator should satisfy this condition, and this GCO should contain all the unstable zeros
of the given system, and also the zeros of one manner GCO should include all the unstable poles
of this GZAS, so these two conditions are to ensure stability, this condition is to ensure
realizability of the controller, and the final condition is to ensure zero steady state error,
which was just derived, so we have four conditions, four necessary conditions
when you choose your GCO, but necessary means not sufficient, so to make your GCO sufficient,
you have to consider the given specifications. Okay, so we have suggested a procedure
for the choice of GCO, so you have to select the desired settling time and other specifications,
such as desired maximum overshoot, actually these are given by the user, the user wants to design
a system to meet some requirement, okay, so these are given, settling time, and also overshoot,
for example, in our last example, like this, yeah, you see here, we have this requirement of overshoot
and also the settling time, yeah, that is, you have to ensure the speed of the car
reach 100 km per hour from 0 km per hour in 8 seconds, so these are given, then based on this,
you select a suitable continuous time closed loop, first order or second order closed system
with unit gains, for example, this one, yeah, you use these two conditions to find out
a closed loop transfer function, okay, then
this is the continuous closed loop transfer function, either first order or second order, now
you can convert this continuous transfer function like this to GCO by using,
for example, Poiseuille matching or some other transformation method, like a binary transformation,
so this is to consider the specification to get the GCO, but this GCO may not satisfy the
requirement, so you have to verify if the GCO meet the four conditions, yeah, I just mentioned
the four conditions, yeah, these four conditions,
if this satisfied, then you just use this GCO, then once you get this GCO, you can compute
your consumer using 511 to obtain C, so that's how we obtain our C, if this GCO does not meet
the four conditions, you have to modify GCO to meet the four conditions,
okay, now let's consider some design example, okay, assume we have DC motors
to be considered, to be considered, yeah, that is our continuous plant,
yeah, this is a continuous plant, it's a DC motor,
and the output of the DC motor here is a speed, okay,
and of course you have a zero order hold in front,
the transfer function for this DC motor is given by this, the output is speed, the input
can be considered as a voltage,
now we are going to design controller to obtain zero steady state error
due to a unit step input, yeah, that is this is a unit step input,
and we also have a requirement of settling time of about four seconds,
the sampling time period is choosing as 0.02 seconds, so this is the given design program,
now we have to find this digital controller, that is we need to find this CZ here,
to meet these two requirements for this DC motor control program, okay, now let's
solve the problem, first we have to find this transfer function, yeah, I believe you know how
to find this transfer function, yeah, basically we have formula for this transfer function
of zero order hold together with the plant, which is 1 minus Z inverse times the Z transform
of GS divided by S, okay, so yeah, I don't have to do the calculation, you just substitute the
transfer function, yeah, this is the transfer function here to the formula,
and of course, so in this case you have to find the Z transform
corresponding to 1 divided by S times these two factors,
after calculation you get this result, so that's the GZAS we obtain with this sampling period,
okay, so we have obtained this here, okay, next
you do an inspection on the transfer function here, you can see for this GZAS we don't have
unstable zero, we don't have unstable pole, so you don't worry about the
two necessary conditions for stability, yeah, because you have no such zero,
no such pole outside the unit circle, okay, now we are going to check how we find our GC AOS,
and based on the specification, our desired continuous closed loop transfer function
with damping ratio 0.88 and the nature frequency 1.15 can be chosen, that is we have this
closed loop transfer function, yeah, that's our first step,
yeah, how do we find this, actually we have two requirements,
remember our settling time, yeah, this Ts is 4 sec, then based on this,
this, you should have 4 divided by Zeta Omega N
should be equal to 4 here, okay, yeah, we started this in week 4, when we consider the mapping
between S-plane and Z-plane, yeah, we have an example showing how the settling time is computed,
okay, so based on this our Zeta Omega N is equal to 1 here, so that's why
we have Zeta Omega N equals 1, so with this condition you can choose a damping ratio of 0.88,
if this is chosen as 0.88, then Omega N is chosen to be this,
yeah, of course there are many other choices for the damping ratio and Omega N, so this is one of
the combinations, as long as this is satisfied, then it's okay, okay, so that's the Zeta and
Omega N, and you have to ensure 0 is 0 here, so the DC gain for this is also 1,
yeah, for continuous case DC gain is computed when S is 0, so from that the numerator should
be equal to this, okay, so now this we desired closed loop transfer function can be converted
to GCL in a discrete time domain by using pole-zero matching, in fact we did this earlier,
if you remember in our example here we have this conversion, so this is the continuous
closed loop transfer function obtained from the specification, now with this
sampling period it can be converted to this, okay, yeah, that is this here, okay, so now
that's how we get GCL, now we have to verify if this GCL meet our requirements,
first the relative degree, what's the relative degree of this?
It is 1, correct, yeah, this denominator is second order, numerator is first order,
so relative degree here is 1, but for our GZAS the relative degree is also 1, so the equal,
therefore the first condition is satisfied, yeah, as I said we don't have unstable zero and
also no unstable pole, therefore we don't worry about the second and the third condition,
yeah, so we don't worry about this condition two and the condition
three, no this one, yeah, just now we have the four necessary conditions here,
yeah, we don't worry about this second one and the third one, and the fourth one is already
satisfied when we choose GCL, yeah, you can compute this is also equal to 1, when Z equals 1
that's 1, so this GCL is acceptable, now with this GCL you can apply the formula
to obtain our controller, yeah, this is the formula used to do the calculation,
so you have this CZ, yeah, that is the designed controller, now we have to do verification
yeah, you just compute, yeah, you use MATLAB, you just substitute this CZ here,
yeah, that's CZ to this block and also our GZAS to here, with this unit step input
you can compute, you can use MATLAB to find the output which is this, so that's the output
and we can see that the settling time is 3.71 seconds, which is less than 4 seconds,
and in the end the error, the tracking error will approach to zero, so our design is successful,
okay, so that's our example, now let's consider another example,
suppose we have this transfer function in S domain, yeah, that is our plant given here,
this plant
has this transfer function, it's the first order together with a time delay,
yeah, this is e to the power 5 S, S is a non-plus transform variable,
so this e to the power 5 S is the time delay term, so the, yeah, this plant is described by
this, now we have to obtain a controller, yeah, this CZ to meet this two requirements,
zero is the error due to a unit step input, that means this is a unit step input,
you should have zero status error.
And the settling time is about 10 seconds,
with 5% error tolerance.
And there is no overshoot for this system.
The sampling period is choosing as one second.
OK, how do we do the design?
First step, we have to obtain this gzas.
Yeah, in fact, this is a delay.
e to the power of negative 5s means
you have a delay of five seconds.
So when you do the sampling with one second,
this e to the power of 5s can be converted to z
to the power of negative 5.
So this is the z domain representation of the term
e to the power of negative 5s.
Now for this part, you can use the zero order hold together
with a planned transfer function to get the answer.
So this gs is this here, and then divide by s.
You find the corresponding z transform, that will be this.
So that's the gzas.
Now, to meet the causality requirements,
a delay of five sampling periods must
be included in the closed loop transfer function.
Yeah, in fact, you can see that you
have z to the power of negative 5 here.
So that should be included in the closed loop transfer
function.
And also, your settling time is 10 seconds.
But among the 10 seconds, five seconds will be in the delay.
Because of the delay, you cannot do anything.
The delay is inherent from the plant.
So when you design your controller,
you should have five seconds to be considered.
Yeah, 10 minus 5, so you have five seconds left.
So to do this, you can choose this closed loop transfer
function as this.
Because you have no overshoot, we
can consider first-order transfer function.
Because you shouldn't have overshoot,
so we use first-order.
Maybe you choose gcAO first.
That should be a first-order.
And you have to choose this s plus sigma.
For zeros, this should have a sigma here.
So now, how do we choose this sigma?
Sigma depend on the settling time.
For 5%, the settling time is zeta omega.
For first-order, we don't have zeta.
It's just sigma.
So in this case, you should have Ts equals,
settling time is 3 over sigma.
5% is 3 in the numerator.
2% is 4 in the numerator.
So this should be equal to 5, because all together,
you get 10 seconds as the settling time.
But among them, 5 seconds is occupied by the delay.
So you have 5 seconds left.
That's why it's 5.
So from this, our sigma is 0.6.
Yeah, this is the boundary.
Yeah, I said this is the boundary, sorry.
The boundary is 5 seconds.
OK?
So now, the boundary means this.
That's negative 0.6.
That's the boundary.
So you can choose a pole on the left of the boundary.
So in our solution, we choose negative 0.7
to get some margin.
That is, you don't choose the boundary settling time.
So this negative 0.7, our transfer function
is choosing as, for the continuous case,
is 0.7 divided by s plus 0.7.
So this negative 0.7 pole is mapped to the z domain.
You have negative 0.5.
Yeah, that is how we beat the settling time requirement.
OK, for the zero status error, in the continuous is this.
But you can also do computation directly from the z domain.
So we use this condition.
You can find that k is also 0.5.
Now you are applying the formula 5.11.
That is this formula here.
You can get the controller.
So this is the controller.
And then you can see that the relative degree here
beat the requirement for this relative degree.
In fact, you can see that the relative degree is,
if you include this z to the power negative 5,
it will be 6.
You put this as a 1 over z5.
So the relative degree is 6.
And our gzas obtained here is also 6 here.
So they are the same.
So this is how we obtain the controller.
Now you do verification.
You have this response.
Yeah, that is you have a delay.
And then you eventually approach to 1 in about 10 seconds.
So that's the response.
OK, so this is how we designed this CZ based
on the third approach, which is based on closed loop transfer
function.
And also, of course, the given transfer function, gzas.
Now we have some special case under this approach,
like the finite settling time design.
Yeah, maybe we have a break for 20 minutes.
Then we continue with the topic of finite settling time design.
OK.
Let's continue.
Yeah, now we consider some special cases.
The first special case is finite time, finite settling time
design.
Yeah, as we know for continuous systems,
the output of the system can track the reference input
any one time go to infinity.
But for discrete time system, the output of the system
can approach the desired reference output
after a finite time.
And it will follow it exactly after that finite time.
So if we consider a special type of plant,
that is all the poles and the zeros of the plant or process
are inside the unit circle, you can choose the closed loop
transfer function, GcAoZ as z to the power of x to k,
where k is bigger than or equal to the intrinsic delay,
for example, the five second for the previous example,
plus the relative degree of the discretized process.
So with this choice, that means the closed loop transfer
function is just z to the power of x to k, OK?
Yeah, that's the GcAo, that is this.
So your yz, in this case, will be z to the power of x to k
times Rz, right?
Then you take an inverse z transform.
What do you have?
This will be ykT.
Yeah, you'll apply the shifting theorem.
This will be Rt minus k.
Maybe this k is not the same as this k.
Maybe I put this as a bigger k to denote the time.
So this one will be bigger k minus this small k.
Yeah, this k is this delay, T, like this, correct?
It's delayed by small kT sampling period.
So in other words, our output, y,
will be the same as R in k steps, k sampling period.
And it will stay there afterwards, exactly.
OK, so that's the meaning here.
Yeah.
Actually, it's not just a necessary unit step.
For any input, you have this result.
That is, the reference input is tracked perfectly
after k's sampling period.
Now we also have the concept of deadbeat control.
I think in state space design, you also
consider this deadbeat control.
This means the controller will bring the output
to the steady state in the smallest number of time steps.
Yeah, here, this k is bigger than equal to this.
So the smallest time is equal.
So the smallest time for the output
to follow this reference input will be the intrinsic delay
plus the relative degree of the discretized process.
If there is no intrinsic delay, it's
just a relative degree of the discretized process.
Yeah, that's the minimum or smallest number of time steps.
This time step is sampling period.
Yeah, smallest number of sampling period.
OK, so that's the response.
Now, with this closed loop transfer function,
we can find our Cz using this formula.
You just substitute z from x to k into this formula.
You get this answer, Cz.
So as you can see, for such a design,
any parameter to be considered is the sampling period.
Why?
Because for different sampling period,
you have different transfer function here.
So that's any design parameter.
So this design is very simple.
OK, let's look at an example.
If GzAs is given to be this transfer function,
you have to design a deadbeat controller for this system.
Yeah, actually, equivalently, this system
has this transfer function.
You multiply z squared in post-numerator
and denominator, you have this.
So the relative degree here is true.
Yeah, when you consider relative degree,
you have to use the positive powers for the numerator
and denominator.
So this, you have to convert this to that form.
So this relative degree is 2.
And we don't have 0 outside, as you can see here.
We don't have 0 for this transfer.
But you have a pole at z equals 1.
So this is the boundary of the unit circle.
According to earlier requirement,
this pole should be included as the 0 of 1 minus GcAoz,
because that's not strictly inside.
So we also need to include this boundary pole inside
as the 0 of this.
Yeah, this is one of the conditions mentioned earlier.
So we can set our closed loop transfer function as this.
Because with this choice, you can see it will have a 0.
Yeah, you can consider this.
What is 1 minus GcAoz?
Yeah, with this GcAoz, R1 minus GcAoz
is equal to 1 minus z to probability 2,
which is z squared in the denominator,
then z squared minus 1.
OK?
So this is z plus 1, z minus 1.
So it has a 0 at this position.
OK?
Yeah, that meet the requirement here.
So we can choose our GcAoz to be this.
OK, now you can compute the controller using our 511.
Yeah, that is this formula here.
So this formula is quite important.
You do a calculation by substituting this into here,
you have this result. And that's the equivalent to this.
After you simplify this.
OK, so that's the controller we obtained.
Another example, design a deadbeat controller
with its output to a zero order hold for DC motor speed.
Control system with analog transfer function given here.
Yeah, this one was considered earlier.
And the sampling period is 0.02 second.
And later on, you have to do another design
with the sampling period of 0.1 second.
Yeah, now you can find the transfer function, GcAs,
by using the formula 1 minus z inverse times the z transform
of Gs over s, which is this.
Yeah, we did this earlier.
Yeah, of course, that's with this sampling period.
You can see there is no pole, no zero outside the unit circle,
as I mentioned there before.
And this relative degree is 1.
So we can choose the closed loop transfer function as this.
Yeah, remember our G closed loop transfer function.
We have the requirement and the k value.
Yeah, this k should be bigger than or equal to the intrinsic delay.
Yeah, for this, we don't have any delay.
I mean the intrinsic delay.
But the relative degree here is 1.
So k should be bigger than or equal to 1.
Then we just choose 1.
So that's why we have this closed loop transfer function.
With this choice of a closed loop transfer function,
the consumer design can bring the output to the desired reference in one step.
Yeah.
So, yeah, actually, you just use this 5.12, yeah, using this.
You can find your controller will be this.
Yeah, you just substitute the obtained gz s.
And this is z inverse divided by 1 minus z inverse.
You get this answer.
So that's the controller.
Now we can find the response of the closed loop system.
Yeah, I just show you the response in this diagram.
Yeah, here.
You can see the output behaves like this.
If you look at the sampling instance, yeah, it's starting from here, 0.
Yeah, then at the first sampling instant, it is equal to 1 already.
Then after this, at all the sampling instance, the output are 1.
Yeah, at the sampling instance.
Of course, you can see between the sampling instance, you have some overshoot or undershoot.
But at the sampling instance, the values of the output are all 1.
Yeah, this is the statement.
The sampled process output attains the value after just one sample, not the 0.02 second.
So yeah, but between the samples, the output oscillates wildly, as you can see.
Actually the control variable, yeah, this is the output.
We also consider the intermediate or internal signals, such as the control signal.
Yeah, this is the control variable.
It is like this.
You see the magnitude is very big.
Yeah, this is 10 to the power 4.
Yeah, over each sampling period, it is a hold as a constant because of the zero order hold.
Okay, so this is the output.
So you have very high magnitude.
Yeah, as you can see, the oscillatory behavior of the control variable,
yeah, this control variable causes unacceptable inter-sample oscillation.
The reason is this.
Yeah, this is the observation.
You have finite settling time, which is, for this example, just one sampling period.
Such designs may exhibit undesirable inter-sample oscillations because the control is unchanged
between two consecutive sampling points, as you can see here.
It is a hold as a constant.
So this control is just a constant.
So that may not give you good response.
That is cause the inter-sample, yeah, large inter-sample behavior.
And also this control variable has very big magnitude.
In practice, you have saturation in the implementation.
So it may result in unacceptable system behavior in this case.
Yeah.
Therefore, after you finish your design, you do a simulation study like this.
If the performance is not good enough, then you cannot implement the controller.
For example, this case, this controller may damage your control system because of the large magnitude.
Therefore, you have to redesign the controller.
Yeah, in this case, we consider a larger sampling period.
So with a larger sampling period, the transfer function will change to this.
Yeah, just now, for smaller sampling period, this transfer function is this, OK?
We have the same GCL, and you can compute the controller to be this.
Then you do a simulation study, and this time, the performance is much better.
Yeah, because you have a large sampling period, so the response will have this output.
So you can see also at the sampling instance, the output are one.
After the first sampling period, it remains one.
It reaches the reference input in one sampling period.
After that, remains as one.
Yeah, the magnitude of the control variable also reduced significantly.
So when you consider such controller design, any parameter you can change is the sampling period.
So you have to adjust the sampling period to check the performance, OK?
For both cases, the output will approach to one in one sample in period,
and remains at one for the remaining sampling instance.
OK, that's the finite time, finite settling time controller design.
So in summary, for this case, you just choose your closed loop transfer function as z to the power of negative k.
For example, for this case, we just choose z to the power of negative one.
OK, this design has disadvantage, as I just mentioned.
Even for this case, you still have a large overshoot.
So maybe we can consider a new design approach called repo-free controller.
Yeah, that means we don't want this inter-sampling behavior.
Yeah, here we have this inter-sampling behavior.
So is it possible to remove this inter-sampling behavior in our design?
Yeah, that's the topic here.
So to avoid inter-sample oscillations, we can maintain the control variable and output constants after n samples,
where n is the degree of the denominator of the discretized process.
Yeah, this is also a special situation.
That is, we will consider the reference input as a unit step function.
OK, let's consider our...
Yeah, this block diagram here, 5.2.
So based on this diagram, you can see that our control u, yeah, this is the u, is equal to y divided by this.
Because y equals gz s times u, so u will be equal to y divided by this.
OK, so that's just simple mathematical calculation.
And now, here, u times r and divided by r.
So this is same as this.
And our yz divided by rz, as you can see, yz divided by this rz is the closed loop transfer function.
So this uz is changed, is found to be this.
OK, now we are going to obtain a suitable GCL based on this uz or ez.
Yeah, sometimes we have to use ez.
Yeah, I will show you an example when we use this uz and when we use this ez.
So from this, we can obtain GCL and also, so based on the constraint here,
yeah, the constraint is that the output and also the control u should be constant after n samples.
We are in the order of this transfer function.
Yeah, because we want to have zero status error, so this should be considered when you choose this GCL.
Yeah, once you have this GCL obtained, then you can use our earlier formula to obtain our C.
Yeah, this earlier formula is 5.11.
I believe, yeah, it worked.
Yeah, I just used that page many times, which is the formula to compute our C.
Yeah, so once you have a GCL, you just use this, you can calculate your C.
OK, so now, yeah, maybe I just use this diagram because this is the same as 5.2.
OK, let's illustrate the design of, yeah, the critical part is to find the GCL.
And our reference input here is a special reference input, which is unit step input to the system.
So now, let's look at an example to show how we find our GCL.
Yeah, we want to design a ripple-free data bit controller with zero order hold
for type 1 vehicle positioning system with this transfer function.
Yeah, so this is the transfer function for this type 1 vehicle positioning system.
Now, the sampling period is choosing as 0.1 secant.
So, from this, you can find the transfer function GZAS, yeah, by using the formula
for the plant to geyser with the zero order hold.
So that's the transfer function, GZAS.
And as I said, this is also a special case.
The reference input is a unit step.
And we are going to design, yeah, we are going to design the controller C such that our output, Y,
yeah, our output Y will follow this input in two steps in this case.
And after that, the output remains as 1.
Not only at the sampling instance, but all other times.
Why two secant?
Because our denominator here is 2.
So that's the order, you see.
The requirement is n samples.
Where n is the degree of the denominator.
Okay?
So that's the requirements.
Okay, from the, this formula, 5.13, you can compute your U as this.
So this is GZL to be determined, R is this, and the GZS has been found just now.
So you substitute your GZS and R and you do a calculation, you get this.
So that should be your U.
Now how do we choose this GZL?
Yeah, we obtain this GZL based on this U, based on this U.
And we said this U should be a constant after two samples.
Yeah, because that's the requirement here.
Yeah.
Yeah, you see, after two samples.
This, because our n here is 2 in the example.
Secant order.
So for this to be possible, our U should be this, correct?
Yeah, there is a case for this U, because this is a type one.
Yeah, because our integrator in the plant.
Yeah, just write, use this diagram here.
So this transfer function, GZS.
In our example, you can see there is an integrator here.
OK?
From this.
You have an integrator in the continuous plant, you also have this integrator.
So that's why it's called a type one.
So if you have an integrator here, and your U here is a constant after two samples.
What this constant should be?
This constant should be zero.
Because if it's not zero, it will be integrated by the integrator in this transfer function.
Then the output will continue to increase.
OK?
So what is the constant?
This constant should be zero.
In other words, after two samples, your U should be zero.
Yeah, so generally, our U should be, based on this transform,
based on Z transform, our U should be equal to A0 plus A1 Z inverse plus A2 Z inverse
squared and so on, right?
Now, this A2 is actually, that's U2.
Yeah, here is actually U1, that's U0, based on the definition of Z transform.
So as I just mentioned, because of the integrator inside this, after two samples,
this should be zero.
Yeah, because after two samples, this should be a constant.
If this is a non-zero constant, it will be integrated to infinity.
Therefore, this constant should be zero, so that the integration of this zero
remains as a constant.
Yeah, that is just dependent on the initial values of this.
So that's why this U2, U3, and so on.
Yeah, in other words, UKT, yeah, maybe we put a sampling.
It's UT, U2T, UKT, and so on.
This UKT should be zero for K bigger than or equal to two.
So with this, our UZ should be equal to that.
Okay.
The reason is just because of the integrator inside here.
If that's not zero constant, it will increase to infinity.
If it's zero, the integrator, yeah, actually the integration here is just, for example,
is UKT, DT, yeah.
For example, that's from 2T, yeah, because after 2T is a constant,
this should be a constant, C, to any value.
Any, for example, to infinity.
Then this should be equal to, yeah, because this is a constant C, for example, or just a U.
So the integration will be U times T, okay.
This U is the constant that we consider.
So this T is from 2T to infinity.
If this U is not zero, then that will go to infinity.
Okay, so we just have two terms in our UZ.
Yeah, there's two terms, A0 plus A1Z inverse.
In other words, U0 may not be non-zero, UT may not be zero.
So you have these two values.
After that, this should be zero.
Okay, for this to be possible, your GCL should cancel out this denominator.
Therefore, our GCL should be equal to K times this denominator.
Because with this cancellation, you have two terms in the numerator.
So that's how we choose GCL.
Okay, yeah, after you choose GCL, this GCL will cancel out the denominator.
Then you have this two terms.
Of course, you have to determine this K.
How do we determine this K?
You use the steady state error requirement.
Yeah, just now at the beginning, I said when we design GCL,
you have to use this condition also.
Okay, so now when Z equals one, this term should be equal to one.
From that, you get the K.
Okay, so this K is 0.5083.
So we have this GCL.
Yeah, you just substitute to that K value here, you get this GCL.
Once we have this GCL, you can compute your control C using this formula.
So you substitute that GCL to 511, you get this C.
So that's the controller we obtain.
Okay, now once you get this controller, you can do verification.
So you just substitute this C to here.
And of course, we have our GZ earlier.
And this is a step input.
Then you can find the output by using computational tool like Matlab.
So you have this response.
Yeah, this is the response.
And this is the control variable.
You can see the control variable has two non-zero values.
This value and this value.
Then after two samples, it remains as zero.
And our output also reaches one in two samples.
After two samples, it remains as one.
Even during the inter-sampling period.
Yeah, so you have no inter-sampling behavior.
Yeah, this is a very nice response with our controller here.
Okay, so that's the first example.
When our GZs contains integrator.
Now, in some case, our system has no integrator.
For example, for this system, this transfer function is
one over S plus one times S plus ten.
So we are going to design a repo-free data-based controller for this system.
And of course, we have zero order hold involved.
The sampling period is choosing as 0.1 sec.
With this sampling period, you can find the corresponding
Z transfer function or pulse transfer function for the zero order hold
together with this DC motor speed control system.
So you have this GZs.
That's this.
In this case, we don't have integrator in the plant.
So we have no integrator here, so this cannot be zero.
If this is zero, the output will be zero.
Because you have no integrator, this is just a non-integral action
on this input.
So if this is a pure constant applied to this, then that will be
a constant.
But if this is zero, the output will be zero.
Okay?
And we don't want the output to be zero.
We want the output to be same as the input.
So how do we do this?
This time, we need to have an integrator in the controller, C.
Okay, so we are going to consider the arrow in this case.
Okay, so let's look at how we do that.
This is the step input.
Again, we also consider the control input, U, by using our equation here.
Yeah, you just do a calculation.
GCL is to be determined.
RZ is that.
GZs has been found.
So you do a substitution.
You get this times GCL, Z.
Okay, as I said, in this case, your UK shouldn't be zero.
But it should be a non-zero constant for KB line equal to N.
Of course, our N was true.
Because this GZs is second order.
So after two sampling periods, your UK should be a non-zero constant.
As required here.
Yeah, should be a constant after two seconds.
Okay, now we just consider our arrow.
This arrow should be zero after two samples.
Actually, for both cases, your arrow should be zero.
Yeah, even for the previous example.
Because this arrow is the input minus the output.
So after two samples, this output should follow the input.
So after two samples, this arrow will be zero.
Okay.
Therefore, our Z-transform for the arrow will have two terms.
In the same way as I did for the previous example.
So we have EK equals E0 plus E1, Z inverse.
Now how do we use this?
Now to use this, we find our G in terms of U.
So based on this, our G is one over C times U.
Yeah, that is, this U divided by C is G.
So E equals that.
Then you just substitute the U we just obtained.
Yeah, this part is GCAO.
Yeah, you just do a substitution.
Yeah, this is our U obtained earlier.
So this divided by C, you get this.
You just put the C in the denominator of this result.
Okay, so now let's look at the result here.
Your CZ must have an integrator to cancel out this one under Z inverse.
Yeah, where is this one under Z inverse from?
That's from this here.
So you cannot use GCAO to cancel out this because that's a boundary.
So CZ should cancel out this.
So for CZ to cancel out this, that means the denominator of C should contain this factor.
Therefore, C must have an integrator to do this.
Then our GCAO should cancel out the remaining part in the denominator.
That is, GCAO should cancel out Z inverse times this.
Yeah, this factor is cancelled out by this CZ.
So this is how we choose GCAO.
That is a constant times Z inverse times this.
Actually, with such choice of GCAO, later on when you compute this CZ,
the numerator of CZ will cancel out this two factor also.
With the cancellation, our EZ will have two terms.
Yeah, actually CZ just cancel out one of the terms here.
So this is the choice of GCAO, which is basically cancelling Z inverse and this factor.
Now we have to find the value of K by using the state error requirement.
That is, GCAO should be equal to one.
From this, we can compute our K.
So this K is 0.5901.
Then you apply this formula again by substituting the obtained GCAO.
Yeah, our GCAO is...
Yeah, this is our GCAO.
So you just use this GCAO and the formula here.
You can get this C.
Yeah, of course, this K should be substituted here before you do the calculation.
Okay.
Actually, as I just mentioned, this C we computed.
Yeah, this C we computed here.
We have two zeros and they will cancel out these two factors here.
Yeah, you see, we have this two zero.
They will cancel out these two factors.
Then in the end, your EZ, just the GCAO times this and also this.
Yeah, you can do a calculation.
In the end, your EZ will be in this form, just two terms.
Yeah, these two terms.
So that's how we obtain the ripple-free control of CZ.
And you can also do a simulation to find out the output and also the control variable.
Yeah, you can see the control variable will maintain as a constant 50 after two sampling periods.
Yeah, it's not zero because our CZ is this and our plant has no integrator.
Our output will be this.
So it will be maintained as constant after two sampling periods.
Okay, so that's the design of ripple-free control.
We have two situations.
One is the plant involves an integrator and the other has no integrator.
But in this case, your C has an integrator.
Okay, so that's the third approach of designing controller.
But this controller design is just for such a block diagram.
As you can see, this block diagram has a unit feedback here.
Actually, this type of design is just one degree of freedom feedback controller.
I'll show you why this is one degree of freedom.
Okay, so this can be written as this form.
Yeah, this is the plant.
I just say it can be written as B divided by A.
That's the transfer function.
And this is the controller, which has a numerator SC and RC.
Yeah, this time here, we have no disturbance considered.
So here, if we have this disturbance considered,
we will have this computation for the output.
Yeah, you can obtain the output by superposition.
Here is a little bit misusing of notation.
Yeah, this N is in some times, in some textbook,
they use N as a time domain variable, just like our K earlier.
So this output has two terms.
One term is due to the reference input.
So it's the transfer function of the unit feedback system times the reference input.
And the other term is due to the disturbance.
So you can find the transfer function from V to Y, it will be this.
Yeah, we also mentioned this during week four.
So we have these two terms.
So the output will be, yeah, we just deluged this transfer function as a TZ
and this as SZ.
Yeah, that's a notation.
OK, in the design, we may have two requirements.
We want the output Y to follow the reference input as close as possible.
Right, because this is the desired output.
So you should have this Y to approach this R.
So this, we have to ensure or make YN follow R and your acceptable manner.
And on the other hand, this Y should be independent of V.
Or you have to eliminate the effect of V.
OK, so we have to remove the effect of V and Y,
so that the disturbance effect can be reduced.
So we have these two requirements.
To achieve this, we should be able to modify our S and T independently.
Yeah, we have two terms.
This is S, that's T.
So we should be able to achieve these two requirements simultaneously.
You have to modify S and T independently.
Can we do this?
Actually, we cannot, because if you add T with S, you get one.
OK, so once you specify your S, you can find the T from this equation.
So T and S are mutually dependent in this case.
Therefore, you only have one freedom, even though you have two requirements.
So you cannot choose your S and T independently.
OK, so this type of controller is just one freedom, one degree of freedom feedback controller.
So, so far in this chapter, the system,
or the controller design here is just one degree of freedom.
So to achieve this, we must have two degrees of freedom of feedback controller.
Yeah.
I think we come back next week to further study two degrees of freedom feedback controller.
Yeah, which is in this form.
So we stop here today.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you.