driving and sounds
th
okay uh... greening class
right so we'll come back uh... so before we start the lecture today just want to
remind you right in case some of you uh...
may not be aware
so uh... today is twenty second of august so we are supposed to have a lecture in this LT
which is LT2A
but for the next two weeks we'll be having our lectures in this Lee Koon Cheon LT here
so this is the LT near Can Thim B
okay so just to remind you that
for the next two weeks the lectures will be in Lee Koon Cheon LT
above or near Can Thim B
okay and also uh... in case some of you are not aware
right so you can uh... download the lecture notes and some
uh... exercises from the uh... folder
right so from the course folder and also there's some recorded lectures so each week
the lectures will be recorded
okay so if you want to do some revision you are welcome to
uh... watch these particular lectures
so also from
can you all hear me from the back
yeah also from past experience we will
you know tends to notice that as
you know the lecture progress
the number of students will start to decrease
so last week you can see lots of seats are taken this week already there are some
uh... empty seats
so we expect the train to continue
right so one of the possible reason is that
uh... some students told me before they find it
you know they can watch this recorded lecture
and they can make the speed to 1.5
they said that when I speak my pace is a bit slow
so if they speed up the
this lecture speed by 1.5 times
he can actually cut down one hour so instead of coming here and stay for three hours
you just need to
you know spend two hours to watch the recorded lecture
okay so anyway that's a joke aside so uh... yeah please continue to come and attend the lecture
but just to let you know that there's this recorded lecture that you can watch
uh... afterwards if you find that there are some
uh... concepts that you are not clear with
okay so uh... today we are going to continue on with our lecture so we are going to move on to
part two now
so part two will be mainly dealing with image compression and jpeg standards
right so again these are some references should you have any questions that you want to
uh... find out more about the
uh... the topics or the content for this part of the course you can refer to this reference
material
or again you can go to google or use chatgpt to help you to
improve your learning experience
right okay so in part two these are the outline for the topics that we are going to cover
so first of all we are going to learn some basic terms and concepts
and afterwards we'll go through the entropy coding
and then we'll learn about some basic image and video compression
okay we'll learn about transform based coding
and afterwards we'll move on to DCT which is a very popular
uh... you know transform technique that's used in many media compression including
jpeg as well as mpeg compression
so we'll spend some time to learn about this particular DCT, discrete cosine transform
and afterwards we'll learn about the jpeg standards
so these are the topics that we are going to cover in part two
right okay so first let's try to go through some basic terms and concepts
just to make sure that everyone is on the same page
right okay so what is compression
or coding so in the context of media compression
right when we say compression it actually means the same thing as in coding
so in this article course
when we refer to compression it means the same thing as coding or encoding
they are all the same
right so what is the objective of performing compression
right so if you think about for typical for example image and video so from
last week we just do a simple calculation to see if you have a small video
right it already require a very large bit rate
okay hundreds of uh...
megabits per second so therefore there's a very strong motivation for us to
perform the compression
because if you don't compress it then it's very hard for us to store
in some uh... storage devices or transmit over the network
so therefore there's a strong motivation for us to perform compression
because without compression
right the data, original data is just too demanding in terms of
storage and bandwidth requirement
so therefore we need to perform compression so what's the objective of it
is to reduce the number of bits
that's needed to represent the information
okay so i think the motivation is quite straightforward
so what you have is that you have some input data
so this input data can be for example text, it can be audio, it can be image, it can be video
but in the context of this particular course
our focus mainly will be on
uh... image and video
right okay because we are talking about video signal processing
so we have some input data which can be for example image and video
and then you go through the encoder
right so the encoder in this particular context is actually used for compression
so we have an original for example image file
when we go through the encoder, we try to compress it into a small file
or low bit rate
right so that
right when the file is small then you can either store it or you can then transmit it
so you can then either store it
right as an image and video file or you can transmit over the network
okay so later on, suppose it is a network then at the receiver end
then you need to perform the decoder
right so you need to let it go through a decoder
so this decoder's objective is to perform decompression
so decompression means that you take some compressed bit stream
and you try to recover the original data
so this is the meaning of decompression
and afterwards you have the output data
right so that's the very basic ideas of a data compression
framework or pipeline
right okay so next we need to introduce this concept or this term compression ratio
but so what is the definitions of a compression ratio
so the definition of compression ratio is data storage requirement
of the original data over the storage requirement for the compressed data
so it's a number of bits or the storage requirement
for the original uncompressed data
over the data storage requirement for a compressed data
so by the definition, if your method is performing the compression well
do you think the compression ratio should be greater than one or less than one?
If you define compression ratio as the data storage requirement for the original data
over data storage requirement for compressed data,
and if your method is working properly,
you expect the compression ratio to be greater than one or less than one?
Greater than one.
Because definitely this is the original data storage requirement
therefore your compressed data is going to be much smaller.
So it's going to be a larger value over a smaller value.
Therefore your compression ratio typically should be greater than one.
So therefore the meaning of a compression ratio is quite straightforward.
It's a matrix or a way for you to measure how much the data has been compressed.
So it's defined as this B naught,
which is the number of bits before compression or is the original data storage requirement,
over B1, which is the number of bits or the storage requirement after the compression.
So because after compression you expect this number to be smaller than this.
Therefore typically for compression ratio it should be greater than one.
And usually the larger the value, that means the smaller size you can compress it into.
So from the compression perspective you want the value to be as large as possible.
Okay, so next we are going to touch on some basics on information theory.
So the concept that we are going to introduce is the entropy here.
So this entropy or using this symbol called eta is the measures of the amount of information in some data source.
Or sometimes it's also an indication of degree of randomness in the data source.
So the entropy eta for an information source, suppose this information source what you have is that you have a set S,
which consists of a number of different symbols, S1 all the way up to Sn.
So we are trying to measure this entropy, that means we are trying to measure the amount of information inside
or the degree of randomness inside this particular data source here.
So that's a very formal definition for entropy.
So for those of you if you have studied digital communication, you should definitely know the equation.
So the entropy eta is given by this particular symbol here, H.
The entropy for this set S is defined by this equation here, Pi.
So this Pi here is the probability of each of this particular symbol in this set here.
So this Pi, log Pi with a base of 2, and then you sum up over all the possible symbols in the set.
So that's the definitions of the entropy.
And afterwards if you can simplify this a little bit, Pi is P to the power of negative 1, you move it down here,
then you can rewrite in this form here.
So therefore for entropy you can also write it as Pi, log Pi to the base of 2,
you sum up over all the symbols in the set and you put a negative sign in front.
So this is the entropy.
So as I mentioned before, Pi is the probability of a symbol Si that occurs in this set here.
So what is the significance of this particular entropy in the context of compression is that
entropy is the smallest number of bits on average that you need to represent a symbol.
So for example, now you have a set S, you have many different symbols.
So on average, the smallest number of bits that you can use to represent this set of symbols is known as entropy.
So for example, if you are given a particular symbol, a set S with a certain number of symbols,
say suppose here you have 8 symbols, you can easily use 3 bits to represent it.
If you want, you can even use 8 bits or 10 bits to represent it.
So you can use a larger number of bits to represent it.
But if you want to reduce the number of bits, continue to reduce the number of bits, that is a theoretical lower bound.
So the theoretical lower bound, the number of bits on average that you need to represent this particular symbol is known as the entropy.
So that's another interpretation of the entropy in the context of compression.
Okay, so now we have introduced some basic terms.
Now we are ready to cover the next topic, which is the entropy coding.
So as I mentioned, coding and encoding refer to the same thing.
There's no difference between them.
Okay, so there's different ways of performing entropy encoding.
So for this course, we will be focusing on Huffman coding,
because Huffman coding is one of the most commonly used coding used in media compression,
either image compression or video compression, and there are corresponding standards,
such as JPEG standard and the MPEG standard.
So therefore, we'll be focusing on Huffman coding here.
And also just to make a note, because for this particular class here, the background is actually quite diverse.
I understand that there are students from SPML, students from communication, students from control, even some students from power, and also CCA.
So the background is quite diverse.
So therefore, in order to make sure that everyone understands it,
we'll try to cover it in such a way that at least the majority of students will be able to understand.
So therefore, in case if you're already familiar with some of the concepts,
just take it as a revision or sometimes you may gain a certain new perspective.
Right, okay, so having said that, next let's look at what's the Huffman coding.
So Huffman coding is the types of variable length coding, or VLCC.
So what is the, you can see by this particular term here, variable length coding,
it does already tell you some indication about what this coding scheme is.
So this particular coding scheme means that for different symbols, all right, different symbols, you use different bits to represent this particular symbol.
So symbol is a very general term to describe any kind of a data source that we have.
So to give you an example, if we refer to English, right, English, so most of you know English.
So English, we have 26 alphabets.
So if you want, for example, you can use 8 bits to represent each of these particular alphabets.
So for each English alphabet, if you want, you can use 8 bits to represent it.
It's not a problem.
But if you do that, it may not be so efficient, right?
It may not be so efficient.
Okay, another thing about this entropy encoding is that for example, if we take the example of the English, right,
some actually alphabets or some letters occur more often than the others.
So for example, in English, what are the letters that occur very frequently, very often?
Can some of you suggest some English letters that occur very often?
First, we have the vowel, A-E-I-O-U, those occur very often.
And then if you have the consonant, consonant is like T, I just given you one, T, S, M, yeah,
and these are very common kind of a consonant.
So therefore, you have these letters which occur very often.
So for these letters that occur very often, if you want to design certain codes to represent it,
do you think you should use a shorter code work or longer code work to represent it?
Shorter code works means you use a smaller number of bits.
Longer code works means that you use a larger number of bits to represent.
So for those letters that occur very often, do you think you should use less letter,
less number of shorter code work or longer code work to represent?
Would you use?
If they occur so often, because in the context of this particular course is we want to perform compression.
So when we want to perform compression, that means we want to use as few bits as possible to represent our information source.
So if you know that certain letters occur so often, therefore you should use shorter code work,
that means smaller number of bits or longer number of bits to represent it.
Shorter code works or smaller number of bits, it's very intuitive.
So on the other hand, if you think about it, so for some letters like in English,
what are the letters that occur very rarely, very infrequently?
Q, Z or Z depending on whether you're American or British.
So these are some very rare kind of English letters.
So for those letters, should you use a longer code work or shorter code work to represent it?
You should use a longer code work, because they occur so rarely,
so you can afford to use a longer code work to represent it.
So therefore, the idea now is quite clear, depending on the probability of how often a letter appears,
you assign different code work length to represent this particular letter.
So this idea now is reflected by variable length coding.
So what it means is that for different symbols or letters, we'll be using different variable,
we'll be using different number of bits to represent the letter.
Hence the name, variable length coding.
So this is as opposed to, for example, just now we say, if you want, we can use 8 bits to represent each letter.
But if you do that, we don't take into account the probability distribution of the letter.
So therefore, it's not a very clever way of doing it.
So therefore, the idea now is quite straightforward.
So the idea of variable length coding, we have just gone through an example to provide the motivation.
So the approach is that higher frequency patterns or symbols are assigned shorter code work.
Shorter code works means you require smaller number of bits.
So on the other hand, the reverse is also true.
That means lower frequency patterns or symbols, you will assign longer code work.
So the objective of you doing that is that such that on average,
the number of bits that is required to represent each pattern or symbol will be reduced.
So on average, the average number of bits to represent a symbol now will be shorter.
So that's the idea of variable length coding.
So in the context of Huffman coding, as I mentioned, typically we use this work symbol to represent
it's a very general term, symbol.
So for example, just now in the context of the English letter, the symbol can be used to represent the letter.
So in the context of example, if you are trying to perform some image compression,
you may partition the image into small image patches.
Then the symbol can be used to, for example, represent a small image patch.
So therefore, symbol is a very generic term that we use to describe a pattern.
Okay, so next we'll use a simple example to explain how do we exactly perform this Huffman coding.
So what it means is that given a particular set of symbols with their corresponding probability distribution,
we want to generate the code works that can be used to represent this particular set of symbol.
So that's what we plan to do. This is the objective of Huffman coding.
So we take a simple example first.
Suppose this particular example is that we have strings of character like this.
So we can see we have four A's, two B's, one C and one D.
And then we want to generate this Huffman code work set for these sets of letters with this probability distribution.
So we can see in this case here, A occurs four times, B occurs two times, C and D occur once.
For each of them, it occurs only one time.
So therefore, from our understanding, if you want to represent this particular letter A using code work,
you want it to have a shorter code work or longer code work?
You want it to have shorter code work.
And which are the symbols that have the longest code work?
It should be C or D.
So even before we do that, we know that that is the high level intuition.
So next, I'm going to go through with you a systematic way of generating the Huffman code work set.
So actually, there are many different ways you can do it.
But here in this course, we are just going to introduce one way of doing it, which is usually quite a common way of doing it.
So what we'll do first of all is that we can see that A occurs four times, B two times, C and D occur once each.
So the first thing that we'll do is that we'll write down this particular symbol in the decreasing order of occurrence or the decreasing probability.
So we write down A, B, C and D. It's because A occurs four times, B is two times, C and D is one time each.
So we write it down in the decreasing occurrence, number of occurrence here.
This C and D, you can actually sort it. It doesn't matter you sort the order.
But no, because in English, C occur before D. So we just happen to write this way.
OK, so we write down A, B, C, D. And then next week, we write down the number of occurrence, four, two, one, one here.
So the next thing is that we take those two symbols with the lowest number of occurrence, the C and D, we add them up, write the number.
So you can see one plus one, it becomes two.
So once you have this two here, we move it to the next column.
But you try to rearrange the next column again in the decreasing orders of occurrence here.
So if you add up one and one is two, so two happen to be the same as this number two above.
So if the number is the same, usually we try not to disturb it so much. We just move it at the bottom.
So now we have this one plus one is two here. So the rest, we just move it over. This A4 and B2, we just move it over.
And then afterwards, we repeat the same thing. We take the two smallest occurrence, two and two, add up is four.
And then four should be the same as this A4, so we just put it at the bottom here. And then the rest, we just move it up here.
Okay, so we have done the first step. So the second step is that we assign, we need to assign the bits patterns already.
So for this particular course, because we are following these textbooks, so they assign the bits as in the top branch is one, bottom branch is zero.
So they assign one zero, one zero, one zero here.
Okay, so if you want to assign zero one, zero one, zero one, actually it's also okay.
But for this particular course, let's try to stick to the convention that this book introduced.
So that in the event if I ask a question during the quiz or exam, I don't have to check all the possible version.
So we stick to this particular convention here, one zero, one zero, one zero.
Okay, so now we have more or less finished this part already.
Okay, and then next is we just try to transfer this symbol, the symbol, right, just before it's being merged.
Just for it, make it easier for us to do the tracking. So A, before it's being merged here, it's here.
And B, you can continue to write here before it's being merged, it's here. And C, and V are here.
Okay, so we have done this already. The next thing is that we need to build a Huffman code tree here.
So for this Huffman code tree, we start on top. On top is actually four plus four is eight.
Just now there's no need. If you want, we can add them up further to become eight.
But it's actually not really necessary.
So anyway, we start with the root node of eight, which is four plus four, eight.
Right, okay, for this Huffman code tree branching, okay, the left branch we assign a bit of zero,
and the right branch we assign a bit of one. So it's zero and one here.
So you can see this zero here corresponds to this value four, and then this one here corresponds to this branching on one, which is A4.
So we just write it down. Okay. And afterwards, we look at this particular four value again.
Left branch is zero, right branch is one. Okay, so now this zero corresponds to this two.
We write it down. This one here corresponds to this point, which is B2. So we write it down.
Okay, and then finally, from this two, left branch is zero, right branch is one.
So left branch is D1, okay, one is C1. So we'll be able to write down this particular Huffman code tree already.
So the last step that we need to do is that we need to write down all the code works already.
So if you want to write down the code work, for example, A, right, for the code work A,
we just start off from the root node and trace it until this leaf node here.
The number of bits that it travels through and you collect along the way is your Huffman code work.
So in other words, if you want to write down the Huffman code work for this number A,
we start from the root node, which is eight, okay, and then we traverse to this leaf node A, right,
the number of bits that you collect along the way is one. So therefore, the Huffman code work for A is one.
Okay, let's just take one more example. Suppose if you want to find what's the Huffman code work for this symbol D, right?
So we start from this root node, okay, we want to traverse to this leaf node, so you traverse through this path here.
So along the way, the number of bits that you collect is zero, zero, zero.
So therefore, for this symbol D, right, okay, the Huffman code work is zero, zero, zero.
So this is one way for us to generate the Huffman code work set, a very systematic way of doing it.
Okay, and also just now when we look at this particular Huffman code tree here, you can see the root on top,
we call it the root node, okay, the branch that, no, the node that has the branching, we call it the branch node, okay.
The node at the bottom, there's no further branching, we call it the leaf node, okay,
so that's the definitions of root node, branch node and leaf node.
Okay, so we are going through one simple example of showing how we can create a Huffman code set for this particular example.
So let's go through a bit more explanation. So this explanation here, just now I already covered earlier.
So a Huffman code tree is a binary tree with branches assigned a value of zero and one, okay.
It has a tree structure, so the root node is on top, okay, the root of the tree.
The branch node are the nodes that you have the branching, okay, and the leaf node is the termination nodes of the tree, right.
So as seen, this is the root node, these are the branch node and at the bottom, these are the leaf node.
Right, so at each branch node, zero and one are assigned to the left and the right branch accordingly, like what we have seen, okay.
Zero and one, zero and one, zero and one.
Okay, the code word used for each character or symbol is determined by tracing the path from the root node to the leaf node.
So the path from the leaf node as you trace traversed from the root node to the leaf node and the number of bits you collect along the way is actually your Huffman code.
Right, okay, so that's all is actually a very simple kind of example that we have gone through.
So next, in order to make sure that you fully understand what's the best way, yeah, the best way is for you to do an exercise, right.
So actually there are two exercises, okay, and it turned out that later on I find that exercise two is probably a bit easier than exercise one.
So therefore we'll probably swap the order a little bit.
Let's try to solve this exercise two first, right, and then afterwards we'll come back to exercise one.
So let's look at this exercise two.
But it states that in the compression scheme, a data source consists of eight symbols with the following probability distribution is given in table one here.
So in this data source, you have eight symbols, S0 to S1, and these are the probability of occurrences here.
So in part one, it asks you to design a set of Huffman code work set for these eight symbols and clearly show all the steps and calculations involved.
Right, okay, so yeah, I'll give you a bit of time, right, to try out and then we'll try to go through the answer together.
So I know that the earlier example is a bit simpler because it only involved four symbols and this one is eight symbols.
But you should be using the same principle to solve it.
So I'll give you a bit of time to think about it, yeah, and then we'll go through the answers together.
What you're looking
Okay, yeah, before you continue, perhaps allow me to play a very short video clip and then perhaps you can tell me what this thing is.
Okay, there's a voice coming out.
Right, do you know, any one of you know what you're watching here?
Yeah, it's actually the neuron growing the connections between two neurons.
So yeah, I just happened to attend one of the parent-teacher kind of meeting for one of my kids in secondary school.
So they actually explained to us that if you want your kids to learn effectively, you need to provide opportunity for them to think.
So if you attend any lecture and then if you just listen, usually you'll probably only retain about 30% of the material.
So 100% come in, you keep 30%, 70% of the material will go out.
So therefore we need different way to retain this knowledge.
So how you retain this knowledge, right, it can be, for example, by solving some problem like what we are trying to do now, or even writing some books or drawing some pictures when you do the revision.
All those activities will help you to strengthen these connections of the sameness, right, to improve your learning effectiveness.
Okay, I can see many of you are very eager to solve the problem, so I'll let you continue.
Okay.
So at least you have some time to get your brain start working and thinking about it.
So let's try to go through the key steps that we should do in order to solve the problem.
So based on the steps that I've described earlier on in the previous example, what's the first thing that you have to do?
What's the first thing that you have to do?
Anyone?
Yeah.
Okay, we should try to rank all these symbols in the decreasing probability of occurrence and then go through the steps of taking the two lowest probability, try to add them up, and then for the next column, try to rearrange the probability.
Okay, and after we take the last two probability, add them up, and then try to reorder in the next column.
So you do that repeatedly doing that.
Okay, so that's a step one.
And afterwards, what's step two?
Step two is you assign the bits on that structure, right?
So the top branch is one, bottom branch is zero.
So one, zero, one, zero, one, zero, one, zero.
So you do the branching.
Okay, and then afterwards, what's the step three?
You construct the Huffman code tree.
So you build the Huffman code tree, right, just following the structure.
You build the Huffman code tree.
And then finally, if you want to determine all the code words, you just trace from the root node all the way to the corresponding leaf node for the symbol.
And the number of bits you collect along the way will be your Huffman code tree, I mean the Huffman code word.
So that's the basic high-level ideas of how we can solve this particular problem using the approach that we have just introduced.
So let me try to go through the...
Okay.
All right.
Okay, so this particular solution file, I'm going to upload to the course site afterwards.
After today's lecture, I'll upload to the course site, so there's no need for you to take pictures or copy.
So afterwards, yeah, latest by tomorrow, you can go and download the solution already.
Right, okay, so what we should be paying attention is how do we solve this problem?
So you can see, if you look at this particular set of symbols with their corresponding probability, as we have mentioned, step one, what we need to do is try to write down these symbols in the decreasing order of probability.
In our previous example, it's occurrence.
In this particular example, it's a probability.
So probability is a more common cases.
So if you look at this set of symbols, you can see S7 has the largest probability and S0 is the smallest.
So therefore, we need to write down this symbol in the decreasing order of probability.
Okay, so from 0.26, which is the largest, to 0.02, which is the smallest.
And afterwards, we take those two symbols with the smallest probability.
Okay, for example, 0.05 and 0.02, we add them up.
So we add them up, we'll notice that it's 0.07.
So now, if you compare this 0.07 with respect to all the other probability, you can see it's the smallest.
So therefore, it needs to be ranked at the bottom and the rest of the probability will just simply transfer over.
Okay, so this in your next column.
And afterwards, we repeat the exercise. Let me just do it one more time.
For example, this 0.08 plus 0.07, that is 0.15.
So once this probability is 0.15, okay, when you move it over to the next column, you can see that 0.15 should be between this 0.16 and 0.14.
So therefore, we need to move it up here, right, the rest of the probability we transfer over.
So for the one that's been replaced, you have to move down here.
Okay, right, so this is for the next column.
So we repeat this exercise. Yeah, so let's just do it one more time.
For example, 0.14 plus 0.1 will give you 0.24.
So 0.24 compared with the other probability, this 0.24 now should be here.
Okay, so 0.26 you move over here and then this 0.19 you move it down.
So that again, this is still in the decreasing order of probability.
So you repeat this particular process, all the, okay, since there are still a few more, let me just continue.
So 0.16 plus 0.15 now is 0.31, which is the largest as compared to the others.
So you need to move the top, the rest you just transfer over, shift it down.
Okay, and then 0.24 plus 0.19 is 0.43, right, which is the largest now.
So it's 0.43 here, 0.31 and 0.26 you just transfer over, but need to move down.
Okay, and then finally 0.31 plus 0.26 is 0.57, right, which is larger than 0.43.
So you move it up and this you move it down.
So yeah, so the first step is we just simply do the process that we have just described.
And then step two is that you need to assign bits to this branching now.
So for this article course, the kind of convention will be used is that the top branch is V1, bottom branch will be 0.
So it's 1 0, 1 0, 1 0, 1 0, 1 0, 1 0 and 1 0.
Okay, so that's step two.
And step three, in order to make it easier for you to trace, right, where the original symbol is,
it's always a good practice that you try to trace this symbol, for example this S7, before it's being merged,
okay, before it's being combined here.
So we just write down S7 here.
So this is combined, before it's combined, this is S7.
Okay, so we do the same as well, S6, we follow the path, just before it's being combined is here.
So we write down this S6 here.
So we repeat that for all the other symbols here.
Then you'll be able to write down the instance of all this symbol before it's being combined.
So this is to make it easier for you to track, okay, all this symbol.
So now we have finished this particular, you know, this step already.
And the next thing that we need to do now is that we need to build a Huffman-Coco tree.
So the Huffman-Coco tree, you start off with a probability of 1, okay.
And the left branch, as we have mentioned in the previous description, left branch is 0, right branch is 1.
So these zeros here correspond to this here, 0.43.
So we just write down 0.43.
And this 1 here corresponding to this branching of 1, okay, is 0.57.
Sorry, the resolution is a little bit low, but you can probably still make it up.
It's 0.57. So we write down 0.57 here.
So you have done the first branching.
So the second branching is actually coming from 0.57.
So therefore the second branching is from 0.57.
Left branch is 0, right branch is 1.
So the left branch of 0 corresponds to this branch here.
So it's 0.26S7. So you just write down 0.26S7.
And the right branch here is actually 0.31, okay, a bit of 1.
Okay, so 0.31 here.
Okay, so let's just do it one more time and then the rest you should be quite clear already.
So the next branching is actually 0.43, so which is coming from here.
Left branch is 0, right branch is 1.
So this branch of 0 here, okay, corresponds to this 0.19S6 here.
So it's 0.19S6.
Okay, the branch of 1 here corresponds to 0.24.
So you just write down 0.24.
So if you repeat the whole process, you will be able to build up your, sorry,
you will be able to build up your Huffman, you will be able to build up your Huffman code work set here.
Okay, and then next, right, finally, you will be able to build up this Huffman code tree here.
And then finally, if you want to write down the Huffman code work for each of the symbols,
for example, if we talk about S0, S0 is here.
So as we traverse from the root node through the leaf node, so you can see, right, it's through this branch here.
The bits that you collect along the way is 1, 1, 0, 0, 0.
So therefore this symbol S0 is 1, 1, 0, 0, 0.
Okay, and then let's take one more example.
Suppose S6, if you write down the Huffman code work for S6, you start from the root node, you traverse to the leaf node.
The bits you collect along the way is 0, 0.
So S6 here, the Huffman code work is 0, 0.
So therefore by repeating this process, you will be able to write down the Huffman code work set for this particular data distribution.
So that is actually the answer to part one.
So next let's continue to part two now.
So by the way, this is actually one of the past year exam questions.
So I also mentioned in last week's lecture that I'll try to put in some past year exam questions so that in the class we can go through some of the questions and answers together.
So you also have some idea about what kind of question will come out in the exam.
Also for those discussion questions, you have some idea how to respond to those questions.
Okay, so let's continue.
So for part two now, it says that a student originally used eight bits to represent each symbol in an uncompressed scheme.
So you're asked to find the compression ratio of the Huffman coding scheme developed in your part one, when compared with the original uncompressed scheme.
So in other words, you're asked to find what is the compression ratio for the Huffman code work set that you have just designed in part one.
Okay, I'll give you a bit of time to think about it and then we'll go through the answers together.
Right, so yeah, for those of you who have not obtained the answer for part one, I'll leave it here because you will need it to solve your part two.
Okay.
Okay, so again, you probably have some time to think about it already.
So, okay, any suggestion?
How do you find the compression ratio for this particular part two?
Any suggestion?
So if you remember, just now in the earlier part of the lecture, we said that compression ratio is defined as the data storage requirement for an uncompressed data over the data storage requirement for compressed data.
So in this case here, we want to look at a typical, on average, if you are talking about a symbol or a letter, on average, how many bits is required to represent a symbol?
Right, if it's uncompressed scheme, uncompressed or the original scheme, how many bits do you need to represent a symbol?
According to the question is?
8 bits, right?
So therefore, the storage requirement to represent for the uncompressed scheme is actually 8 bits per symbol.
Okay, now the next question is that what is the average number of bits that is required to represent a symbol for this compressed scheme?
In other words, for this Huffman code work set that you have designed just now, what is the average number of bits that is required to represent a symbol?
So we have just now designed our Huffman code work set already.
What is the average number of bits that is required to represent this symbol using this Huffman code work set?
How do we do that?
Okay, so but the approach is that you need to find the expected number of bits per symbol, right?
So which would then be, how do you find the expected number of bits required to represent the symbol?
Is the probability multiplied with the number of bits, right, for the particular symbol, the probability of the symbol multiplied with the number of bits required to represent the symbol, and you sum up over all the symbols.
So in other words, if you look at it, okay, for this S2, the probability that you occur is 0.02.
And how many bits is required to represent this S0? For S0, the probability is actually 0.02.
So how many bits is required to represent this S0 based on what we have designed?
It's actually 5 bits.
So therefore, the probability now is actually 0.02 multiplied with these 5 bits, yeah, plus, okay, what is the probability, if you choose any symbol, what is the probability that it will be S1?
It will be 0.05. And if it's S1, what is the number of bits that is required to represent it?
It's actually 5 bits, huh?
Okay, so, and then if you choose a symbol randomly, what is the probability that it will be S2 ASB?
It's actually 0.08. And with 0.08, how many bits is required to represent it?
It's actually 4 bits, huh?
So therefore, you can see pretty much it's like this. You ask the question, if you choose a symbol randomly, what is the probability that it will belong to each of these particular symbols?
Okay, and then you need to multiply with the corresponding number of bits to represent the symbol and then add them up.
That's pretty much the answer.
Okay, so therefore, let's try to go through this part two.
So part two, you can see, first we need to calculate the average number of bits that is used to represent the symbol.
So as I mentioned, to do this calculation, we ask ourselves, if we choose a symbol randomly, what is the chances it will be a symbol S0?
Okay, so the probability is 0.02. And if it's S0, the number of bits that is required to represent it is 5 bits.
Okay, and afterwards, if you choose a symbol randomly, what is the chances it will be S1?
So it's actually 0.05. And if it's S1, then the number of bits that is required to represent it is 5 bits.
Okay, and then, yeah, and then so on and so forth.
Let me just do one more. If you choose a symbol randomly, what are the chances it will belong to S2?
So it's 0.08. So if it's 0.08, how many bits is required to represent it? It's 4 bits, so you multiply by 4.
So you continue for all the symbols, and afterwards, at the end, you'll see that it's 2.77 bits per symbol.
So on average, that means on average, you require 2.77 bits to represent a symbol.
Okay, so now, as explained earlier on, from this question, it still tells you that for uncompressed scheme,
you will be using 8 bits to represent a symbol. Now, if you use our Huffman code work set that we've designed,
the number of bits to represent, I don't know why, is 2.77 bits per symbol.
So therefore, the compression ratio is a storage requirement for uncompressed data over the compressed data.
So if you do some calculation, you'll see that it's 2.888. So this is the compression ratio for this scheme.
That means you're actually almost able to achieve a compression ratio of every 2.88 bits, you can compress it into 1 bit, yeah?
Okay, which is pretty good. So next, let's look at the last question.
So last question, it asks you to find the entropy of this data source,
and briefly discuss whether it's possible to design a Huffman code work set which can achieve a target of less than 2.5 bits per symbol.
Okay, right, so we have just learned about the entropy for a data set. Let's try to calculate using the formula.
You can do a bit of calculation, and afterwards, based on your result, try to answer the question,
can we ever achieve a target of less than 2.5 bits per symbol?
Again, I'll give you a bit of time to think about it, and we'll go through the answers together.
Okay.
Okay, so yeah, at least you have some time to think about it.
Any suggestion? How do we find the entropy of this data source?
Just apply a formula that we have learned earlier on, right?
Okay, so I think that part should be quite straightforward. Okay, so let's go ahead and do it.
Right, okay, so therefore the answer to that part is that we just applied this formula that we have mentioned earlier on.
So the probability Pi, log Pi with a base of 2, you sum up over all the possible symbols in this data set,
and you put a negative sign in front.
Okay, so therefore for this particular question, you can see the first term is actually 0.02.
So 0.02, log 0.02 to the base of 2, right, add up, second term is 0.05, log 0.05, and then you repeat for all the symbols.
Okay, you add all of them up, and finally you put a negative sign in front of it.
So if you're not so familiar with using the calculator to do it, yeah, probably it's a good time for you to familiarize yourself how to do some logarithm with base 2.
Or you can actually also use some simple mathematics to convert it into base 10 as well.
So anyway, either way, just do the calculation, you see that it's 2.733 bits per symbol.
So then with that particular answer, now we need to answer the last question, which is,
discuss whether it's possible to design a half-moon cobalt set that can achieve the target of less than 2.5 bits per symbol.
So is it possible to do that?
Is it possible?
No, huh?
So earlier on, if you remember what we discussed, right, so entropy actually is the smallest value that you need, right, in order to,
the smallest number of bits that you need to represent a symbol, right, so theoretically it's a theoretical lower bound, you cannot go anything below it.
You can use more bits to represent each symbol, but you cannot use less bit than this entropy.
So since entropy is already 2.73, you cannot get any value less than that, okay.
So therefore, the answer to that part is that as the target of 2.5 bits per symbol is less than the entropy,
it's not possible to design a half-moon cobalt set that can meet this target, right.
So that's the answer to this question.
So as I mentioned, the answer to this question, I will upload to the course site and then I'll release it by tomorrow.
So tomorrow on works, you can go and download it, okay.
So that's the answer to question one.
So let's move on to question two.
Right, okay, so today we start out with two pretty lengthy exercises, right, so let's try to do it,
because sometimes it's easier for you to learn through exercise rather than just reading.
So let's look at these questions here.
It says that in a compression scheme, eight symbols are used to represent different patterns in the information source, right.
The symbols are encoded using this particular code, codebook A.
So codebook A and the probability of occurrence is given in this table, whereas m and n are positive real value.
So you have this particular set that consists of eight symbols, s0 to s7, right.
So these are probability of occurrence, okay, m and n, we do not know their value yet, okay.
And we also have a particular codebook A.
So someone has come up with this particular codebook A, and this is the codebook A here, right.
So now let's look at the first question.
So the first question is that in the first scenario, if the average number of bits per symbol for the compression scheme
need to be less than 2.86, right, find the required condition for this value m and n, right.
So I think the question is quite straightforward, okay.
You have this particular, this set has eight symbols.
These are the probability of occurrence, and m and n are known, right.
This is, someone has already designed this codebook set here, right, we call it codebook A, right.
And you are told that for this codebook A, right, the number of, if the average number of bits per symbol
need to be less than this value, what should be the condition that this m and n need to satisfy?
Right, okay, so again, I'll give you a bit of time to think about it, and then we'll go through the answers together.
Okay.
Yeah, again, I hope that you have some time to think about this question.
Right, okay, so yeah, in order to find out the condition, so what do we need to do?
So we need to establish some inequality, right.
So first of all, how do we find out an expression, right, for the average number of bits that's required to represent a symbol for this scheme here?
How do you find out the average number of bits that's required to represent a symbol in terms of m and n here?
What do we have to do?
We take m multiplied, okay, so again, we use the same argument like the previous question.
If you choose a symbol randomly, what is the chances it will be s0?
It will be m, right?
m is m, how many bits do you require to represent?
Two bits, so it's m times 2.
Plus, if you choose a symbol randomly, what's the chances it's s1?
It's n, huh?
If it's n, how many bits do you require to represent it?
Three bits, so it's three times n, right?
Okay, and what is the, choose a symbol randomly, what's the chances it will be s2?
It will be 0.15, m is 0.15, for s2, how many bits do you require to represent it?
It's three bits, so you just actually do that, right?
You just take a probability, multiply with the number of bits, and you sum up over all the possible combination,
but that is the average number of bits that is required to represent a symbol.
Okay, so, and you know that the average number of bits that is required to represent a symbol
need to be less than 2.86, so therefore, you will have your first inequality.
Actually, I don't want to show so quickly.
Yeah, so you can see, right, m times 2 bits plus n times 3 bits plus 0.5 times 3 bits and so on and so forth,
you add up over all of them.
If you have done that at the end, okay, it will be this particular expression.
It will be this particular expression.
And we know that this is an average number of bits for a symbol,
and from the question you are told that this number needs to be less than 2.86,
so this number needs to be less than 2.86, right?
If you do some simplification, you can see then 2m plus 3m needs to be less than 1.41.
So that is the first inequality.
So are there any other conditions that you can impose for this question, for m and n?
Any other condition?
Yeah, so the sum of all the probability must be equal to 1, right?
So therefore, what it means is that if you sum up all this probability, it should be equal to 1.
Then afterwards, you can obtain your second condition.
So with that in mind, knowing that sum of probability should be equal to 1, okay?
So we just add up all this probability here.
You can see it's equal to 1. We simplify a little bit.
We see that m plus n is 0.54, or you can write n is equal to 0.54 minus n.
So you have one inequality and one equality.
So afterwards, you substitute this 2 into 1.
I think most of you should be familiar with this.
So if you simplify a little bit, you can see that you can derive the condition m needs to be greater than 0.21.
And then likewise, if you simplify a little bit further, you put this condition into, put this thing into here,
simplify a little bit, you'll be able to see n will be between 0 and 0.33.
So this is how you can find the condition that m and n need to satisfy for this question.
So let's continue.
So next it says that in the second scenario, in the second case now, if the value of m is 0.3, n is 0.24,
discuss the effectiveness of code work A in encoding the symbol to achieve compression.
And then afterwards, they ask you to compare code work A and Huffman coding and discuss whether code work A is optimal
in terms of performing the compression.
So let's look at the first part first.
They say if the value m is 0.3, n is 0.24, discuss whether code work A is effective in performing the compression.
And if you have a quick look, if m is 0.3, this is 0.24, and this code work A is, this is the pattern here.
So based on the principles of entropy encoding, does it seems reasonable?
So if this is 0.3, this is 0.2, you can see this is actually in decreasing probability.
And also if you observe the number of bits, right, for those symbols with larger probability, the number of bit is actually less.
Those with the smallest probability, the number of bit is larger.
So therefore, from the principles of entropy encoding or variable length coding, it seems reasonable.
It seems reasonable.
It's consistent with our understanding of how variable length coding should work.
But now, okay, the next one is they ask you to compare code book A with Huffman coding.
And then afterwards decide whether this code book A is optimal, whether it's the best.
So this will require you to do some calculation.
So I'll give you some time to think about it or to do your calculation.
And then we'll go through this last part together.
So this is Huffman.
Yes.
Can we answer the question a bit later?
Sorry?
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Yes, you see this.
Okay, so any suggestion
on how we can do this part B?
You want to compare this
codebook A and the Huffman coding,
whether this codebook A
is optimal or not, what should we do?
So first of all, we need to...
Sorry?
Yeah, okay, so we need to go through the process
of building the Huffman codebook set
and afterwards, suppose once you have done that,
once you have done that, what should we do?
What should we do?
Calculate the average number of bits per symbol
that's required for Huffman codebook set, right?
And afterwards you compare which one is larger, right?
So if, for example, your Huffman
codebook set can represent the symbol
with a smaller number of bits per symbol,
then that means your codebook A is not optimal already.
So that's pretty much the plan.
So that's what we need to do.
So in order to do that, we need to go through the process.
So this process I will not
go through too much in detail.
But anyway, from the earlier part,
we say that in order to see
whether, for example, codebook A, whether it's reasonable
from the entropy coding perspective,
so we can see that from the probability of occurrence,
larger probability corresponds to shorter codebook.
This is the idea of entropy coding.
So early on, you will see this is point three and this is point two,
just like we mentioned here.
Larger probability is shorter codebook, smaller probability larger codebook.
So therefore, this is actually consistent
with the idea of entropy coding.
So now, however, to check whether this codebook A is optimal,
we need to actually derive this Huffman codebook set.
So we go through this particular motion,
this process that I mentioned to you before.
So we try to rank this particular symbol
in decreasing order of probability.
And then for the two smallest probability, we add them up.
And then we move it to the next column
by rearranging the probability.
So this is point seven, it should be here.
The rest just transfer over.
So we repeat that particular process,
we'll be able to draw these particular structures here.
So that's step one.
Step two is that we assign the bits, top branch is one, bottom branch is zero.
One zero, one zero, one zero. So that's step two.
Step three is that we transfer this particular symbol
just before it's being merged for easy tracking.
So this is zero, this is S1.
So for easy tracking when you want to draw the Huffman code tree.
So suppose we go through this particular process.
Let's continue this one, we can skip for one moment.
So based on this particular structure,
then we can build our Huffman code tree.
So let's assume that you can go home and try it out yourself.
You will see that this is the Huffman code tree
that you'll be able to construct.
And then finally, if you want to find out what is the Huffman code work for each of the symbols,
for example for S0 which is somewhere here,
the code work should be 1, 1.
If you take one example which is S7,
which is here, as you can see from this root node,
is 1, 0, 0, 1, 0.
So S7 is 1, 0, 0, 1, 0 here.
So you'll be able to write down all the code works
that you want to construct.
So you'll be able to write down all the code work
for this particular Huffman coding here.
So once you have built up this particular Huffman code work set here,
you can go through the process that we have mentioned a couple of times already.
We can calculate the average number of bits per symbol for this Huffman code work set.
So if you do that, you can see,
so the probability that it will be this symbol S0 is 0.3,
and it's 2 bits.
If it's the probability it will be S1 is 0.24 from the question,
So if you do that, you do the calculation,
you'll see that it's 2.66 bits per symbol.
This is if you use the Huffman code work set that you just derived.
So on the other hand, if you use just now the code book A,
so this is the code book A,
so the code book A, the number of bits per symbol that we have,
if you choose this particular symbol S0,
it's actually 0.3, and it's 2 bits.
If you choose that the symbol randomly is S1,
the probability is actually 0.24 from the question,
and it's 0.24, and the number of bits that is required is 3 bits.
So if you choose the symbol S2, the probability is 0.15,
and for code book A, it's actually 3 bits.
So therefore, for code book A,
if you calculate the average number of bits per symbol,
if you go through the process and you do the calculation,
you'll see it's 2.77 bits per symbol.
So on the other hand, if you go through the process,
you build your Huffman code work set,
if you do the calculation, you'll see you only require 2.66 bits per symbol.
Therefore, using your Huffman code work set is actually more effective
and more efficient.
So therefore, from that particular perspective,
we can say that this code book A is not optimal in terms of performing the compression,
because at least the Huffman code work set that you've designed
is more effective in terms of compression as compared to code book A.
So therefore, you can see that code book A requires 2.77 bits per symbol,
which is greater than 2.66 bits per symbol by Huffman coding.
So therefore, we can conclude that code book A is actually not optimal.
Even though at first glance it looks like it's actually good,
because it's consistent with your entropy coding principle,
but if you do some closer examination,
if you compare to Huffman coding, which is usually the benchmark,
you can see that your Huffman coding is actually more efficient.
So therefore, your code book A is not the optimal choice.
So this is the answer to this exercise.
So as I mentioned, both exercises I'll upload to the course site after tomorrow,
so you can go and download it.
So we spent quite a fair bit of time going through these two exercises,
and hopefully you have a better understanding about this entropy and coding
and Huffman coding process already.
We'll take a short break.
Now it's 8.02.
So probably let's come back at 8.20.
Ah.
So you're not saying that the probability is not M?
No, no.
There's no need to say that the probability is not M.
Just that I wanted to make it easier for students.
In the exam, I intentionally increased the probability of the answer.
But I don't necessarily say that the probability is not M.
Okay, okay.
That's it.
Could you show me the X is one in first scenario?
One limitation is 2M plus 3M is less than 1.41.
How is the second limitation?
Okay, because this is a probability,
so all the probability add up must be equal to 1.
Okay, I got it.
Thank you.
So this is the first one.
If this is a big or small table,
should we keep a N?
Actually, this question is the same as what the student said earlier.
In fact, it doesn't say that the probability is not M.
Just that the other symbols,
the probability is all 8 to 5.
These two are actually M.
So actually, N can be a big or small table.
This is basically the Hafen rule.
Hafen rule itself is a rule.
These are the processes we analyzed earlier.
In fact, people have already analyzed it.
This is a rule.
So it can't be more than, or more than 1M?
Actually, in the Hafen rule,
it is possible that there is a condition of 0 and 1.
But this question, because of its probability distribution,
the probability distribution causes this Hafen rule,
which is the smallest, the biggest opportunity for the symbol to be a 0.
What I want to say is,
if your question is,
is it possible that there are some symbols in the Hafen rule,
just one 0 or something?
It is possible.
But this question, because of its probability distribution,
the shortest Hafen rule is not a 0 or something.
But this 0 cannot be a 0?
This is a probability distribution.
Because according to its probability distribution,
and the description process,
it is a systemized,
a small, half-or-half rule.
This is a standard rule.
So this is a 1?
The above 1 is a type of 1.
This is the question.
This question is calculated by the length of the smallest average
and the length of the code.
Can it reach 2.5G?
No, it cannot.
This is the second question.
It is the last question.
It is called entropy.
Entropy is the smallest theory.
But in many cases,
you cannot find the lower bound.
So generally, we will not...
If you say you want to force it,
you will know immediately by using entropy.
No, it is not possible.
Because entropy is the smallest of the theories.
So if you want to be smaller than this value,
entropy can tell you.
I know if it can be smaller than this.
But if you want to be higher than entropy,
there are different codes and methods.
The half-code is the smallest.
It is not necessarily the same as entropy.
Sometimes it will be higher than entropy.
But I read in the CSDN,
it can say that this question is 00 and 10.
But I can say that...
Because it is different from the latter,
I can use 0 and 1 to express it.
Because the design of the half-code
is not just about the average number of bits,
or symbol.
That is not the only thing.
So we can consider uniquely decodable.
When you have a bitstream,
it must have no half-code.
It must have only one way to decode it.
If you do not know the process,
when you decode it,
sometimes it will have a half-code.
You have to cut it into different symbols.
It will have a mess.
When I press and hold the button,
it may change.
It will not know where to cut.
If you use half-code,
it has a concept called uniquely decodable.
You have to use this method to cut it into symbols.
So it must be using 00 and 10 to express the difference between 0 and 10.
This is the probability.
If it is not half-code,
or if I use other codes to express it,
it can cut it into shorter symbols.
Half-mode pudding can actually be calculated as the shortest.
You mean it is the shortest.
It is not shorter than it.
I understand. Thank you.
This is the method.
OK.
I want to ask about the official website.
I saw that you have a new project.
But a student said that she is not doing it.
She wants to change to another project.
So you have one?
I see that there is a problem with the system.
There is one now.
It is because a student has launched it.
I will show you the link later.
You can show me.
I have an account.
OK.
I want to ask about this.
It should not be three people to express this.
It is two people.
It means that N is smaller than M.
But I saw that you wrote N is smaller than 0.33.
It is bigger than 0.
It should not be smaller than 0.27.
It should be smaller than half of this.
OK.
Because this A is not the ideal code.
It is designed by someone.
It is the ideal code.
So this is only for the Pokemon code.
Only higher code will be smaller.
Yes.
The other idea is that the code A is designed by someone.
So it does not follow the code.
This is the code that is designed by someone.
Thank you.
I want to ask if you can wear a calculator when you take the exam?
What calculator?
When you take the exam.
What should I wear?
Calculator.
I just draw this when I take the exam.
Or I have to draw this?
Generally, it is better to draw all the steps.
Because it is like this.
Because it is like this when we change.
We change it like this.
Because we have to change the words in a short time.
So we usually look at the answer.
If the answer is the same as the words,
we will not understand it.
Because it is not possible to say that the process is wrong and the answer is wrong.
So if the answer is wrong, we look at the artist and give the artist a point.
The problem is that if the answer is wrong,
I will look back when the answer is wrong.
If I find that there is no step,
you just write this to me.
Then I will get a point.
Understand?
Our code is calculated from the smallest probability.
I saw that there was a probability on the Internet.
I think it is a big and small number.
In fact, the code is fixed.
Some people have different methods.
We use different methods.
Although I started to talk about how to generate this code.
Some people use a slightly different method.
We use a standard method.
The most common one.
Because it is a most common method.
So if you want to simplify it,
there are several methods that you can find.
Although it may not be the fastest,
it is the most standard.
I think we should follow this method.
I suggest you use this method.
Because the time difference is not too big.
So it is 4 plus 4.
That is why it is big here.
But most of the questions are given in the following.
Therefore, the examples given in the exercises are the more common ones.
This is just an example.
This example is by occurrence.
But most of the time it is given in the following.
Then we will talk about the step.
This is the step.
If I draw the numbers and know that they are related,
then in this case, I need to consider the size of M0.15.
Or this situation will not appear?
If I understand your question,
you mean if the
If the
The question just now
is not the one that provides the number 1111.
The reason is that
if I cross a number of steps,
I will get the number of steps.
Do you know that question?
Generally speaking,
we can do it in one direction.
I know.
I don't think it will appear in the question.
Generally speaking,
it will not appear.
I heard that student said
that it is reasonable.
I am sorry.
Okay.
Welcome back.
Let's continue on with the
image or video compression basics.
Why do we want to perform
image or video compression?
Earlier on, I already mentioned
for media types such as
image and video,
the data storage requirement is very large.
If you do not compress it,
then it is very hard for us
to either store or transmit it.
That is the key motivation.
Why do we want to do that?
Why do we want to perform the compression?
You can see that
image and video compression is necessary
for two reasons.
One is to reduce the storage requirement.
The other is that if you want to
transmit over the network,
then you can reduce the bitrate
or the bandwidth requirement.
The next question is that
we know that there is a motivation
why we need to perform the compression.
But what is so special
about this media type
that allows us to perform the compression?
The next question is
why is it possible to perform the compression?
The reason why
for image and video
it is possible for us to compress it
is because it contains some redundancy.
What is the meaning of
this word redundancy?
This word redundancy
means that it is the extra
unnecessary information
that is captured in the
image and video domain.
There are two types of redundancy
in terms of image and video.
The first one is known as
the statistical redundancy.
It is the extra unnecessary
information from the
statistical viewpoint.
The first type is the spatial redundancy.
This word spatial,
what is the word spatial?
Spatial means it is a space-based redundancy.
Space-based redundancy
means that it is a redundancy
that exists in an image.
Anyway, this slide will just give
a quick overview.
Afterwards, for the next few slides, we are going to
explain a little bit more
in detail. Therefore,
spatial redundancy refers to
the redundancy that exists in a
single image or single
frame.
The next word is the temporal redundancy.
Temporal come from
the base term time.
It is a time-based redundancy.
When you think about time-based redundancy,
what comes to your mind right away are
things like audio or
video. For video,
it is nothing but a sequence of frames.
Across
two different frames, usually because
for the motion to appear to be
smooth, each frame must be
very similar to the next frame.
What it means is that the movement
of, for example, an object in one
frame and the next frame, they are very
similar. If these two
frames are very similar, that means there are lots of
extra,
they are very similar, that means there are lots of
extra unnecessary information
that exists across a frame.
And across a frame, because
this frame is in the
time axis, so that's why
it's also known as a temporal
redundancy. So,
this is the redundancy that exists in
the video. Okay, the next
one is the coding redundancy.
Coding redundancy is the extra
unnecessary information that exists
in terms of how you
represent the information. Like, for
example, early on we compare
uncompressed versus
Huffman coding. So, it's the types of
coding redundancy.
If you don't perform things like Huffman
coding. So, the next types
of redundancy that we have is called
psychovisual redundancy.
So, psychovisual is how
human visual system perceives
an object. Okay? So, specifically,
there are two types. One is the frequency masking.
So, frequency masking
actually means that, you know, how our
eye perceives to different frequency
components. So, our eyes
are more sensitive to
any changes or noise
in smooth regions. Okay?
And it's, you know, less sensitive
to any distortion in the
texture region. So, one very
simple example is, you know,
if you look at, for example, the shirt I'm
wearing here is quite
smooth. So, you can see there's this
patch here. So, this is
when, this patch here, that means
actually it's low frequency region.
So, if there's particular spots
here, most of you will be able
to spot it quite readily.
So, this is because our eyes are more
sensitive to any noise or
distortion in low frequency
region. Okay? Anyway, later
on we'll explain a little bit more.
This color masking is actually
based on what we discussed last time.
Our eyes are more sensitive to the
brightness or the luminance component
and less sensitive to
the color or the
chrominance component. So, we can also
use that to help us to perform
image and video compression.
So, because there are lots of
redundancy across this
statistical and psycho-visual
redundancy, that's why it allows us to
perform decompression.
Right, okay. So, next
we are going to explain a little bit more
about each of these
redundancy a bit more in detail.
So, the first one is a spatial redundancy.
So, spatial redundancy
refers to the statistical correlation.
So, correlation means
similarity or relatedness
between
pixels within an image
or more specifically, within a small
image neighborhood
here. So,
spatial redundancy, pretty much the high-level
concept is like this. So, if you
look at the image, okay, and specifically
if you look at a small
kind of image
region, the pixel values
tends to be quite similar
to each other. For most
natural image, right, we are
talking about most natural image,
if you look at a small pixel
neighborhood or image neighborhood,
the pixel values tends to be
very similar to each other.
So, if the pixel values tends to be
very similar to each other,
that means there is lots of extra
unnecessary information
that exists in a small
image region. Because
instead of representing each pixel
in this small image region,
you actually just need
to have one single pixel, it can
more or less represent this region already.
So, if
you are using every single pixel
to represent this image region,
that means you exist lots
of redundant information
already. So, this kind of redundancy
is known as the
spatial redundancy.
So, for example, if you
look at this image here, if you
look at a small image region, for example
here, you can see within this small
image region or patch,
the pixel values are very similar to
each other. So, if the pixel values
are very similar to each other,
that means there is lots of redundant information
there. But there is no need actually
for you to represent each
pixel.
So, this type of redundancy
is also known as the intra-frame redundancy.
Intra means
routine. So, it's the redundancy
that exists
within one single frame.
So, therefore, spatial
redundancy is actually
also known as the intra-frame redundancy.
Redundancy that exists across
a single image or frame.
So, the
next one is the temporal redundancy.
So, temporal redundancy, as I mentioned,
I actually explained to you earlier.
So, let's look at the definition.
So, temporal redundancy refers to the
statistical correlation.
So, this word correlation means
similarity or relatedness.
Between pixels from successive
frames in a video sequence.
So, if you look at this particular example
here, this is different frames in
a video, just as we mentioned.
In a video,
if you have many different frames, and for
this particular video to appear to be
smooth, each of the frames are
very similar to each other.
So, if you, for example, look at a small
image
regions here,
you can see this current
frame and the
next frame, they'll be very similar.
So, if these regions are very similar,
that means there are lots of
extra unnecessary
information, or what we call redundancy.
So, this kind of redundancy
exists across
the frame axis or the time axis.
So, that's why it's called
temporal redundancy.
So, temporal redundancy is also
known as inter-frame redundancy.
So, you can guess more or less why that's
the case, because it's the redundant
information that exists across
different frames, specifically
for video.
Right, so, next one is
the coding redundancy.
So, coding redundancy actually is
how you represent the
information, just like in our
previous part when we talked about entropy
coding. You can already
see just by analyzing
the data a little bit more
carefully, and then try to
assign shorter
code work to more probable
symbol and longer code work to less
probable symbol, you can already
reduce the number of bits
to represent the symbol. So,
this is a type of coding
redundancy. So, that means if you don't
exploit those properties, then there's
lots of redundant information
in your, like, fixed length
representation already.
Okay, so coding redundancy
focus on representation of the information
or the code itself. Right, so
the easiest way to understand this
is through an example.
So, you look at this example here. Suppose we have
five symbols, A1 to A5,
and this is the probability of occurrence.
So, now, based on what you
have studied in the previous part, you can see
there's a few different ways you can represent
these
symbols using the bit patterns.
So, one simple way, if you use a very
naive way, which is
uniform length coding
or fixed length coding,
because you have five symbols,
so you can actually use three bits
to represent. So, if you decided
to use three bits to represent each
symbol, okay, for example, you use
this bit pattern
to represent this symbol. So, you can see
in this case, the average
number of bits that's required to represent
a symbol is actually three bits.
But, on the other hand, if
you're a little bit more clever, especially after
you have studied the
first part of the lecture, you know that
for those
symbols that has a higher probability,
we should assign a shorter
code. Those with a lower probability,
we should assign a longer
code. Just by being a little bit more
clever about it, using
this variable length coding,
if you try to calculate
the average number of bits per
symbol, so like what
we mentioned just now, probability multiplied
with the number of bits, in this case it's four
bits,
probability of 0.2 multiplied with
two bits, by repeating the process
that we have explained earlier,
we can see we can obtain 1.95.
So, in other words, what it means
is that just if you are a bit more
clever, if you can come up with some
more intelligent
way of designing your code,
actually you can
achieve better
efficiency or representation.
So, that means in terms of code itself,
there's some kind of redundancy.
If you don't do anything, there's some redundancy
inside that you can exploit
to remove it.
So, the next one that
we mentioned is a psychovisual redundancy.
So, the first one is
frequency masking. So, earlier on,
I mentioned that human
is less sensitive to noise or distortion
in the high frequency component.
So, this frequency masking
is like this.
So, I believe most of you have
studied time-based signals.
So, for time-based signals,
for example, if you are measuring the
temperature in this room, the
horizontal axis is the time,
vertical axis is the temperature.
So, then you have the signal,
time-based signal, which looks like that.
So, we know that for time-based
signal, when you say
for a time-based signal, it has high
frequency component.
What does that mean? If you have
a time-based signal, for example,
temperature in this room,
and you say that
this time-based signal or temperature
in this room has high frequency
component, what does that mean?
It means that your signal is
fluctuating very quickly.
High frequency means that it's changing
very quickly. So, that's the interpretation
in the time domain,
which is a 1D signal.
But, if you are talking about image domain,
so for image domain, what we
have is that, for example,
this image here,
we have the x-y coordinate
system,
x and y coordinate system.
And then afterwards, from last lecture,
we know we have different pixels.
If you look at each of the RGB
channel value,
it can be interpreted as a
z-value, the
z-axis value. So, therefore,
for an image like this,
this is the x and y
coordinate system, and each
of the RGB channel can be
interpreted as the z-value,
or like the mountain and valley,
the landscape. So, therefore,
for an image like this,
you can interpret it like,
you have a landscape,
you have mountains and valleys.
So, if these particular mountains
and valleys change very quickly,
then we say that this image
has high frequency component.
And if,
for example, in this particular image,
these regions here,
you can see the pixel value change
very slowly. So, this is the
x and y coordinate. If the
pixel value change very slowly,
then we say it has low frequency component.
But if the pixel value
change very quickly, we can say
that it has high frequency component.
So, this is the interpretation for
image and video, when we are
talking about a high or
low frequency content. So,
therefore, if we take this particular
image here, you can see that this image mainly
has low frequency content,
because the pixel values change very
slowly. Okay? In a small region,
the pixel value changes slowly.
But this particular image, we
can say that it has high frequency component,
because in a lot of these
small regions, the pixel value
change very quickly. So, this is
the high-frequency- this image has lots of
high frequency component. This
image has lots of low-frequency
component. Okay?
So, now we know how to interpret
the meaning of low frequency
and high frequency component. Next,
we look at just now the example
that we mentioned. Right, okay.
So, again, we take the example of
the clothes I'm wearing today. Right?
So, this particular- the clothes
I'm wearing today mainly has
lots of low-frequency component,
because you can see lots of regions
changing very slowly. So,
our eyes are very sensitive to any
noise or distortion,
or changes in low-frequency region.
So, what I'm trying to say is, imagine
if just now dinner time, I eat some
noodle, and then there's a spot here,
right, most of you will be able to
identify quite quickly. Right? Because
if this is a low-frequency region,
if there's any noise or distortion
in low-frequency region, our eyes
can notice it very quickly.
Yeah. So, as opposed to that,
right, for example, if I'm wearing
a shirt, which has
lots of vertical stripe, you know,
if there's a shirt with lots of- or
checkered shirt, you know, checkered shirt,
yeah, and if I have the same spots,
most of you will not be able to notice it,
because our eyes are not so sensitive
to any changes in high-
frequency component. So, that's one example.
So, if you take this example,
we can see this image has
low-frequency component,
so if there's any distortion,
for example, if there's a small bird here,
most of you will be able to spot
it very quickly. As opposed to
this, suppose this is an image
with high-frequency component,
if there's a small bird here, most of you
cannot see it so quickly.
So, this particular thing is known as
the frequency masking. A human
is more sensitive to noise or distortion
in- is less sensitive,
less sensitive to noise and distortion
in high-frequency
component. So, the reverse
means that it's more sensitive
to noise and distortion in low-frequency
component. So, this
property will be exploited
later on when we study about
image and video compression.
So, later on, we'll- when we come to
the necessary place, I'll explain
a little bit more. So, the next
one is that colour masking.
So, human is more sensitive to the
luminance or the brightness
component. Sometimes we also call
it the luma, okay?
Then, the colour or the
chrominance or the chroma component.
So, this point we have actually explained
in last lecture
as well. So, this is also
another property that
we exploit to
perform image and video
compression. So, how do we do that?
So, the first thing is that
for those colour channel,
so if you remember
in previous lecture, we say that
in image and video compression,
very often we represent the image in
Y, C, B, C, R kind of colour model.
And Y is the component,
C, B and C, R is the colour
component. So, because our eyes are
not so sensitive to the C, B and C,
R, the colour component,
we can afford to drop some of the
sample. So, that is the
idea that will be used later on,
as we will see later,
to perform image and video
compression.
Right, okay, so,
I think about
10 years ago, around 10 years
ago, this is a very famous kind of
image.
I'm just wondering whether
any one of you has seen this image before?
Any one of you
has seen this image? That means you are
all very young.
I think it's more than 10
or 15 years ago already.
Right, okay, so this particular
image, what is so interesting about this image
is that different person
will perceive this
image differently. Okay,
so, I just want to
check, okay, how many
of you can see this particular image
as a gold and white
colour? Gold and white.
Can you just raise your hand?
If you see this particular
dress, the colour is
white and gold. Please raise your hand.
Wow, okay, your class, not so many, but
some to see it. Okay,
so, some other people, what
other colour do you see?
Black and?
Black and blue, right? So some of you see
as black and blue.
Can I just have a show of hands?
I just want to see the
statistics roughly. Black,
who of you see black
and blue?
Okay, I think more
than just now the gold and
white. Actually,
for myself, I see it as white
and gold colour. This is gold colour
and this is white colour.
So, okay, so actually this is one of the
images that account
it depends on
human vision system. Therefore, human vision system
is very imprecise. Different people
would perceive it differently.
So, according to some studies,
they say that it depends on
each individual's
types of, you know, how many
rod and cone
perceive different colour.
So, that's why some of you will see
the colour slightly differently.
So, there's no right and wrong, it's just
how human vision system
perceives it.
And then later on, there was someone who actually
take an image. So, because
what happened is that, you know, person who
see as white and yellow,
they do not know what other people are
seeing. And other people see
black and blue,
they also do not know what other people are
seeing. So, this is one image
that try to show
what the other party
see. So, according to what they say,
some people see this colour
white and gold, some people
see this colour more like closer
to blue and
black, but actually I still see
gold and white, but
okay, can some of you who
see
black and blue see this gold and
white here?
Can some of you see?
Okay, or do you see two different
set of colour?
Okay,
so anyway, this is
a very interesting thing. Last year
actually, I asked a student as well,
it turned out that about two-third of them
see them as black and blue,
about one-third see
as yellow and white.
So, obviously I'm the minority
here as well.
Right, okay, so
let's continue.
Right, okay, so the next
things we want to explain is this concept
about lossy and lossless compression.
So, what is the lossy and lossless compression?
So, lossless
compression is like this. So, initially
you have the media, right?
You perform the compression to make it into
a smaller file size, and afterwards
you decompress it
to make it into a bigger file size,
to reconstruct the media.
So, if you're reconstructed,
for example, image, you're
reconstructed data, and your
original data are exactly the
same, then we call it lossless
compression, because no
information has been lost. Okay?
So, therefore that's quite clear. So, that's
lossless compression. So, as opposed to
that, lossy compression means that
you have the media, right, or data,
you compress it to become smaller
file size, afterwards you
try to decompress it to
reconstruct your data. If your
reconstructed data is different
from your original data, then
this is known as a lossy compression,
because some
information has been lost already.
Okay? So, therefore the definition
between lossless and lossy compression
is quite clear. So, in
most of the typical
image and video compression,
do you think most of them
fall under lossy
or lossless compression?
So, now that we understand
what's lossy compression and what's
lossless compression, in most
kind of typical
application, right, do you
think we use lossless compression
more or lossy compression more?
Lot?
Actually, I can't hear
so clearly. It seems that there are
a mix of, some
people say it's lossy, some people say
it's lossless. Right, okay.
So, if
you are a beginner, if you have not studied this
topic before, you will tend to think it's
lossless, right, because lossless is good, no information
is lost. But it turned out that
actually we use lossy
compression more.
So, what's the reason actually we use lossy
compression more?
So, anyone?
What's the reason actually we use a lossy
compression more, in
real life?
So, what's the objective of performing
compression?
What's the objective of performing compression?
You want to
reduce the number of
bits or file size, right?
So, it turned out that lossy compression
is more effective in compressing
the file into a smaller
file size as compared to
lossless compression.
So, the reason why we use lossy compression
more is because, right, your
compressed file size is actually much
smaller as compared to lossless
compression. Even though you
may have a little bit of distortion,
but lots of these changes of distortion
is not so perceptible
by human. That means when human, you
see it, you hardly tell there's
any difference in it.
So, therefore, that's why lossy compression
is actually more commonly used.
So, now let's look at this
lossless compression. So, lossless compression,
as we have already explained,
your reconstructed image
is the same as
your original image after reconstruction
or decompression. So,
we use lossless compression in important
media such as medical images.
Because for
medical images,
sometimes you don't want to
have any changes. Because any
artifacts or any changes,
sometimes the doctor may interpret
it's actually a cancer. So, therefore,
for those cases, your
reconstructed data
and your original data must be
the same. So, that's
for lossless compression.
For lossless compression,
we typically use it in media such as
image and video.
So, the reason why we use it
in image and video is because if you have image and video,
you compress it and afterwards
you reconstruct.
You have this reconstructed or
decompressed media. Even though
your original data
and your reconstructed data are a little
bit different, but from the human
perception,
from the human perception perspective, you can hardly
tell the difference. Just now,
for example, the image that we show,
even the image, different person
will perceive it a little bit differently
already. So, therefore,
for these types of approach,
lossy compression,
even though your reconstructed data
is different from the original data,
but these two data, actually, there are
so little difference that human
cannot tell the difference. So, therefore, it's
okay, even though they are not exactly the
same, but it's okay because we can hardly
tell much difference in it.
But the advantage of this now
is that we can deploy
method to compress it much better
into a smaller file size.
So, for media like image and video,
it's not necessary to display
more information
than what human can see or hear.
So, in these types of cases, actually,
the compression technique will
may discard data
with little perceived difference by human.
That means it will throw away those
information that human can actually
not tell much
difference as compared to the original data.
So, your reconstructed data
is different, not
identical or different from the original
data after decompression.
So, that's the basic idea of lossy compression.
So, there's a few different common
matrix to measure
for this lossy
decompression.
So, first, you have this
X, we call it the original data.
Suppose the original data we call
X, the reconstructed or
decompressed data we call
Y. So, therefore, there's a few
different ways we can measure the
difference between them for lossy
compression. So, the first one is
known as a mean square error.
So, for the mean square error, if you look at the
equation, you try to take the
difference between your original pixel
and
the reconstructed pixel.
And then you square, you sum up over
all the pixel, for example, in an image.
And then you divide by
the total number of pixel in the image.
This is known as a mean square error.
So, obviously,
the smaller this value is,
that means the better your reconstructed
image is.
So, that's the definition of the mean square error.
So, the next one is the signal to
noise ratio. So, the signal
to noise ratio is defined by this equation.
So, this is a signal power.
This is the noise power here.
So, the signal power is defined
by, right, so the
this particular symbol here,
the average square value of your
original data.
So, each of the pixel value,
right, you square and then
you take its average, right, so therefore
it's a signal power.
And then this noise power,
noise power here is actually just now
the error that we have found
earlier on. So, if you take the signal
power, the average
signal power divided by the noise
that we have computed earlier,
then this is actually known as a
signal to noise ratio, or S and R.
So, for a good
reconstructed
compression method,
you want your S and R to be as high
as possible, because you want
your noise to be as small as possible.
If your noise is small, that means
this value will be large.
Right, okay, so the third commonly
used matrix is known as peak signal
to noise ratio. So, the peak signal
to noise ratio, if you look at this
equation and this equation, they are very similar.
The only difference now is that
here, in this signal to noise
ratio, this is the average signal
power. But, for this
peak signal to noise ratio,
this one here, we just take the maximum
value. For example, if you use
8 bits to represent it, then
this value will be 255.
Okay, this X peak here
will be 255, 255 square.
Okay, so, therefore
this particular matrix
is known as peak signal,
the largest value.
Peak signal to noise, noise
is the error. So, peak signal to
noise ratio. So, this is another
common matrix to measure the
distortion between your original
data and your reconstructed
data.
Right, okay, so the next
topic we are going to look at now is a
transform-based coding and compression.
So, transform coding.
So, why do we want to do transform coding?
So, what is this idea of transform
coding? So, the idea of transform
coding is that, right, so you have
for example, original
data, right, so
for example, let's start with the image.
You have some images, right,
you may want to do some transformation
into a
transform domain. So, the
image in its original
form is called in the pixel domain.
Right, so after you
have performed some transform, so
some transform is a mathematical
operation, right, so you have the
image in the pixel domain,
you let it go through some transform
which is a mathematical operation
to get your transform domain
or transform kvc.
And then afterwards you try to perform compression
in this transform domain
using the transform kvc.
So, at high level,
why do you want to do that?
Why do you want to take the data
from the original pixel, right,
domain, or the individual pixel
to transform it into
some transform domain and
then perform compression on this transform
domain? Why do we want to do that?
So, the reason why
we want to do this mathematical
mapping or transformation is
because, right, the data once
is transformed into the transform
domain, it has some good properties
that we can exploit
to perform the compression. At high
level, this is what it is. It has some
good property in the transform domain
that we can use to
perform the compression. So, this is a
high level idea, and later
on we are going to take some example and
see this point a lot
more clearer.
So, therefore, why do you want to do this
transform? The
idea is we want to convert the data
into a form, right, which
is more suitable for compression, that means
into the transform domain.
So, the transformation
may have some good properties. So,
one is called energy compaction,
the other is to offer
redundancy reduction.
So, this energy compaction
at high level, what it means is that
initially you have this particular
image, which is in the pixel domain
or image domain. After
you have done the transformation, you have
it in the transform domain. So, this
energy, right, okay,
the energy will be packed into a small
number of kvc. Right, so, in
your original image or pixel domain,
right, okay, how do we measure
the energy in the
image is that we take
each of the pixel value and we
square. So, each of the
pixel value, if we square,
that will reflect the energy.
So, in the original pixel
domain, okay, right,
because we do not know
each pixel, whether the value
is large or not. So, therefore, in the
original image or pixel domain,
we do not know where the energy
is concentrating.
Because if you think about even a
particular image, for
each of the pixel value, do you know
which pixel value is large
or small in advance? You
do not know, right. So, therefore,
you do not have a good way to know where
the energy is located. But,
if you apply the transform,
once you have the data in the transform
domain, you can see most of the energy
will be concentrated to a small
number of kVc.
So, this is the high level
kind of explanation.
Later on, when we study about DCT,
a lot of this concept will
become a lot more concrete and clear.
So, anyway,
this is the point I was trying to say.
But after the transform, the energy
will be focusing to
a small number of kVc.
So, the second
is that it offers a redundancy
reduction, so which means that
you reduce the correlation between
the transform kVc. So, what it means
at this point is that if you look at the
original image
domain or pixel domain,
if you know this current pixel,
do you think you more or less
know what is the pixel value next to it?
In the original
image domain,
if you know this pixel value,
do you think you more or less know
what is the pixel value next to it?
Yes or no?
In the
image domain, if you know this current
pixel value, do you think more or less
you know the pixel value surrounding it?
Yes or no?
In order to answer this question,
kind of go back to just
a few slides ago, one of
the redundancies that I mentioned to you,
which is specifically spatial redundancy.
What does spatial
redundancy tell you?
If you look at a small
pixel neighbourhood,
the pixel value tends to
be very
similar to each other. For most natural
images, that is the case.
If you look at a very small
pixel neighbourhood, like for example,
4x4 or 8x8, the pixel
values tends to be very similar
to each other most of the time.
So, if the pixel value
tends to be very similar to each other, that means
if you know this current pixel value,
do you think you more or less
can tell what is the pixel value close
to it? Yes, right?
That's what I've been telling you,
the spatial redundancy.
Most images have this kind of redundancy,
which is spatial redundancy.
So, if you, in the image
domain, if you know this current pixel value, that means
you also know the pixel values around
it, okay, from the
compression perspective, this is not
good. Why? Because you
store lots of redundant,
unnecessary information. For example,
if you look at a 4x4 pixel block, if
all the pixel values are very similar to
each other, why do I need to store
all the pixel value?
I just need to roughly store one pixel
value, more or less can represent this block
already. So, therefore,
okay, if you are talking
about image in the original
image domain, it contains
a, right, okay,
knowing this particular
pixel value means you also
more or less can tell the pixel value
surrounding it. So, that means
they actually have strong correlation.
The pixel value,
the current pixel value and its surrounding
pixel value has strong
correlation. When they have strong
correlation, that means there's lots of redundancy.
And when they have
lots of redundancy, this is not good
from the compression
perspective, because you have so much
extra unnecessary information
that you are storing. Okay? So, that's
what it states here.
On the other hand, right, this particular
image in the original pixel
domain, if you transform it
into the transform domain, so in
the transform domain, you have some
transform coefficient.
Right, so just based on what I
explained, do you think that in the transform
domain now, knowing this
pixel value will tell you what is
the, knowing this coefficient
will tell you what is the
coefficient next to it?
Chances are, no.
Okay, in the transform domain now,
in the transform domain, you have lots
of transform coefficient.
So, if you know this transform coefficient,
it doesn't tell you much
the transform coefficient next
to it. So, this is
actually good from the compression perspective.
Why? Because knowing
this particular coefficient doesn't tell you
the coefficient around it. That means you
remove lots of the redundant
information already.
So, from the compression perspective,
that is good. Right, so again,
this is high level. Yeah, later on when
we study DCT, we will give you
a lot more concrete example.
But in short, what it means is that it offers
redundancy reduction.
It reduces the correlation, or the
similarity, okay, between
the transform coefficient, just like what I mentioned.
Now, in the transform domain, knowing this
pixel value doesn't, knowing
this coefficient doesn't tell you the
coefficient surrounding it.
Okay, so which is good from
the compression perspective.
And then for this transform coding,
it's a reversible process.
That means the original
signal can be obtained by applying
the inverse transform. So, if you
have the data in the
image domain, you can perform the
forward transform to get the transform
coefficient. And for this particular
transform coefficient, you can
take the inverse transform to recover
your original pixel.
So therefore, it's actually
a reversible process.
That's what I mean by reversible
process here.
Right, okay, so let's look at some typical
transform-based image compression scheme.
Right, so there's many ways
for you to perform image compression.
So, transform-based image compression
is one of the most popular
way to perform compression.
Right, so techniques such as
standards such as JPEG compression
and MPEG compression is based
on transform-based image compression.
So, what's the typical
pipelines of a transform-based
image compression?
Right, so a typical transform-based image
compression consists of the following steps.
Yes, image partitioning, transform,
quantization and coding.
So, let's look at each of these steps a bit
more in detail. So, first of all,
right, we have an input
image, supposed to be an input image.
The first thing is that we do this
particular partitioning. This image,
we partition it into
numerous sub-images
or pixel blocks.
So, we can partition
to construct end-by-end
sub-image or pixel block.
Right, okay, so and afterwards
for each of this sub-image or pixel block
we'll let it go through a forward
transform. Okay, let me just
repeat. Given the image,
we partition it into numerous
pixel block or sub-image.
For each of this particular pixel block,
we can do the transformation
to transform it into
the transform coefficient.
So, this is what it means
by the forward transform.
So, this
pixel block,
you do the transform, you have the transform
coefficient now. So, this
transform coefficient next, you need to go through
a quantizer here.
So, the objective of this
particular quantizer is because
for our work,
nowadays we are using
a digital representation.
That means we are using computer
and computers are using some
finite number of bits
to represent it. So, right,
when you do this
forward transform, the value
potentially are continuous value.
It's a continuous
value signal.
But we are using computer to represent
this data. So,
when using computer, that means you are using
a finite number of bits.
So, finite number of bits means that you can
only have a finite number of levels
to represent it. Right, so,
therefore, in order to
be able to use only finite number of
levels to represent, we have to perform
quantization. So,
this quantizer is to perform
the quantization, similar to
any, you know, similar
quantizer you have studied before.
So, once you have quantized it,
the output at this
particular junction is you have some symbol.
So, you have some pattern.
So, this pattern, now you have some patterns
here. Some of these patterns will occur
more often than the others.
So, then, in your mind,
right away you think, okay, if that's the case,
then what I'm going to do is I'm going to use
a symbol encoder,
such as a Huffman coding, to
perform decompression. So, therefore,
this is the typical pipeline.
Right, we have image, we partition into
numerous pixel blocks or sub-image.
Each of the blocks we let it go through
a forward transform. We
let it go through a quantizer to quantize
into a finite number of patterns.
Okay, and then we use a symbol decoder,
because some patterns occur more often
than the others. We use some symbol decoder
such as Huffman coding, right,
to convert it into
the bitstream. So, when you see this
compressed image, then it means that now
you have a compressed bitstream already.
So, this is the
encoder. So, encoder
means that you take an image,
right, after you have gone through this
encoder, right, you will have
the compressed bitstream.
Okay, it's much smaller.
Right, so this particular figure now is a
decoder. So, the decoder means
that you have a compressed image
of bitstream, right, after you
go through this decoder, you'll
get your reconstructed
or decompressed image.
So, for this particular process here,
it's the reverse of this.
So, first you have the compressed image of
bitstream, you let it go through the symbol
decoder. So, this is encoder,
this is decoder. Right, and
afterwards, actually there's a missing block here,
right, this textbook
missed out this block. So, this block here,
this is quantizer, this is the de-quantizer.
It's just performing the reverse.
One of them you divide the other,
one of them you divide the other, you multiply.
Okay, this is a
full transform, this is the inverse transform.
You partition it into numerous
blocks, this you put the blocks
together. Right, so that's pretty much
the reverse of it. So,
this full transform, this is the inverse
transform. Okay, so
next let's look at some of the
common transform.
So, okay, so for this common
transform is that we apply a one-to-one
transform to the input data.
So, this transformation is a
one-to-one transformation. Okay,
so why do we want to do the transform? I think we
mentioned it early on.
The reason why we want to perform the transform
is the transform output is in
a representation which is more
suitable for efficient compression
than the raw image data. So,
this point pretty much is what I mentioned.
Yeah, once you have this particular
small image
block, okay,
when you do the transformation,
once it's in this transform domain,
this transform domain, you know,
has some good property that we can exploit
or its representation
is more suitable for compression.
Yeah, okay, so
among all those transform, one of the
most popular transform is the
DCT. Okay,
so DCT is a
unitary mapping.
So, unitary mapping
means that this particular transform
matrix, if you call this
transform matrix T,
then it's T, T-transposed
is equal to T-transposed,
T is equal to identity.
So, anyway, for those of you who study
linear algebra, you
know that this particular
properties of unitary
transformation.
Okay, so DCT is a
type of unitary
mapping. So, later on, when we
study about how do we perform
this DCT will become clear.
So, DCT has a good property
because it can pack the energy
into a small number of kVc.
So, just like what I mentioned
earlier on, so if you look at
a small pixel block, we do not know
where the energy is located.
But after you use a DCT
transform, the energy will be packed
into a small number of kVc.
So, once we can pack into a small number
of kVc, then we can pay our
attention to try to represent
data for this
small number of kVc.
So, there are some
well-known transforms,
which include, for
example, some of the well-known transforms.
It's a DFT,
discrete Fourier Transform,
discrete Cosine Transform, discrete
Wave Flare Transform. So, these are some of the
popular transforms that have been used.
But for JPEG
and MPAC, we will be using
this DCT. That's why we will
study, our key focus will be studying
on this. This
DWT is used in JPEG
2000, right? Actually,
now it's less commonly used.
That's why we will not touch on it. We will
only be focusing on this DCT
transform. And then, based on
this DCT transform, then we will explain
all those properties that we have just mentioned.
So, just now, this slide here is pretty
much explaining about this transform
block. So, the next
block that we have is the quantization.
So, as I mentioned, the objective
of quantization is that you want to generate
a small number of symbols
from the transform coefficient.
Because, alright,
after you have performed this
transform, the output, right, so
for example, the signal
at this particular junction is
4x4 pixel block.
After you have performed the transform,
what you have is a 4x4, for example,
transform coefficients
here. So, this transform
coefficients, their values are
continuous value.
So, therefore, if you want to use
a computer to represent,
we must perform quantization.
So, it's to generate
a finite number of symbols from the
transform coefficient. Because transform
coefficient initially is continuous value.
So, we need to perform quantization.
So, it's irreversible
many-to-one mapping causing information
loss. So, for many of you
who have studied your undergrad before, you
know that once you perform quantization,
information will be lost.
So, information, when information is lost,
that means it's an irreversible process.
So, what it means is that
if you look at this simple scalar
quantization, your horizontal
axis is the input and the vertical axis
is the output. So, suppose
if your input is in this
range here, you can see the input
in this range here will be mapped
to this same output of 0.5.
For this range of input,
okay, this range of input
here will be mapped to this output value
of 0.5. So, that means when you do that,
it's a many-to-one mapping.
Many value from here
will be mapped to this single output
value. So, it's a many-to-one
mapping. When you do that,
that means some information has been lost
already. Why do we say some information has
been lost? Because now
you know the output is 0.5,
can you recover what is your
original input? You cannot. You do
not know which of this
input value mapped to this output.
So, therefore, you can see quite clearly
from this particular example, it's a
many-to-one mapping,
and some information has been lost
already because input value within this
range will be mapped to this output
value. So, from these output values
of 0.5, you cannot recover
your original input.
If that happened,
that means some information has been lost.
So, these are some, two examples
of the scalar
quantization just to illustrate
the point.
Right, okay. So, now we have gone through
the, we have explained about
this quantization already.
So, the last one is a symbol
encoder.
So, the symbol encoder,
as I mentioned, after you
have done the quantization,
so, very often, some pattern
will occur more often than the others.
So, once you hear that some patterns
occur more than the others,
that means you know that for different patterns, there are
some probability distribution.
So, when there are some probability distribution,
some pattern occur more than the others,
then right away, you know, you have to
use techniques such as entropy and coding
to compress it,
because it's more efficient.
So, this coding part, the objective is to
assign a code word of
patterns to each symbol
at the
output of the quantization.
So, you can, of course, you can choose
to use a fixed length or variable length
coding, but nowadays, you already know,
after you have studied the first part, you know
that variable length coding is definitely
a much better choice.
So, the idea of variable length coding
or entropy coding is
like what we mentioned before, you assign
the code in such a way,
such that the average length of the
code word will be reduced.
So, those more probable
symbols or more common symbols, you assign
shorter code word.
Those less probable symbols, you assign
a longer code word, so that overall,
the aim is that the average
number of bits per symbol is reduced.
So, this is achieved
by assigning shorter code word
to more probable symbol,
and this is the fundamental principle
of entropy and coding, such as
half-moon coding that we have studied.
So, I think
we'll probably stop today.
So, that was...
Thank you.
I'll see you next week.
I'll take it down for you.
Okay.
This sigma s square is
according to its description,
it's more like the average to the power of q.
But according to this formula,
it's more like the variance.
So, I wonder what you mean.
This is a signal.
This is not a noise.
This one is x.
So, this is the signal.
This is the signal.
This is not a noise.
This one is x.
So, in the pixel,
in the pixel,
if you talk about image
as an example,
so, image has different pixel values.
So, that means what? Each of the pixel values
is squared.
Each of the pixel values
is squared,
and afterwards, you take the average.
So, yeah.
The term below is a noise.
Okay.
So, it's more like...
It's more like this one?
Yes.
Okay. Thank you.
So, what's x, d indicate
in the
peak signal
signal-noise ratio?
So,
as it is, I just pick
signal to noise, right? Pick signal
means that the largest
value in the
original sequence of the signal.
Okay. So, suppose
if you take the...
This signal-noise ratio is
a common matrix used in
measuring the quality for image
restoration.
So, for image,
for example,
if you talk about grayscale first,
so, grayscale, each pixel, you use 8 bits
to represent. So, that means
it's possible values from 0 to 255.
So, this peak value is
255. So, therefore, the number on top is
255 squared.
I know.
I have a question
that's not relevant to the course.
Because my
annual project is
a newer system of
EMT. I'm a year-old student.
And I see
he informed me there's a
joint PT with Shanghai Jiao Tong.
For
PT.
For him? Yeah, for him. I also see your name
there. The question is
it's not the topic.
It's just his annual project. You really don't know
so much information.
I don't know if you have any connection
or existing PT students
who like under this program.
Who is the supervisor?
I mean, the
I still don't quite understand what's the question
you're trying to ask. I just want to ask
if there's any existing students
who under this joint PT program,
like, I want to ask him
if there's some
questions about the degree
verification for Chinese, because
we need the distribution system.
Oh, so you're saying
is there are there some other
seniors who have actually gone through this
kind of program before?
My prof is a new prof, so I think he
don't have that cut out. Actually this program is
very new. This is also the first time
I'm doing it. Yeah, so it's a very new
program. So if you have such
a question, the best is to ask the office.
They even show me the sample of the degree.
But
we cannot say like for
the site of China, if they verify
like a foreign or local.
So I know the US have
a connection with them
for a long time, but NTU is
from...
There are some universities
that we have some collaboration
for, like, Tsinghua.
Yeah, this Tsinghua
collaboration with Tsinghua has been ongoing
for some time already.
But other
universities like
Shanghai, Jiangtong, De1,
or at least this is the first time I see
it. Yeah.
Yeah, so, but I know it's
pretty new.
So therefore, again,
I think this
kind of question is definitely hard for me to answer.
I cannot answer that.
So far, at least for myself,
is that I don't have...
I'm not aware of any
senior who have
gone through this program yet.
Yeah.
Okay.
I have another
question.
So how
I can comprehend
that the
entropy
can indicate the
smallest number of bits
necessary to
do the encoding?
Okay.
So this entropy,
this term, actually, loosely
speaking, they are using...
they are more commonly used in communication theory.
Yeah.
So in the communication theory,
it's an indication of the degree
of randomness and how
much information is contained
in the source.
But in the context of our
compression
perspective, this entropy,
if you have a data source that
consists of different symbols,
but you can calculate its entropy.
When you calculate the entropy,
this number actually
indicates to you what is the smallest
number of bits
per symbol that you
can use to represent
a symbol.
So it's
easy to understand. For example, you have
a symbol. You can always use more bits
to represent. You can use three...
I mean, you can use eight bits, you can use
ten bits, you can use twenty bits. More is
okay. But when you try to
use what is the smallest
number of bits that you can use
to represent this symbol,
there's a theoretical lower
bound. So this theoretical lower bound
is the entropy
from the context of compression.
Okay.
So
.