[SILENCE]
OK.
[HAND CLAPS]
Can you hear me?
Right, OK, sorry for the delay.
Right, it's just there's a bit of issue with the audio system.
Right, OK, so in last lecture, actually, we
covered a number of video compression standards,
and mainly we covered the MPEG standard.
So we'll continue on.
So the next standard that we have is the MPEG-7 standard.
So the key point to take note of is that for MPEG-7 standard,
it's not a video compression standard,
but rather a content indexing system,
so that you can perform indexing and retrieval.
OK, so that's one of the important aspects of MPEG-7.
So we can see the goal is to perform
content-based retrieval.
So it's for indexing and retrieval.
It's not for compression.
So its initial target application
is for content creation and consumption.
OK, so it was established in 2001.
So the former name for this MPEG standard
is known as a multimedia content descriptor interface,
and it's not a video coding standard.
So we are not going to pay too much attention to it,
since it's actually not a video compression
standard in our context here.
Right, OK, so we have pretty much covered the MPEG series
of standards.
So next, we are going to move on to the H.26x series
So if you remember, so this H.26x series of standards
actually developed by the organization known as ITUT.
So this diagram actually gives a pretty comprehensive kind
of a different standard that was developed over time.
So I think in last lecture, we have actually
spent quite a fair bit of time to cover
most of the important standards.
So for this slide, we will not go through every one of them,
but rather just to focus on the H.26x series of standards.
So we start off with the H.261.
So this is the early years of standards,
mainly for video conferencing.
So it's low bit rate, kind of close to real time
communication.
And afterwards, we move on to this H.262.
So this H.262 is also known as MPEG2,
which is for applications such as the commercial DVD.
And afterwards, we move on to the H.263.
So this is the better improvement as compared to H.261,
again, targeting for low bit rate applications.
And afterwards, we move on to this H.264.
So H.264 is also known as advanced video coding.
So 264 here.
So this is a very important standard
as far as video compression is concerned.
That's why for today's lecture, we're
going to spend more time talking about H.264,
because it is quite a major difference as compared
to the earlier standards.
And afterwards, we move on to the H.265.
So H.265 is also known as a high efficiency video coding here.
So this H.265 actually is quite similar to H.264.
It only provides incremental improvement.
And then finally, we have one of the most recent ones,
which is H.266, also known as the versatile video coding.
So as far as the H.266 series standards are concerned,
it's mainly aligned along these directions here.
So again, the approach we are going to use
is that we are going to start off with a 261.
And afterwards, we are going to explain
for the subsequent standards what are the major improvements.
So first, we'll look at 261.
Actually, 261 standard come out before MPEG-1.
So actually, it was like the ankle for the video compression
standard.
And then many subsequent video compression standards
then learned the lessons or incorporate many features
from this H.261.
So let's look at a quick overview of 261.
So it was developed in 1990.
So initially, it was targeted for video conferencing.
So you can think about it.
Video conferencing application means that your encoding
need to be fast because when I'm talking to you,
you need to be able to receive my--
talk to me very quickly.
So the encoding has to be fast.
And also, the bit rate that I'm going to transmit
need to be low bit rate.
So these are the basic characteristics
to support applications such as video conferencing.
And then the technique that we use
is actually based on the motion compensation idea.
So this idea we have already mentioned.
We have the I-frame that we encode independently.
And we have the P-frame, which we encode it using motion,
estimation, and compensation.
So this is the standard that actually kicks
start this series of video compression approach.
It also supports this 4.2.0 video format.
So in terms of video format that is supported by H.261,
you can see this is the--
the first one is actually the requirement.
It's actually supported by H.261.
The second one is actually optional.
So let's look at the requirement.
So the requirement that we have is a quarter CIF format.
So if you use them for a quarter, that means 1/4 of it,
this common interchange format.
So it's a type of video resolution.
So for quarter CIF, for the luminance plane,
this is the resolution.
And for the chrominous plane, this is the resolution.
So you can see actually the image resolution
is very small because it's used in early years.
So the technique is not so sophisticated.
And also because it's for real-time video conferencing,
so we can only handle very low resolution video here.
So the bit rate is around 9.1, make a bit per second.
OK, so and then for the CIF format, which is four times
the quarter CIF, so you can see horizontally
as well as vertically in terms of resolution,
it's a factor of 2.
So therefore, together it's a factor of 4.
So that's why one is called quarter CIF, the other is CIF.
So this luminance and chrominance resolution,
and the bit rate for uncompressed scheme
is about this resolution.
I mean, this number of bits per second.
Right, OK, so next we are going to look
at some quick overviews of some of the H.261 video format.
For 261, actually there's only two frame type.
You only have the iFrame, which is the intra frame here,
and then pFrame, which is the in the frame here.
So there's only two frame type here.
So as we can be seen here, you only
have the iFrame, which is you encode it independently,
just like MPact1, and then you have the pFrame,
which is you encode it with respect
to the previous reference frame.
And we do not have bFrame for MPact1,
because this then actually is before MPact1.
So iFrames are encoded independently,
and pFrame actually refer to the macro blocks
in the preceding iFrame and pFrame.
So it's the reference frame here.
So this is the basic frame organization,
how it differs from the MPact1.
So in terms of decoding for the iFrame,
just like MPact1 that we've studied before.
So first of all, you have this particular macro block here.
So this macro block consists of one 16 by 16 wide channel,
one 8 by 8 CB block, and one 8 by 8 CR block here.
So if you partition into-- for this macro block,
if you partition it into 8 by 8 blocks,
so you can see you have four 8 by 8 blocks of wide channel,
one 8 by 8 CB, one 8 by 8 CR here.
So each of these blocks, you are going
to go through the compression standard, just like JPEG.
So as we have studied in the JPEG,
we're going to perform DCT, quantization, and trophy
encoding, and then we'll generate the bit stream.
So just very similar to what we have studied for MPact1.
So we can see for iFrame, each macro block consists of four
wide, one CB and one CR, a block of 8 by 8 pixel block,
as mentioned before.
And this particular format is following 4, 2, 0 chroma
subsampling.
So the macro block is of dimension 16 by 16
for the wide channel, 8 by 8 for the CB and CR.
So for each 8 by 8 pixel block, once you partition it
into 8 by 8 pixel blocks, there are six of them.
We perform DCT, going through quantization, Z-Z scanning,
the entropy encoding, and so on.
So this text here pretty much just describes the process
here.
So next for PFrame, so PFrame, the idea, again,
is similar to MPact1.
So we'll just go through it quickly.
So the PFrame encoding is based on motion compensation,
estimation compensation.
So you refer to the previous reference frame.
So for each macro block in the target frame, the current frame
that you have, the PFrame, you perform the motion estimation
to search for the motion vector.
So once you have found the motion vector,
your current macro block, you compare
with the best match block in the previous reference frame.
You take the difference or the prediction error.
And then this prediction error, you go through the standard
steps of encoding it, DCT transform, quantization,
entropy encoding.
So that's the basic idea.
So after prediction, a difference macro block
is computed to measure the prediction error.
And then each of these 8 by 8 blocks
then go through DCT quantization and Z-Z scanning and entropy
encoding.
So the PFrame encodes the difference macro block
or the prediction error.
And also the motion vector, the difference
between the motion vector for consecutive blocks,
we also use the differential coding
to code it first before we let it go through the entropy
encoding.
So exactly similar to what we have
described for the PFrame encoding of MPEG-1.
So there's nothing really that new here.
OK, so this is the visualization to show
how do we perform an encoding for PFrame in H.261.
So suppose this is our current frame that we want to encode.
So we partition it into numerous macro block
of 16 by 16 macro block.
Suppose this is the current macro block that you want to compress.
So you perform a motion estimation.
Compare with the previous reference frame
to see the positions of the best match block.
Suppose this is the positions of the best match block.
So this is the current block and this
is the position of best match block.
Then you can find out what is the motion vector.
So this motion vector, you can let
it go through a differential encoding,
and then afterwards, entropy encoding.
So the next thing is that your current block
that you want to compress and your prediction error.
So the current-- sorry, your current block
and the best match block, when you take their difference,
this will be the prediction error.
So this is called the difference or the prediction error.
So this prediction error can be divided into six blocks.
Each of them, we let it go through DCT, quantization,
and entropy encoding, and finally generate bit stream.
So quite similar to MPEG-1.
So the next thing we want to very briefly touch on
is how do we perform the quantization under the H.261.
So again, the quantization steps is
very similar to what we have in the MPEG-1,
except for 261, because it's an earlier standard,
so there's a little bit less flexibility.
So in terms of their quantization,
matrix is a bit more constrained.
So the quantization matrix used in H.261,
they use a constant step size for all the DCT coefficient
within a macro block.
So if you remember for MPEG-1, which is like the JPEG,
actually for different step size in your quantization matrix,
you have more flexibility to change the value.
Horizontally, vertically, diagonally, the step size
tends to increase.
That's for MPEG-1.
For 261, actually, the step size actually
have constant value.
So if you look at this particular equation that
relates your quantized DCT coefficient and the DCT
coefficient, suppose you have a DCT coefficient,
you want to obtain the quantized DCT coefficient.
We know that what we do is we let it divided by the step size
and then we round it.
So for 261, they have a bit more constraint.
For the DC coefficient of the intra-frame,
this step size is chosen to be a value of 8.
But for all the other coefficients,
all the other 63 coefficients, the quantized DCT coefficient
is given by the DCT coefficient divided by this step size,
whereas this step size is 2 times the scale value.
So the scale value can take any integer between 1 to 33.
But once you choose this value, all the other quantized step
size is the same.
So long story short, it's not as flexible as MPEG-1
because it's an earlier standard.
So these are just some minor differences.
In terms of quantization, for 261,
it's not as flexible as MPEG-1.
OK, so then let's try to look at the quick summary of 261
because it's very similar to MPEG-1.
So I only try to highlight some of the more salient differences
because if I explain too much here, after a while,
all of you are going to start yawning
because it's a reputation.
There's lots of reputation for different evolution
of this video compression standard.
So in terms of the intraframe coding,
so this intraframe, also known as the intra-coding,
as we've seen, this is just exactly similar to JPEG standard.
We take a particle frame.
We partition it into numerous macro block.
So each of the block, we just encode it independently.
So for the interframe, it only consists of P-frame.
So we use a DCT base.
So for each of the block, we try to perform motion estimation
to find the best match block with respect
to the previous reference frame.
So these two blocks, we calculate their difference
or the prediction error.
And this prediction error, then we
let it go through DCT quantization entropy encoding.
So therefore, the prediction error
is subsequently handled using DCT transform.
And then it's used a fixed block size motion estimation,
because you can see it's actually a 16 by 16 macro block.
So the reason why we state here is a fixed block size
is because subsequently, when we look at this H.264,
you can see that there's a contrast.
For 264, it allows different block size
to perform motion compensation.
So some other key feature, it only has I and P-frame,
because it's targeting for video conferencing.
So you can expect to have low resolution and low bit rate.
So it was targeting for video conferencing application
in those early years.
So that was 261.
And afterwards, we move on to 262.
So can any one of you remember 262 is actually
corresponding to MPEG what?
262, H.262 correspond to MPEG?
Two, well, correspond to MPEG two.
Since we have already spent some time talking about MPEG two
in the earlier lecture, so this will not
repeat too much information here,
since it's just the same standard,
but it's used a different name,
because it was jointly developed between this organization,
ITU-T, and ISO and IEC.
Right, okay, so the quick overview
is jointly developed by this ITU-T.
Right, okay, actually, more specifically,
is this study group 16, which is called
Video Coding Expert Group, okay, or VCEG here.
And then also the ISO, IEC,
Moving Picture Expert Group, MPEG.
So it's between these few organizations.
That's why it was called these different names here.
Right, so it's actually known as the MPEG two,
part two, specifically part two is a video compression
part of MPEG two.
Right, it also has this name here.
Okay, right, it's developed in '95.
Okay, so 262 and MPEG two has some basic properties.
I think we have already covered some of the important
expect in previous lecture.
So we'll just highlight, actually it has three frame type,
I frame, P frame, and B frame.
So intra-coded predictive coded frame
and bi-directionally predictive coded frame here.
So you can see, therefore, how it differ from 261 now
is that it introduce the B frame, okay?
Right, okay, let's continue on.
263 and 263 plus, and actually there's also
the 263 plus plus as well.
Right, okay, so what are some quick information
regarding 263?
So it's the basics of development for the subsequent
MPEG four that we have actually covered in last lecture.
Right, okay, so 263 is developed in '96,
263 plus in '98, right?
So kind of early years.
Okay, so right, the objective of course is always
continuously trying to improve the performance
of the standard, right, at lower bit rate here.
So it offer improvement to 261, but it's also
targeting for video conferencing application.
Right, so 263 series is also targeting
video conferencing application.
Right, for 263 plus, it support this subpixel
motion factors up to one eight pixel
of the pixel accuracy for improved compression.
So can anyone of you still remember what's the meaning
of this subpixel motion estimation,
or subpixel accuracy for motion estimation?
Right, so if you think about it, right,
how do you achieve subpixel?
Right, so you have, for example, this current,
this is your current frame, right, partitioned
into numerous macro block.
This is the current macro block that you want to encode.
There's many different macro block.
Suppose this is the macro block you want to encode, right,
and then you refer to the previous reference frame.
So the previous reference frame, you also have
different grid structure, right, grid structures here.
So you have this macro block that you want to
kind of compress, and then, yeah,
in the previous reference frame, usually you would define
a search window, and then you try to find
where is the positions of best match block, right.
So in the early years, when you try to do it,
when you do the checking or moving of this pixel,
it's at the grid level or integer level.
Yeah, so therefore, if you want to actually obtain up
to the sub-pixel level accuracy, what you need to do
is that for this reference frame, right,
suppose these are the two, four pixel values
in the reference frame, yeah, these two are integer
pixel value, you try to do some interpolation, right,
for the values between this integer pixel value.
So if you can do some interpolation between this particular
pixel value, then your previous macro block then,
you can check, right, where is the best match position,
even at the sub-pixel level, okay.
So therefore, right, so for this part here,
pretty much is that you use the interpolation,
to try to interplay some sub-pixel value
in the reference frame, and afterwards, then you can check
what is the motion estimation up to the sub-pixel level.
Okay, so that's the basic idea here.
Right, okay, so for 263, some of the supporting standards,
yeah, so we will not spend too much time on this,
this kind of very detailed information.
So as far as the exam and, you know, is concerned,
right, these are considered as like, you know,
secondary information, or actually it's more like
just for your information, right, you don't really have to
kind of memorize those information, okay, no need to.
Right, so anyway, right, so for H.263, right,
so these are the wider range of the resolution, right,
it correspond to these resolutions here, okay,
for the luminance and the chrominance plane.
Okay, so the bit rate for the uncompressed
and the compressed bit rate, okay, yeah,
is, yeah, so, sorry, this is the maximum bit rate,
and this is the uncompressed bit rate
that it can support, okay.
Right, so what are some of the important features
of 263 plus, right, so it provide more flexibility
in terms of different source format,
that means it can support even larger range
of different resolution, different aspect ratio, right,
okay, the ratio of the width to the height
of the image plane, okay, it also support temporal,
SNR, and the spatial scalability, similar to,
now what we have studied about MPEG-2, right,
it also include this deblocking filter, all right,
so this deblocking filter is because, if you remember,
right, for all this video compression standard,
it's based on the idea that given a current frame
that you want to compress,
you partition into numerous macro block.
So for each block here, right, when you find the motion
as, you know, the best match block,
you take their difference, you encode it, and so on,
you expect that between this current macro block
that you encode and the flowing macro block
that you encode at this boundary, right,
there will be some discontinuity, right,
there'll be some artifact or there'll be some distortion.
So therefore, right, usually between the blocks,
one macro block and the other macro block,
there'll be some visually not very pleasing
kind of artifacts in between, right,
so therefore, for this 263, actually,
they introduce this deblocking filter.
So, as the name suggests, deblocking means
that you want to remove this blockiness effect
at the boundary of different macro block, okay?
Right, so this deblocking filter will actually,
you know, become more important
in the subsequent standards, okay?
But it started in this 263 already.
Okay, so you can see, again,
for this video compression standard, right,
a lot of them is actually kind of,
how should I say, it's an evolution.
You kind of, for different standard,
you start to improve, you know, gradually and gradually,
yeah, but H.264 is considered as a slightly more different,
right, because a lot of the technique used
is quite different from the previous one.
So, that's why 264 is considered
as a more important standard, as we'll see later.
Right, okay, so these are,
just now what we covered before,
261, 262, 263, those are considered
as slightly kind of earlier standard.
So, the more recent standards actually
are 264, 265, 266, so these are considered
as more recent standard, and they are also
commonly grouped together because they have
shared lots of similarity, okay.
So, 264 has a bigger difference
compared to the earlier standard,
but subsequently, 264, 265, 266 are a little bit closer
in terms of the approach they're using.
Right, okay, so who developed this, right,
so it was developed by this ISO/IEC,
and PEC, and the ITUT video coding expert group, right,
okay, like we have mentioned before.
So, what's the objective of these standards here, right?
You can more or less guess already, right.
So, number one is of course to improve
the coding efficiency, you want to code it
into smaller bit rate, but at the same time
still achieve better compression performance.
Right, another thing is that over time,
when you're starting from 264 onward,
the resolutions of the video become larger and larger.
So, therefore, in more recent standard,
you need to be able to handle larger video resolution
and a higher frame rate, okay.
So, therefore, in the more recent standard,
you will try, you need to handle increase
in video resolution as well as the frame rate,
okay, for example, from HD to ultra HD.
Right, and then for 266, the most recent standard,
actually it further develops some other new emerging issues
like high dynamic range video, right,
360 degree video, right,
paranormal video, and so on, okay.
So, it addresses some more emerging situation and use cases.
Okay, so, yeah, so we have covered just now
261, 262, 263, now we are going to come to the focus
of today's lecture, which is 264, right.
Okay, so let's do a quick overview of 264.
So, for 264, it was developed, so this slide
is more like fact-sharing information.
It was developed by ITUT, Video Coding Expert Group,
and this ISO, IEC MPEG Group in 2003, right,
quite some years ago, right, so it was also known
as Advanced Video Coding, or AVC, right,
also known as MPEG 4 part 10, right,
so these are some alternative name.
Okay, it can offer 50% better compression efficiency
than MPEG 2, right, and up to 30% better than 263.
Okay, it has support a wide range of application,
right, including internet video, computer,
you know, Blu-ray, and many others.
Okay, so it will improve the motion compensation
with variable block size, so later on we'll see
what's the meaning of this variable block size,
as well as the multiple reference stream.
Okay, so these are some of the features of H.264.
Right, okay, so let's look at the encoder of this 264.
So encoder means that you have some original video frame,
right, after you encode it, right, what you have
is that you have the encoded bit stream or the compressed
video, so how does it work?
So what you have here is that first of all,
you have some input video frame, okay,
so this is your current frame, suppose this is the current
frame that you want to encode, yeah, you partition
into 16 by 16 macro block, right, so if this is the current
frame you want to encode, right, so you partition it
into numerous 16 by 16 macro block, so this is similar
to what we have studied before.
Okay, and then for one moment let's assume that, right,
okay, at this signal, at this particular juncture here
is actually your previous reference frame,
your constructed reference frame, okay, so this is
the current frame you want to encode, okay,
this is the current frame that you want to encode,
signal at this particular juncture here is your
previous reference frame, okay, you already have
the previous reference frame sitting here already,
okay, previous reference frame sitting here.
So what we do now is that we have our current macro block
in our current frame that we want to compress,
we compare with the previous reference frame here, okay,
so we perform the motion estimation, so once you perform
the motion estimation, right, you can then obtain
the motion vector, right, this motion vector can then
go through the entropy encoding, yeah, okay,
so this part is quite straightforward, and once you have
found out, okay, what is the best match block
in the previous reference frame, okay, so, yeah,
you can take the difference, so this process here
is actually, you can find the best match block, right,
so this best match block then, you take the difference
between your current macro block and the best match block,
okay, so the difference here, this is your difference,
also known as your prediction error, okay,
so your best match block and your, no, sorry,
your current reference block and your best match block
through the motion estimation, okay, so afterwards
you take the difference, okay, so this small arrow here
is you take the difference here, so you have the prediction
error now, so once you have this particular prediction error,
the next thing that it does for this H.264 is that
it go through integer transform, so you can see
this is how it differ from the previous standard,
so for the previous standard, what is the block
we are using here?
For the previous standard, like MPEG-2, MPEG-1,
what is the transform we use?
Anyone still remember?
DCT, right, so for previous standard, they used DCT,
but for H.264, they used integer transform,
so later on, we are going to spend a little bit more time
to find out about this integer transform,
why is it being used and how do we use it, okay,
so, but anyway, at this moment, just know that, right,
you use an integer transform, okay, in H.264,
and afterwards, you go through the scaling and quantization,
similar to the earlier standard, right,
there are some small differences, but in terms of
the basic principle, it's the same, all right, okay,
so once you have done that, then what you have now
is that you have this quantized transform coefficient now,
right, so this quantized transform coefficient,
you can then go through entropy encoding to generate
a bitstream, okay, so you can also see that, right,
you have this particular, sitting on top of this, right,
is that you have what is known as a coder control,
so this particular coder control actually is used to
control the bit rate of your generated video, right,
sometimes you may want your generated video
to have a low bit rate, sometimes, low bit rate,
but you are okay with some lower quality,
sometimes you want a better quality video,
and you can tolerate some higher bit rate,
so this will be controlled by this coder control here,
right, so you use to control the bit rate of your
generated or encoded video, right, okay,
so it can control it by controlling this quantization
steps here, okay, and the corresponding
inverse quantization steps, okay, right, okay,
so anyway, right, so earlier on, we already said that
this is actually our quantized transform coefficient,
right, quantized transform coefficient for the
prediction error, for the prediction error,
okay, so afterwards we do the inverse of the quantization,
inverse of the integer transform, okay, right,
so at this point here then, what we obtain is your,
you know, kind of a reconstructed error
or prediction error now, so signal at this point now
is your reconstructed prediction error, okay,
so this prediction error now, you add with the previous,
no, macro block or the previous frame, okay,
then you can then generate the next frame, okay,
the next frame, right, so this next frame will go through
a deblocking filter to remove the blocking artifact,
okay, at each of the macro block, right,
so then afterwards, at this signal, at this junction now
will be your reconstructed frame, okay,
your reconstructed reference frame now,
so that's pretty much the basic principles
of the H.264 encoder, right, so for the next few slides,
we are going to look into each of this component
a bit more in detail now, right, okay,
but before that, let's look at some high-level properties
of 264, okay, so in terms of the 264,
from just now the diagram, you already see
there's a few important aspects,
number one is that it performs integer transform, okay,
so as opposed to DCT transform that you are familiar with,
for 264, right, so it uses integer transform,
and it's in the block size of four by four blocks,
okay, integer transform in four by four blocks here,
right, so some of the advantages of this integer transform
as you will see later is that it's low complexity,
because for this particular transform matrix
that we are using, right, so the transform matrix
that we are using, each of the coefficient
in the transform matrix, in the transform matrix
are integer, okay, so therefore it takes this name,
integer transform, right, so later on we'll see,
because we are using integer, so, right,
in terms of computation, it's fast,
so therefore it's low complexity,
and also there's no drifting, no drifting is because
previously, when you are using the DCT, right,
because DCT is actually a floating number,
a floating point number, you usually need to round up
this floating point number, and if you do this DCT
many, many times, then your value will start to drift,
okay, so this is known as a drifting problem,
but if you are using integer transform,
all the coefficient in the transform matrix
are integer value, therefore the value will not drift,
right, because there's no rounding off kind of effect.
Okay, so that's one of the important aspect
you use the integer transform, the second one is that
you use a variable block size motion compensation, right,
so in terms of the block size, as opposed to,
you know, the standard before that you see
is always 16 by 16, for H dot 264, right,
it has a wider range of different block,
so the block size can be ranging from 16 to 16,
to four to four, right, so it has different block size here.
Okay, so in terms of the accuracy,
it has a quarter pixel accuracy in motion vectors here,
right, and how it can be achieved, right,
as we have mentioned before, is that we perform
interpolation at the reference frame, okay.
Right, on top of that, for H dot 264,
it can also, you know, provide multiple reference frame
for motion compensation, why do you need to perform,
why does it want to support multiple reference frame,
multiple reference frame motion compensation, any suggestion?
So if you remember, so when we studied about
this reference frame, specifically the P frame
and the B frame, so we say that for P frame, right,
if this is a current frame you want to encode,
for P frame, you refer to the previous reference frame,
okay, so you only have one reference frame to refer to,
but for B frame, for example, for B frame,
if this is the current frame you want to encode,
you have the previous, okay, reference frame,
and you have the flowing reference frame,
so you can refer to two reference frame
to perform the motion estimation and compensation.
So at the time, we say that if you are using B frame,
because you now have two reference frame
to search the best match block,
the chances of you finding a best match block is higher,
yeah, so therefore you can then, you know,
actually achieve a better, kind of,
achieve a higher compression ratio,
because you can find the chances of you finding
a better best match block is higher
respect to your current block.
If it's more similar, that means this arrow is smaller.
If this arrow is smaller, that means you can
compress it into smaller bit rate, so this is good,
but the price you have to pay is that
now you have to do a search for two reference frame.
So that is for last time when we studied about MPEG-1,
so for this, actually, the idea is the same, right,
when you have numerous multiple reference frame,
you have more reference frame that you can refer to,
that means the chances of you finding
a best match block will be higher,
that means you can find a block which is more similar
to your current block.
If you can find a block among all the reference block
that's more similar, that means your arrow is smaller,
arrow is smaller means that you can compress it
into a smaller bit rate, okay, so that's the advantage,
but the disadvantage is similar to the bit frame,
that means during the coding time,
it's going to take a long time to do it,
and for some application, you cannot afford to wait,
right, especially for those, you know,
kind of real-time teleconferencing
or video conferencing application.
Okay, so anyway, there's this option
to support multiple reference frame,
you may choose not to use it,
but there's a such option for you to choose, right, okay,
and then another important difference is that
for the P frame, the intra frame here, the I frame,
I frame is known as intra frame,
also known as intra-coded frame,
they all refer to the same thing,
so for the I frame here, right,
they use a directional spatial prediction, okay,
so later on, we're going to spend some time
to see what's the meaning of this directional spatial
prediction for the coding of the intra frame,
and then also it make use of improved in-loop
deblocking filtering, so this point,
actually we have already mentioned earlier.
Right, so a bit more to continue on,
so for this 264, they also make use of
a context adaptive variable length coding,
and context adaptive binary aromatic coding here,
so these two are entropy,
both are entropy encoding technique,
so what it does is that, for example,
for this context adaptive variable length coding,
is that as opposed to the previous variable length coding,
you only have one codebook, yeah,
or you only use one single Huffman codebook,
for example, right, to do the encoding,
but for 264, you'll look at the context,
what is the current situation for this particular frame is,
and then you may choose one of the most suitable
Huffman codebook or variable length coding
to help to perform the compression,
so that means you'll look at the context
of the current frame, okay,
and then try to choose one of the most suitable
codebook to do the compression, okay,
that's why it's known as
a context adaptive variable length coding, okay,
so this aromatic, binary aromatic coding
is based on the same idea,
so later on we'll talk a little bit more about that,
okay, so it's more robust to error,
data error and loss, okay,
it still employs hybrid coding,
that means you try to encode,
the intra-frame is encoded independently, okay,
right, so, and then you have the other reference frame
that make use of inter-frame motion,
estimation and compensation,
and afterwards, right, the residue error,
you use the transform coding,
in this case it's your integer transform,
so the basic principle is still kind of
inherit some of the basic idea before,
yeah, but it has a relatively major improvement
as compared to the earlier standards,
okay, so let's start off with the motion compensation,
so earlier on we mentioned that for 264,
it actually use a variable block size motion compensation,
okay, so what it means is now,
as opposed to the previous standard,
which always use 16 by 16 blocker,
for H.264 it can use, you know,
either 16 by 16, right, which is known as the M type,
or eight by eight partition,
which is called the eight by eight type here, right,
so it can make use of these two different block size here,
right, and then for each of these block size here,
you can actually further partition it,
for example, this M type,
you can further partition into two eight by 16,
all right, two horizontal one,
or two vertical 16 by eight,
or four eight by eight,
actually each of these you can further partition it
into, you know, ultimately four by four, okay,
so therefore you can see that there's many different kind of
you know, different blocks that you can partition into,
so likewise for this particular eight by eight block,
you can also partition into four by eight,
eight by four, and also four by four blocks here, right,
so this particular ability to use different block sizes
to cater for different needs,
for example, sometimes your certain blocks
is actually quite smooth, right,
there's not lots of texture,
then you can use this kind of 16 by 16 block to encode it,
right, to represent, it's quite good already,
but sometimes you have some certain region
that lots of detail or texture,
then you may want to choose some smaller blocks
to represent it, okay, so that's the basic idea.
Okay, so anyway, by default,
the macro block size is 16 by 16, right,
and then each of these starting from 16 by 16,
or eight by eight, you can further partition
into smaller partition, as illustrated in this figure.
Right, okay, so the next topic that we want to talk about
is the motion compensation.
So for H.264, right, the motion compensation,
estimation and compensation,
is up to a quarter pixel accuracy, okay,
so quarter pixel accuracy in the Luma channel, okay,
so the values at the half pixels and the quarter pixels
can be obtained through interpolation, right,
so for this point here, right,
I'll just quickly move to this particular slide here,
so for example, right, for this particular slide here,
these are some integer pixel value, okay,
so for example, you have an image, right,
this particular point here, okay,
these pixels shown as in this kind of shaded color,
these are the original pixel value,
so all the original pixel value,
so you can actually perform interpolation
to estimate what is the pixel values,
so for example, each of these,
they are some, you can estimate,
they are intermediate values here,
but we will only pay our attention
to these current pixels here, okay,
so these four are integer pixel,
we will only pay our attention to this,
not all these subpixel values
within these four pixel values here,
but the same actually happens to all the other pixels,
yeah, but we are just focusing at these current pixels here,
so you can see that, right,
even this integer pixel value,
actually you can try to use interpolation
to guess or to estimate what are the values in between,
for example, these values in between,
so for these values in between here and here,
this is a half pixel accuracy, right,
so you can see this is integer pixel,
for example, this pixel, say, three,
this is pixel four, right,
so this pixel now is 3.5, so it's .5,
so this is a half pixel accuracy,
so B and H is half pixel accuracy, right,
and then this A here now is,
you can see quite clearly,
is a quarter pixel accuracy,
so therefore, by trying to guess or estimate
or interpolate the values between this integer pixel,
right, once we have found these values here,
then later on, when we perform the estimation,
we can find which of this position
it correspond to the best match block, okay,
so this is the idea that I've been saying
a few times already.
So our focus for the next few slides
will be to see how can we perform
this particular kind of interpolation
to support the motion estimation and compensation.
Right, so let's continue.
Okay, so the pixel value, right,
B and H at half pixel position
are estimated using a six-step filter here,
so if you refer to this figure, B and H is here,
so this B and H is a half pixel value,
so this half pixel value here
is estimated using a six-step filter here.
Six-step filter means that it's a filter
that makes use of six coefficients, right,
so you can see, right, it's a filter
that makes use of six coefficients,
one, minus five, 20, 20, minus five, one, okay?
Right, so specifically, right,
if you want to, for example,
calculate this value B1, how do you do it?
If you want to calculate this, okay,
actually, at this stage here, I'll just,
okay, maybe let me just, right,
so these equations here are the same
as these equations here, right,
so we'll use this equation to show it, right,
so for example, if you want to calculate
this particular pixel value, what do you do?
Right, so first of all,
you calculate intermediate value B1 first,
so this intermediate value you can see
is by performing filtering operation
on this pixel value E to J,
so where is this pixel value E to J?
It's actually at this position, EFGHIJ,
so therefore, if you want to estimate
or interpolate this pixel value B,
first of all, you calculate the intermediate value B1 first,
and afterwards, once you get this B1 here,
you take this B1 plus 16, right,
and then afterwards, you convert this
into a binary number, and you shift to the,
no, shift to the right by five position, okay,
so this particular process here is that,
okay, you take this value, intermediate value B1,
you allow 16, all right,
and then you convert this into a binary number,
and then you do a binary shift, right,
this value, you shift it,
so this particular process is actually equivalent to,
you take this value B1, you divide by 32,
because if it's a binary number,
every time you shift to the right by one spot,
that means you divide by two,
but you divide by two, divide by two, divide by two,
so if you divide by two five times,
that means you divide by two to the power of five,
which means you divide by 32, right,
so the reason why you also add half of it, 16 here,
is because you just want to make sure
that it takes into account the rounding effect,
yeah, it takes into account the rounding effect.
Okay, so anyway, right,
so that's how you can use these values
to approximate your value for B, okay?
So if you want to estimate your value for H,
then what you do is that, first of all,
you take this pixel value ACGMRT, okay?
You use this filter coefficient to multiply,
to generate your intermediate H1,
so this formula here actually means that, right,
the H1, you divide it by 32, and you do the rounding
to the nearest integer, that would give you H,
but in terms of the programming,
usually it's easier if you just simply add up,
because this number in binary representation,
often is in binary representation,
this value here, you just simply add up with 16, right,
and then you do the shift to the right five times,
it's faster, okay?
But actually, in terms of the objective, it's the same.
Right, okay, so let's continue, so with that,
that means you can calculate B and H value here.
Right, so let's continue.
So therefore, by looking at some surrounding pixel value,
right, you should be able to estimate, okay,
or interplay the subpixel value B and H here, okay?
So early on, you can see this particular process here
is actually equivalent to this B1, right?
You divide by two to the power of five,
which is 32, and then you ground it
to the nearest integer value, that is a B, yeah?
But in terms of the implementation in the,
you know, the coder, it's more efficient to do it,
okay, so anyway, this is the same as this,
but in terms of the implementation and coder,
it's easier to do it this way.
Yeah, you add up with 16,
because they are all in binary numbers already,
you just shift, okay, to the right five spots, right,
to throw out the spots here.
Okay, so anyway, yeah, you can either interpret as,
no, this is how you do it to find this B,
or if you are more comfortable,
you can also interpret as converting it into binary number
and then do a shifting by five times, okay, to the right.
Okay, and afterwards, this B and H,
finally this B and H value will be clipped
to the image range, which is typically
from zero to 255, right, okay?
So we kind of give a very quick introduction,
so let's just, you know, repeat the steps here, right,
so again, what's this particular story here,
is that number one is that you have all this
integer pixel value that we know, okay,
coming from your reference frame.
We have all this integer value here,
now our focus is to try to find the subpixel
and the quarter pixel value for this particular region here.
Okay, so early on just now we already said, right,
if you want to find this pixel value, for example, B,
okay, if you want to find this pixel value,
this half pixel value B, right,
so first of all, we use this equation.
So this equation is also known as filtering, okay,
using, okay, this pixel value, one, two, three, four,
five, six, right, so, which is corresponding EFGHIJ, okay?
Right, so you'll get your intermediate result B1,
and then once you get the intermediate result B1,
you can then use this process.
So this process is equivalent to,
you divide by 32, you round to the nearest integer,
then you'll get your integer value for B.
So by using the same process, if you want to find H here,
right, first of all, you calculate your intermediate value
H1 by using this one, two, three, four, five, six, yeah,
using that, you'll get your intermediate value H1,
and afterwards, by doing this equation,
which is the same as divided by 32 and round
to the nearest integer, you'll get this value H.
So therefore, B and H you can find already.
And afterwards, right, suppose if you want to find now
this J, this value here.
So if you want to find this value J here,
then first of all, you have to get
this intermediate value J1.
So this intermediate value J1 will depend on,
you can see, this AA1,
okay, this AA, BB, H, right.
Okay, this one here, BB1, the H1, M1, CC1, DT1,
is actually the same as how you calculate this B here.
You can see, right.
So for example, this is, right, you use this five,
your six pixel value, one, two, three, four, five, six.
You can first of all calculate the intermediate values
of AA1, and afterwards AA, okay, similar to this.
So in other words, actually by using the same idea,
you can actually find the value here, AA1, BB1,
the intermediate value, okay, before you reach AA,
AA1, BB1, and so on and so forth.
So that means you can actually calculate these values here.
Okay.
So once you can get those values,
then you can use to calculate your J1.
So once you can get your J1,
you can use the same process to calculate J, okay.
So in other words, you can use this formula here
to calculate your J, yeah.
Okay, and then once you have found B, H, and J,
if you want to find this A,
you can see this A is pretty much B plus H plus one,
and then afterwards, shift to the left,
shift to the right by one,
that means divided by two, round to the nearest integer.
Okay, yeah, so that means we can then find out the value A,
and if you want to find the value E,
it's pretty much take the average between B and H, okay,
you can see B plus H plus one,
and then shift to the right by one,
that means divided by two.
So that means essentially you are taking the average
between B and H, okay, and round to the nearest integer.
Okay, so this is just some equation to show you
how you can perform the interpolation, right,
in the event you do not know how to do it.
So anyway, right, we'll have one exercise
for you to give it a try, right,
we are not going to go into too much detail,
but just one simple exercise,
at least let you have a feel about
how do we perform these interpolations here.
Okay, so in this exercise here, right,
the same similar setting as before, okay,
so these are the integer pixel value, right,
and then these are the equation that's given, okay.
Right, okay, so to estimate the half pixel, okay,
and then to estimate the quarter pixel at A and E, right,
so all the formulas are given, right,
and then all the relevant pixels are also given,
so the pixel values are given, okay,
A is 50, 60, and so on and so forth.
So they ask you to find the half pixel value at B and H,
and the quarter pixel value at A and E, okay,
so yeah, I'll give you a bit of time to give it a try,
and then we'll go through the answers together.
(papers rustling)
(coughing)
- Okay, so at least you have some time to think about it.
Right, so yeah, so actually when the formula is provided,
it's relatively straightforward, right?
The only thing about this particular part,
which is a little bit, may not be so familiar.
So as I mentioned, this particular part here
is actually equivalent to, you just take B1 divided by 32
and then round it to the nearest integer.
Then it's equivalent to these steps already.
Yeah, okay, so let's try to go through the answers together.
Right, okay, so the steps, there's nothing tricky about it.
It's just, you know, pretty much just make sure
that you apply the formula, right?
And then, yeah, so for example, for, yeah.
Yeah, when you want to find out this particular value B,
first of all, you need to calculate this,
the kind of intermediate value B1.
So you have this intermediate value B1.
You just plug in all the values
for the corresponding coefficients, okay?
Right, B is here, so corresponding coefficient here.
Just plug it in, do a bit of a calculation at home, right?
Or later on, you'll see that you get the intermediate value
for B1 and H1 here, right?
And afterwards, for these two steps here,
you can either convert it into binary number
and you do the shifting, which is what the computer would do,
or you just simply, you know, divide by 32
and round to the nearest integer, right?
And then if you do that, you'll see that B is 35 and H is 65.
That means you actually find the value
at this half pixel positions already.
And afterwards, if you want to find this value A, right?
So this value A is at this positions here.
So it's given by this formula here.
So this formula, you just, you know,
since you already just found out about B, right?
You also have the G value, right?
You can do this operation.
So this operation is the same as you take G plus B,
right, divided by 32, round to the nearest integer, right?
You can see it's 33, okay?
And then the likewise for this one,
you take 35, add up with 65, okay?
Plus one, right?
So this is actually your B and H that you found earlier on.
Okay, so 35 plus 65, okay?
You add them up, divided by 32,
round to the nearest integer.
Sometimes there's a little bit of ambiguity, right?
You know, sometimes if it's 0.5,
it can be, you know, going to both way,
either way we do the rounding.
But because we are doing,
if you use a computer to do the implementation,
actually it do the shifting.
That means usually it will round down, yeah?
So that's why the value is, in this case, is 51.
You can go and give it a try, yeah.
Okay, so that's pretty much, right,
so this particular exercise pretty much just tell you
that how you can actually use to perform,
use interpolation to find the sub-pixel value.
So once you can estimate a sub-pixel value,
then when you do the motion estimation,
then the accuracy can be up to a quarter
of a pixel value accuracy.
Okay, so that's this part, what it's trying to say.
So let's continue for a few more slides.
Right, okay, so for 264,
there's also some additional option that you can choose.
Right, so some additional option is that
when you do the video compression using 264,
you can choose not to use B-frame, okay?
So you have the option of not using B-frame.
So you can kind of easily think about
when are the cases you may not want to go for B-frame.
Without even reading the text,
you can use a common kind of understanding.
Where are the cases you may choose not to use B-frame?
When, you know, B-frame is good, right?
B-frame, because you can actually then,
you know, get a best match.
Chances of you getting a better match block is higher.
That means you can, you know, when this,
you can find a better, if this is a macro block,
the chances of you finding a better,
best match block is higher, right?
That means error is smaller,
you can compress it into a smaller bit rate.
So James-Pikin is good,
but what's the price you have to pay?
The price you have to pay is you have to do
a lot more motion estimation, and this is expensive.
So therefore what it means is that if your application
is meant for those fast application like
those close to video conferencing,
then you may not want to do,
you may not want to use B-frame because it can be slow.
Okay, so that's the reason.
Yeah, okay, so the prediction of macro block in B-frame
can introduce delay and also require more storage, right?
So therefore in some cases, for example,
applications such as video conferencing,
you may not want to choose this option
because 264 will give you this option
whether you want to use it or not.
So if you choose this option,
that means you'll only be using I and P-frame, okay?
So what's the price you have to pay?
The compression efficiency is low now
because chances of you finding a best match block
will be a little bit less.
That means the prediction error will be a bit higher,
right, so you cannot compress a bit as effectively.
Okay, but the good thing about it is good for applications
such as video conferencing because it's faster.
Okay, so this is actually supported in the baseline profile
and the constrained baseline profile in 264.
For 264, they also have different profile to support,
to provide a target for different target application.
Just similar to the level and the profile in MPAC2.
Right, okay, so on the other hand,
as opposed to use no B-frame,
you can also choose that multiple reference frame, okay?
So for example, in this case here, right,
you have one I-frame and then you have a P-frame here.
So this P-frame can refer to this reference frame
and this P-frame can refer to previous two reference frame.
This P-frame can refer to previous three reference frame.
So that means when you are using more reference frame,
the chances of you finding a best match block is higher,
therefore you can compress it better, right?
But the price is that now it's going to be a lot slower.
Right, okay, so the opposite of it is that
you can choose multiple reference frame, okay?
So therefore, the idea is you try to find the best match
from each macro block in your P-frame, okay?
Right, you can go up to N reference frame here.
So the good thing is that you can improve the efficiency,
you can compress it into much smaller bit rate, right?
But the price you have to do now
is you have to do a lot more computation
because you have to check respect
to each of the reference frame.
Right, okay, so the next topic we are going to cover
is this integer transform.
It's probably time for us to take a break.
So let's come back at 8.05, okay?
Let's come back at 8.05.
(rustling)
Okay, so welcome back.
Right, so there are a few students who asked regarding the assignment.
So I think, yeah, it's probably time for me to just go through the instruction one more time.
Right, I know when you get old you tend to be very repetitive.
But just to make sure that no one missed this information.
Okay, so number one for this assignment in terms of submission,
please only submit one soft copy PDF file.
Okay, so only one file.
Don't submit anything more than one.
So one way you can do it is for example, for this assignment there's two parts.
One is a calculation, the other is more like a report writing.
So what you can do is that for part one when solving the problem,
you can write on a piece of paper.
You can take pictures of it, you can scan it.
And afterwards you paste this particular picture into the work document.
Yeah, for example for question one.
And afterwards you continue with question two to write your answer.
Yeah, and then from this work document you convert it into PDF.
So this is one way.
Of course there are other ways you do it.
But the most important thing is please only submit one file.
Because when I download the file for marking, I'm going to download 500 something files.
And sometimes if you don't follow the instruction, some of the files may be missing.
Okay, so therefore very very important to submit only one soft copy PDF file.
Okay, and the deadline is 4th of October.
Right, and also submit your file using this structure.
Surname_given_name_matriculation_number.
So for example, if the student's name is Tan Surname_YiMing is the given name_matriculation_number.
Please stick to this very, stick to this particular standard.
Don't change your name.
Some people like to only use their nickname and so on.
And I cannot find who this person is.
Yeah, so it's going to create lots of problems.
So please only follow this naming approach.
Right, so write your full name and matriculation number on the first page just to be sure.
Right, in case there's some ambiguity.
In the past, there are students, we actually, they don't follow this instruction and we find it very difficult to find out who this person is.
Yeah, and then we have to look at the first page.
Yeah, so don't, I mean make life easier for me.
If you make me happier, I'll mark you more linearly.
Okay, so late submission or non-compliance, if you don't follow these instructions here, you may be penalised.
Okay, right.
So the next is regarding the assignment.
So it's quite clear this instruction is the same as before.
You have two questions.
So the first question is compute manually using this two-stage decomposition.
So this, when I say two-stage decomposition, what I mean is that you have to make use of this formula.
Compose it row by row and then column by column.
Don't use the matrix multiplication.
Use a row by row and then column by column two-stage decomposition.
And then for this particular question two, it's supposed to be an open-ended problem.
And you're only asked to write one page.
Yeah, one page.
Right, so you can see that because you're only asked to write one page, there's only limited space you can write.
Okay, so therefore I don't expect you to write all these things here.
Okay, right.
No, your one page write-up doesn't have to be covering all these things.
It doesn't have to cover objectives, applications, training, challenges.
No, it's not that.
Yeah, you just have to, for example, you can see here, objectives, yes, you probably have to talk about objectives.
But afterwards, you can either choose application or train or challenges or if you want a combination of one or two.
So you can see the sign here is all.
So therefore you just choose one topic that you really feel is something that's important.
Yeah, it's not supposed to be a comprehensive report or summary, but rather choose one or two topics that you feel is really important, you want to highlight it.
Okay, so it's not supposed to be a comprehensive report to cover every single aspect.
Yeah, you can just focus on the challenge or just focus on the train.
Okay, or just focus on some very interesting application you have encountered recently and you feel that it has an immediate impact.
Right, for example, the CHETGBT-01 recently.
Yeah, that could be something that's very interesting recently.
Right, you can see what it can do.
Yeah, and actually just recently I also see that, heard that one of the professor, I'm not sure whether it's from Harvard, they are teaching the mathematics.
So this, I think, math professor, they actually asked their student to use, to train some LLM model.
And afterwards this trained model would then represent them to sit for some math test.
Yeah, and their score would be based on how well they train this particular model, LLM model to do the score.
So that could be something very interesting.
Yeah, because nowadays there are so many tools there.
If you really can develop or train a model to help you to solve the problem, it could be quite interesting as well.
So any, therefore, it's open-ended.
Yeah, please choose any topics that you feel is interesting.
It can be application, train, challenges.
Yeah, okay.
Any questions?
Yeah, because there are some students asking this, so I just want to clarify this.
All right, okay.
So then this part is clear.
And the submission, as I mentioned before, you just come to the assignment, you just click it.
Yeah, and then afterwards you can just upload the file, just upload one PDF file.
That's it.
Yeah, end of the story.
And you are only given, I think, two or three times to submit it.
So make sure that before you submit, you check everything is correct.
Right, okay.
So with that, actually I just happen to have a -- let me see.
Yeah, I'm not sure whether some of you have seen it before.
Right, so it's actually a video, yeah, it's in Chinese.
I cannot find any, you know, subtitle in English, so that's why I have to play this video in Chinese.
But for those of you who don't understand Chinese, you can kind of guess what it's trying to talk about.
It's about homework.
So if you have watched it before, yeah, just bear with me.
So let me just play this video for you.
[video playing]
Yo, it's very loud.
Okay, let me just reduce the volume a bit.
[video playing]
Right, and there may be a few slightly vulgar words I understand from my students, so just don't get offended.
[snoring]
[video playing]
Okay, so let's hope it will not happen to you.
Okay, so let's continue on.
So the next topic we're going to look at is the integer transform.
So as we have explained earlier on, so for 2.6.4, we use integer transform instead of DCT.
So why do we do that?
Right, so the reason why we use integer transform is that traditionally DCT may cause some prediction shift.
So what it means is that DCT, because it's actually a floating point number, right,
so therefore you actually need to cap it within a certain digit of representation, and this will cause some error.
If you repeat the process many times, because we are doing video compression, you need to compute this DCT many times,
so the error will start to accumulate.
Okay, so that's not good.
Right, so therefore, DCT will cause prediction shift because this floating point calculation and the rounding error will result in this accumulation of error during the transform and the inverse transform process.
Right, and this error can be accumulated because you do the DCT many times.
So therefore, this may result in some larger error towards the end.
Okay, so therefore, for 2.6.4, we use integer transform to address this issue because for 2.6.4, we use integer transform,
whereas the coefficient in your transform matrix is actually integer.
So therefore, you will not have these problems here, and also it's more efficient because you're using computation using integer.
Right, okay, and 2.6.4 will also make use of the quantization scheme with some nonlinear step size.
The step size is actually nonlinear to help to control the rate value later, so later on we'll talk about this point.
Okay, so next let's quickly look at how do we perform integer transform in 2.6.4.
Right, so just a quick recap. So for 2DDCT that we studied before, it can be done using multiplications, can be realized using consecutive 1D transform.
Or in other words, the 2DDCT can be implemented using these equations here.
Okay, so for example, F is your pixel block, in this case for example, the 4 by 4 pixel block,
and if this T is a DCT matrix, therefore in order to obtain the 2DDCT, we just simply need to apply this formula,
and you'll obtain the 2DDCT through the matrix multiplication approach.
Okay, so specifically, if you look at this particular DCT matrix here, this 4 by 4 DCT matrix, right, it can be written in this form here,
whereas this value A here is actually half, this value B here, right, is this, and the value C here is given by this.
So therefore, given A, B and C, you can actually write down this particular 4 by 4 DCT matrix.
Right, okay, so early on, as I mentioned, for this DCT matrix, one of the issues is that it's a floating point number.
So therefore, in our case here, because we want to reduce these accumulations of the floating, you know, rounding error,
and also we want it to be more efficient, so therefore, our aim is to take this 4 by 4 DCT matrix and convert it,
or approximate it using some kind of an integer matrix here.
So how do we do it?
So one way we can simply do it is that we take our 4 by 4 DCT matrix, we multiply with a particular scaling coefficient called alpha,
and we round to the nearest integer, okay, then we'll get this particular matrix.
So this is your transform matrix that you use in the integer transform, okay.
So for this integer transform, the value that we choose for alpha is 2.5, right.
So if we use just now the DCT matrix shown in the previous slide, we multiply with the scaling coefficients of 2.5,
we round to the nearest integer, right, then you can go and check that this is how your matrix looks like.
Okay, so this is the matrix that is used in your integer transform.
So if you look at this particular matrix here, you can see for each of the row here, right, they are actually orthogonal, right.
So that means this vector, you take the dot product within this vector and any of the row vector is actually equal to zero.
So therefore, for different row, right, they are orthogonal, yeah, for different row they are orthogonal.
But if you look at their row, their norm or the length of each of the row vector is different, okay.
So therefore, right, this is one of the properties between different row, they are orthogonal,
but the unit length vector for each of the rows are different, okay.
So this is something that needs to be taken into account later on when we do the quantization.
Okay, so this is what we mentioned here, right, so for each of the row, actually they are orthogonal.
However, each of the row no longer have the same norm, right, some of them is larger, some is smaller.
So therefore, later on we need to somehow handle this, right, such that because each of this particular norm for each of the row are different,
so we need to handle this and how we handle it is we will do it during the quantization step later.
So later on we will see that the normalization step, right, to handle different norm for different row is managed by the quantization step that we will show shortly.
Right, okay, so we have the forward transform, so for the inverse transform, this is the given inverse transform here.
Okay, so next let's see how do we perform this integer transform, right, coupled with scaling and quantization in H.264.
Right, so for H.264, suppose, right, if you remember the block that we used to perform the processing because the most basic block is a 4 by 4 block.
So we will take F, for example, F is a 4 by 4 input matrix, 4 by 4 pixel block, right, okay, and if we call this F cap to be the quantized transform output,
okay, this transform now is the integer transform.
So therefore, the forward transform, how do we do it is that first of all we perform this particular process here.
So this is the 4 by 4 pixel block, so you multiply with H and the H transpose.
So you can see these steps here is actually very similar to your DCT, except now instead of the DCT matrix,
now you are replacing it with this particular integer transform matrix now, okay, H.
Right, okay, and H has been given already.
So after you calculate this, right, so this you can kind of interpret as your integer transform output already, okay.
So for this integer transform output, the next thing is that, right, in the previous MPEG study,
what you do next is that you divide by the quantization matrix Q, yeah, we divide by the quantization matrix Q,
but for H.264, it's common that we represent slightly differently by, you know, showing that you multiply with this matrix MF here, okay,
and then you divide by this scaling coefficient.
So this is, you know, kind of a little bit, okay, in H.264, right, we call this MF the quantization matrix,
but it's actually a little bit different from the quantization matrix that we have in the MPEG.
Okay, so anyway, this part is to perform the integer transform, this part is to perform the quantization,
and afterwards, if you remember, after you perform the quantization, you round it, okay, and then you'll get your quantized transform output.
Okay, so this operator here is the matrix multiplication, this dot here is the element by element multiplication, okay,
and this MF here is actually a 4 by 4 quantization matrix that is, you know, derived from a smaller matrix called M,
and then quantization parameter QP. So later on, we are going to see, right, how this matrix M can be constructed from this matrix M as well as this QP here.
So, but before it, I just want to very quickly draw the attention here, which is --
Okay, so if you refer to this particular equation just now we introduced regarding the integer transform coupled with the quantization scaling in 264,
so you can see this equation, right, is nothing but you have a 4 by 4 pixel block, you take the integer transform, okay,
and afterwards, you multiply with this particular term here. So this particular term here, this term here, you can interpret it almost like, you know,
similar to whatever that you have divided by this quantization matrix, okay. So if you remember the DCT, DCT pretty much is that you have the output, okay,
and then you divide by the quantization matrix, yeah, but for these particular equations here, right, this is your transform output and you multiply with this.
So this term here, this particular M term here, you can kind of think about is the reciprocal of the quantization matrix that we have studied in JPEG as well as the earlier MPEG, yeah.
So, yeah, anyway, this is what the approach they introduced, but I just want to kind of relate, link you back to your previous understanding of what's happening, okay.
So because previously when we studied about JPEG as well as the earlier MPEG, we said after we performed the transform, we divide by the quantization matrix, okay.
I mean this is the, no, I mean the, each individual value we divide by the corresponding quantization step size, yeah, or the matrix.
But for this 2, 6, 4, we represent it in this way here, okay. So therefore the relationship now you can see is actually more like reciprocal.
If this MF is large, then this Q is small, right. If it's Q, if MF is small, then this Q is large. So it's a reciprocal relationship.
So this point I just would like to highlight this so that it probably will be a bit easier for you to understand because you are more comfortable with the output of the quantization divided by some value, right, the quantization step size rather than multiplying with this, okay.
But now with this relationship, right, at least it's easier for you to follow. Okay, so anyway let's just continue.
Right, okay, so next, right, this particular matrix MF, how do we obtain this matrix MF?
So for this matrix MF, okay, if for this quantization parameters here, so this quantization parameter is used to control the bit rate, okay, of your scheme, yeah, if used to control the bit rate of your scheme.
So if the quantization value is large, that means your bit rate will be small, yeah. If the quantization value is small, that means the bit rate will be larger, okay.
So let's look at this particular, right, so anyway this quantization parameter is a parameter to control, as I mentioned, to control the output generated bit rate, okay.
Right, so for the range of quantization parameter between 0 and 6, right, okay, for this matrix here, MF will be given by this table here.
Right, so for this table here, you can see that there are actually three possible entries. One, okay, first of all, it's depending on, each of these values is depending on the quantization parameter Qp, okay.
Each of these entries here, right, depends on Qp and it also depends on the second parameter 0, 1 or 2, right.
So therefore, for each of the entries, okay, in this particular matrix MF, will depend on what is the quantization parameter and also what is this value 0, 1 or 2, okay.
So fortunately, for this particular value here, there's a lookup table. So you can refer to a lookup table to find out exactly what each of these values is, okay.
So this lookup table is given here. So this is the lookup table. So this lookup table, you can see that Qp, right, okay, the Qp value, first of all, for the value between 0 to 5, right, for the corresponding value 0 to 5, these are the corresponding values for these positions here.
So for example, let's take the first example. When Qp is equal to 0, okay, right, you can see the positions at 0, 0, 0, 2, 2, 0 and 2, 2, that means these four values, 1, 2, 3, 4, will be taking this value, okay.
When the value Qp is 0, right, okay, the position at this, no, 1, 1, 1, 1, okay, because the index starts from 0, so 1, 1, 1, 3, okay, 3, 1 and 3, 3 will be taking this value, okay.
And then the rest of them, which is indicated by 2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 2 will be taking this value here, okay.
So therefore, first you identify what is the Qp parameter you decide to choose, yeah, and afterwards, right, by using this lookup table, then you'll be able to fill in the value 0 using this, 1 using this and 2 using this value, okay.
And then using this lookup table, you'll be able to write down, for example, the quantization matrix that correspond to Qp value of 0, okay.
Let's take one more example.
Suppose now, right, you decided to use a quantization parameter of 1, okay, suppose you decided to use 1 now, okay.
So for 1 now, right, so if you choose a value Qp of equal to 1, then these four values, 1, 2, 3, 4, will be taking this value, okay.
Those values that correspond to the second parameter of 1 will take this value and those that correspond to the parameter of 2 will take this value.
So therefore, with that, using this lookup table, you'll be able to write down this particular matrix Mf, okay, for the range from 0 to 6, 0 to 5.
But what if your value Qp is greater than 5?
So if your value Qp is greater than 5, then what you do is that you take each of these corresponding entries, you replace by these particular expressions here.
So these expressions here, these particular notations here is a modulo, right, that means you take the remainder, okay.
So this modulo, you take the remainder and this part here is you divide by 6 and you take the floor, the lower value, right.
So therefore, if the range is greater than 6, each of these values, once you have found it, you just perform this operation and you'll be able to still write down your matrix Mf, okay.
So this is how we generate this Mf here.
Actually, this is a little bit more on the secondary detail.
I mean, if I really want to ask you, I would definitely provide this Mf for you or provide this table for you.
I would not expect you to memorize it because it's just not possible to memorize.
Okay.
So next, so therefore we have already explained, right, so in the 264, when you want to perform the quantized transform coefficient, this is how you do.
You do the transformation, you multiply with this particular matrix, okay, which is equivalent to like you divide by the Q matrix in the previous kind of understanding, right.
You drown it, okay, then your output now will be the quantized transform coefficient, okay.
So now if you want to do the reverse, yeah, to do the reverse is actually very similar, okay.
So now, suppose this is your quantized transform coefficient now, right.
So first thing first, you need to de-quantize it by multiplying with Vi, okay.
So this is the de-quantization.
So after you're performing the de-quantization, then you multiply with the, you know, this particular inverse, okay, inverse matrix here, right.
And then afterwards, you round to the nearest integer, right.
And then you'll be able to obtain your reconstructed pixel block, okay.
So this processes, you know, just a reverse of just now default transform.
Okay, so how now for this equation here, right, we just now the H inverse is already given in the equation, right, the previous slides.
So this Vi here, the de-quantize matrix here, so how do we obtain this de-quantize matrix here?
So Vi is a 4 by 4 de-quantization matrix and it can be again obtained through a lookup table of this V and the quantization parameter, okay.
So let's look at it.
Right, okay, so again this Vi here, similar to just now the Mi, this Vi here, right, you have 4 by 4 entries here.
So for each of this entry here, it depends on two parameters.
What is the quantization parameter Qp and what is the second index, whether it's 0, 1 or 2, okay.
So for the range of Qp between 0 and 6, you can refer to this lookup table here, right.
So for example, let's just take one example here.
When you have a Qp of 0, suppose in a particular compression scheme, right, to compress a certain video, you decide to choose a Qp of 0, yeah.
That means now, okay, we have decided Qp is going to be equal to 0, okay.
So this value that corresponds to 0, the position 0 here, right, will take this value, okay.
Those correspond to 1 as the second index, will take this value.
Those that correspond to 2, right, will take this value here.
So therefore, once you decide what's the Qp value, you'll be able to write down this particular de-quantization matrix, okay.
So likewise, if you decide, for example, if the Qp is equal to say 4, right, therefore 16, 25 and 20 will be used to fill up this table here.
Right, so therefore, what it means is that for Qp value between 0 to 5, you can write down this de-quantization matrix.
If the value is greater than 6 here, then what we need to do is that, right, this, each of this entry that we have obtained earlier is going to be replaced by this, yeah.
So replaced by this means that now your Qp is taking modulo of 6, okay, that means modulo means you take the, divide by 6 and you take the remainder, okay.
Right, and afterwards this term is that Qp, you divide it by 6 and you take the floor, right, okay.
So with this equation, that means no matter what it is, once you decide what is the Qp parameter, that means you decide what is the bit rate you want for this particular compressed video,
then you'll be able to generate this de-quantization matrix.
Okay.
So as I mentioned in, you know, if in the exam or in the quiz, yeah, I would not, you know, kind of, yeah, I would not ask you to memorize all this value.
If there's anything, if I want to ask, I'll provide, you know, the values for you, right, so that you can just compute it directly.
Okay, so now let's take the examples here now.
Right, so the examples now, let's look at this, for example, right, we start off with the Qp parameter of 0 and then later on we're going to see what is the effect when we change different Qp parameters here.
Suppose we start with the Qp parameter of 0, right, so now for the Qp parameter of 0, once we decide the Qp parameter, that means we decide, we can write down our quantization matrix Mf, okay.
So we can write down this Mf here from just now the lookup table.
Right, suppose the current block that we are considering is this particular 4 by 4 pixel block, right, you go through this particular quantization matrix in 264, alright, okay, and afterwards we use this formula to do the calculation, you will see that this is your quantized transform coefficient.
So afterwards, during the inverse process, we use this equation to calculate, right, so again, given the Qp parameter, that means we can write down this Vi matrix just now from the lookup table, right.
So afterwards we have this formula here, right, we have the quantized transform coefficient, right, we have this Vi, we can go through the calculation and we'll then obtain your reconstructed pixel block.
So now if we compare our original pixel block and the reconstructed pixel block, you will see that the error in this case is 0, they are all 0, okay, so this is what we have.
So you can see that when your quantization parameters is actually 0, right, so when your quantization parameter is 0, your error is small.
So, okay, we can just continue on with a few and afterwards we'll try to draw some conclusions, okay.
So now, suppose we choose a quantization parameter of 6, right, so if we choose a quantization parameter of 6, that means we can write down this matrix, okay, MF and this inverse matrix Vi, okay.
Right, so suppose now same pixel block as before, right, going through just now the equation, we can obtain the quantized transform coefficient.
So given the quantized transform coefficient together with the quantization matrix, we can reconstruct our pixel block.
So now if we compare this to original pixel block and your reconstructed pixel block, okay, you can see that now the error is becoming a bit bigger, okay.
So you can see now when your quantization parameter is 6, your error starts to increase.
Okay, let's continue one more before we try to draw the conclusion.
Now if our QP parameter is 30, right, if our QP parameter is 30, from just now the process we mentioned, I know it's a bit cumbersome for you to see now,
but if you go through the motion, you can actually write down your MF matrix and the Vi matrix here, okay.
Right, so now, okay, again, given this same pixel block, going through the same process, just now using the equation, we can calculate your quantized transform coefficient.
From this quantized transform coefficient, using the formula, we can calculate your reconstructed pixel block.
If you compare, you'll see that this is the error now, okay.
So what do you notice as you increase the quantization parameter, what do you notice in terms of the error, the reconstructed error?
You see quite obviously as you increase this QP parameter here, the error will start to increase, right.
So why is it the case?
Okay, so we can see earlier on we say that QP is a parameter to control the bit rate of a generated video, right, so it's a parameter for us to control.
Okay, so now another thing you notice is that as QP is becoming larger, say suppose you go down this, as QP becomes larger,
the values in this matrix here actually become smaller, correct.
If you go down the row, as QP becomes larger from 0, 1, 2, 3, the values in each of these entries here actually become smaller, right.
So that means as QP becomes larger, okay, the value in M becomes smaller.
If the value in M becomes smaller, that means the value in Q becomes larger.
This Q is the traditional quantization step size that you have studied in JPEG, right.
So as your QP becomes larger, go down the table, as it becomes larger from 0 to 5, the value in M becomes smaller.
If the value in M becomes smaller, that means your traditional quantization step size will become larger, right.
So, right, if you remember just last time when we studied in JPEG standard, if the quantization step size becomes larger, what will happen?
In the JPEG compression, if your quantization step size becomes larger, what will happen?
To the quality of your reconstructed video.
If your quantization step size becomes larger, that means your quantization error would be larger,
that means actually your reconstructed error will be larger as well, correct.
So that's why you can see just now, as your QP increased from 0 to 5, for example, your M value becomes smaller,
going down this table you can see it becomes smaller, that means your step size in Q becomes larger.
And the step size becomes larger, that means your reconstructed error will become larger, just like what you have studied in JPEG.
And when this Q becomes larger, the quantization step size becomes larger, that means the reconstruction error will increase, correct.
But the bit rate would decrease.
So this is, therefore, it's just in terms of this particular notation, right, because somehow in 264 they use this MF notation as compared to this Q notation.
Therefore, you can see by changing this particular value QP here, you can control, you can do a trade-off between the bit rate that you generate versus the error that you have.
So when your QP increased, just now, you can see from this particular video, this particular result here,
when your QP increased from 0 to 6 to 30, you can see that the corresponding error quantization, the error will start to increase.
But the advantage that you obtain is that the bit rate will start to reduce, so you have a smaller file size, or your bit rate is lower.
So therefore, this QP parameter is a parameter, user-designed parameter, you can decide for your application what is a suitable value you want to choose to achieve your target bit rate.
Right, so let's continue.
So the next thing we are going to look at is the intra-coding.
So we are going to look at the coding of the intra-frame here.
So for the intra-coding of 264, the intra-coded macro block are predicted using some neighboring reconstructed pixel block.
So this one we are going to see how is it a little bit different from the previous JPEG as well as the MPEG 1 and 2.
Because it uses neighboring pixels to help to do the prediction.
So later on we will see. And then also for the intra-coding under 264, it can use different prediction blocks, for example 4 by 4, 16 by 16.
For 4 by 4 blocks here, there is a 9 prediction mode, and for 16 by 16 there is a 4 prediction mode.
So later on we will see a little bit more about what is the basic idea behind this intra-coding of 264.
But let's try to go through some of this particular text information first.
And then later on when we come to the slide, the slide will be a lot easier to understand.
So for each of the prediction modes, the predicted values and the actual values will be compared to produce the prediction error.
So for example this is a current 4 by 4 block that we want to encode in iFrame.
We use a neighboring pixel to do the prediction. So we use a neighboring pixel to do the prediction.
So once you have done the prediction, then the predicted value and the actual value, that means the error or the prediction error,
you will be able to obtain the prediction error or the residue.
So the mode that generates the smallest error or residue will be chosen as a prediction mode for this block.
And afterwards this residue is then sent to the integer transform for the transformation.
From this particular write-up it may be a bit harder for you to understand, but it's easiest if you try to look at some of these particular slides here.
It can make the understanding a lot easier to understand.
So for example, in this 264, if you want to encode an iFrame, you can partition into many different block structures.
But one of the most basic block structures that you have is the 4 by 4 block.
So we are going to use the 4 by 4 block as an example because there are a few different variations.
So we're going to use this 4 by 4 block as an example here.
Suppose if you want to encode this 4 by 4 block here, what do we do?
So what we do is that we make use of some neighbouring pixels for this 4 by 4 block here.
So these are some neighbouring pixels here, some neighbouring pixels, centered at this 4 by 4 block here.
Afterwards, we'll use this different direction as a prediction to see what would be the predicted value for this 4 by 4 pixel block here.
So suppose if you use a mode of zero, that means if you want to find out what are the values here, we'll use this pixel A to predict all these values here, if you're using mode zero here.
So for mode zero, you can see our prediction is in this vertical direction here.
So to predict all the values, these four values here, we use A to predict these four values.
We use B to predict these four values, we use C to predict this and D to predict this.
And afterwards, we take this actual pixel value minus the prediction that would give you the prediction error for mode zero.
So later on we'll have some examples, it will become a lot clearer.
So if we use mode one, mode one you can see is horizontal, that means we use this pixel value, the neighbouring pixel value to predict the four pixel values in this block here.
So you use I to predict this, J to predict this, K to predict this and L to predict this.
So once you do the prediction, you have the actual pixel value and you have the prediction, you take that difference, then you can get the prediction value for mode one.
So you're going to go through all these different modes.
So for different modes, you're going to get different predicted values.
So for each of the predicted values, you're going to get the different prediction error.
And afterwards, you're going to see which of these modes gives the best prediction or the smallest prediction error.
Then you're going to say that, okay, the particular mode that gives us the smallest error, that is the one we're going to use as a prediction.
So therefore, you can see in this intra-coding, the basic idea is that instead of, if you remember previously in JPEG,
what we do is that we partition into numerous, this 8 by 8 pixel block and then we kind of more or less encode it independently.
But in this particular case now, for 264, we are using the neighbouring pixel to guess what this kind of pixel is first.
And then get the error, the prediction error, and then only afterwards, we go through the transform.
So this is the main idea. That means we try to do the prediction first by using this direction.
So you can see a different directional spatial prediction.
So that's why this is the name. Direction, because you can see you have different direction.
And spatial, because the prediction is in the space domain.
So it's a directional spatial prediction.
So more specifically, just now you can see we have these eight directions here.
Actually, the mode, they are all together nine modes of them.
So there are nine intra 4 by 4 prediction mode for this H.264 intra-coding.
So early on, for example, if you look at mode zero, it's a vertical.
That means we use, this is the 4 by 4 block that we want to encode.
We use the four pixels above it, A, B, C, D, to predict their value.
And afterwards, we can then get the prediction error.
So this is if you use mode zero, we call it vertical.
If we use mode one, horizontal, that means if this is the block we want to encode,
we take the four pixel value next to it, we predict the value for each of this row.
Afterwards, you'll be able to compute the prediction error using mode one.
For mode two here, you're using this four eight pixel value, A, B, C, D, I, J, K, L.
You take the average of this eight pixel value.
So this average value will be the predictor for all this pixel value within here.
And afterwards, you can then get the prediction error for this.
So therefore, you can actually go through all these different nine modes here.
And you'll be able to actually get the eight, all these nine different prediction error.
And then the one that gives you the smallest prediction error, you're going to use the particular mode.
And afterwards, you're going to let it go through the integer transform to transform this particular prediction error.
So that is the high level message.
So again, by just looking at that, it may be a little bit unclear what exactly does it mean.
So the best way to understand is go through one example.
Because once you have one example, if you can understand, that means you actually understand what it's trying to say already.
Okay, so let's look at this particular exercise here.
So this exercise here says that let's consider a simplified H.264 4x4 intra-coding.
So the coding is for the 4x4 block, is for the intra-coding, for the intra-frame.
That use only mode zero, mode one, and mode two.
The original actually had nine, but to make this particular example simpler,
we'll only be focusing on this mode zero, one, and two, to make it easier.
So we'll only be focusing on these three modes here.
And afterwards, it says that, okay, no, assume...
Assume we have this particular 8x8 image here.
It asks you to find the smallest prediction error for the indicated 4x4 pixel block.
So suppose now you have this particular image here.
This is the current 4x4 pixel block we are focusing on.
So it asks you to find the smallest prediction error for this particular 4x4 pixel block using these three different modes here.
Let's give it a try.
Use these three different modes that I explained to you before, mode zero, one, and two,
and try to find the smallest prediction error for this 4x4 pixel block.
[silence]
So therefore if you look at this particular result here, so you can see therefore if you're using mode 0, the vertical predictions,
right, you can see the prediction now is the first column is all 70, right, second column is 70, 90, 90, right?
So that's a prediction. And afterwards, what is the error? So the error is that you simply take the original value minus your predicted value.
So for example, 80 minus 70 will give you 10, okay? 90 minus 70 will give you 20. So if you do that, you'll be able to get the prediction error using mode 0.
So for mode 1, we are going to use now horizontal. That means this row, we are going to predict using 60. So the first row is all 60,
second row is 60, third row is 80, okay? Last row is 80. So this is our prediction. Afterwards, we take the actual block minus predicted block,
we get our error, okay? So that's mode 2. That's mode 1. Mode 2, we'll take the average, right, the average of this 4 plus this 4, 8 pixel value.
So if you want to calculate the error, you just take the calculation, you'll see it's 75. So therefore, our predictor, our prediction is actually a block of 75.
If you want to calculate the error, you just take this block minus this block and you'll get the prediction error here.
So therefore, now for three different modes, you'll get three different predictions, right? So this prediction is in the form of a matrix, okay?
A matrix like this. Right, so the question actually asks next, right, find the least prediction error block, okay, for this 4 by 4 pixel block.
That means in this simple example, we're only going to look at this three mode and see which is the one that gives you the smallest error.
So in order to find which is the one that gives you the smallest error, you need to define what's the matrix you're using, right?
So the matrix to define this in our example here is we'll be using the sum of absolute error.
Okay, that means each of these terms here, we take its absolute value, we sum it up, okay? We take its absolute value, we sum up all these values, right?
So, okay, because all these numbers are positive, right, in the case, for example, some of the numbers are negative, you just take the absolute first.
If it's negative 5, take the absolute, it becomes 5, and then you sum up all of them. Right, so if you do that, right, by doing that,
you'll be able to see that, okay, which is the one that gives you the smallest error. So as I mentioned, sum of absolute error means that you take the absolute value of each of these terms,
and afterwards you sum them up, right? Then you'll get the sum of absolute error for mode 0, mode 1, and for mode 2.
So, right, if you go through the exercise for this, you'll see that the one that gives you the smallest error is actually mode 0.
Okay, so this is the one that gives you the smallest error. Okay, so therefore we answer the question, the smallest prediction error is actually this block here.
Right, so in this case, a prediction error is actually a block or a matrix. Okay, so let's continue.
Okay, next it says that, right, we already found the prediction error just now, okay, right, it says that this prediction error is going to be passed through the integer transform,
okay, given by this particular matrix here. Okay, so ask you to find the output of the integer transform. Okay, so output of the integer transform.
So you already obtained the prediction error. Now you are supposed to let it go through the integer transform to get the transform output of this prediction error.
Right, so let's give it a try, okay, to calculate this, to perform this transform.
Okay, I'll show you this intermediate result because you need the intermediate result.
So the intermediate result just now, we already see that this is the smallest prediction error.
One is the one with the smallest prediction error.
Okay.
Okay, so anyway, I think that part is just a matter of some familiarization because I think the steps are quite straightforward.
So therefore, what you need to do is now that, okay, so for you to obtain the integer transform, this is the formula we'll be using, okay, similar to the DCT,
except for this matrix H now is actually given by this particular integer matrix here, okay.
Right, so next, right, so we just need to do the multiplication. So for the solutions here, first of all, you multiply these two, okay,
this matrix H together with this to get the result, the intermediate result, and then this intermediate result, you multiply with this H transpose.
And if you go through the calculation, you'll see that this is the result that we have, okay.
So this is the result for this part here. So that's pretty much the answer to this question.
So from this particular question, you already can see that, right, the idea of using these three different modes.
Okay, I think the high-level idea already mentioned is that for this 264, the intra-coding, we make use of the neighboring values,
because since they are there, we should try to leverage on the information.
And then, but which way is the best, right, we have nine different schemes to come up with it, okay.
So what we'll do is that for each of these nine schemes, right, we'll try to see which one gives us the smallest prediction error,
and this smallest prediction error will then go through the integer transform. So that's the basic idea.
And the exercise actually only focuses on these three different modes, yeah, but in the rear H.264 for 4x4 mode, actually there are nine different modes like this.
Right, okay, so I think, yeah, okay, maybe I'll just quickly go through this particular question, and then you can think about it at home, yeah,
and illustrate today, the solution today. So the next exercise is on the integer transform for P-frame coding, yeah.
So it says that for P-frame coding, right, in 264, right, you'll be using the integer transform.
So in this particular example here, right, we'll, okay, assume that using this simple operations here, this transform operations here, right,
and the matrix, the integer DCT matrix is given here, okay. So it asks you to find out what is the two advantages of using integer transform as compared to DCT, yeah.
Right, and afterwards, okay, the next part is that they assume that, okay, so the target frame is a P, assume the target frame below is a P-frame, okay,
and this is part of the, okay, so this is the target frame, and we are only focusing on this particular 4x4 macro block here.
So, okay, so this is our target frame, and this is a P-frame, okay, and then afterwards we assume that the macro block we are looking at is only this 4x4 block here, okay.
So they ask you to find out, okay, for this particular current macro block here, what is the motion vector, okay.
So this is the target frame, and this is the reference frame. So you're supposed to find out what's the motion vector, right.
So afterwards, you're supposed to find out, okay, what is the corresponding, in this particular equation here, what is this corresponding item that it should correspond to, okay.
And then afterwards, what is the output of this particular transform, okay.
So pretty much these questions for P-frame encoding, right, so this current target frame, you're only looking at one particular 4x4 pixel block, right,
so you're supposed to do the motion estimation, right, to find out what's the motion vector.
Once you've found the motion vector, you're supposed to find out what is the predicted error, okay, what's the prediction error, okay, or what's the difference.
And afterwards, once you've found the difference, you're supposed to actually do the integer transform, okay.
So that's pretty much what this question is asking about.
Okay, I think we'll probably go through the answer next week, right, we'll call it a day. I'll see you next week. Okay, bye-bye.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
[ Silence ]