Good morning. Can you hear me?
Okay, great. Right. So, yeah, just want to make sure that everything is in order before
we start the class today. So let me just quickly check through the setting because there has
been some time since we conduct a class in using Zoom. So let me just check the settings.
Everything is proper. Okay, so yeah, just for your information. So, yeah, first, can
you see the share screen? Okay, good. Right. So these lectures will be recorded. So at the
end of the lectures, I will try to post this recorded lecture online. Yeah, just for your
information. So before that, yeah, since we are going to conduct the quiz, yeah, in RIP
10, so I thought it's important that we go through this announcement again, right, in
the event some student missed it. Right. So the first thing is that, okay, so this quiz
will be conducted on week 10, right, which is the 24th of October at 8pm. Right. So, yeah,
so in the on the day, right, we will conduct the lecture for about one hour and then you
have a break and then followed by the quiz. So the venue is in this little chain LT. Right.
So the top cover is part three and four. Okay, so on the day, make sure that you bring along
your student card because we are going to take the attendance. And if for whatever reason,
you are absent, yeah, please try to know a semi-email, right. And then let me know why
you are absent. And then if the reason is valid, then we'll arrange a make up for you.
Right. Okay, so this is the class list. Right. As I mentioned a couple of times, but just
remind you one more time is that please check your name against the serial number. Okay, because
when on the answer sheet itself, you need to write down your serial number. Right. So this is
to make it much easier for me to take that attendance as well as to tell you the answer
straight at the end. Right. So this is a sample cover page of the question booklet. Right. So
you have this serial number that you need to indicate here and then write down your full name
as well as the matriculation number. And then there will also be, you know, at the bottom,
there will be some spaces reserved for you to write your answer. Okay. So the quiz will consist of a
few questions. Right. So there will be some calculation question. There will be some question
where you have to answer some, you know, descriptive parts and so on. So it's a combination of some
calculation as well as the descriptive questions. Right. Okay. So because this year your class is
quite big, so we are going to conduct the quiz in this, the Ligong chain LT. So I've decided to
arrange a sitting in such a way based on your serial number. Right. So for a student with a
serial number from one to 100, you'll be seated in this section. 101 to 200 will be in this section.
Okay. 201 to 300 will be here. Okay. 301 to 410 will be here and 411 to 517 will be here. So on the
day they try to sit, you know, based on this, you know, this sitting arrangement so that it will
make our, this answer script collection as well as attendance marking much more efficient.
Right. Okay. So that's all this information is already given in under the content folder,
right, under this C2 quiz folder in the course site. So if you cannot remember all those information,
just need to go to the course site and all those information are there.
Right. Okay. Are there any questions so far regarding the quiz arrangement?
Okay. So if there's no questions, then we'll continue.
Right. So let me just close this.
Okay. So again, before I continue, just want to make sure that can all of you see the,
no, this share screen, the lecture notes share screen.
Okay. Right.
So, okay. So someone in the chat box mentioned what are our questions in the piece. So as I
mentioned, right, there'll be a few questions. So it'll be a combinations of some calculation
question as well as some question that will be you have to know write down some short answer.
So a combination of calculation and descriptive questions. Yeah.
So the sample is kind of a little bit similar to some of the sample examples that we have
kind of a share in the lectures.
Okay. So please try not to change the caption language to others. So we'll use the English
caption. All right. Because this is a English lesson. So we have to use the English
caption because I see that some, some of you actually change it to other languages.
Okay. So, right. Okay. Let me just check one more time because I remember,
no, in some of the early years, there was a lecture, the lecture keep talking until the end
they find that the student cannot hear, right, or the student cannot see the share screen.
Okay. So just check one more time. So can all of you see the share screen on the lecture notes?
Okay. Please let me know in the chat box because that's been quite some time since I use it.
Can you see the share screen on the lecture notes? Okay. Yeah. Thank you.
Right. Okay. Then let's start the lecture today. If you managed to finish earlier,
no, that would be good for everyone. We will have a glorious Saturday afternoon.
Okay. So in last lectures, actually, we introduced the concepts of this
and so we are going to continue on to talk about the training and optimizations of the INM.
Right. Okay. So the basic ideas of the trainings of this
INM is very similar to that of CNN. So just a quick recap of what we discussed before
about CNN. So when you train a new network, the objective is actually try to minimize or
optimize a loss function. So the other day, actually, I give you this visualization. I say
it's that suppose let's assume for one moment that this network only has two parameters, right,
for simplicity. So suppose this is the X1 and X2 parameter. So you have those X1 and X2 parameter.
So at each of the parameters, then you have a loss. Yeah. You have a particular
loss function. Okay. So therefore, for different parameter value, right, this loss can be
visualized as a landscape mountain of valley. So when we start training the network, we do not
know where it is. So let's say that, no, we start off at a position there and then this is corresponding
loss. Yeah. So our goal here is to reach the minimum. So what we do, the strategy is very
intuitive and simple, which is we look around, okay, and then we try to find the direction of
the steepest distance. Right. So suppose this is the direction of the steepest distance,
then we'll try to walk, okay, a certain distance, right, based on which is controlled by the
learning rate to the next position. And then once you reach this position, you look around,
okay, suppose this is the direction of the steepest distance, then you just walk in this
direction. So you continue repeatedly until you reach the local minimum. So this is the idea
that we introduced on stochastic gradient descent. So this approach is known as a stochastic gradient
descent. All right. So in order to train it, we need to build a computational graph, right, and then
we'll try to generate the gradient and then we'll just go through the strategy that I've mentioned
to you to update the parameter. Okay. So for, and it's based on the similar strategy.
Right. Okay. So let's try to see how we can build a simple computational graph for this
and now. So, right. So first of all, we start off with our initial memory or hidden state,
right. Okay. And then we have our current input. So based on the particular mapping,
those two equations that we have mentioned before to generate the next memory, then we can actually
generate the next memory at the time step h1. Okay. So this formula to recap is given by this
equation here. So by applying this equation, you can find out your current memory from your previous
memory as well as the current input. Right. So therefore, based on your previous,
to calculate your current memory at each one, you make use of your previous memory h0 as well as
your current input, you go through just now the particular mathematical operation, you'll get your
h1. Okay. And then if you want to get h2, then you repeat the same process. Right. So you take
your previous memory h1, you take your current input h2, you go through just now the mathematical
operation, which is the linear, you know, just on that, yeah, the equation I shared with you,
you'll get your h2. So of course, you can repeat that, you know, for a number of steps, then you'll
be able to generate your h3 and so on and so forth until you're in ht. Right. So this is how you
actually generate the hidden state or memory at different time steps. So one thing to take note
of is that in the process of doing this particular generating different memory at different time
steps, the equations or the formula that you're using here, you're using the same
weight matrix. Okay. The weight matrix that you have from the hidden state to the hidden state,
as well as from the input to the hidden state. Right. Which is, you know, jointly described by
this big W matrix here. Right. We use the same matrix at different time steps. Okay. So that's
one thing that you want, probably want to take note of. So you can see the comment here is that
we'll reuse the same weight matrix at every time step. Okay. So now let's continue. Okay. So now
that once we have got the memory at different time steps, then what we can do is that we can use it
to generate different output at time step y1, y2, y3, and so on and so forth. Okay. So this is your
generated output here. So now if you compare your generated or predicted output with the ground truth,
okay. So at each time step, you have the ground truth. So if you compare your predicted value
with the ground truth, then at each time step, you have an error function or loss function. So this
error function we call it, for example, at time step one, we call it L1. At time step two, we call
L2 and so on and so forth. So now at different time step, at each time step, we have a particular loss.
So for this loss, if you add them up together, then this is the total loss. So this total loss now
is the summations of individual loss. Right. And then our goal, right, we are trying to train this
network is that we want to optimize or we want to minimize this particular loss function, right.
We respect to this particular weight parameters. Okay. So we want to minimize this loss by adjusting
the parameter W here. And this particular parameter W, as I have indicated a few times,
are the parameters that you have here. Okay, WHH, WXH as well as the WYH. So those are the
parameters that you need to train. Right.
Right. Okay. So now when you do the training, there's actually a few different strategies. So when we
are doing the training, actually, you have many, many different sequences. You have many sequence,
input sequence and the ground truth, input sequence and ground truth. So you have many,
many different input sequence together with the ground truth here. So when you do the training,
there's a few different strategies you can do the training. So one way is that we can use a strategy
known as a full batch training. That means we take all the sequences and then train together in one
goal. So if you make use of the entire sets of the training sequence at each iteration,
then this is known as a full batch strategy. Okay. So now if you try to visualize this particular
diagram here, for this particular diagram here, all these lines here indicate the loss function
with the same value. Right. Okay. Again, we are assuming that in this simple illustration,
there are two parameters on the X1 and X2. So at this graph here, actually are connecting all those
points of X1 and X2 that has the same loss value or same error value here. Okay. So for example,
the next contour will be connecting all the points that have the same error function or
loss value here. Okay. So now we assume that this point is actually the local meaning.
So suppose if we are starting from a random point somewhere here, if you use a strategy of a full
batch, that means we take all the sequence and train it at each iteration, then we'll see that
actually the loss function will start to decrease quite smoothly until you reach somewhere close to
the minimum. So that's known as a full batch strategy. So as opposed to full batch strategy,
for each training, you can also choose to use one sequence at a time to do the training.
So if you only choose to use one sequence to do the training one at a time, then this is known as
a stochastic approach. So for stochastic approach, suppose we are starting, this is our starting point.
So you can see in the process of reaching this global meaning is actually very erratic.
Okay. It'll go through many different erratic until you reach this minimum.
Right. Okay. And then as a trade off between the full batch and the stochastic batch,
you have what's known as a mini batch. So mini batch as the name suggests,
that means you take a few sequence at the same time. So you take a few sequence to do
training at each iteration. So now for this mini batch strategy, we can kind of visualize,
suppose this is our starting point, right? We're trying to move towards the minima.
Right. So it's not as erratic as this single sequence, but it's not as smooth as this full
batch as well. So it's a compromise in between. Right. So usually we want to use as many sequence
to train in one go as possible. But what the limitation is depends on the memory storage
of your GPU. Your GPU may not be able to take such a big batch. So therefore, even though we want to
use as many sequence, our batch size, you want to be using as large as possible, but often is
limited by the memory of your GPU devices. Okay. So next, let's continue with the training strategy.
Right. So let's look at this particular diagram here. So for these diagrams here, we can see that
actually this red boxes here is your input. The green boxes here is your unend of the memory.
Okay. And then this blue box here is the output. Right. So during the training strategy, so what
we can see is that as our input, okay, start to go into our network and okay, we'll start to generate
the output at different time steps. Okay. So you generate the output. So suppose just now early on
from the diagram, you can see at every time step, at every time step, you're going to generate a loss.
So therefore, the total loss will be the submissions of all these losses. Okay. So therefore, when you
do the training, when you want to do the training, first of all, you must provide all the input, okay,
which is indicated by this particular great, great error here. Okay. You generate all the output.
Right. So and then this output will calculate the loss. After this loss would then be back
propagated. Okay. In this reverse directions here as indicated by this grid line here. So this
loss function will then be back propagated to update all those with power. Okay. So that's the
basic idea. So therefore, it takes this name called back propagation through time. So the training
idea is back propagation through time, because you can see that it's back propagation, but it's
two different time steps here. Okay. So that's why this is called back propagation through time
learning strategy. So, but if you look at this particular back propagation through time strategy,
you'll see that there's actually, if you think about it, there's actually a limitation or disadvantage
of this particular strategy. Can anyone think about it? What's the problem with or issue with
this particular strategy? Anyone, if you have some thought or some comment, you can enter in the chat
box. Okay. So yeah, vanishing gradient is true is one issue if the sequence is very long. Yeah.
Okay. But in the, in this particular steps here, one thing that I want to highlight is that,
okay, if again, if your sequence is long, if before you can generate this output, you can see
that it would take a long time for you to actually generate the output. Okay. Okay. To find about the
loss before you manage to do the back propagation. In short, right, this, if you just simply use this
strategy or back propagation through time, that means you have to wait for a long time to generate
all the output before you can do the back propagation. So this potentially could be very slow.
So therefore, one way to mitigate this issue that you need to wait for a long time before you can
generate your final output is that we are going to use a strategy known as, let me see the children
next slide, known as a truncated back propagation through time. Okay. So the idea of a truncated
back propagation through time is actually quite intuitive. So as the name suggests truncate,
means that you just chop it up into different blocks or pieces. So what we do is that when we
use this truncated back propagation through time strategy, we are going to take this sequence,
we are going to chop it into pieces. For example, we are going to chop it into the first chunk
of the data. So we'll go through these pieces of the training data to generate the output and then
calculate the loss. And then afterwards, this particular loss will do the back propagation
through this chunk of the data. Okay. Right. So and then afterwards, we are going to continue on,
we are going to take the memory that is the hidden state that we calculated, we're going to
know kind of continue on to bring it forward. And then next, we're going to take the next
chunk of the data, okay, do it the forward direction to generate the output compared to the
ground truth to calculate the loss. And then this loss would then be back propagated again to update
the parameter. Okay. So therefore, this idea actually is quite intuitive. Pretty much just
what it means is that you have a long sequence of training data. So we are going to chop it
into different chunks. So at each chunk, we are going to do the training. Okay. At each
chunk, we're going to do the training so that this particular update can be more efficient.
So this strategy is known as the truncated back propagation through time.
Right. Okay. So the next each topic issue that we are going to talk about is this
exploding and vanishing gradient problem that some of you have highlighted here.
Okay. So next, let's look at this particular INN
you know, kind of a model. See, actually this particular diagram here, it looks a little bit
complicated, but actually it's nothing but just that INN cell that we have mentioned before.
Right. So each of these is a know an INN cell at different time steps here. So if you just take
one and quickly explain. So what you have, for example, if you want to get our hidden state at
H1, we take our previous memory, okay, at H0, current input at X1, you stack them together into a
long factor, you multiply with this matrix W. So this matrix W is actually consisting of the
WHH and the WXH. Right. Okay. And then afterwards, after this multiplication, we let it go through
the 10H function, then you will be able to generate your memory, right, your H1. And then this particular
memory can then go through the particular matrix W, HY to generate your output at time step one.
Okay. So therefore this particular cell, the operation is what we have studied already. Yeah,
it just looks a little bit complicated, but it's exactly the same. Right. So you have different
INN cells at different times that X1, X2, X3 and so forth. Right. Okay. So for this particular
site here, the topic that we are trying to highlight is this the vanish exploding or vanishing gradient
issue. Right. Okay. So first of all, right, let's look at what is the loss. So the loss,
right, for when we want to do the training of the INN, the loss as we have seen before is actually
the summations of all the different time steps. Okay. And for each time steps that individual loss,
right. Okay. So the loss is actually consisting of individual loss at different time steps. We
sum it up. So afterwards, when we want to differentiate this total loss with respect to this
weight parameter, those are the parameters that we want to do the training. So we perform the
partial derivative here. So you differentiate, then this is what you're going to obtain.
Okay. So now in particular, we are going to look at, for example, the partial derivative for the
last term. Okay. Differentiate LT respect to this W here. So this LT is a loss at the last
time steps here. So if you go through some mathematical manipulation, right, you can
actually derive it and see it arrive at this particular results here. So in this particular
results here, one term that is, that we need to further explain and explore is this matrix terms
here. So this matrix terms is WHH. Okay. You multiply it by T minus one times here. So you
multiply T minus one times here. And this particular matrix here, okay, WHH, actually
for those of you, if you have studied linear algebra before, you know that you can perform
a singular value decomposition, right, to decompose it into three matrices. If you perform
this singular value decomposition here, then one of the matrix inside will have some singular value.
Okay. Because this course is not about linear algebra, so we are not going to go into the
details, but I just want to give you some high level intuition. So this particular matrix WHH,
you can perform, you know, this singular value decomposition. And then in this singular
value decomposition, there's one particular matrix that will consist of what is known as a
singular value. Okay. So one of the properties of this particular singular value is that,
right, okay. So this singular value, you can kind of think about it, is can either be greater than
one or less than one. So what will happen if the singular value is greater than one, right? So when,
if there's a singular value is greater than one, right, that means when this particular matrix here,
you multiply, you multiply itself by T minus one times, that means it's actually an exponential
function. You keep multiplying. So it's a value, for example, if the singular value, let's take
an example, suppose it's like two. So if two multiplied by two multiplied by two, if you keep
multiplying many, many times, because this value T is very large, then you can see the value is going
to start to increase and explode. So this is known as the exploding gradient. Right. So in other words,
if this particular matrix WHH is singular value, no, is greater, the largest singular value is
greater than one. Okay. And if you keep multiplying many times, then the gradient will start to explode.
Right. So this is non ideal. Okay. So can you develop some strategy to handle it? So the answer is
actually yes. You can do that. So for exploding gradient problem, what you can do is you can
perform a gradient clipping. So when you detect that the gradient is actually become very large,
you just click at the maximum value. So that's a strategy that you can use to handle this
exploding gradient problem. So, but on the other hand, this particular
time that we have just now, right, if our largest singular value is less than one.
So when the largest singular value is less than one, for example, is 0.5. Okay. So now,
this singular value, you're going to multiply, okay, you're going to multiply by itself. Okay.
Many, many times. So it's like 0.5, multiply by 0.5, multiply by 0.5. Right. So after a while,
you can see that you are going to know the value is going to decay exponentially decay very quickly.
So this particular effect is known as the vanishing gradient. Right. The means of gradient is going
to decrease very, very quickly. So when your gradient is going to decrease very quickly,
so what it means is that suppose if you have, for example, iron and car model, that's many
different time steps. So in theory, even though we say that, right, the memory at the much later,
the memory at the later time step, what depends on the input from all the current input as well as
the past input, even though in theory, that's the case, but in practice, because of this vanishing
gradient problems, that means the input in the very long past actually has no impact,
right. It's partly because of this vanishing gradient problem. So for this vanishing gradient
problem, it turns out that there's no effective way you can handle this. Yeah. So because there's
no effective way we can address this vanishing gradient problem, therefore, what we have to do
is that we have to change our iron and mortar architecture. So that actually provides us with
the motivation to look into the next types of extensions of the iron and mortar, which is known
as LSTM. Right. So some of you, if you have studied this AI model that handles sequential data,
you probably heard about this model before. So LSTM stands for long shutter memory.
Okay. So our next topic, therefore, we are going to study about this LSTM model.
Right. So what's the basic architectures of LSTM model? So this is the basic architectures of LSTM
model. So again, at first glance, it looked a little bit complicated, but don't worry. Later,
we're going to explain it in a systematic manner, right. And then you'll be able to see,
and explain this LSTM model. Okay. So we're just going to leave this for the time being. Later on,
we'll explain this based on the formula, because in order to understand LSTM, one of the easiest
ways is to understand from the mathematical operation perspective. And after we come back to
look at this cell, it will become quite easy to understand. Okay. So let's look at some key ideas
of this LSTM. Right. So again, we put the LSTM cell structures or architectures next to it.
And then we also put down the defining equations. So these are the key equations that describe an
LSTM. Right. So let's look at what it is. So first of all, for this LSTM here, right, there's a few
key concept or idea. So an LSTM, right, it has a long-term memory cell that can retain its state
over time. So one of the advantages of LSTM compared to RN is that it can retain long-term memory.
Okay. It can retain long-term memory. So we are going to see how it can achieve that. Right. So for
LSTM, it has this, what we know as a cell state, okay, CT, a hidden state, HT, and then there's four
gates here, which is known as IFOG. Okay. I is input gate, F is forget gate, O is output gate,
and G is a gate gate. Anyway, it will be explained later on. So for LSTM, it has this cell state,
okay, CT, hidden state, HT, and four gates here. And what is this cell state here, CT? So this cell
state here, CT is also known as a long-term memory. Okay. So CT is long-term memory.
And HT is interpreted as a short-term memory. Okay. So HT is a short-term memory here.
Right. So next, let's look at this particular equation. So we'll pause here for one moment,
and then later we'll cover the rest of the points here. So let's look at this particular set of
equations now. Right. So first of all, this HT minus one just means that the previous
short-term memory, okay. So the previous short-term memory at times that T minus one, okay, so which
is actually a vector. And then afterwards you have this particular HT, which is your current input
HT, right. So you can concatenate them together to form a long vector now. Okay. So you have this
long vector. And afterwards you multiply with this W matrix here. So this particular W matrix is
actually a bigger matrix that can be further divided into four sub-matrices as we'll see later.
Okay. So this big matrix, yeah. Okay. So this big matrix W can be divided in, you can kind of think
about it, can be decomposed into four sub-matrices here. One is corresponding to the IE.
Is it already a question? Yes. I can hear someone talking. Is there some issue?
Okay. I assume there's no issue. Right. Okay. So this particular big matrix W can be divided into
four sub-matrices. One for each of these gate, IFOG. I think someone probably forgot to mute your
okay. Probably let me just mute one.
Right. Okay. I think it's mine now.
Right. Okay. Maybe we did this too many times already. So this matrix W can be divided into
four sub-matrices that correspond to this IFOG gate here. Okay. And afterwards, so what we have
is that we have this particular factor concatenated and then we have this big W matrix that is
consisting of four sub-matrices. And then the output of this particular multiplication is going to go
through this for different gating function. So the first three components is going to go through
this sigmoid function. Okay. The last component is going to go through a 10-h function, see activation
functions here. Okay. So it's an element by element operations here. And after the output here will
be, you know, what you obtain here, IFOG. Right. So typically we try to remember this particular
form here or sequence here, IFOG, IFOG. So IFOG is easy to remember. IFOG here. Right. So this is
IFOG, the activation function that we have, the first three is the sigmoid function. The last
one is the 10-h function. Okay. So this is how, first of all, right, we use our previous memory
and our current input going through this mathematical operation to obtain these four gates here,
IFOG. So these four gates here has its own interpretation that we'll explain a little bit
about it later here. Okay. So let's continue on. So let's look at the next equations that we have here.
So these equations that we have here, right, so this CT here, right, if you can remember,
what is this CT? This CT is a long-term memory. All right. So you can see that our current
long-term memory or the long-term memory at this current time step T actually depends on the previous
long-term memory at time step T minus. Okay. And then this particular operations here is actually
an element by element multiplication. So this particular CT here is actually a vector. Okay.
It's a vector. And this F here is also a vector. Okay. It's also a vector. So you have this CT
minus one, which is a vector. And F is also a vector. So we perform an element by element
multiplication. And then you'll be able to obtain the output. So this is what this
particular operation is. Okay. Element by element multiplication here. So anyway, let's come back
to this. So what it says is that this long-term memory at this current time step depends on the
long-term memory in the previous time step. Okay. And then you perform element by element
multiplication with this F. F is a forget gate. So as the name suggests, forget gate means you
how much you forget or how much you retain. Okay. So this is the goal of this particular
forget gate. That means, okay, your previous long-term memory, how much of them you want to
forget and how much of them you want to retain. If the values F here, because you can see this
function F, actually it's the output after going through a sigmoid function. A sigmoid function
has a value that maps to between zero to one, between zero to one. So this F value, if this F value
for a certain element is very close to one, that means you actually retain, okay, the long-term
memory from the previous time step. On the other hand, if the F value is very close to zero,
whatever multiplied with zero will become very close to zero. That means, no, the previous
long-term memory will be lost. So therefore, the objective of this particular F gate is actually
a control gate. Right. So it's a forget gate to decide how much long-term memory from the previous
iteration you want to retain or you want to forget. So hence this name forget gate here.
Okay. So we have just actually explained about these terms here. But okay, if you think about
this term here, it's probably not enough because there's no new way you can generate new content to
your long-term memory. So therefore, you need to have another term here. So this another term here
you can see is consists of this I is known as the input gate. Okay. So I is actually your input gate
here. And G is known as the gate gate. A bit funny, but it's called gate gate here. So this input
gate is you can interpret is the new input you want to generate to replenish your long-term memory.
So this input gate is like the new gate, new content that you want to generate to update your
long-term memory here. Okay. Right. So this is the roles of your input gate. And then this gate is
an additional control operation to decide how much input will be updated to the long-term memory.
Okay. So let me just, no, now that we understand all this, let's just try to
summarize one more time. So this long-term memory at time step t will depends on the long-term
memory in time step t minus one. It means a previous long-term memory. You perform element
operation with this forget gate. Okay. This forget gate is role is to control how much of this
previous long-term memory will be propagated to the next time step here. Okay. And then this input
gate is the new content that we generate, right, in order to update our long-term memory. But this
input will be further controlled by a gate gate operation. Okay. Yeah. So therefore now we fully
come to explain about this particular equations already. Okay. So the next equations that we have
is that once you obtain the long-term memory, this long-term memory need to be, you know,
outputted as a short-term memory. Okay. So therefore what we do is that we take this long-term memory,
we let it go through a 10-hitch function, and afterwards we perform element by element
multiplication with this output gate here. Again, this term here is actually a factor.
This output gate is also a factor. So we perform an element by element multiplication to obtain your
short-term memory here. Okay. So this O here is output gate because as the name suggests,
it actually output from this long-term memory to the short-term memory. Okay. So that pretty much
kind of, you know, explain all these equations here. So once you have roughly understood this
equation, let's try to go back to see the text right up here. So the next point is that the cell
state, okay, which is our CT undergoes changes by forgetting the old memory through the forget
gate. Okay. So the first part, simply say that, you know, our long-term memory, the current long-term
memory depends on your previous long-term memory controlled by this forget gate, either by forgetting
or pretending it. Okay. And also we add the new memory. So this new memory is true. Okay. This
input gate and that is controlled by this gating function. Right. Okay. So this is this point here
pretty much correspond to this equation. And after all, so the next sentence says that the
hidden state HT is updated by passing the cell state CT through the output gate here. Right.
That means your long-term memory after going through the 10-H function and which is controlled
by this output gate would then be used to generate your hidden short-term memory or hidden state HT
here. Okay. So you can see that in this particular STM here, actually there are four gates here,
I, F, O, G. So these gates here, these four gates here will control the flows of information.
Right. Do the memory. Okay. You can see F, I, G and O all control the flows of information
to this long-term memory and short-term memory here. Okay. So gates are obtained through this
sigma and 10-H layer as shown here. Right. And then they update the short-term memory and
long-term memory and short-term memory through point-wise multiplication operation. So this is
a point-wise or element by element multiplication. Okay. So, right. I can't explain about this.
So next we are going to see how we can understand this particular LSTM cell right from this formula.
Pretty much this particular diagram is just an interpretation of these equations here.
So first of all, let's look at it. We have this previous long-term memory,
right, at time step T minus 1, okay, coming in here. So we have first of all, okay,
the previous short-term memory or hidden state. Okay. And then our current input,
we stack them together. So this step here corresponded to this. And then afterwards we
multiply by this big W matrix here. Okay. So the output now will go through this
for activation, this activation function and then it will generate the 4 gate that we have.
I, F, O, G. Okay. This 4 gates here. So next we want to see what happened to our
current long-term memory. So our current long-term memory will depend on our previous long-term
memory. Okay. Perform this element by element operation with our Fourier gate and then add
up with our new input gate, okay, and our gate gate, okay, perform element by element
multiplication. And then this, we add them up with this, right. So therefore this path here
pretty much explains the first equation. And then the second path here, what we have just now is that,
okay, we have our new long-term memory already. It let it go through a 10-h function,
which is this part here. And afterwards this thing here will be controlled by this output gate here.
We perform element by element multiplication to generate our short-term memory, HD here.
Right. And then afterwards when, if you, for example, you want to predict at this particular
time step, what is the output, right, we will be using this short-term memory, okay, multiply with
some, for example, matrix to generate our predicted output. Okay. So that's pretty much the high-level
ideas of LSTM. Okay. Are there any questions so far?
Okay. Perhaps we can go through the next few slides because this one is like a high-level
summary, even though I've already explained the most important concepts of LSTM. But what we
will do is that in the next few slides, we are going to go through each of these calculations
one step at a time. And afterwards we have one exercise. Yeah. So after the exercise, I believe,
no, it should make this particular process and calculation a lot clearer. Okay. So let's continue.
Okay. So if you do a quick comparison between AN and LSTM, so the vanilla AN and that we have
studied before, you can see, right. So what we do is that we can concatenate our previous
heat and state and our current input, right, we can concatenate them, right. And then we multiply
with this particular big W matrix here. Okay. So this big W matrix here can be decomposed into the
WHH and the WXH matrix that we have covered in the previous lecture. And afterwards, we go,
let it go through a 10-H function to obtain our current heat and state here. Okay. So this is the
vanilla AN and for LSTM, this is the steps of equations. Yeah. I've just gone through with you.
Okay. So next, we are going to go through a few slides to explain each of these,
no, steps a little bit more detail and also to provide some visualization. So it's easier for
you to see, right. So first of all, we are going to look at how do we generate this particular
gate here. We're going to see how do we generate this particular gating function here.
Right. So quick recap. So first of all, we have our previous short time memory,
okay, and our current input will concatenate them into a vector here. Right. So and afterwards,
we multiply with this particular big W matrix. Right. Okay. So in terms of visualization, we can
also think about it, it's like this. Yeah. Okay. One thing to take note of is that these figures
here, actually the X and this H factors here, the order is not so consistent with this. So I'll
probably suggest that in your notes, you may want to swap the order here if you want it to be
consistent with this interpretation here. Right. Okay. So anyway, you have the, yeah, if you swap
the order here, this part here is pretty much you just concatenate your previous short time memory
and your current input, you concatenate them and make it into a long factor. Okay. And afterwards,
you multiply with this particular matrix. So this matrix is W. Right. Okay. This big matrix,
W can be further partitioned into four sub matrices here. Each of those sub matrix will
correspond to this I f o g component. Okay. Right. So the output of this particular
multiplication, you'll get a factor here. Right. So this is what you have here. And afterwards,
you'll go through this activation functions here. Okay. The first three is a sig mod. The last one
is a 10 H function. So once you do that, you will have this I f o g here. All right, which is this
output. Okay. So this is how you can generate this particular, no, gig, gig functions here.
So for the gig, gig function, it will be actually going through the 10 H function.
Right. And earlier, as you mentioned, what is the role of this particular gig functions here,
this gig functions here. So the role of this gig function is that you will, you know, control
how much of this new input will be, you know, updated to your long term memory. So it's a
gating function to decide how much of this newly generated input will be updated to your long term
memory. Okay. So once you understood just now the diagram, the rest are actually quite similar to
that. So this slide here, see, let's see how do we generate this particular input gig now. So by
now you should know this input gate is actually the new content that you generate. Okay. So the
new content that you generate to update your long term memory. So in terms of the mathematical
operation is similar to before you have this concatenated factor multiply with this W matrix.
Okay. But for this, if you're talking about this, I get here, it will be the first sub matrix that
you have here. Okay. So you multiply with it, you let it go through your stick mode function,
and then you'll be able to generate your gig here. Okay. And for forget gig, right, the
roles of this forget gig we have explained probably many times already is it decide how much of this
previous long term memory you want to forget or retain. Okay. Right. So the calculation is,
similar to what we have mentioned before, concatenated factor multiply with the corresponding
sub matrix go through the, this particular signal function, you'll get your forget gig.
And then last, this output gig, right, the objective of this output gig is how much of this
long term memory will be revealed to your short term memory here. Okay. So this output gig,
so the calculation is similar, right, this two concatenated vector multiply with the
corresponding sub matrix that correspond to the output, let it go through the signal function,
then you'll obtain your output gig here. Right. Okay. So we have kind of gone through quite a bit
of a discussion about it. So I think probably now it's time for you to get your hand dirty,
but to do some calculation to see whether you understand what we have just explained.
Right. So let's look at this particular exercise here. You can see it's one past the exam questions.
It says that an LSTM has a flowing something, right. It has the initial hidden state,
right. And they also have the initial cell state is given, right. And then now you're given the
forget gig matrix. Okay. You're given the input gig at time step one gig gig at time step one
output gig at time step one, right, as well as the initial input, right, the square loss parameter.
Okay. So assume no bias is used in the computation is this LSTM, right. And the sigma and 10h
function is given by this formula here. Okay. So now they ask you to first of all,
find out the forget gig at one at time step one. Okay. And then comment on your obtain result.
Okay. So I'll give you a bit of time to go through all those formula that you just now
I've introduced to you and then, you know, try to look at this question and see whether you can
solve this part one. Okay. I'll give you some time to think about it.
Okay. So you probably have some time to think about it already. So any suggestion, how do we find out
the forget gig? If you have some idea, you can actually enter into the chat box.
Okay. So you can see, right, in this case, okay, before that.
All right. Okay. Before that, can I just check, can you hear me?
Okay. Okay. Great. Thank you. Yeah. So you can see that if you want to find the forget gig,
so from the earliest slides, what we can see is that what we need to do is
find this forget case slides here. So first of all, we need to concatenate our previous
short-term memory, our current input concatenate. Okay. This matrix W here usually is a big matrix,
but there are four submetrics, each correspond to IFOG gig here. Since now we're talking about the
forget gig, that means you'll be looking at this particular submetrics here, okay, which is even.
Right. So this part of the submetrics, multiply with this, let it go through a segment function,
and then you'll be able to obtain your forget gig. All right. So that's pretty much what you need to do
for the first part.
All right. Okay. Yeah. I think one of your friend also give the right answer. So let's
then in the case, let me just go through the first part of the answer with you.
Okay. So can you see the share screen for the solution?
Okay. Good. Right. So as you can see, earlier on, this is the part that I mentioned to you before,
right? And this is the corresponding equation. So what you need to do is that first of all,
right, you have this particular two, no, these are previous short time memory and HD,
which is from here, right? You multiply. Okay. So in this formula here is this big W matrix here,
but since we are talking about this forget gig here, so we can, we'll only be looking at this
particular corresponding submetrics that correspond to the forget gig, which in this question is called
WF here. All right. And afterwards we'll go through this particular segment function here.
Okay. So pretty much this is the equations that we have, right? And then this particular
matrix WF here, actually, if you want, you can further divide into two parts here, right? So one
is the submetrics due to hidden, no, hidden state to the forget gig. The other is the input,
the forget gig. Sorry, the resolution is a bit low, but I think you can probably still figure
right. Okay. So now our question is that we want to find the forget gig at time step one. So we
simply let T be equal to one into it, right? So we, right, then this is our formula. Okay. And if
you want, you can either find from using this form or in this form either way, right? So, okay,
anyway, you just put in the time steps. And then finally, now we are ready to substitute all the
values. So these two, right, submetrics, this here, right from the hidden state to the forget
gig and from the input to forget gig, this are given. Okay. And then we know the
short time memory at time step zero, the input, okay, at time step one. So we put all of them
value in, right? So after some doing some calculation, right, you have this. And then for this
course here, I will strongly encourage you to, you know, to memorize the formula, right, for this
sigmoid function or no use of calculator to make sure that you can calculate the sigmoid function
and the 10-H function. Right. So anyway, yes, this is a sigmoid function. If you plug it in,
you'll be able to obtain your result here. Okay. Right. So this is the result. So now, if you look
at this particular forget gig here, what do you notice? You'll notice that values are quite large.
So when the value f is large here, right, this, so this factor f is large here, that means,
right, most of your previous long-term memory should be able to retain because whatever
multiplied by value, which is very close to one, will retain the previous value. So therefore,
you can see that the self state at t is equal to one, right, will retain most of the memory from
the previous self state, right, because this value is very large. Okay. It's very close to one.
Okay. So that is the answer to part one. So let's continue with part two.
So now in part two, it asks you to find the self state c1 at times that one. So just now,
we already found the forget gate, right, and from the question, right, you can see that they also
tell you the input gate and the gate gate, right, because I want to make the question a bit more
manageable in the exam. So I give you the some of the value as well. So now you're supposed to find
the self state at times that one. Okay. I'll give you a bit of time to try it out, and then we'll go
through the answers together.
Okay.
So I think you probably have some time to think about it already. So let's look at the
second part. So the second part, right, you want to find the,
this particular long term memory. So this is the equation we're using. So our current longer memory,
it depends on previous long term memory. Okay. Multiply element by element multiplication with
forget gate plus your input gate, element by element multiplication with your gate gate here.
Right. So just now for this particular question, first of all, we substitute t
to be equal to one. We can write down these equations here. So from the part one, we have
already calculated this forget gate at times that one. Okay. So the other parameters like the
previous long term memory, the current input gate, as well as the current gate gate are all
provided by the questions. So you just plug everything in. Right. So for these examples
here, for example, this element by element multiplication is right. This multiplied by this.
Okay. For the first value, second value is this multiplied with this. Right. Then you'll get the
factors already. Likewise for this, you can repeat that after you've done some calculation,
then this is the result. Okay. So this is your, this long term memory at times that one.
Okay. We still have the last part, which is they ask you to find the hidden state h1 at times that
one. Right. Okay. So again, I'll give you a bit of time to think about it and then we'll go through
the answers together.
Okay.
Actually, there's one questions on the chat by Carol. Okay. The question is why don't I use this
formula? Okay. The question that you have for gate i,
for gate i. Yeah. Okay. From the questions, actually, the input gate is already provided.
Yeah. So if you want to, yeah, because the gate i is already provided and the corresponding
made this, let me just,
yeah. If you want to calculate this gate i, if you use this particular formula here, that means
you need the corresponding sub matrix that correspond to this gate i. Right. So if you use
from this particular visualizations here, if you want to calculate this gate i here,
right. First of all, you need to have this sub matrix corresponding to the gate i,
but we don't have the piece of information. So therefore, you cannot calculate your gate i
through this and this sub matrix. Mainly it's because the sub matrix correspond to gate i.
The information is not available. Okay. But instead, they actually already give you what
this gate i is. Yeah. So therefore, you just get whatever information from the question directly.
Okay. Yeah.
Right. Okay. So I think it's probably, you know, you have some time to think about it. So let's try
to go through the answer for the last part. You want to find the hidden state or the short time memory.
Right. So yeah. So this is the formula that relates our long-term memory, our output gate and the
short-term memory. Right. So from this equation, we can see that from early on, we already calculate
the long-term memory at time step one. Right. The output gate is given from the question. So
pretty much is the issue. No, you just plug in the value and make sure that, you know, your
cuckold e famurize yourself with how you can calculate this 10-h function using our calculator.
All right. So this is important. Okay. So if you know that, right. So this is the value. And
then afterwards this performing this element by element multiplication to be able to generate these
results here. So are there any questions?
Right. Okay. So after once we have, we have actually explained about the LSTM, the important
expect and, you know, going through this particular exercise, probably you have a,
you know, much better understanding about this LSTM already. So right. The case, let's continue on
with the
right. Okay. So the next thing is we are going to very briefly touch on some sample applications for
no, our, our, and LSTM. Right. So one very common kind of application is time series predictions.
Like for example, you want to predict what's the share price, no, for the, no following days.
Yeah. The other very popular kind of application is machine translation. Right. So the idea of
this machine translation, high level idea is that, you know, you want to give input sentence, for
example, no French, you want to translate into English. Right. So in previous lecture, we also
mentioned about these ideas of encoder decoder architecture. So this diagram again is showing
the same thing. So we have, first of all, this is the encoder. Right. So the ideas of this encoder
seat is that we want to take this input sentence, right. Okay. And then we will try to extract some
information here, right in the form of some context factor. So this particular context factor,
right, in this case would probably be, for example, the memory, correct, the memory at this time
steps here. So this context factor will actually, no, come extract all the necessary information
from your input sentence. Okay. And afterwards at the output side, we'll be using a decoder.
Right. So this decoder is grow is take the context factor and then try to generate your target
translated sentences here. So the structure is quite common is that you take your context
factor, you start with the first token, which is start. Okay. And then you generate what's the most
likely first work for example, is he and afterwards you take this he, right, you use it to
no count generate what's the next likely works, for example, is he okay, and so on and so forth.
Here. Okay. So this is the basic architectures of the encoder decoder architecture. So later on,
in the next part, once you study about transformer, we are going to spend a bit more time talking about
it. Yeah. But one of the shortcoming or limitations of this are and and when we use on and to do this
machine translation is that for on and you need to extract one single context factor.
And this single context factor need to actually represent the information from your input sentence.
And this is very difficult, right, because it's very, very difficult for you to simply just get
one factor. And this factor yet need to have no capture all the information from your input
sentence. So because of that, this is considered as the information bottleneck here, right. And it's
because of this reason, no, your traditional on and it's actually, I mean, they are okay, but they
really have some limitation in terms of their performance. So because of that, no, it provides
motivation for no better model, which is the transformer model that we are doing this study next.
Right. So therefore, for this section, we actually study the following, right, we talk about
introduction, we study about on and how to train on and just now we cover LSTM and also we only go
through some selected application quickly. Right. So the next topic we're going to study is
transformer first transfer. I think for those of you who know AI, you know, this very, very
important, very hot topic, or most of the state of the art AI models is based on that. So we are
going to spend some time to talk about it later. But I think before that is almost time to take
a break. So we'll probably take a short break. We will come back at 10 30. Right. So let's come back at 10 30.
Okay. So, yeah, welcome back before we continue. Just want to check in your
C here as well as see the share screen.
Okay, great. Thank you. So right in the case, let's continue. Right. So the next topic we're going
to study is the transform. Right. So for this section, we are going to talk about this. What is
the concept of the attention and after we introduce transformer and followed by vision
transform. Right. So what's attention? So attention, actually, the concept is actually
kind of a simple. So if you think about, suppose if I tell you, you know, something is actually
a mouse, yeah, I say, no, about a mouse. So when you think about this word mouse, it can either be,
for example, the computer mouse that you have, or it can be the cat and mouse that we have.
So in order to have a good understanding where you use this word mouse, why this you really need
to have some surrounding text to have certain understanding about this word mouse, why this.
Okay. So therefore, actually, in our case here, when we want to introduce attention,
pretty much is that suppose if you have a particular sentence, right, so a sentence
have many different works, right, when you are considering this current works, what is the
importance or contributions of the other works with respect to this current works you are
considering. So the amount of importance, okay, or the relevance, okay, or contributions, or
the works this current work, right, this is known as attention. Okay. So therefore, you can kind of
think about it. If you have a particular sentence here, right, suppose if you want to look at this
current works here, the importance, okay, or the relevance of all the other works with respect
to this current works, this is called the attention. The attention to all the other works with respect
to this current work. So for example, those lines that stick, actually, it means they have higher
relevance or importance. Okay. So it can be either interpreted in terms of a sentence, or it can be
interpreted in terms of the image. For example, this image we can partition into many different
patches like this, right. And if you consider this current patch here, what is the importance or
contributions of all the other patches with respect to this current patch, for example,
this is known as attention, right. So that's a high level intuition. So therefore, you can see
attention is used to determine which input token. So in the context of a transformer, the work that
we use is called token. So this token could correspond, for example, to different works in
NLP, or it could correspond to, for example, image patches in computer vision, right. So the general
term that we use in a transformer is called token. Yeah. So it would determine which tokens are
actually relevant to the current input or token, right. So how do we compute this attention?
So attention is computed using what is known as a dot product between two factors, or this
dot product is also correlation. So when you want to determine two example tokens, each token
typically can be represented as factor. So you want to see the kind of attention or similarity
or relatedness between these two code token or these two factor, we perform a dot product. Okay.
Multiply their corresponding term and sum it up. Right. So this dot product is also known as the
correlation. For those of you who study communication theory, you know, it's correlation, or it's a
degree in measured similarity. Okay. So by performing this dot product or correlation,
actually you are measuring either in terms of a similarity, relatedness, or importance of,
you know, one token respect to the other. And this is known as attention. Okay.
Right. So in transformer, how exactly do we compute this attention? Let me see. That's the
right. Okay. So just now what we in previous slide, we introduced a high level intuition. So
next we are going to see how do we exactly compute attention, right, in transformer. So first of all,
right, for each input token, it can be a work, it can be an image patch. What we will do is that
we try to generate three vectors. So these three vectors are known as query, q, key, k, and value,
v. Right. So even a particular token, which is represented as a factor, how do we generate this
query, key, and value? So how we generate them is that we multiply with three corresponding
matrices. Okay. Wq, Wk, and wv. But before that, why do we want, given a particular
token, which is represented as factor, why do we want to generate this three additional
factor, okay, query, key, and value? So the reason why we want to generate these three additional
factors is because these factors can provide a more flexible representation. Okay. It can
make your representation, right, richer, right. Okay. So it provides a more flexible and richer
representation. Okay. So, and this is done through a linear mapping by multiplying with these three
matrices. Right. So with this richer representation using q, k, and v, you can learn the underlying
relationship or tension between the input token. Yeah, because if you just use one input token
compared to the other token, maybe what you can do is more limited. But once you project into a query,
key, and value, actually the way you can do this representation can be richer. Right. So just that,
just now what we mentioned is that suppose we take the example of a set of two works,
thinking machine. First of all, each of the work we can convert it into a factor. This is known as
embedding because, you know, for each work, we need to represent as a vector. So after we've each
vector, we let it multiply by these three matrix, w, q, w, k, and w, v. Then for each input vector,
we can then generate this query, key, and value vectors here for each works here. Right. So this
is what is described in the previous sentence. Right. So next we are going to explain how do we
compute attention right in transformer. So we start from here. Suppose we have two works,
thinking machine. First of all, we'll do the work embedding to convert them into some factor
representation. Right. Okay. And then by multiplying with these three matrix for each of these
factors, you can generate query, key, and value vectors here. Right. So next we want to see how
do we compute the attention between this, you know, this factor and this factor. So the first thing
that we do is that what we do adopt product. Right. Suppose we know consider this kind of
thinking. Right. Okay. So we do we compute a dot product between this query and this key. Right.
Okay. Query and key. And also the dot product between query and key two. So now that works,
we perform a correlation between query one and key one and query one and key two. Right. So if you
do that, then you'll be able to get to score. Right. So this results here when you perform this
you know, dot product or this correlation, just like what we mentioned, we are trying to measure
the similarity or the importance of other works with respect to this kind of first work here now.
So once you have these two scores here, the next thing that is that we'll do some scaling.
Right. So we'll divide by the square root of the dimensions of the vector dimensions of this key
vector. Okay. DK is the dimensions of your key vector and you take a square root. Suppose this
value is eight, then we take each of them, we divide it by eight. And afterwards, these two
value will perform the stock max. So if you recall, soft max means we want to convert it into the
probability. So now we'll convert it into the probability. And after works, we multiply with
the corresponding value vector. So this one multiply with this plus this one multiply with this.
And then after works, right, the output of this particular summation is what we know as a context
vector z one here. So this is the context vector z one. Right. So you can actually repeat the same
process to, you know, obtain the context factor z two as well. So what is so important about this
z one is that this z one factor is the this context factor is a better representation
than this context factor x one. So can anyone tell why is it better?
Why is this context vector z one a better representation than the original vector x one?
Okay, so the reason why z one is more important is a better representation with x one is because
it incorporates information from other works already. That means it actually capture or
incorporate information from the other works or actually is able to obtain the context from the
other works. So it's not base x one is only x one is a representation due to this single work.
But now z one is a better representation because it also take into consideration of all the other
works, their contribution to work set. So that's why this context factor is a better representation.
All right. Okay. So one of your friend Haro, I think also give the right answer.
So let's continue. Okay. So this slide here actually is just really much like, you know,
what we have just mentioned before. Right. So this particular process is known as a scale
dot product attention. Right. So to perform this attention, first of all, we perform this
dot product and afterwards we have this scaling up process. So since we've explained in the previous
slide, so I'm not going to repeat here, but just one thing I want to highlight here is that,
okay, so early on we have explained how we can generate this other context vector z one. So z
one is a better representation for x one. You can also repeat that to generate a context vector x two
for this vector x two. That means if your input has a few different vectors, then at the end of
this particular attention operation, right, you're going to get some better vector representation
known as x one, x two and x three and so on. So each vector, you're going to get a better
representation. Okay. So it turns out that mathematically, there's a easier way and more
efficient way of computing it, which is through this particular equations here. Right. So this
equation here is the, this is the attention. This q k v are actually matrices formed by,
you know, stacking all these factors together. Right. So for example, right. Okay. So anyway,
this attention is given by this equation here. So this q here, right, for example, this q is
actually the query matrix. This query matrix is obtained by taking each of the three vector
and we stack them together to form a matrix. Okay. For example, like this. And then this k here is
the key matrix is obtained by taking these key vectors and you stack them row by row to become
a matrix. And afterwards, it may become a transpose. This is what you have. Okay. So likewise for this
particular v matrix here. So therefore what it means is that, right, in order to generate this
particular individual context factor, right, so what you can do is simply applying this formula.
Right. So you will form this query key and value matrix. You apply this particular formula and then
you'll be able to generate this particular context matrix. Now, for this context matrix,
each of the row in this case represent the corresponding no context factor. So that's all
from the computation perspective is very straightforward. We just apply this particular formula.
Okay. So next, we have some basic understanding we can proceed to introduce a transformer. So
transformer is actually an AI model that use attention mechanism that we've studied before
to process the input sequence in parallel. So you can process it in parallel because you can see
our computation is through this matrix multiplication is through these equations here.
And this thing can be done concurrently to generate context factor. Okay. For different
position together. So therefore we can do it in parallel. Okay. So it may use of the attention
mechanism that we have introduced. And it also it may use of MLP, fit forward or dense. These are
equivalent. All right. It's just a different name. Right. You'll make use of this MLP layer or the
fit forward layer. So that part we'll later on explain to you later. Okay. So earlier on, we can
see it's highly parizable because you can for each of the input factor, you can generate the context
factor in parallel. No, as opposed to I and N, you need to process one input at a time, which is very
slow. Right. So the next point is that it can provide global attention. Providing this global
attention means that, right, if you want to look at the importance of this current, the contributions
of other tokens or works with respect to this card works, the contribution can be for all the works
in a particular, for example, paragraph. So this particular token can be very, very far away. And
it can be for all the, you know, works in the paragraph. So therefore, it can obtain global
attention. Global means that you can look at the contributions of all the works in that particular,
no, for example, paragraph, whatever context that you have. Next, it can perform good long range
you can model long range dependency. That means even works that are very far away, you can see
is contribution towards this type of works. So this is long range, the ideal long range
dependence. So this is as opposed to CNN, CNN, because you're using a small filter. So for small
filter, you can only look at the contributions of neighboring pixels, right. So it's not long,
short range, but for transformer, because you can look at works of patches, which are very far away.
So it can model long range dependency. Right. So why is this transformer so important? Because
currently it can achieve state of the art performance. Yeah. Okay. And it also leads to many
state of the art motors like bugs, no, GPT and so on and so forth. Right. So next, we are going to
explain a little bit about this transformer in the original paper, right. So the original paper,
the use of transformer is used in machine translation. So now we are trying to explain it
step by step, starting from high level picture and then progressively, you know, add in more and more
detail. Right. So the original paper of the transformer is to perform machine translation.
So for example, you have a French sentence, you go through this transformer, you want to translate
into an English sentence. Right. So this transformer, it can be further divided if you start to zoom in,
this transformer can be divided into two parts, encoder and decoder. Right. Just like what we
explained a little bit a while ago. So we have this input French sentence, you'll go through the
encoder. So this encoder will extract some information, right, some useful information that
represent this input sentence. And then this context information will be passed to the decoder.
And then this decoder would then try to generate the translated English sentence. Okay.
So that's if you start to zoom in. Now if we further zoom in, so this particular encoder here,
right, instead of using one single encoder, right, we can actually, you know, let them go through
this encoder a few times. Right. No, it's just like, no, if you are generating some money instead of
generating the money once, you probably want to do it a few times so that hopefully you can do better
after a few times. So therefore, generally speaking, instead of one encoder block, you will let this
encoder block do, will have a few encoder block. Right. So that's rich with each encoder block.
We hope that it can know after each block, it can extract the context vector, a context vector,
and better. Okay. Right. So now therefore this encoder block instead of one single block actually
it consists of multiple encoder block here. Right. And therefore this decoder here instead of one
decoder actually it consists of multiple decoder block for the same argument because, you know,
you think that with different block actually after each block will become better and better.
So therefore you want to do it a few times here. Right. And then this particular direction here,
these are the text vector that we have extracted. So suppose if you're, this is your input sentence
of three words here, you have later on three input, no, factors here at the end of it,
after this encoder, you have these three output context vector. So this output context vector
would then be, you know, pass to input of each of these encoder to generate your translated sentence.
Okay. Right. So next we further zoom in. Now let's zoom into this encoder and see what's the
structures of this encoder here. So the structures of this encoder here actually has two key layer.
One is the self attention. Yeah. So this self attention is what we have already explained
earlier on in the previous part. That means you have a few input vectors after this self
attention. So your input is actually, for example, a few input vectors correspond to different books.
After this self attention, you will have some context vector. So these context vectors are
better representation than your original vector, like what I mentioned, because they extract
information from the other books already. Okay. So you know, so you have a better context vector
here. And afterwards you will go through a fit forward layer. So this fit forward layer, just
like we studied here then before, is a general purpose transformation to make your feature
slightly better. Right. So therefore we'll go through the fit forward layer and then you'll
have the output here. So this is how the structures of this encoder is. And for this particular decoder
here, this is a structures here. So the structures of this decoder here is that first of all,
you have this self attention here. So the self attention here and the self attention here are
doing the same thing, but accept that for this self attention here because it's for the purpose of
a machine translation. So initially your input here are some French works. Okay. So assuming that
after you've done some translation, your output here, you have some because this translation,
each translator work will be, you know, bring it back. Each translator work will be bring it back.
So assuming that you have really translated a few English works. So this self attention now is
actually the self attention for the English works, translator works here. Okay. Right. So and then
afterwards you have some better context vector. So the next layer is what is known as encoder
decoder attention. So what is the objective of this encoder and decoder attention? The objective
is because, right. So earlier we are doing the attention only for the translated English work,
but we have not looked at the relationship between the translated English work and the original French
work. Okay. So we also want to see what is the contributions of the French work to works, you
know, this current English works. So that's why we have this encoder decoder attention.
Okay. Right. It's to find, right, the attention between your encode, your, this encoder output
as well as your decoder. Right. And after works, you'll go through this fit forward layer. Yeah.
So that's what I mentioned before, right. Just do is a general purpose mapping or transformation to
make your context vector even better. Right. Okay. So finally, let's try to zoom in this encoder even
a bit more. So you can start see, we start with some works like thinking machine tool works here.
We have the context user work embedding the converted into factors. We perform self attention.
Right. Then we have a better context factor X one, a Z one and Z two, right, which is better than
X one and X two, like what I mentioned before. And afterwards they go through this fit forward
network here, right, to generate even better factors R one and R two in this case here. Right.
Okay. Now, next, let's move on to this particular model attention is all you need. So this is the
full structures of this attention or unit transformer. Okay. So later on, we're going to
explain a little bit more about this transformer. So let's provide some high level information.
So first of all, it's designed for a neural machine translation. So later on is extended
to many other tasks already. Nowadays is over the place, but it's extended for to
visual tasks like recognition detection with good performance. Right. So it leverage on this
attention mechanism that we have explained, right, to analyze the importance of a token. So this
token token can be a work or can be a patch respect to other token. So for a transfer for a
transformer, actually it consists of an encoder and decoder architecture. So later on, you're going
to see this part is the encoder and this part is the decoder. Right. So next, actually, they are
these two slides, which will explain about each of the key steps in this transformer,
but we are going to leave it, we're going to skip it for one moment. Let's try to go to the diagram
first. So we'll explain the diagram and the lay down will come back to these slides to explain
this point. Right. Okay. So let's look at the architectures of this transformer. So this is
the transformer here. So this transformer roughly speaking can be broken into a few different blocks
here. So first of all, we have this encoder. Okay. And then we have the decoder. And then this part
here is known as the input pre processing. Right. So it's the input part. So this part is the output.
So we call it output pre processing. And this part we call it output post processing. So it can
be divided into these few key blocks. So next we are going to look into each of these blocks
one at a time. What do they do? Right. So, okay. So now next we are going to look at this encoder
and the decoder. So for this encoder, if we zoom it in, you'll see that first of all, we have this
particular input cell attention. So if you remember a few slides back, we have actually this cell
attention and then we have the fit forward and work here. Right. So this cell attention more
explicitly is for the input. So we call it an input cell attention. Right. And then this part,
if you remember, is a decoder. So decoder, you have this particular cell attention here as well.
As that now is for the output. So we call it the output cell attention. Okay. Output cell attention.
And you also notice that there's this particular work mass. So the reason why there's this work
mass is that during the training process now, because for example, this is a translation.
So translation, you would have, for example, no, in your training data, you will have this
particular translated output standards already. But during the training, because you're generating
the work one at a time. So suppose your translated work is I am, okay, I am, for example, suppose
the full sentence, I'm am a boy. But no, in the process of you doing the training, okay,
after it's translated this work I and M, right, the future works that has not been generated
yet by right should not appear in your training because they have not standard yet. So therefore,
this masking is the process to mask up the future works right in your training data that you should
not have seen yet during the training step. So this is the masking process. Okay. And then
afterwards, this is the encoder decoder cell attention. So remember this part is that you
still want to find the relationship between your original French works and your partly translated
English work. You still want to find the relationship between them. Okay. All right. So that's why we
have this encoder decoder cell attention. This cell attention at this step is only to find the
relationship between your translated English work. But this part here is to find the relationship
between your translated English work and your original French work because you also want to see
the relationship. Okay. And afterwards, you have this fit forward network, which is like a general
transformation to make it better. Right. So this part here is actually just like just now,
the high level overview that we have shown you a bit earlier on. Yeah, this part here. Okay. But
as that now we put in the actual blocks to make it more concrete.
Okay. So next we are going to see how do we compute this cell attention here now? Right. So
how do we compute these cell attentions here? So how we compute actually we already covered in
the early part of the lecture. So for example, we have some input factors. Suppose initially it's
a few different works, each of the works will be converted into a factor using work embedding. So
this is your factors here. Right. So after works, once you have these factors, we need to know that
from our previous explanation, we need to make use of this particular matrix to convert into the
periky and value vectors. And then afterwards, we go through the, you know, the attention
computation to generate context factor. Okay. This context factor. So in this slide here,
they use set to see to represent the context factor. Right. But in the previous figure,
you know, the previous figure, they use the set to represent the context factor, but actually,
they are the same because, you know, I just obtained from different sources. That's why
they are slightly inconsistent. But the context factor that we have here is nothing to see here
is the same as the context factor set in the previous slide here. So pretty much this particular
part here, we are doing the self attention. Right. Okay. It's represented by C is the attention of
this sentence with respect to itself. So it's called the self attention because it's the same.
For example, in this case, the French, you know, the sentence with respect to itself.
So your input is actually a collection of your input factor, or x1 to xm, the parameter that
you need to train will be these three meters. Okay. So the output is actually your context
factors here. So this is a self attention layer here. So this self attention layer is actually
correspond to this part here, as well as this part here. So this part is for your input in our
context is actually, for example, French translated to English. So this part is the attention for
your French, you know, works. This part is actually the self attention for your translated English
works here. Then let's continue. So the next part that we have now is called the cross attention.
The cross attention is also known as the encoder decoder self attention. So which is highlighting
this block here. Okay. So you can see encoder decoder self attention here. So the high level
visualization is like this. So first of all, we have, for example, these are French works. Okay.
The factors representing the French works here. And then we have some partially translated English
works ready. So this is the factors are responding to partially translated English works. Okay,
we'll go through this particular attention layer. First of all, it needs to make use of this
main pieces to generate the query key and value vectors. And then afterwards, we will go through
this particular equation, right, the attention equations to generate the context factor now.
Okay, to generate context factor. So high level intuition is like, as I mentioned, you have some
original French works, you have some partially translated English works, you want to find the
relationship across them. Okay, you want to find the relationship across them. Right. So in this
case here, actually the query, okay, the query is actually coming from this park here. Okay,
in our application is the translated English work. And the key and the value is actually coming from
this park here, which is our French works here. And afterwards, we simply use this equation to
generate our context factor. And this context factor is supposed to be a better representation
than your original factor because it also exorbit some information from your original French work.
Okay, so that's a high level idea. Because your query and your key and value is from across different
one is decoder and encoder. That's why it's called encoder decoder, self attention or cross
attention. Right, okay, so we have actually covered some of the basics already. Let's continue to
provide a little bit more detail about some of the parts in the transformer. So we can see in
this transformer, we have actually covered some of the basic components already, you can see the
concept of transformer is not really that difficult. Yeah, but there's still some detail we did talk
about. So the next part is this multi hit attention. So multi hit attention is here. So later we'll
explain a little bit more about it. So this multi hit attention, we have the fit forward
layer, which we can't really explain. Right, we have this position encoding here, residue connection
here, normalization here, input output embedding here. And then afterwards the mass attention here,
the masking we have kind of explained. So maybe I will just explain very high level at this slide
or explain very high level information. And later on in the subsequent slide, I'll explain a little
bit more. So this multi hit attention here, right is here. So the objective of multi hit attention
is that instead of doing one copy of this network, we can generate a few copy so that the performance
will be better. Later slide will explain a little bit more. Fit forward we already mentioned is a
general purpose transformation to make it a bit better. So the position encoding in this particular
context here is you want to indicate the positions of different works. Okay,
right, residue connection. Actually, there's yeah, and anyway, I think probably better with
move to the next slide because otherwise I'm going to repeat too many times already,
remove the following slide and then we'll explain that. All right, so first let's look at this multi
hit attention. So for example, this is multi hit attention see, okay, multi hit attention. So as
the name suggests, multi hit attention, what it means is you have multiple copy of the attention.
So in our previous explanation, we only focus on one copy of the attention. Yeah, so for example,
you have some input factors, we let it go through just now the scale dot product attention. Yeah,
and then afterwards you generate some copies of your context factor. But if you think about
if you just have one copies of this, or if you just do only the scale dot product attention once,
sometimes this particular mapping may not be so good. It's just a little bit like when you're
buying share, you don't want to buy just one copy one one share, you want to buy a few different
share because one of the stock or one of the share can perform better. So therefore the reasoning
is the same here. Right, so instead of only performing this scale dot product attention once,
okay, using one copy of the parameter, we are going to repeat it a few times. Okay, we are going to
repeat it a few times with the hope that one of the copies of this particular, you know, output or
context factor will be performing better. Right, then later on in the later linear layer, it can
then focus on that particular copy that's performing better. Okay, so therefore you just do it a few
times and then afterwards for each of those, for example, your first copy, you have a few context
factor, the second copy, you have a few context factor, you just concatenate them right to form
longer factor. Okay, so that's a very simple idea here. Right, so for each copies of this particular
attention, it can be described using this equation. So this is one copy of them. Right, so this process
we already know, right, the query and the key will perform the matrix multiplication.
Afterwards, this one is scaling followed by this masking. If it's at the output, then you mask it
based on what I explained to you before. And afterwards you go through this stock max to
convert it into a probability. And afterwards you multiply with your value vector and afterwards
you generate your context factor, one copy of the context factor.
So next, let's move on to position encoding. So what is the objective of position encoding?
Right, so in the context of machine translations or image understanding, very often the positions
of the works in the sentence or the positions of image patch in an image is important. So therefore
you need to capture those information. Right, so the goal of position encoding is to represent the
position information of individual input token. It can be the position of a work in the sentence
or a position of a patch in a big image. Right, so how do you represent this position information
is typically using some sine cost function. Right, so if you are interested, you can read up
the original paper. So anyway, in terms of this position encoding, what you have is that suppose
your initial French works are this tree, right, you use the work embedding you can represent into
three different factors. And then now we add in with this position encoding, like first, now
position one, two and three, you'll use three different vectors to represent the position of
the works. And then afterwards you add them up. Okay, so then the adder up now is actually a
embedding with the time signal or, you know, this position, you know, this embedding with the position
information now. And afterwards, then you just pass it into your encoder. So you can see as we go
through different slides, we start to add in a little bit more information one at a time now.
Okay, and then afterwards, this slide actually showed the residue connection and the layer
norm. Right, so if you look at just now the transformer, we can see that we actually also
have this particular residue connection, a skip connection. So if you then you remember a few
in last lecture, we started about rest that we also have the particular skip connection. So the
objective is exactly the same. Okay, so we'll make use of this particular residue connection,
right, and leveraging on the same idea of this residue learning in breastnet. No easier back
propagation. Also, no, we are learning a smaller delta function so that you can more learn more
effectively. Okay, and we also have this layer norm to perform some normalization, right, just to
make sure that your subsequent, no data range is normalized. So far, right, you can see that what
we have is that we have these two works, we have the original works thinking machine, we convert
it into factor, we add in the position information, right, and then afterwards, okay, these two here,
we have the attention to calculate that to get a better context factor. And also we introduce
this residue learning all the skip protections here, and we introduce a normalization. Okay,
and then afterwards, okay, this factor here will go through fit forward network, right, and then we
also have this add a normalize. Right, okay, so we have put most of things in already. So now if you
put everything together, so this is what we have now, right, yeah, okay, so you can see we have this
two works thinking machine, we convert into two factor, we add in the position, right, so this
part here is, you know, trying to find the style attention of the input works, right, and afterwards
this part is your fit forward, you know, kind of a general transformation, and then we leverage on
this particular residue learning or skip connection here to make it learn better. Okay, and we also
perform normalization, okay, to make sure the range of the data is better. So pretty much we
complete one encoder block, right, but we know the next encoder block is just a repetition of the
previous encoder block. And then if you look at the decoder, right, it's very similar as well. Okay,
so right, so the decoder, first you have this, you know, self attention, you study the, you know,
relationship between translated English work, right, this cross attention or the encoder decoder
attention, you find out the attention between translated English work and the original French
work. And afterwards we have this fit forward layer to map the mapping a bit better, right, and then
also we make use of the residue learning, okay, as well as the normalization, so that we complete our
decoder block once, and then afterwards you have a few further decoder block, and then at the end
we have this linear layer and softmax layer that we're explaining next. Okay, so we are almost
done already, so let's look at the last few already. So the last part that we have is a linear layer
and the softmax layer, right, so earlier on, right, so if we go through this particular decoder block
a few times, right, suppose if you go through this decoder block a few times, if you look at your current
output here, you would have a context vector that looks like this, yeah, okay, so that you let it
go through a linear layer, which means you multiply with a matrix W and then project it into a long
output here. So the lack of this output here is corresponding to the size of the vocabulary, for
example in English if you have 10,000 work, then you use this linear layer to project it into a
10,000 dimensional vector here. So this 10,000 dimensional vector, you can see the output is
actually called the logic like what we studied before, we'll then go, let me go through a softmax
to convert it into the probability. So the particular entry that has the highest probability,
that means that is the next work we are going to generate. Suppose the next though, the work that
corresponds to position five is m, that means the next work that we are going to generate is this
next work m. So the high level ideas of this, yeah, the high level ideas of this particular
translations like this, yeah, so first of all, you have some, for example, your French sentence
come in, yeah, the French sentence and works coming in, you are going to extract, you know,
the context vector for each of the French works here. So this context vector will come here,
so initially when you start off, you have not translated any work. So you start off with,
for example, a standard spoken course. So this part here will then go through the path that we
mentioned just now to go through it and then afterwards a softmax to say what is the most
likely work that is going to be generated, that suppose it's called i. So this one i would then
be pulled down here, okay, pulled down here, right, it will become the first work already i. So this
i here would then go through the do the self-attention, cross-attention, you know, and then afterwards
go through the process to generate the next work. Suppose this work now is called m, this m work now
will be pulled down now. So now you're at this point here, you already have i, m, okay, these two
work, i, m, you can calculate the self-attention, cross-attention, right, and then you'll go through
the path to generate the next work, probably it's r, then this work r will come now here,
then it will become i, m, r, right. So then so progressively you add in more and more works,
right, so for the decoder, you calculate the self-attention, right, for the translated English
work, you calculate the cross-attention between this translated English work and the French work,
and then feed forward linear projections, softmax to generate the first work. So it's like work by
work generation. Okay, so now with that, if you do a quick comparison between LSTM and
transformer, so the advantage of LSTM that we've studied is that it can represent a sequence
better than i, m, but the shortcoming of LSTM, you still need to generate the output one at the time
after, you know, you need to generate output one at time, so it's very slow, okay, so as opposed to
that transformer, it's very good at handling long sequences, as the attention they look at,
you know, all the inputs explicitly. Also, it can do things in parallel, okay, so that's good,
but the shortcoming of transformer is you require lots of storage, you can see there's many linear
layers, many of those W matrix, which is expensive, right, and also because there's so many parameters,
it also requires lots of training data. Okay, so I think we pretty much kind of cover this,
but let me just quickly go back to just now these two pages that pretty much is just a
summarize what I've explained earlier on, but in works. So the transformer encoder,
you have this input pre-processing, so if you remember, you have mapped your input works or
token, for example, in our cases, French work into the text embedding and vectors, and afterwards,
we add in the position information, okay, so there's a pre-processing. For the encoder, we'll
map this input from the pre-processing into context factor using self-attention, so it
generates vector vector, so this context factor will then go through the fit forward layer to
actually generate the output now. So this encoder output has a better representation
with compared to the input because it leverage on the context information from all the other input
tokens, okay, due to this attention mechanism. So the output of this particular encoder now
will be passed to the decoder. So now let's look at the decoder. So the decoder side, we have the
output pre-processing, so this output pre-processing is that to map your translated output in our
context is the English work into the text embedding factor, and then we add position to it as well,
because translator works also have different position, okay, and then afterwards in the decoder,
there's a few parts. The first one is the output must-tell attention, yeah, so you'll try to
map the output factor into context factor, right, pretty much it's just trying to find
the context factor for the translated English works here. Masking is used to hide those unseen
work-due training, as I explained, and then afterwards you'll go through this encoder-decoder
self-attention or also known as cross-attention, which is to perform the cross-attention between
your context works, okay, from the self-attention, that means they're from your English works,
right, the context factor from English work, as well as those from your decoder output,
just the encoder output is now from the French words, right, okay, and then afterwards the result
will pass through the fit forward layer, right, to generate the output, okay, so you can see for
this particular decoder here, it leveraged on, first we perform the self-attention between the
translated English work, and then afterwards we perform the cross-attention between the French
and the English work so that you can get better representation, okay, and then finally for the
output post-processing, we map the output, okay, using softmax function to generate the next output
looks, yeah, so that's pretty much a quick summary of all the points that we have discussed just now
in all the previous slides here, okay, so we probably still have one last topic to cover,
which is the vision transformer, yeah, so what's a vision transformer, so after people develop
this transformer initially, as I mentioned, is for language translation, they find that the
performance is very good, that's why then they start to extend it to many many other different
applications, so vision transformer is the extensions of the original transmitter, but into
the domain of computer vision, specifically is used for image classification, yeah, so therefore we
can see this vision transformer is currently a state-of-the-art image classification model,
okay, based on the transformer model, let's see how it works, so first of all, right, suppose
now the goal is we want to perform image classification, so what we do is that given this
particular image here, we'll try to partition into numerous image patches, so this image will try to
partition into numerous image patches, right, and then after we have these different image patches here,
so each of these image patches now will go through a linear projection of flattened patches,
so what is this flattened patches, this flattened patches means that for each of these image patch
that you have, right, 16 by 16 image patch, now we scan it row by row, okay, and channel by channel,
right, just like what we have discussed a number of times before, so each of these image patch now
can then be converted into a vector, so this is called a fluton patches now, so afterwards each
of this particular vector will multiply with a matrix to become another vector, this is known as
a linear projection, so linear projection just means that you multiply with a particular matrix,
right, okay, to project it into some other vectors which is, you know, have a better representation,
right, so after you perform this linear projection of flattened patches, you'll get some vectors,
so these vectors are represented by this, you know, ping box here, so you have this vector here,
this vector here, and so on and so forth, okay, so the next thing that we are going to do is that
we are going to introduce a particular token known as the, you know, a learnable classification
token, so we are going to introduce this particular a strict term here which is known as the extra
learnable classification token, so this is the particular, you know, you can call interpolate,
it's a factor that can be learned, okay, a factor that can be learned, so we will introduce this
extra learnable classification token, okay, and then afterwards we are going to introduce
the position information now, so we are going to include the position embedding information,
right, so the reason is like what we mentioned before, right, we also need to know the positions
of different patches in the image, so therefore we need to introduce a position, so that position
or the other patches is one, two, three, four, five, we want to know the positions of patches
in this image, and we also, for this extra learnable classification token, we have, we give it
positions of zero, okay, so now, all right, so together with this now we are ready to do the
next step, so each of this now is actually a factor now, okay, a factor, all right, so this
factor now will go through the transformer encoder block, so this transformer encoder block is just
like, is this part there, so you can see this part is actually very similar to just now the,
you know, the early on for the transformer we have two parts, right, we have the encoder
component as well as the decoder component, for vision transformer we only focus on the encoder
block, the decoder block we don't use it, yeah, so therefore we only use this particular encoder
block, so this encoder block, you can kind of think about it, is that this encoder block actually
you have the style attention, and you have the MLP, yeah, and then you do it L times here, right,
so this encoder block what it does is that it would just, at each of this particular block here,
you extract better and, you extract better representation, context factor representation
compared to the original block, okay, so we are going to do this a few times, at the end your
output here is that you are going to have some context factors that are much better representation
than your original factor, right, and then afterwards you're just going to take the particular,
you know, context factor that correspond to this classification token, you're going to let it go
through the MLP, right, and then you're going to classify into one of the category for this image,
okay, so the reason why you're only using one particular context factor that correspond to
this is that in the process of the attention, actually after each encoder block, you already
found the contribution of all the other blocks, you already found the contribution of all the
other vectors, respect to this current token of vectors, so you already progressively extract
information from all the other patches, so therefore even though, you know, you only have one
factor here but it has already absorbed information from all the other image patches, really, so
therefore at the end you just need to use this to perform the classification, so is it possible
that you come out with some variants, like for example you may want to use no context factor
from RTRS, yeah, you can also do that, but for simplicity, right, and also because this particular
context factor already absorbed information from all the other tokens, this one itself can do the
job quite well, so therefore we only use the context factor correspond to this input factor
to perform the classification, okay, so next, all right, then this slide, see, actually just
summarize what we have discussed before, so the key steps in using this vision transformer is
first we partition image into different patches of token, and afterwards we flatten these patches
and token using lexical graphical order row by row channel by channel, right, to convert into a
vector, right, we generate the linear embedding from the flattened patches of token, linear
embedding means that we multiply with a matrix W to make it into a vector so that this vector is
slightly better representation, we introduce this extra learnable class embedding, okay,
so now just another extra token, okay, we add in the position, right, and afterwards we pass it
through the transformer encoder, so you go through this encoder, you can kind of think about it,
high-level intuition is at the end, you will have some context factor which is a much better
representation than your original vector, okay, and then afterwards we take the encoder output
from the extra learnable token, pass it through an MLP, right, to perform the classification,
so right, if you know, because training of this vision transformer is quite expensive, right,
so typically the common strategy is that someone has spent lots of time to train this
VIT on some large-scale data set, so typically, you know, someone has already
do the training, that means there's a pre-trained model already, so when we want to take this
pre-trained model for our application, so what we typically do is that we take this pre-trained
model and we only fine tune it, we only adjust a small number of parameters using our target
data set, suppose initially this someone has spent lots of time to do some, to train this data set,
for some general purpose application, but suppose our target application is to classify, you know,
an image into different plans, so and we only have a small data set for this, yeah, so therefore it's
very hard for us to train this VIT from the scratch, but fear not, what we can do is we can take the
pre-trained model, someone has trained it, okay, so that means someone has really trained this,
yeah, what we need to do is only fine tune our MLP for example, this could be one strategy,
yeah, so we take the pre-trained model, someone has trained, we only use our small data set,
our plan images, all right, to fine tune our MLP network, right, so this could be one way, right,
to do the fine tuning, so therefore training often will involve using a pre-trained model
and then fine tune it, all right, using our target data set, for example our, you know,
flower and plants, our data set for our target application,
okay, so yeah, I just, yeah, okay, so I think at this juncture we have already gone through,
you know, this a few different AI models, so let's continue, so let's continue with this question,
it says that a user would like to develop an image class application using a model that can
actually good, you know, accuracy and that also uses a tension mechanism when performing classification,
he's considering three possible candidates, either VGG, VIT, we'll just study and the LSTM,
we just study, so state which model is most likely going to meet the user's needs and justify your
answer, so you can think about it for one moment and then you can let share with me what is your
answer on the chat box, so what is the most stable model, right, to perform this image classification
and you want it to have good accuracy and use attention,
anyone, if you have some idea, please type in the chat box,
okay, we have some, yeah, some of you mentioned that vision transformer, yeah, is spot on,
I mean, based on if you understand what we have studied before in the previous lecture,
you'll know it's a vision transformer, so why, because vision transformer is, you know,
is goal is to perform classification and we know that, right, you use this transformer encoder,
so it makes use of the attention mechanism, so how about VGG, VGG actually and also vision
transformer, it has good performance, so high accuracy, VGG is a CNN, right, so it use this
convolution idea, it doesn't make use of that tension, so VGG, even though it can be used to
perform classification, but it doesn't make use of the attention mechanism and in recent years,
actually we also consider VGG performance is not so strong, okay, LSTM is to work to handle
sequential data, it's not suitable to perform image classification, yeah, and it also does not make
use of the attention, so therefore the answer clearly is vision transformer, so let me just
share with you the, yeah, so the answer is therefore vision transformer, you can see VIT
manages a transformer architecture, it use attention and it can achieve good performance,
VGG may use a CNN, it does not leverage on this global attention, right, it use convolution to
extract this information layer by layer, right, LSTM right is good for sequential data, it's not
so suitable for image classification, okay, so that is the answer, so next let's continue on,
right, okay, so yeah, good news, we are coming to the end of this section three, so in section
three summary, we covered the following, we started about attention transformer, sorry attention
transformer architecture as well as vision transformer, so therefore for part four, right,
these are the AI model we have studied, CNN, INN, LSTM and transformer, so we cover some of the very
important AI model for the context of this particular course, yeah, so we completed part four,
so in part five we are going to start to see how we can make use of this AI model in various kind
of video application, so again there are many of them but we are going to only select a few,
in particular like object detection, tracking, no post estimation and action recognition,
so those are the topics we are going to cover in part five, but as far as the crease is concerned,
it will be going to be part three, yeah, as well as part four, right, okay, I think we
managed to finish the class a bit earlier, so everyone is going to have a
gorgeous, right, we can't hit it, so any other last question before I kind of wrap up this to this class?
Okay, let me see this question, we'll try so much.
Okay, so I think you have one of you actually asked this question, why do you need to perform the
masking, so this is actually mainly during the training and how should I say, the representations
of the data during the training, because during the training it's much easier that you just take
the whole, no, you already, because when you need to train, you need to have the ground truth,
and it's much easier for you to just simply take the whole ground truth that you have and then
just use some mass to hide it out, rather than doing the training, generate training ground
truth output of different lengths, yeah, because that's very cumbersome, so therefore during the
training it's much easier just to have the output ground truth and then you just hide it, yeah,
use some mass to hide it, so it's mainly from the, how should I say, the most efficient way to
implement the strategy, yeah, I mean of course you can also generate training
sequence of increasing length, but it's very troublesome, yeah, so it's just a
a neat way of implementing this training strategy, okay, so that's the answer to the
answer, okay, I hope that particular, yeah, kind of answer,
kind of, yeah, that answer, I mean the the query that's been raised here, okay, so then that's the
next question, is that well the content today being included in the test, yes, right, I think, yeah,
that's in the brief, how should I say, in the quiz information I already clearly mentioned that
no part three and part four, yeah, will be included in the quiz, so therefore today's content, yeah,
can be tested in the quiz, right, okay, any other questions?
So if not, right, just a last reminder, so next week there's no regular lecture now,
because we have this makeup today, but in week 10 we are going to have the quiz, so please everyone,
please, you know, attend the quiz on week 10, right, so have a good weekend, I'll see you again, bye-bye.