Thank you.
Welcome back to the lecture. So today before we start just a quick announcement. So on week
I think 11, yeah, which is last Thursday, it was a public holiday. So that's why we
we don't have lecture on that day, but instead we have arranged a makeup
lectures on the 9th of November, which is this coming Saturday from 9am to 12 noon,
to replace the lectures on week 11. So this is just a reminder to tell you that we have a
makeup lecture on this coming Saturday. So the link is already sent to you in the email,
or you can go to the course site and you should be able to see the link to the Zoom lectures on
this Saturday 9am to 12 noon. All right. Okay. So the next thing I just want to very quickly
mention is that on I think week 10 we have the quiz, right, on Thursday. And then actually on
Friday I have to take a flight to attend a conference in Abu Dhabi. So I was on my way to
the airport. Now sometimes I have a habit of browsing Xiao Hongsu a little bit. So and then I
was suddenly shocked. I see why there's a few of you who is a little bit concerned about
the difficulties of the quiz, the CA2. So here I just want to kind of reassure you that you don't
really have to worry about it. Right. The situation is like this. So I think it's because
there are a number of you who actually are a little bit concerned. So that's why I'll try to
kind of let you know. Actually for CA1, which is the homework, right, I actually have marked quite
a number of them already. So majority of you do very well. The average is actually very high.
Yeah. So that's why because CA1 is kind of easy and the average is very high. So that's why
CA2 initially I planned it to make it a little bit more require a bit more thinking.
But it's actually not initially I thought it's not that difficult. I thought it's a bit more
difficult, but not really that difficult. Yeah. But it turned out that right based on what I
kind of fit that I heard from Xiao Hongsu. So it seems that some of you think that it's a little
bit difficult, but you don't have to worry about that because as I mentioned CA1, the average
is very high. Yeah. So for CA2, when I do the marking, right, I'll try to mark more flexibly.
That means right. So you don't so long as you write something and it makes sense even for
meta marks for methods or steps, you'll get some marks. It doesn't have to be that your answer is
a correct. Then you'll get the full mark. So long as you write something, it looks reasonable,
you'll receive marks for it. Yeah. And also if necessary, I'll also do some adjustment. So
just put it this way. I'm more worried if you do not do well. Right. So yeah. So we'll try to make
sure that your marks are reasonable. Right. So you don't have to worry too much about it.
So that's number one. Number two is also partly because for this year, right, some of the classes
actually I just take over from previous lecture. So I also need some time to really find out
where is your relative car expectation. So that's why we usually need to take a bit of time to
adjust it. Yeah. Okay. And then also just finally to make sure that actually for the quiz, question
one is relatively standard. Right. There's a little bit of difficult parts, but usually those
marks are scalable. Usually I see if the student have some difficulty in answering those questions,
then I'll try to reduce the percentage of marks allocated for those more difficult parts. So for
question two, again, there's an easy and difficult part. Right. So the slightly more difficult part
actually is within the scope of this course as well. Right. So it's not outside the scope.
Actually, we have gone through some example. Yeah. But you require a bit more thinking.
Okay. So I think I probably explained quite a fair bit. So long story short, what I'm trying to say
is don't worry too much about it. Yeah, it should be fine. We'll do some adjustment if necessary.
Okay. So don't get to lose the sleep over it. All right. Okay. So yeah, with that out of the way,
yeah. Another thing I probably want to quickly highlight is that I'm not sure whether you have
received some email to perform some teaching feedback assessment of my teaching. If you have
done that, if you have received the email, please just spend one moment or two to complete the
teaching feedback, right, for this course. Yeah.
So any questions or any concerns? Right. Okay. So if not, let's continue on with
today's lecture. Right. So for today's lecture, before we start, because as we are moving more
and more into some slightly more advanced topics, sometimes we need to leverage on some of the
AI models and understanding that you have studied in the previous lectures. So I just want to very
quickly kind of highlight or recap your memory about the CNN as well as the vision transformer,
because for the next few parts of today's lecture, we need to have some basic understanding of those
concepts. So that's why here, I just want to very quickly do a quick recap, right, so that you
can still remember some of the key properties of the CNN as well as the vision transformer,
so that later on when we go into the explanation, you wouldn't feel that suddenly there's something
that you cannot get the connection. So if you remember for a CNN, this is the typical structures
of a CNN. So you have the image, right, afterwards it will go through the convolutional layer.
So for the convolutional layer, it, you know, let it go through the filter or kernel to extract the
feature, right, to extract the features from this particular image. Okay. And then typically you'll
go through the activation function, right. Okay. And then finally by the pooling to reduce the size.
So typically this convolution activation function and pooling you'll repeat this process a few times.
Okay. So the process of performing this, right, performing this convolution and pooling,
essentially you're extracting some feature from the image. Yeah. You're extracting the features
from the image. And afterwards once you reach the last steps here, typically we'll do a flattening.
We'll scan it row by row. Okay. Channel by channel and convert it into a vector. So this vector here
is what we call a vector or a descriptor or an embedding which, you know, contain useful information
to represent this image. Yeah. So this is a very high level kind of understanding just to recap your
memory. So therefore when we say that we perform a CNN, right, if you look at this particular domain
here, right, so this will be some feature that is extracted from the image to represent the image.
So it extracts some useful feature to represent the image or equivalently if we flatten it into
the vector, then this factor contains some representative information to represent this image.
Okay. So that is for the CNN. So next let's move on to the vision transformer.
Okay. So next we want to quickly recap your memory about how a vision transformer works.
So how a vision transformer works is that, right, okay. The original goals of the vision
transformer is that given a particular image, yeah, you want to classify into a different
category. So what do we do? So what we do is that we take this particular image and we partition it
into numerous patches, okay, numerous patches here. Right. So now this image should be partitioned
into numerous patches. Okay. So this is what we have. Right. So in each of the patch here,
we'll convert it into a vector. We'll use a lexical, graphical or string scan it row by row.
Okay. Channel by channel to convert it into a vector. Right. So each of this now will become a
vector. So after each of this vector will go through a linear projection of the flattened patches.
So this flattened patches actually refer to, we scan it row by row, column by column, right,
to convert an image patch into a vector. So this is known as a flattened patches now.
So each of this now, after you flatten it, it become a vector. And then this linear projection
just simply means that this vector, you multiply with a matrix. Yeah. You multiply with a matrix
and output is another vector. Okay. So that's the meaning of the linear projection. So after the
linear projection now, what you have is that you have a bunch of linearly projected embedding.
Right. Embedding is just a representation or you can interpret as a vector. Okay.
Right. So you have now the projected vectors here, right, which is shown in this pink color.
And afterwards you add in the position, right, because for vision transformer,
you need the positions of the patches and in an image is important. So therefore you need to
add in the position by one, two, three, four, five. So these are all the positions. So you add in the
position information. Right. And on top of that, you have one particular additional,
no token, right, which we call the no learnable class embedding or token here. Okay. Right. So
now you have this bunch of defectors and then we put it into the vision, this transformer encoder.
So if you remember that for trans, this transformer, there's two parts, you have the encoder and you
have the decoder. So we put it through this particular transformer encoder here. So this is
the structures of the transformer encoder. So what you have here, this embedded patches is actually
all these vectors here, right. You do the multi-hit self-attention, right, that we have explained
before. You go through the MLP and then your output is a bunch of vectors. So high level
interpretation, what we have is that your input is a bunch of vectors. Okay. Your input is a bunch
of vectors. After you go through this transformer encoder, right, your output is also a bunch of
vectors. Okay. Also a collection of vector. But your output here is a collection of vectors here.
But these collections of vectors is better than the original embedded vector. Can you remember
what is the reason? Why the output of the vectors is better than, you know, the input
to the transformer encoder? What's the high level reasoning?
Without going into the detailed mathematics, right, just a high level reasoning. Because
sometimes when you are the, how should I say, and when you are studying deeper and deeper,
sometimes you know, you have to leave some of the detail and then just try to understand the high
level intuition. Yeah. But first, if you want to recall, you can always go and read up a little
bit more. But high level understanding is your input is a bunch of vectors, collections of vector.
You let it go through a transformer encoder. Your output is also a collection of vector.
But why is this output vector better than the input vector?
Can anyone still remember? Because this is the basic essence of transformer. Why transformer is
good? Without even going into the mathematics, you need to know this.
Okay. Right. Probably it was a few weeks ago already. So the reason why your output,
right, vectors, which is also known as the context vectors, are better than the input,
is because when you look at the transformer, essentially what you have is that if you remember,
last time the example that I told you is that I said that if, you know, this is actually a mouse,
right? So if I tell you a mouse, it may not be clear to you whether it's a computer mouse,
or whether it's a cat and mouse. So in all that, in order for you to fully understand this word
mouse, what does it mean? You need to know the surrounding context works. So therefore,
there's this idea here. If you want to have a better representation of this current work,
you need to know the relationship of all the other works to the, to work this current works that you
are not looking at. So by trying to find the importance or contributions of other works,
to work this current, this current work, then you can actually extract a vector representation.
And this vector is a better representation because it found out the relationship or contributions
of all the other surrounding works to work. So that is in the image, in the language domain.
In the image domain, it's also the same. You have different image patches,
which convert into a vector now. It's equivalent. So you want to look at the relationship of other
image patches to work sit. So that the output now actually is a better representation because
they found the relationship of other image patches to work sit. So therefore, long story short, what
it means is that the output of all these factors here, output vectors of this transformer encoder,
they are better representation that this input vector because it looked at,
right, for example, if you look at this output here, it looked at the contribution
or importance of other patches to work sit. And then afterwards extract a better,
no feature representation, which is known as a context vector. And you repeat these steps,
no number of times, actually L times here. Okay. And then finally, you just simply take the output
from this particular learnable token here. Okay. And then you let it go through MLP
hit, right, to perform the classification. Why you can only need to take the output from
this particular token is because, right, throughout this different process, you already continuously
trying to extract information from other patches or other token already. So that,
therefore, even though you are taking one single hit here, but it should contain
sufficient information for you to perform the classification. Okay. So that's a quick recap
of this vision transformer understanding, right, because later on, we are going to,
no, look into the next part on the DTR. Okay. So this vision transformer.
Yeah. I think this transformer is probably a bit too, let me see. Right. Okay. Maybe I also quickly
explain, just refresh your memory about this transformer, right. So for the transformer,
initially is used for language translation, yeah, for machine language translation. So what you
have here input, right, is a sequence of, for example, French, right, French sentence you want to
translate into English. So therefore your input is actually a bunch of, you know, these
factors, right, okay, work embedding, right. Okay. So the input factors for the French works,
and afterwards, they add in the position and information because you need to indicate what
is the positions of the works in the sentence. Right. Okay. And afterwards, we go through this
particular module. So this part here is your transformer encoder, right, exactly similar to
what we have mentioned earlier on. So you let it go through n times the miss each time you're going
to extract vector and vector vector representation. So that after a couple of times n here, your output
here will be a bunch of vectors. Okay. That has a vector representation as compared to your input.
Okay. So this output from this particular transformer now is going to go into this particular part,
if you remember, this is the decoder, right. So the decoder part here, right, so the decoder part
here, what we have is that this output here, right, this output here is a translated language,
for example, from French to English, that means it's your progressively translated English, right.
Say suppose we have already translated a few works. So say suppose we have translated, you know,
two works, I and M here in English, then it will go through this work embedding to get this
vector representation, right, we call it the output embedding here. And then you add in the
position information to indicate the positions of your translated English works. Okay. And afterwards,
you go through this module. This module is actually, you can see, is a multi-head attention. This part
here is trying to find the relationship between the translated English works so far. So that you
look at the translated English work so far, you look at the contributions of the translated English
works so far to get a better English kind of a vector representation. So this is the objective
of this. That means you're trying to look at the attention between the translated English works.
And afterwards, at this point here, then you take this part here is the cross attention,
or sometimes also known as the encoder decoder attention. So because this part is the decoder,
sorry, encoder, this part is the decoder. So this module here is trying to perform the encoder
decoder attention or cross attention here. So what they are doing for this particular module is that
you have your, no, this particular French context vector, okay, coming from the decoder. And also
you have some partially translated English work, English factors. You want to find the
relationship between them. Okay. Previously, it was fully written English French works, and then
between translated English works, but the cross relation is also important. So this is the part
we do that. So we do the cross tension here. And afterwards, we let it go through a fit forward
layer. So fit forward layer, as I mentioned to you before, is like general purpose transformation.
It's expensive. That's why we don't use it so much, but it can improve the performance. So we
generate, okay, we let it go through the fit forward. So the output here will be a bunch of,
no, vectors, which are much better representation, right, because it consider
the relationship between the translated English work, as well as the relationship between
the translated English work as well as the French work. Okay. So now output here, now it's a better
representation. It capture all the relationship between all these different works. And then finally,
you let it go through a linear layer. You let it multiply with a matrix, the build, right, and then
you let it convert it into softmax probability to see what is the most likely next work that is
going to be translated. For example, if this works, I am, and then later on the next work, it says,
if it's after the softmax is c set, the most likely works is, right, I am, I am, I say it's
a, then this, this work will then be pulled down here and then you repeat the process. Okay. So that
is the kind of recap of, you know, what a transformer, how it works. Okay. So hopefully this will refresh
your memory. With that next, we can continue with today's lecture.
Okay.
Yeah. So in the lectures, in the previous lecture, actually we cover some of the basic
object detection methods, right. And then afterwards we stop at this particular slide. So
now we are going to continue on to look at another object detection method. So the next
object detection method step we are going to look at is known as a detection transformer,
also known as DTR. So DTR is an end-to-end object detection with transformer. So this is one of the
very kind of popular recent object detection method based on transformer. Okay. So let's look at some
basic information regarding this method and afterwards we'll try to explain how this particular
DTR method works. So first of all, it's a popular recent object detection method, right, as mentioned
early on. So it tried to predict in parallel the sets of the detection by combining a common CNN
with a transformer architecture. So later on, when we explain about this DTR object detection
transformer, you will see that it may use of the CNN, okay, right, and it also make use of the
transformer. You can see this is a transformer encoder and this is the transformer decoder.
And it will try to predict a set of objects, okay, in parallel. Okay. So you have a bunch of object
query and then you will try to detect all these detected objects at the same time in parallel.
Okay. So these are some of the key features. Right. Okay. So this decoder is different from the
original attention or it's all unique design. So the attention is all unique design is just
now the original transformer architecture that I have very briefly explained to you.
So for this DTR, the decoders here, you are not generating the works one by one. So if you remember
just now we have just explained the original transformer, when you try to do the translation,
it generates the works one at a time. Okay. But for this DTR methods, it actually put in a bunch
of object query. Okay. And then you obtain the detected object bounding box as well as a category
at the same time. Okay. Right. So the input to the decoder is given a sequence of position
encoding or object query. So for this decoder here, your input is a bunch of these object queries here,
which is some kind of embedding of vectors that you can learn. Okay. So right. So those are some
high level kind of context understanding. So next let's look at this particular
no DTR decoder here. So first of all, what you have is that you have some backbone
networks here. Right. Okay. So these backbone networks, you can choose any suitable network.
For example, you can in this original design, they use a CNN. This CNN can, for example,
be a RESTnet. It can be a VGG or some other network. Right. So it's a general CNN network here.
Right. So you will obtain this particular, no, you'll let it go through a CNN. Right. So you have
an originally input image. Right. You'll let it go through a CNN. Then afterwards you'll obtain
the features. Right. Because it goes through many different convolutional layer. Okay. At the end,
you will have a particular kind of a feature, feature map that correspond to the CNN. Right. So
this is what you have. Okay. And afterwards for this particular feature map, right, you can partition
it into numerous patches. Yeah. Partition into numerous patches, just like the, the early parts
of just some of the vision transformer. So if you remember the vision transformer earlier on,
we also partitioned into numerous patches. But for this DTR, what it does is that first of all,
it let it pass through a CNN to extract some features. Right. Before, you know, you partition
into different patches. And then afterwards you add in the position information. Right. Because for
this, once you partition into different patches, right. So you have different patches that indicate
different location in the image. So you introduce this position encoding to indicate where is the
positions of the patches. Right. Okay. So now the output here is you have a bunch of factors here
now. Right. So you can see this output, you know, this thing is put it as an input to this
transformer encoder now. So the input now is actually a collection of factors. Okay. Just like,
just similar to the vision transformer. Right. After you pass through the CNN, you extract the
feature, you partition into numerous patches. Okay. You flatten it into a vector. You add in the
position information. So now you have a bunch of vectors at this position here. Okay. So this bunch
of vectors you can kind of interpret is like, for example, if you have an image, right, if your
image is a vector, you have one vector for each of these particular patches. Right. Okay. And
afterwards we let it go through a transformer encoder and you obtain the output here. So what is the
purpose of this transformer encoder here? Can anyone still remember?
Okay.
What's the purpose of this transformer encoder?
So this input here is just a bunch of factors corresponding to different patches in the image.
Right. So you let it go through a transformer encoder. What's the objective of this transformer encoder?
Yes.
Yeah. You want to extract some context factor that we're exploiting. Right. The contribution
or no relationship of the other patches that works it and these particular processes perform
using the attention because the attention mechanism. So that's exactly right. All right. So please
remember the objective of this particular transformer encoder is that you want to take these input
factors, right, and then you want to perform the self-attention to find the contributions of other
vectors to work it so that your output now, right, is a bunch of context vector that has a better
representation than your original context vector because they found the relationship from other
patches. So now after you go through this particular transformer encoder, your output is actually a
collection of vectors now with a better representation. Okay. That described this image. Right. That described
this input image here. Right. Okay. And then after we are going to let it go through a transformer
decoder now. So this transformer decoder is similar to the transformer decoder that I have
just mentioned to you before. Except the difference now is that, okay, right. This input now is
actually what is known as the object query. Okay. So this object query is like some initial
position, learn position embedding, some initial learn embedding, which is a vector that roughly
represents where the initial guess of the starting point of your object. Right. So you have some
vectors or embedding. Okay. Which is your initial guess of where the object is. Right. It can be
learned. It can be fixed. Right. Okay. And then after works, you are going to let it go through
the transformer decoder. So this transformer decoder as early on explained is you are trying to find
out the relationship between this vectors here. Okay. And this vectors here. Right. So this vectors,
actually this bunch of vectors here actually contain the visual information of different patches
in the image. This bunch of the vectors here contain the initial position information of your
lightly object. So you want to take on one side is your image region. On the other side is your
initial guess of the position. You want to find out their relationship. You want to find out,
you know, where this object likely corresponds to which region. So we let it go through this
particular transformer decoder. Right. Okay. The internal operation is similar to just now the
transformer decoder that we have. And then your output now would be some embedding or some vector
that has a better representation than your initial one because it takes into account, right,
the relationship with your initial guess respect to the visual information. Yeah. So therefore,
you actually take the cross relationship, the relationship between your initial object guess
where it is, respect to the visual information. So therefore, the output here is some better guess
of your position, but in the form of vectors. Right. And then finally, right, suppose in this
example, say we assume that, right, we say that, okay, maybe this four objects in this image.
That's why we have four object queries here. And then after we go through this transformer
decoder, you will have four outputs here. Right. So each of these output, you let it go through
FFN. FFN is a fit forward network. Right. You let it go through a fit forward head network.
And then each of these fit forward network will perform a classification to find whether there's
an object and where is the pounding box for this object. So for example, in this case, right, for
the first position guess, right. Okay. It actually found out that, okay, no, the class is actually
a bird. And this is the bounding box. Okay. For the green position query, actually, after this
fit forward network, it says that if I that there's no object there. So therefore, there's no object.
Right. And then this, this yellow one go to a network. Okay. If I that there's actually
another bird there, another category called bird. And this is the bounding box for the other bird.
And then finally, the last one, okay, the last query that you have, you go through this
before on the work, it says that there's no object. Yeah. So therefore, from this four queries here,
after you do the training, you'll be able to detect two objects here. So this particular method is
known as the detection transformer is one of the recent and more important object detection methods.
Right. Okay. So let's look at this particular caption to further see what they describe. So
it says that DTR use a conventional CNN backboard to learn a 2D representation of an input image.
Right. So even your input image here, it let it go through a CNN to extract some visual feature.
Yeah. Just like what we mentioned. Okay. And afterwards, the model flatten it, right. Flatten
means that you chop it into different patches, convert it into a vector. Right. That's what
it means by flattening. Okay. And then you add in the position encoding. You need to indicate
where is the positions of these different patches, right, before you pass into the transformer
encoder. Right. So this transformer encoder by now, you must know, right. You must know that
this transformer encoder, it take a bunch of input vector, right, extract better representation.
Right. Okay. And then generate some better context factor that leverage on the attention
mechanism. Okay. All right. So afterwards, you have this transformer decoder now.
Okay. It takes input, a fixed number of a limb position embedding. So this transformer encoder,
transformer decoder, it bring in this object query. This object query is also the position
embedding. So it's some initial guess of where the positions of this object like it is.
Right. So initially it really doesn't matter. You can make some guess or you can learn it.
Okay. So this position embedding is known as object query here. Okay. And afterwards,
it attend to the encoder output. That means you try to find the cross attention between this
position embedding and the visual representations of different patches in the image. Okay. And
afterwards, you go through this encoder a few times. Your output now would be a better position
embedding. That means you learn where likely this object is because you find the cross
attention between your query and your visual representation. Okay. Right. Okay. And afterwards,
we pass each output embedding, each of this, okay, to a shared feed forward network. So you pass it
through each of this feed forward network here. Right. And then you will then do a prediction.
All right. So whether you can do a detection, whether an object exists and also if it exists,
where is the bounding box? Right. If not, then it will say that, no, for this particular query,
there's no corresponding object to it. Right. Okay. So that's a basic idea of DTR. Okay. Please
spend some time to understand it. Right. Okay. So next, let's look at the performance comparison
with this DTR here. So for this DTR, you can see that, right? So we have some comparison with respect
to the faster RCNM that we have studied before. And also there's a few different variants of
this DTR here. Right. So some of them is based on ResNet or 50. Right. Some of them is based on
ResNet 101, 50 layers or 101 layers. Right. Okay. Anyway, these are some details. Probably you
don't have to worry too much. But pretty much what we have is that these are four different variants
of the DTR implementation. And this is an earlier important object detection method known as a faster
RCNM. Right. Okay. So if you look at it, these are the number of floating points operations here
and the frame per second, number of parameters. Right. So, okay. And then in terms of performance,
usually a bold means that is the best among each of these. So this AP here is a performance matrix
that we have introduced in previous lecture. So all in all, it can be seen that DTR is a relatively
good performance, has relatively good performance as compared to the previous faster RCNM methods.
Okay. So this method was proposed in 2020. Right. It still continues to be used in quite a number.
Subsequently, there are some improvements and it's still one of the very popular methods even
until now. Okay. Right. Okay. So this particular diagram shows the visualizations here. So the DTR
visualizations here, for example, if you take one of this, but during the transformer encoder stage,
right, during the transformer encoder stage, right, so we take this input image,
we let it go through, we have an input image, we let it go through the CNN, we will get some, you
know, feature representation. Yeah. We partition it into different patches. Okay. We partition it
into different patches and then we have these different patches here. So each of these different
patches, if you remember, right, when we perform the self-attention, you need to project into the
query key as well as the value. Right. So if you take the current patch, you want to find the
relationship, okay, or the importance of other patches towards this, right. If you remember,
we actually do the inner product between query and key and afterwards we take the
softmax normalization. Yeah. You want to see other patches. What is their contribution
towards your current patch? Yeah. So that's what we are doing here. So if you do that,
suppose if you look at this, this is your current query, right, this is the current patch you want
to look into. You want to see what is the contributions of other patches towards it. So if you do that,
using the DTR, you can see for this current patch location, right, these are the regions that indicate
importance towards this current patch, right. Okay. So now if you take this current patch as a query,
these are the regions that show the importance towards this current patch. So likewise, if you
take this as a query, these are the regions that's important. And then if you take this one, these
are the regions. So up to a certain extent, you can see that by looking at this particular hit map,
right. So this sometimes we call it the attention map, right. So we can see that if you are looking
about this current patch, what is the importance of other patches to work? It actually has some,
it makes, it's part of meaningful because this is part of the cow. So this part of the attention
actually corresponds to this part of the cow, right. This one here corresponds to this part of
the cow. Okay. This one here, this region here corresponds to this part of the cloud, cow,
and this region here corresponds to that. So it actually kind of gives you some visualization
and confidence that those patches actually are important towards current patch that you are
looking at. Okay. Right. So we spent some time talking about it. So next, let's move on. Okay.
So the next exercise is that, right. Okay. So this is the passier exam question. It says that
state clearly whether the following object detectors are one stage or two stage, okay,
for RCNN and YOLO V7. And then which of these two object detector is a more suitable choice
if speed is a key consideration, right. So justify your answer. So I'll give you one moment to think
about it, right, to see whether you can still recall that and then we'll go through the answers together.
Okay. So I think we have some time to think about it. But so which of them is a one stage detector
and which one is a two stage. So RCNN is a one stage or two stage, two stage, right. And then YOLO
V7 is one stage or two stage, one stage, right. Okay. So which of these detector is more suitable
choice if your key consideration is you want it to be fast. So which one is faster? Typically one
stage is faster or two stage is faster. One stage, right. So one stage is faster. Okay. So therefore
YOLO V7 is a more suitable choice, right. And also YOLO V7 is a much later iteration as compared to
this RCNN. So in terms of speed as well as performance is actually up-perform RCNN. Okay.
So,
right. Okay. So the answer is here, right. So RCNN is a two stage detector. YOLO V7 is a one stage.
So YOLO V7 is a more suitable choice because it's a more recent one stage object detection.
And one stage tends to be faster, right. Okay. So therefore, you know, a more suitable choice is
a YOLO V7, right. So this answer I'll upload to the course site later.
Okay. So as I mentioned, please try to spend some time to understand this DTR.
Okay. So with that, actually we complete our part on object detection. So for this part here,
we actually studied the following, right. So we covered the introduction, right. And after
works under the object detection method, we look at two stage method, one stage detectors,
lightweight detectors, as well as some new emerging methods, including, you know, the DTR that we have
looked at. Yeah. And also just now, in last week, the SYN transformer approach.
All right. Okay. So next let's move on to the object detection part now.
Right. So under the object detection, we are going to look at the following. So first of all,
we'll be doing a quick introductions and then we'll be looking at MOT, multiple object tracking,
right. And after works, we'll look at some new and emerging directions under this object tracking.
Right. Okay. So what's the objective of object tracking? I think from the name itself is quite
intuitive already. You have multiple object tracking. That means you're trying to track the
movement of multiple objects at the same time, right. So for example, in this case here, you have
three persons here. You want to track the movements of these three persons here. Yeah. You want to
track, you know, whether this person is moving from here, right. This person moved to here and
this person moved to that. So therefore, it's use case is that you actually have a video. You want
to track the movement of multiple objects, right, in a video. So the tracking can involve tracking
of a human, right, which is quite common in many applications, right. It can also be used to track
things like, you know, vehicles, right, and so on and so forth. Okay. So the objective of this
MOT is that you want to track the same persons or objects, for example, vehicles in a city,
in a continuous frame in the video, right. So the objects are typically represented with some
bounding blocks and ID, right. So you'll use some bounding blocks to indicate the object and you'll
also give them some ID, right. For example, this ID one, ID two, ID three to differentiate
different person, right. So typically the results is the input, right. The detection results are
the input to the tracking algorithm. So when you want to track a person, usually the first step
that you do is that even the first frame, you want to detect all the objects of interest in the first
frame and then that will initialize your tracking algorithm to track all your detected objects in
the first frame. Okay. So what are some challenges or issues when you are trying to perform this
tracking here, right. So there are two important factors when you are trying to track a person.
So without even learning about it, I think you can think about it, it's quite intuitive. What are the
things that you should use to track person? If you don't look at the content, just use some
logical thinking. What are the key for us to track person? Number one is your movement, right. So if
you know that this guy is moving in this direction, likely your next frame, this guy is going to move
a little bit in that direction. So that the motion model is one common tool used to perform tracking.
And the second one is visual appearance, right. Because this guy, if I'm wearing like this, chances
you see another person that looks like this, wearing like this, likely it's me if I know a few
seconds later. Okay. So therefore these are the two common cues we use to perform the tracking.
One is the appearance feature. Okay. How does this object look like? The second one is the
motion feature, right. Well, how is this object being moving around? So, right, what's the movement
of the object and in the next few frames, where would this object be? So these are two common
clues or cues that we use to develop our multiple object tracking or MOT algorithms.
Right. So therefore next we are going to go into the multiple object tracking or MOT.
Right. So the idea of MOT is quite straightforward, right. So MOT, right, we aim to track all the
object of interest. For example, person, vehicles or other things simultaneously. Right. So for
example, you have this video clips here. All right. This is a video clips of two ladies walking.
So when you use MOT algorithm, first of all, you initialize two detection bounding box to say,
okay, these are the two person of interest that we want to track. Okay. And then we give it an ID
one and two. And afterwards our algorithm is supposed to track consistently where this ID one is
moving. Okay. And then likewise ID two, where they are moving. So this is very intuitive,
the basic idea of MOT. Right. So what are some of the challenges in MOT? So there are some
challenges in MOT. Number one is that sometimes the objects they are dealing with have a similar
appearance. Right. Maybe you have a few persons wearing similar clothes. Right. So you need to
differentiate them. That's one challenge. Right. Other things include sometimes you may have lots
of background objects. Right. Such as, you know, hydrants.
Okay. So another very important challenge is the occlusion. Right. Occlusion means part of the
body is hidden away. For example, if I know, if there's a, you know, a box somewhere, like walk
into it. So for some moment, no, my body will disappear from your view. And then a few moments
later I reappear. So whether you can actually track when your object is being occluded or under
serious heavy occlusion. So these are some typical challenges for MOT. Right. Okay. So the, there
are many different techniques that to perform this, you know, MOT. But the one that we are going to
introduce here is some of the more popular approach, which is known as a tracking by detection.
So as the name suggests, tracking by detection, that means you try to track by detecting in each
frame. Okay. You try to detect the object of interest and then you try to see what, whether the
detected object in the current frame and the detected object in the next frame, whether they
can be associated together. Right. So this particular approach is known as a tracking
by detection. It's centering on trying to detect or object of interest in each frame. Right. So the
goal is that you want to detect the objects in individual video frames. Okay. And then afterwards
you want to associate whether this bounding box and this bounding box, actually they belong to, for
example, the same person. So we want to perform the association. So you want to associate sets of
detection between frame. Right. So therefore creating individual object tracks over time.
Right. Okay. So you can see, for example, okay, however, there are some problems with this kind
of approach here is that your detection sometimes may not be accurate. Right. For example, you may
get a false positive. Right. You thought there's an object here, but it's actually not an object. So
that's called false positive or missing detection, false negative. Right. There's actually an object
that, but you do not detect it successfully. So there's a false negative. Right. So these are some
of the common challenge. So for example, if you look at this blue bounding box here, right,
so this blue bounding box here, you can see you can actually track this person successfully.
Right. So no problem. Right. But for example, for this orange bounding box from here to here,
you can track properly. But from here to here, you make a mistake because it actually, you know,
do a false positive detection here. Then this will create an error. So likewise for this green one,
right, suppose here you detect this, but here you have a false negative. You do not detect this
person successfully. Then you will not be able to track. So therefore for tracking by detection,
you need to make sure that your detection is reliable. Right. Okay. For your performance to
work well. Okay. So what are some high level steps to perform this tracking by detection?
So first of all, you need to make use of object detector to initialize the track at frame T.
So suppose you have a video, right, you have a video, it starts with frame T. Right. So it
starts with frame T, you will be using some object detection algorithm to detect some objects here.
Right. So for example, you detect this three person. So this will be used to initialize the
track. Right. Okay. And afterwards you are going to use the motion prediction, right, because you
can look at the previous movement of this particular bounding box. Therefore by using some motion
modeling, you can predict what is the likely positions of the next bounding box is. Right. So
this is known as a motion prediction. So you'll try to predict the next positions of the object
using some motion model. Right. There's many different motion model. They don't will see a few.
Right. Okay. So for example, by assuming that previously you have been, you have the information
about the movement of this particular bounding box. Then you can use a motion model to predict roughly.
Okay. Your prediction where the next bounding box in the next frame will be. Okay. And afterwards,
right, for this particular new frame, you also perform object detection, which is shown in this
particular red box. So for this frame t plus one, you also perform the object detection. So this
yellow bounding box is actually your predicted position using the motion model. And the red
bounding box is your detection using some object detection algorithm. So afterwards, you have one
prediction, which is based on your motion. The other prediction is which is based on your
object detection. You want to see how close this two is. So of course, if these two are very close
together, then you have a higher confidence that actually this particular object is arising from
the movement of the previous corresponding objects. Right. So therefore, if these two
boxes are closely aligned or the IOU intersection over unions high, that means we have a strong
confidence, this red detected object and this yellow prediction and this yellow prediction is
coming from here. That means we can actually associate this person, this object here in the
previous frame with this object in the current frame. So I think the idea is actually very intuitive
and easy to understand. Right. So therefore, the next step is that we need to perform the data
association. We'll try to match the predicted position with the detection at frame t plus one,
just like what I mentioned to you. Right. Okay. So next, what are some
way we can model the movement of the object? Right. So motion model, the goal is to do the
prediction based on the movement of the object. We track the movement of the object. Right. So we
need to make some assumption, which is the object is moving at, for example, a constant speed.
Right. You cannot have object moving the field frame moving this and then suddenly change its
direction. Yeah. So if you do that, then your motion model is not going to perform well. So we
have to make an assumption is moving at constant velocity. Okay. So the, there's some common
motion modeling technique, for example, common filtering, particle filtering and so on and so
forth. Right. So you can use any of these techniques to do the motion prediction, but one of the most
popular one is current, currently it's a common filtering because it's actually quite easy.
Right. Okay. So early on we mentioned that we also need to do the data association. Right. So
this data association is pretty much last as I mentioned, right. From the previous track of the
movement, you will get a prediction of in the next frame, where is this object is. And afterwards,
you also do the object detection. Right. To try to detect. Okay. So you have this predicted
object and this is your detected object in current frame. Right. And then afterwards,
these two bounding box, you want to see how similar they are. If they are similar, or if they have a
high intersection over union, that means you know that, right, it's likely the same person. Right.
So the object used to predict your motion and this detector object, they are the same person.
So this is known as the data association. So the basic idea is actually quite simple,
like what I mentioned before, you based on this IOU, kind of matrix here, IOU, if you recall,
is the area of overlap over that area of union. So one of the bounding box predicted
bounding box due to the motion, the other is a detected object, right, from the object detector.
Right. So this is one of them. This is the second one. So if these two are very close together,
that means there's high IOU. So when the object has high IOU, that means you can associate them
together. Right. Okay. So this data association, therefore, is like this. So you can see we can
actually form this particular table here. Right. So the one in this particular role here is a
prediction. So the prediction arising from your motion model. Right. So this column here is actually,
you know, the result that you obtain as the using the detector. Right. So afterwards, you just try
to find, right, know the similarity here. Right. Okay. You can either use a similarity or the
distance. This table here is given in terms of the distance between those two predictions here.
So obviously this same color code refers to the same person. So if you compare this person,
you respect to, I mean, this detection respect to this prediction, their distance is smaller.
Right. As compared to three other prediction. Right. Okay. So therefore, you want to assign
this detection to this prediction. It's a one to one mapping. You want to map one prediction
to one detection. Right. So it's a one to one mapping. Yeah. All right. So anyway, let's try to
go through it. Right. So for this data association, it's saying that a simple matching of the detection
with the predicted box by using common filtering. Right. So this is the prediction is using the
common filtering. Right. So it can calculate the distance between the boxes. Right. So in this
case, the smaller the distance, that means that more similar they are. And afterwards, it will
make use of a Hungarian algorithm. So this Hungarian algorithm is to perform a one to one mapping.
Right. Because you have, for example, in this case, you have four detection and you have four
prediction. So we do a one to one assignment. Yeah. So you, for example, you match this to this,
this to this. Right. Okay. First, this is a simple illustrations. So this Hungarian algorithm will
perform a one to one matching. Right. Okay. To associate a detection with a motion prediction.
Okay. And then the distance is usually based on this IOU matrix that I mentioned. Right. Okay.
Okay. So next, let's look at, right, one of the techniques that we have. Right. So one of the
techniques that we have is known as a deep sort. Right. Okay. So this sort, what does deep sort stand
for? Sort stand for simple online and real time tracking. So deep sort is actually a relatively
popular technique because it's efficient. Okay. Right. It doesn't give you the best performance,
but it's efficient. Right. So for this deep sort technique here, right. So it also adds
visual appearance information. So it makes use of some appearance feature to help to perform the
data association between your detection due to the detectors and the prediction by common filtering.
So previous, until just now when we talk about the motion model, you are simply trying to predict,
okay. Find out the difference between or the similarity between your prediction due to the
motion model as well as detection. So far, it has not leveraged on the visual appearance in other
similarity. It's simply leveraged on the first cue, which is the motion. So motion alone is not
enough. You also need to look at the visual appearance of the object. So that's why for
deep sort, it also further introduce a visual appearance, okay, to help to perform the matching.
So the high level idea is this, right. So suppose you have a video, right. Okay. We have a video.
We can use any object detector. For example, in this case, it's a YOLO V4, right, to perform the
detections, okay, to perform the detections of all the objects across different frame. Right. So it
can also make use of, for example, no, the difference across different frame to help you to perform the
detection. Right. So afterwards, okay, we'll use the common filtering. So this common filtering is
due, as I mentioned, based on the previous bounding box to find, right, in the next frame, where's
the positions of your predicted bounding box. So this common filtering is a motion model.
Okay. So for deep sort technique, what it does introduce is that apart from the motion, it also
extracts the visual appearance information. So it looked at this particular bounding box and
tried to extract some visual information to represent this particular region you're tracking.
So this is the part about this deep sort here. It also introduced this visual appearance descriptor,
right, that's used to describe the visual information of the objects. Right. And then
afterwards, this Mahalo Vist distance is a way to assign or to measure the distance, right. In this
context, we don't have to worry too much about it. And afterwards, we need to let it go through a
Hungarian assignment. So this Hungarian assignment is just out of the table. You have n detected
object. You have n predicted bounding box. So you need to do one to one assignment. Which
one is matching to which one. So this is the Hungarian algorithm. Right. So next, we want to
see how do we exactly extract these features here. Right. So there are many different ways you can
extract the visual features to represent a region. So what is being introduced here is one
simple way. Right. So for deep sort, we need to make use of its visual appearance, right, which we
call no appearance. It can either be a descriptor, a factor, a feature or embedding. It all refers
to the same thing. So how do you extract, how do you train a network to extract the visual
appearance for this bounding box here. So what we do is very simple. Right. Suppose we have some
training data, right. So we have some video clips. And in this video clips, we actually
already know the bounding box. Okay. For all the person, for example, this is a person one ID one,
we have all the bounding box. This is ID two, we have all the bounding box here. So for each of
this particular, okay. And then afterwards, we introduce a CNN network, right, a CNN network
here. Right. So every time we introduce, for example, your input, we provide this particular image as
the input. And then we are predicted output will say that is ID one. Next, if you present this,
we also say it's person one, we present this, we say it's person one. Okay. And afterwards, we present,
next, we present the input as this, we say it's person two, present this, we say it's person two,
present this, it's person two. Right. So that means you have a CNN network. Every time you present
your input, you tell them what is the ID or category this person is. Yeah. So you train your
network to perform the classification. Right. So after you're fully trained, right, the features at
the FC layer. So if you remember, this is the features from the FC layer just now when we,
in the early part of the lecture, we mentioned that this feature is actually
an embedding or factor that contain discriminative information about this input regions here.
So therefore, now once it's fully trained, what we can do is that, okay. Next, suppose during your
inference stage already, when you are testing, what you detect and region, this region, you pass it
through this particular train network here. Okay. You pass it through this train network. The vectors
that you obtain from this FC layer is your embedding or your vector that can represent this image region.
Okay. So therefore, moving forward, that means every time when you detect a region, you can pass it
through this train network. The vectors that you obtain here now will be a descriptor or vector
to represent the corresponding detected region. And afterwards, when you, for example, you have this
prediction bounding box as well as this detector bounding box, each of them also have the
appearance descriptor. You just measure how similar they are. So that means you look at,
for example, this could be a vector from the predicted bounding box due to motion.
This could be a vector or embedding arising from a detection bounding box. And then you see these
two, how similar they are. So this is an additional information that you can use to help to do the
tracking. Right. So now we have, make use of both the informations of the motion model as well as
the visual appearance. All right. So that's the basic ideas of MOT, right. A lot of the MOT technique
actually leverage. The basic principle is based on that. But first, over time, there are more
improvements. So the next one that we are going to introduce is this emerging and new methods in MOT.
Right. So the, let me see. Okay. Probably,
okay. This part I think will take a bit longer. Maybe, yeah, we can take a short break. Let's come
back at, say 8.8pm. Right. Let's come back at 8.8pm.
Okay.
Okay. So let's continue on with the new and emerging techniques in MOT. Right. So one of the very
recent techniques that we have on multiple object tracking is known as the track former.
Right. So the goal of this track former is that you will try to perform the object detection
as well as tracking at the same time. So it performs joint object detection and tracking. And this
tracking is by the attention mechanism that you will see later. Right. So it performs detection
and tracking by attention. Okay. Using a transformer based approach. Yeah. Okay. So
later on you'll see that we'll have the object query as well as track query. So for track
formers, we'll have the object query to perform the object tracking. And then we have the track
query to track the movement of the objects here. Right. Okay. So we'll make use of the object as
well as a track query to perform initialization, tracking of the person. Right. And also following
is a tragic tree. Right. So this is a general kind of an overview of the track former, but this is a
more high level. So in the next slide, we'll explain the basic principles of track former
a bit more in detail. Okay. So let's look at this is the basic architectures of track former.
So before that, let's try to look at some of the basic information about this track former here.
So this track former, first of all, it will has an encoder, right? It will make use of this
encoder here. So the encoder is actually consisting of the CNN. Okay. As well as a transformer
encoder. Right. So this encoder part, this is the encoder part. It has a CNN to extract some feature
first, right, followed by the transformer encoder to further extract better feature. So this idea
is actually very similar to the earlier DTR structure. Right. You can see moving forward,
a lot of this structure actually has some very similar, no kind of structures. Okay. So this is
the encoder. Right. And then for the decoder here, so this is the decoder. So the decoder part, first
of all, it has this transformer decoder. Okay. And then it also make use of this particular
query, no, it's the object query, as well as the track query. So the object query, again,
is very similar to just now the DTR that we have studied. Yeah. So it has this object query,
as well as the track query. Okay. So this will form the basis for this decoder component.
Right. Okay. And afterwards, the output of this, right, this embedding here, right, if you want to
use to predict the new object or the track person. So, right, for the bounding box, as well as the
class prediction, it will make use of an NLP, multi-layer, to do the prediction. Right. So you
can see this track former is strongly motivated and very similar to the DTR object detection
that we've studied. So if you have a certain understanding of the DTR, it's very easy to
extend the idea to this track former. Okay. So let's see how this particular track former works.
So first of all, right, you have a sequence of frames here, for example, t is equal to 0,
right, t is equal to 1, so on and so forth. Right. Okay. So you start with 0 frame and then you have
many, many different frame. And then this is t minus 1 frame and then this is the t frame.
Right. So you have a sequence of frames or video. Right. So if you take the first frame here,
we let it go through a CNN. So this CNN will extract some visual descriptor. Right. Just like
what we explained. Right. Okay. So afterwards, once you have at this particular juncture here,
after the CNN, right, if you recall in DTR, what we do is we partition it into different
patches, right, of the descriptor, flatten it into a vector. Okay. And typically we also add in the
position information. Right. And afterwards we are ready to pass it through this transformer
encoder. Right. So the input here is a bunch of flattened vectors that correspond to, you know,
features from different image region. So your output of the transformer decoder now, what is the output?
Just now DTR, we also spent some time. How about so for this track former, what is the output here?
The output is also a collection of vector, but this vector has a better representation
than your original input vector because it makes use of the attention mechanism to find
the contributions of other vectors to work. Right. So input is a bunch of vector that correspond to
different image regions here. For example, one, two, three different patches. So you have different
vectors here. Right. So output is also a bunch of vectors with a better representation. So that's
the goal of any transformer encoder. Right. So afterwards this transformer encoder, you can see
the output of this encoder is going to pass through this transformer decoder. Right. So in first frame,
right, initially in first frame, you need to perform the object detection first. Yeah. So that's why
in first frame, what we have is first of all, we have some object query. Right. So in frame one,
we only have the object query just like the DTR. Right. Just like DTR. We update, we pass this
object query to this transformer decoder. Then, right, you will have this particular
car for position embedding. Right. And then you will go through an MLP to predict, right,
where is the bounding box and whether there's a person there or whether there's an object here.
So far, this part here is just like the DTR that we have studied. Okay. Right. Okay. So next, once,
suppose, right, in this case here, suppose initially our guess is the four object or four person.
Suppose you want to train the detect person. So we have this four here. So three of the object,
actually, they can detect three different person. But one of the object query actually
it says that there's no object. That's fine because now you detect these three person now.
Okay. So afterwards, in the right, so you'll go through the next frame. So in the next frame here,
what you have now is that, okay, you can see now. Okay. So suppose this is your next frame.
Right. So the next frame will go through the same thing. You'll go through a CNN to extract the
visual feature. You'll go through the transformer encoder to extract, right, the better embedding,
right, okay, or token to represent each of this region here. Right. So this one is going to pass
through your transformer decoder. But now in this current frame here, now you can see your input
here will consist of two parts. First, you have this particular object query. You still have the
object query because in this new frame here, potentially, there may be some new object appearing.
So therefore, you need to have some object query. And at the same time, we also need to take the
embedding from the previous frame. Okay. So this is known as a track query. So your input now,
you have the object query as well as a track query. Yeah. So afterwards, you do the cross
attention between this object query and the track query together with the contact specter from your
encoder, right, the position versus the visual information. And then you let it go through the
MLP to predict, right, where is the position, right, of your new, for this three track query here,
then you'll see where is the position, right, of this new object now. Right. So therefore,
these are the improved position embedding. After you go through the MLP, then you'll be able to
detect the new positions here. Right. Okay. So these three in this illustration, no problem.
Yeah. Okay. But also for this object query, all these four object query here, in this illustration,
three of them do not detect anything, but one of them detect a new person. Okay. So that's why
you need this object query to detect if there's a new person appearing. Okay. So now you have this
four person which is being tracked now. So you move on to the next frame. So the next frame,
you repeat the same thing. Okay. So because this purple one is newly detected, so you need to start
a new track for the purple object as well. Okay. So for the next frame, you go through a CNN to
extract visual feature, you let it go through the transformer encoder to get a bunch of vector
vector representation. Right. Visual representation. Now you take this for track query. Okay. You
introduce some object query. You write this one, you let it go through the transformer decoder
with the input from the encoder as well. And afterwards, the output is now, right. You can see,
for example, in this case, your red, green and purple continue to track. But this blue one now
disappear because maybe this blue person walked out of this image is seen already. It does not
appear. So therefore, your blue object is not tracking anymore. Right. So it disappeared. Right.
And then in this illustration here, there's new object person appearing. That's why it does not
detect any further person. Right. So this is pretty much the basic idea of this track former is
center on DTR. Right. Okay. So the next few slides is just a further elaboration of what I just
mentioned. So you have the object query. Right. By now, you know, object query is to detect the new
object in the current frame. And then once you detect it, then it will serve as the beginning
for you to form the track, right, to track in the subsequent frame. Okay. Also, you have the track
query. The track query is that the object that you already detected from the previous frame. So
that's known as a track query. So you follow the object through a video by carrying the identity
information while adapting to their changing position. Pretty much track query, as I mentioned,
it's just a track. Okay. You already detect a person. Right. So you want to track where this
person is moving. Okay. Right. Okay. And then, right. So yeah, this track query will also,
you know, associate the track object with the bounding box of the current frame. So pretty much
you just track where this person is moving. Right. Okay. So this is a demo that use a track
former. So, no, yeah, if you use a track former, you can see actually you can detect the movement
of all these objects reasonably well. Right. Okay. So this particular site give a performance
comparison based on the MOT16 data set. Right. So the vertical axis is called MOTA. So MOTA is
actually stand for multiple object tracking accuracy. So it's, okay. So for, to evaluate the
performance of different MOT algorithm, there's a whole bunch of matrix here. So MOTA is one of
them. So this MOTA, this matrix here is defined as, right, one minus, okay, this term here. This
term numerator is false negative plus false positive plus ID switch, whether you have a person
switch, because sometimes they're two person walking, they may accidentally assign different ID.
Right. The ID of the person is switch. So this ID switch, okay, divided by ground truth. So if
your algorithm is good, right, that means your false negative should be small. Your false positive
should be small. Your ID switch should be small. Right. So that means your numerator will be small.
GT is a ground truth number of bounding box. So therefore, for good algorithm, the numerator is
small. That means this is a small value. So one minus a small value, that means MOTA should be a
big value. So therefore, that means the larger the MOTA value, the better your MOT algorithm is.
Okay. So therefore, this MOTA here, the larger, the better. Okay. Right. So this shows the timeline
of, you know, in recent year, what are the algorithms that has been developed? Right. So these are the
leading methods in those years here. Right. So you can see track former is somewhere here.
Okay. Somewhere here, about 70 something percent. Right. And afterwards, you have the buy track.
Some of you have probably tried, if you have studied this before, you probably have seen buy track,
BOT, sort, strong sort, and then boost track and so on and so forth. Right. So these are some recent
methods. So by any way, this is quite a novel method. Right. Because yeah, as opposed to the
earlier method than this, this is one of the early method that make use of the transformer-based
approach to perform tracking. Yeah. Right. So we have kind of a conclude about this tracking path.
So under tracking path, we cover the following. We go through an introduction, we explain about the
MOT. Right. And then also we look at one of the new MOT algorithm, which is the track former. Yeah.
Yeah. Because there are many, many methods out there, it's not possible for us to cover
everything. So we try to choose some more representative one and no, probably just one
more recent one, especially for those transformer-based method.
Right. Okay. So for this part, there's also a short exercise. So it asks you to list the
key steps in detection by tracking by detection MOT algorithm. Right. So if you don't refer to
the lecture, see where they can still understand or remember what are the key steps in this tracking
by detection MOT.
Okay. So anyway, the answer is quite straightforward. You can just refer to the
election. So the key steps in tracking by detection MOT is that first you need to do the
detection. Right. You need to use the object detector to detect the object to start your
tracking process. Okay. So detection, use a detector to initialize a track. Okay. And
afterwards you need to use the motion prediction to predict based on the previous movement,
to predict the next position of the object. All right. Using any motion model. And then finally,
you need to do the data association, which is try to match your predicted position with the
detection that you perform using object detection at the frame T plus one. So these are the basic
kind of key step. Of course, you can elaborate more, but these are the, at least the important
step that you should try to highlight. So also this solution, I'll make it available on the NTULun
later. Right. Okay. So the next topic that we are going to look at is the post estimation.
Right. So what is the goal of the post estimation? So the goal of post estimation is that you want
to predict, right, the positions of different joints, right, either for the body, for the head,
or for the hand. So these are the common domain, the full body, right, your head, or the hand.
Right. So these are the common domain that we use to perform the post estimation. So pretty much,
you want to detect what we call the joint, or sometimes they also call it the key point,
key point or the joint. So once you've detected all the joint, then this joint can be connected
to form the skeleton. Yeah. So this is the basic idea. Right. So under this post estimation,
section will be looking at introduction. Then we'll be looking at single person post estimation,
multi-person post estimation, and some emerging and new methods. Right. Okay. So what's the objective
of post estimation is to locate the human body or facial key point. Sometimes we call it key point,
sometimes we also call it joint. Right. We use it in the shape. Right. From either image and video
see it. So for example, in this case here, you can see it's performing the full body,
no joint or key point prediction. And after work, then you can link them up together
for those joints to become a skeleton. Right. Okay. So therefore the goals of post estimation is
pretty much just to predict the key point or the joints of either the body, the hand, or the face.
But for our case, we'll be focusing more for the full body.
Right. Okay. So what are the brief history and milestones of this post estimation? So it started
with a single person post estimation. As the name suggests, single person, that means you only
have a single person and you are trying to find the joint of a single person. And multi-person
means that in your video, you're multiple person and you're trying to find the joint and skeleton
for all the persons here. Right. So there's a whole bunch of methods here. So I'm not going to go
into all of them, but we are going to look at some of the representative one. For example, the HRNet.
Right. HRNet as well as the transpose. Yeah. The HRNet as well as the transpose.
Right. So what are some potential applications of post estimation? It can be used for action
recognition. Right. So for example, if you want to perform action recognition, right, there's many
different ways you can perform action recognition. Right. So you can, for example, just simply look
at the RGB video clip. Right. So for example, now I'm just not, I keep drinking water. Right. You can
look at this video clip and then try to detect whether I'm drinking water. So you can take the raw
RGB video or you can, for example, try to estimate, perform the post estimation to find the joint of
my body. And then once you predict the joints of my body, you can form a skeleton and then you can
study, you know, the movement of this skeleton to see, you know, whether I'm doing the drinking.
So one of the common use cases for action recognition. So you use the body key point to
perform this action recognition. Right. For example, this particular dataset is actually,
I think collected in a row slide in NTU. It's quite a well known dataset.
Right. Okay. So it can also be used for animation and motion capture, right, to build the virtual
factor based on human pose. Right. For example, you have some, you know, this, you have some
skeleton information and then based on this skeleton information, you can use to do some,
you know, animation using some avatars or virtual characters.
Right. Okay. So the next slide, actually, this, just try to give you a few ideas about
kind of what kind of dataset we'll be, know we'll be using. So for the dataset, right, it can be
divided into a single person post estimation. Right. So these are some dataset, probably no
need for me to go into the detail, but you can see most of the data set in earlier years. Right.
Because nowadays, most of the post estimation tends to focus on multi-person post estimation
and also tends to move from 2D to 3D post estimation. Yeah. But for the context of this
particular cost, you'll be focusing on 2D post estimation. Yeah. But actually, you can also
perform the 3D post estimation as well. Right. Okay. So this slide shows some of the common
data set using multi-person post estimation. Right. So, right. So these are some of the common one,
MP1, one. Right. And also, there's actually a human 3.6M, right, which is also popular among others.
So the dataset is in more recent years. Okay. So, right. So yeah, it's corresponding to multi
person. Okay. It can cover different poses. And then depending on what model, it can be ranging
from 14 joints to 17 joints. Some dataset, you know, detect more joints, some detect a bit less
joint per person. Right. There's some performance matrix that we'll go through later. And then this
gives you a breakdown of the number of training, validation, and the test data.
Right. Okay. So this slide shows some sample images, you know, in MSCoco. So if you use MSCoco
to do the post estimation, right. So MSCoco actually provides some of this, you know,
data for you to do the training.
Right. So before we continue, the next thing we are going to look at is a performance matrix.
How do we, you know, measure whether your post estimation algorithm is good or not? You need
to have some way to measure it. Right. So let's look at some of the common way to
performance matrix. So the first performance matrix is known as a percentage of correct
key point. Right. So PCK, percentage of correct key point. Right. So if you want to think about it,
what's the most intuitive way for you to see whether your post estimation method is performing
well? Yeah. So Jane speaking, we'll use a benchmark data set to do the evaluation. And for your
benchmark data set, there's some ground truth, right. People have already spent time, right.
No, to annotate, right. Or no, using some devices to actually capture the joint. So you know,
the ground truth, where exactly is the position of the joint? Yeah. So and then by using your
developed algorithm, you'll be able to predict, for example, there's a joint here. Yeah. And then
your prediction is somewhere here. So what you need to do is that, I mean, if you think about it
logically, is you find the distance, right, between the ground truth, where is the actual joint,
and your prediction, where this, right. So you take the difference between them. If this particular
difference or this arrow or distance is less than a certain threshold, then we say it's correct.
Yeah. So this is the high level reasoning. But if you take this high level reasoning,
there's actually an issue. So what is the issue? If you just simply measure the distance, right,
between your ground truth and your predicted value, right. Suppose this is a ground truth,
this is a predicted value, you simply take their difference, right. You take the distance,
and you say that if this distance is less than a certain value, right, then you say it's correct.
But it's more than a certain value, you say it's incorrect. But if you use this particular approach,
this is actually an issue. What do you think is the issue?
Okay. So one of the issue is that, right, if you just simply use that, it does not take into
account the size of the person. For example, if my size is bigger compared to, you know, another
person, the size is smaller, right, it can be a little bit different. So we need to actually take
it, you know, respect to also taking into the body size of the person that we are considering
detecting into consideration. So therefore what you need to do is that, right, suppose this is the
ground truth, this is a detector key point, after you take this particular distance or error,
you need to be normalized by a certain, you know, kind of a body size of the person. So which can,
which can be, for example, the diameter of the torso or the length of the head, right,
depending on where you are detecting the key point. So by taking a difference, normalized or divided by,
for example, the size of the body, then you can get a more normalized or more meaningful way of
measuring the error. Okay, so therefore that's the basic idea. So if you want to check the
percentage of the correct key point, so what you need to do is that you measure the percentage,
right, okay, percentage of predicted key point that fall within a normalized distance. Okay, so
what it means is that, right, so first of all, you take,
you take the distance, right, you take your ground truth, right, your predicted error,
you take the distance and this distance is normalized by a certain body size, for example,
the diameter of the torso. If you are talking about body, part of key point, you are talking
about the head, then divided by the length of the head, right, then you'll get the normalized
distance and this normalized distance is less than a threshold, right, so for example, for this
percentage of correct key point, usually you need to define a certain value, right, so this is a
threshold. If this value, if this distance divided by the normalized body length is less than your
threshold, this threshold is what you choose, right, it's less than the threshold, that means this
particular key point is detected correctly, yeah, and then afterwards for all the body joints that
you have the percentage of them, how many out of all these body joints, how many do you detect
it correctly, that is a percentage, yeah, so therefore you have the percentage of correct
key point, so we have already described how do we define what is meant by correct key point
detection and the percentage of it out of all the joints, how many do you detect correctly,
it's known as the PCK percentage of correct key point, so you can see the wrap say,
measure the percentage of predicted key point that fall within a normalized distance,
so this is a normalized distance, okay, so for example, for this data set,
percentage of PCK at point two means that the distance between your predicted and the ground
truth joint less than point two of the total diameter, yeah, so if this condition is met,
that means this key point is detected correctly, okay, so unfortunately for this data set, some
different data set sometimes use different performance matrix, yeah, so there's quite
number of different variation, for example, this MP11 data set here is the percentage of key point,
right, percentage of correct key point, but it's for the head, right, and the threshold we use in
this example is at point five, so what it means is that if you find that, okay, your true key point
and the ground truth, the distance divided by the head, segment length, right, okay, to get the
normalized distance, and if it's less than point five, that means it's considered as correctly
detecting the key point, yeah, so this is the key idea, it's a percentage of correct key point,
now next one is the percentage of correct parts, so these parts here refer to the body
limb, for example, instead of one key point, it's trying to say for example, your upper limb,
your lower limb and so on and so forth, so the basic idea is still very similar, so suppose if
you talk about the upper limb, you have this particular ground truth key point here, right,
ground truth key point, and if your prediction is somewhere here, so you just try to find the error
for both of this particular end of this body joint, if both of them divided by the normalized length,
right, which is for example, the length of your limb, right, and if it's less than a certain
threshold value that you choose, then you interpret as this part and detect that correctly,
so therefore this part at high level is trying to measure the localization accuracy of the limb,
right, so instead of detecting whether a joint is correctly, you try to look at for example,
a body limb, a bone, right, whether this particular part or this limb is detected correctly, so you
can see if the distance between two predicted joints and the true limb is less than a fraction,
okay, a certain value that you choose of the body length, right, okay, then we can say that this limb
is considered as detected correctly, yeah, so this is the high level principle, so another
performance matrix, common performance matrix, which is based on this object key point similarity,
okay, so with this object key point similarity, right, we have the average position and the
average recall arising from this object key point similarity, so this object key point similarities
is actually very similar to the mean average presentation that you have studied for the
object detection, right, okay, so this average presentation, average recall, and there are
variants, there are some variants are used in cocoa MP11 as well as the post track as the
performance matrix for post estimation method, right, so this object similarity,
object key point similarity, okay, as play a very similar role to the IOU in the detection,
right, okay, in the object detection, so the definition is that, right, the distance between
the predicted joint and the ground truth joint normalize by the scale of the person, again,
the ideas are all very similar, right, you have the ground truth, you have the prediction,
you get the error, you divide by the normalize body part, right, okay, and then if it's less than
a certain threshold, then we say that, no, you do the detection correctly, so once you can detect
whether a joint can be detected correctly, then you can further extend it to the precision as well
as the recall, right, then you can plot the precision versus recall graph or you can calculate
all these different matrix here, okay, so very similar to the IOU that we have studied in
object detection, right, okay, so there's no need to go into too much of this detail, I'm just trying
to share with you, these are some common matrix use in post estimation because later on when we
look at the performance table, you need to have a certain understanding of what these
matrix are all trying to measure, right, okay, so what are some of the challenges in post estimation,
number one is you want it to be efficient, so you want it to be fast, right, sometimes certain
poles may have, you may have limited data, so I remember, no, a few years back, actually,
there was one company, kind of a, you know, a calm and affection company, they want to study the
impacts of, you know, this ego, what do you call those are,
uh,
mus, mus, musculoskeletal, okay, so anyway, it's the, it's the potential risk to the worker
when they always work in a very awkward position, yeah, so it has to study with their ergonomics,
like for example, you know, those who need to, you know, fix certain, say, suppose there's like
vehicles on top, they need to attach something, so they always have to bend over and do these kind
of things, so that's very stressful to their back or their neck and so on, so actually they want to
have some studies about, you know, the effects of this, uh, long-term effects of, you know, this
composition to, uh, to the health of the worker, yeah, so in order to do that, you know, they need
to also do some post estimation, and among them is that some of the certain posts that you have
is quite rare, all right, some of these posts like this, you cannot commonly obtain it from your common
data set, so this is also one of the potential challenge, right, you may have limited data for
some rare posts that's not so common in the benchmark data set, right, other things are
including occlusion, right, when you want to do the objective, uh, for example, the post estimation,
for example, I'm standing here, my lower part of the body is occluded, so if you want to do the full
body, uh, post estimation, you may not be able to predict it, right, so next let's move on,
look at some common post estimation methods here, so it's divided into two broad categories,
single person versus, uh, multi person, and for this course we'll only be focusing on 2D, yeah,
we'll not be touching on 3D post estimation, yeah, so we'll only be looking at the 2D post
estimation, for single person there's 2 broad categories, one is known as a regression based
method that we'll see later, the other is a body part detection method, okay, for single person,
for multi person there's a broad category, one is known as a top down approach, the other is a bottom
up approach, so under top down we have a hrnet and transpose, under bottom up we have the open post
technique, so later on we'll spend a little bit of time to talk about each of these particular methods,
right, so first of all let's look at the single person post estimation method, right, so the single
person post estimation method, right, uh, one of the broad category of methods under is known as a
regression method, so this idea of regression method is very straightforward, right, so pretty much
for example you have an image, input image, you want to detect the, the joints of this particular
person, so what you need to do is simply train a deep learning base model, it can be for example your
you know, a cnn or some other transformer and so on, right, so you provide the input, right,
you also provide the output, the supervision to say okay where are the joints, so by keep
presenting the input and also the positions of the out, the positions of the joint then you can
train your network to do the regression automatically to find out where are the joints, yeah, so once
it's fully trained then next when you have a new image is being present you'll detect all this
key point, so once you detect the key point you can link them together to form no uh, a skeleton,
yeah, so this is the basic idea of the regression base approach, yeah, so you obtain, you train and
you obtain the feature map from the cnn, right, and afterwards you can calculate the regressor from
the feature map, right, so uh, so for this style of method you can see actually the idea is very
simple, right, so the advantage is very easy and it's quite fast, yeah, but uh the disadvantage
is that it's not so accurate, so that's why uh for this regression base method it was early methods
but nowadays uh usually people don't use it because it's not so accurate, right, okay, so the next
single person uh post estimation method is called the body part methods here, so the body part
methods what it does is that given a particular input image you go through a 2d human post,
hpe is then for human post estimation network and then for each of the joint you will try to
predict a hit map, right, for example, you know this particular joint here you try to generate a
lightly hit map of where this joint is, yeah, so for each of this particular target joint you
generate a hit map, right, to indicate where lightly this particular uh uh joint is located,
right, and then afterwards you know you will try to pull this information together, right,
you will perform the body part association to link all this uh potential joint arising from the
likelihood probability lightly hook map or the hit map together, okay, so therefore the approach
is that you will try to estimate k hit map, right, k is the number of joint that you have,
so k hit map for a total of k key point or joint here, right, and afterwards you will try to assemble
this uh detected uh key point together into the body post or the skeleton, right, so the advantage
of this uh method is is more accurate than the regression based method but the disadvantage is
slow and also more complex, so one of the representative work is called the stack hour glass
network for human post estimation, right, in 2016, but by and large single person 2d post
estimation is not commonly done nowadays, so this one is more just for your kind of information,
right, okay, so if you look at the result performance, right, for this single person post
estimation, right, you can see these are the body part detection approach, these are the regression
based approach, these are a bunch of methods proposed over reasonably recent years, right,
so these are the model, right, okay, so for different uh no body joint, right, and then these are the
performance using the you know the average precision, okay, using this key point similarity uh
object key point similarity matrix that we have just introduced, okay,
right, so the next types of methods we're going to look at is the multi person uh post estimation,
so the multi person post estimation there's two can be divided into two broad category,
one is the top down approach, the other is a bottom up approach, so the top down approach as
the name suggests is quite straightforward and intuitive, pretty much you think about this is
the image of video, you have a few different person inside, so what we need to do is simply try to
detect right, bounding box for individual person, so once you can actually detect the bounding box
for individual person, then for each individual person we can just deploy the single person
post estimation to solve the problem, so therefore it's actually very intuitive, it's just like
you know divide and conquer, you detect individual person, right, and afterwards you perform the
post estimation for each person, right, so the approach therefore is that you detect the person
in the image using some of the shell detector, you detect different person, and then for each person
you perform the post estimation, right, as mentioned, right, so there are some representative work,
one of them is called the HR net, which is called the high resolution net, so for this
type of method the good thing is that it's accurate, all right, okay, it's not so complex,
but the disadvantage is that the runtime will increase with the increasing number of detector
person, because what happened is that suppose this particular image has many many different person,
right, and then for each of the detected person, right, it needs to perform a 2D estimation,
so therefore when you have lots of person, each of the person you have to perform the
post estimation, then it becomes slow, so therefore the runtime will increase, right,
with respect to the number of detected person, yeah, okay, so therefore it's most suitable for
scene when you're a few person, when your imaging scene doesn't have so many person,
but this could potentially be a good choice, so the high level reasonings of top-down approach
is like this, suppose you have an input image, you use off the shelf human detector to detect
individual person, each of the person you can go through the 2D post estimation to
you know detect their post and afterwards you just put them back together, right, so there's a high
level, very simple to understand top-down approach,
so under this we have the, right, so one of the network that is used to perform this is the HR
net known as a high resolution net here, right, so let's look at some fracture information and
afterwards we'll look at this particular diagram to understand how the HR net works here, right,
it says that it starts from a high resolution subnet, okay, right, for example this is a
high resolution subnet, that means that image a network that can handle a large resolution, okay,
and then afterwards it adds high to low resolution subnet gradually, right, so initially, right,
your input is a high resolution, okay, and if your input feature is high resolution,
and afterwards you do the down sampling, okay, you do the down sampling to generate some lower
resolution feature map here, okay, so you have the high resolution subnet and then you have some
lower resolution subnet here, right, so pretty much you can see that, right, so if you look at this
particular diagram here, so your input initially you have an input frame or image, right, so we
let it go through for example a CNN network, okay, so this CNN network here you can see these are the
feature map, all right, so this is a standard CNN network, okay, so you have the feature map here,
but what is a little bit different from this HR net is that at some point in their feature
they perform the sub sampling, right, you can see this down sampling, they perform the down
sampling to reduce the size of the resolution, okay, so therefore you can see there's some down
sampling here, okay, and then in between sometimes you also perform some information
exchange between the higher resolution version and the lower resolution version, so there's some
information exchange between them, okay, yeah, and you can also continue for this particular
version you can further continue to perform the down sampling to become even lower resolution
feature map here, right, so and then after works at some juncture you can have the information
exchange again across no feature map with different resolution, so why do you want to do that, why do
you want to create no feature map with a different resolution, so this idea is actually quite common
right, for example when you talk about object detection, right, when we study about YOLO you
also see that very often we have this kind of feature pyramid, right, feature with different
resolution, sometimes it's for you to handle for example, no person with object with different
scale, right, sometimes bigger scale sometimes smaller scale, so you want to have that particular
flexibility to be able to handle objects of, you know, whether it's small object or big object,
small person or big person, so that's why we have these types of no different, you can see the
horizontal axis is a that, that means the number of a layer that we have and then this axis here is
a scale, that means whether your feature is a large high resolution feature map or low resolution
feature maps here, okay, so it connects multi resolution subnet in parallel, so you can see
high resolution, okay, smaller and even smallest and this is connected in parallel, right, so it
makes use of multi scale fusion, scale in this case just means different size of the resolution,
okay, and it encourage or allow information exchange, you can see sometimes up sometimes down,
right, so it allow information exchange across different scales of feature map, okay, across
parallel multi resolution subnet, all right, so just now we have talked about the top down approach,
now we are going to look at the bottom up approach, so the bottom up approach what it does is that,
right, it try to give an input, it try to detect all the key points, so for example in this particular
image there's many different person, right, so it try to detect all the possible key point that
you have for all the persons in this image and afterwards you try to link them up, associate
them together for okay, so these are key point belonging to person one, these are the key point
belonging to person two and so on and so forth, so because you detect the collections of key point
first and after folks you decide this bunch of key point does it belong to the same person,
this bunch of key point does it belong to the second person and so on, so therefore it's actually
a bottom up approach, you start off with the key point and then you link them up together, okay,
so the high level idea therefore is that you try to detect all the body parts or joints in the image
and afterwards you try to assemble them, you link them together into pose for different person,
right, okay, so one of the most representative work for this is known as an open pose, right,
so the advantage of this kind of technique is that the runtime is fast, right, it's almost
constant with respect to different number of detected person, so whether you have one person
or you have more person the amount of time more or less is the same, okay, as opposed to just now
the top down the more person you have the slower it will become, right, so but the shortcoming of
this style method is this is a bit more complex, right, okay, it's suitable for crowded scene because
when you're more person since their runtime is the most constant the number of person will not affect
their runtime, okay, so the high level idea is that, right, for this bottom up approach you start
with the input image you let it go through the pose estimation, right, so what it does is it detect
all the key points for all the person and then afterwards you go through a body part association
try to assemble or link those key points that belong to a single person together, right, so
therefore you have, you know, for example this is you this bunch of the key point you after some
analysis you know that it belongs to the one person and this bunch of key point belongs to the second
person, right, so then you output some multi-person pose, yeah,
right, okay, so next we are going to look at some new and emerging methods,
okay, so by now you can see that for new and emerging technique usually I try to choose one
which is a transformer based approach, right, so therefore for, you know, this emerging technique
the method that I choose chosen is the transpose method, right, so let's look at a quick high
level this facture information regarding the transpose method, so transformers method is a
transformer based pose estimation, you can see nowadays if it's a transformer based method
usually they either like to use trans or former, if you see trans or you see former, right, likely
is a transformer based approach, so you can see in this case it's a transpose, so it's a transformer
based pose estimation method here, right, okay, so the backbone, right, so this backbone here,
right, oh okay perhaps I can start to explain using this particular figure first, right,
so first of all you have this particular input image that you want to perform the pose estimation,
so you let it go through a backbone, right, so this backbone that we have typically for this
transpose they use a common CNN right to extract the feature, so the common CNN for example one
popular choice of the rest net, okay, or the HR net that we have studied earlier, so we can use
rest net or HR net, okay, to extract the feature, right, to extract the feature, so the output here
now, okay, your input image after your backbone which is typically your CNN, your output now is
actually the extracted feature map now, okay, so this is the extracted feature map, okay, so once
you have this particular extracted feature map what do we do, right, standard like before, right,
we partition it into different patches, okay, we put in the position information to form the token,
yeah, right, the patch of the token, right, so afterwards, yeah, you have, we partition this
output of this feature map into different token or patches, we flatten it, then we have a
collections of vectors here, okay, so this collections of vector, next we are going to go
through this transformer encoder, you can see the steps are quite standard, you let it go through
the transformer encoder, so this particular transformer encoder what it does is similar to
all the previous things is that we want to actually from this original input vector, high-level idea
is that you will try to, you know, extract a bunch of output vector, okay, which is a better
representation because of the attention mechanism that I've said so many times already, okay,
right, so you can see the steps inside is more or less the same, so this part here is performing
the cell attention, if you remember the query key and the value, so if you cannot remember the
detail you can refer to our lectures on the transformer, so this is the calculating of the
cell attention, right, and then this part here is actually your, you know, the fifth forward
network here that we have, okay, so this is the relatively standard transformer encoder layer,
so in this case here we do not make use of the decoder, right, we don't use a decoder, right,
okay, so after works the output at this particular juncture is a bunch of, a bunch of these vectors
corresponding to different region, right, so for each region, for each region here you have one
vectors here, right, so output is a bunch of vectors that correspond to different regions
in the image, and after works you let it go through a head network here, so this head network here
what they will do is that you'll try to find for each of this particular region here, for each
key point, right, so this head network here will actually project into a K key point, right,
K key point, for each of the key point you will see what is the most likelihood that no,
for, all right, because for our body for example we may have a 17 or 14 key point, right,
so 14 key point, so for each of the channel that we have, right, you will see, right, for example
what is the most likely head map, right, that the key point is at this position, see, so you can see
this one likely is corresponding to the the key point near the head here, okay, right, and then
for other key points we could be for example detecting you know either left shoulder joint and so on
and so forth, okay, so pretty much, yeah, you mentioned already input go through the backbone,
get the feature, right, okay, let it go through a transformer, you have different
vectors, better vectors that correspond to different regions, okay, and afterwards you let it go through
a head network, right, so for this head network it will give rise to a K key point maps depending
on how many key points you have, right, okay, but so for each of the key points it will generate a
head map here, right, generate a head map to indicate what's the likelihood that particular joint fall
in the position, the brighter the color that means the higher the probability you will fall in the
positions here, right, okay, so afterwards, yeah, so this is pretty much that, right, okay, so let's
continue, it says that okay for the backbone here, huh, so the backbone it says that we can, I think
backbone we just covered, right, and then afterwards the transformer, so for the transformer we make
use of the encoder only, we do not make use of the decoder, right, so we have an n layer attention,
so you know you repeat this encoder n times, so it's an n attention layers, okay, and then you
have the feed forward, okay, network, right, so the head network as mentioned before, right,
it can make use of some small network to predict the key, key point head map, so for each of the
key points it can generate head map, right, okay, so this particular diagram here just indicated
right, okay, so attention layer one, attention layer two, attention layer n just means that,
okay, so you have actually n layer, right, so you have this n layer here, so each of these
particular slides here just refer to for example if you are talking about the first layer, okay,
or the second layer, or the third layer, and so on and so forth, right, so this one just corresponds
to different layers here, so suppose if we look at the first layer here, right, so the first layer
here, right, so for the first layer here which is for example just one of this block, the first
block that you have, so for example earlier on when you do the prediction suppose you already know,
okay, you can find out that this is the lively position of your head, John, yeah, so what you
can do now is that you can take these particular positions of a head joint as a query, right,
and then you can try to calculate the attention map, right, so the attention map means that,
you know, remember you have the query, you have this query, you multiply with the key
from all the position, and then you let it go through a softmax operation, right, so this
particular figure pretty much just says that suppose I want to use this as a query, this is
the position, I want to find out, you know, what is the contributions of other patches, right, to
work the importance of this current joint position, so this starts a little bit here, but you can see
brighter color means that those patches which are nearby to the head, right, provide strong
contribution, right, to indicate where this head joint would be, right, so for example,
if you now look at another joint, right, so for example one of the detector key point, right,
this is the livelihood where it's belonging to, so if you want to visualize, because very often
when you do this AI model sometimes you cannot visualize it, you do not know whether your model
is doing well, whether it's doing properly, so you want to have some visualization to help you
to understand whether your CNN model or your transformer is really doing what it's doing,
yeah, so therefore what you can do is that suppose, you know, you have this head network,
you have one of this particular position which is a lightly joint, for example, for your foot,
right, so you can use that as a query, maybe for example it corresponds to this one,
and then you try to calculate its attention map, you calculate its attention map, right, which is,
as I mentioned, you take the query, multiply with all the key factors, all right, okay,
and then you let it go to the softmax, yeah, and afterwards this can be interpreted as a
head map, so you can see for example for this joint here, the neighboring region,
the neighboring patches are the one that's going to contribute to work, you know,
calculating that particular joint, yeah, so it gives you a certain visualization that, you know,
these are from the network perspective, they find out which region actually contributes
to work, you know, the estimation of this current joint, so you'll find that when you study
transformer, you know, it's quite a common technique that very often we look at the attention map,
just like just now the detection transformer, we also do that, to see which region actually
is important for this particular current patch position as a query, which other patches are
considered as relevant or contribute more to work this current region, right, okay, so this slide
here shows the comparison of various multi-person post-assimation methods, right, so you have the
top down versus the bottom up method, right, so these methods are more recent years, so these are
a whole bunch of methods, for example, yeah, the HRnet that we mentioned, there's a few variants
here, okay, we have the transpose here, okay, right, so yeah, so these are some of the backbone
they use, right, the image size, and then these are the performance matrix, okay, so the performance
matrix that they use is the AP average positions here, right, okay, the number are not so important
since for this part here, we are more like trying to explain to you, right, so just to give you
about some of the key tools that we are using here, so for example, transpose here is proposed in
21, okay, so this is the performance, not necessarily be the best, but it's actually a
starting point, right, so this is one of the framework that is quite different from the other
previous framework by a transformer based approach, yeah, but of course over time, it becomes better,
right, so under the post estimation method, actually we cover the following, so yeah,
we look at the introduction, single-post, multi-post, and emerging methods,
okay, let me see, right, so the next topic that we have is the
okay, do you all want to have an early break, right, since we come to this juncture which is the
yeah, okay, yeah, doesn't matter, right, today we celebrate a bit, we can have an early break,
so we'll finish our class today, yeah, actually it's almost nine o'clock already,
yeah, so we'll finish a little bit earlier today, so just a reminder, so next lecture will be actually
this Saturday which is a Zoom lecture, right, okay, and also for those of you, as I mentioned,
if you have not done the teaching feedback, yeah, please spare one moment to do the feedback,
right, okay, thank you, I'll see you on Saturday, thank you.
you