Okay, so good evening class, just a reminder, okay, so today is the 5th of September, so
that's why we are in this Leakonshin LT here, but next week the lecture will be in LT2A
again, so it's back to the North Spine, whereas you can have your fried rice over there.
Okay, so just a reminder, next week's lecture is in North Spine.
Alright, okay, so and also the lecture note part 4 is available, so you can proceed to download it.
And then finally, just a reminder again regarding the assignment, because there are always some students
who somehow do not pay attention.
Right, so the assignment one is ready, so the very important thing is that please,
right, submit only a single soft copy PDF file, so don't submit two, don't submit three, just one file will do.
Okay, right, and then afterwards name your file using surname, underscore, given name, underscore,
multiplication number. So for example, the surname is Tan, okay, given name is E-Ming,
and then this is a multiplication number connected by underscore.
Okay, and then, yeah, just to play safe, also write your full name and multiplication number on the first page of your assignment.
Right, if you are late in submission, or if you don't follow this instruction, you can be penalized.
Okay, because I remember last year, no, there are about 300 students and there are some students who do not follow the instruction
and really took me a few hours to sort out all those whose assignment it is.
So it is going to take a long time, so please follow this instruction strictly.
Okay, so for those of you who are new to submission using NTU Learn, what you need to do is simply click on this particular submission button.
So we click it, right, okay, you just need to upload the file. You have one single PDF file, just click on this upload file button,
okay, and then you browse or local file, and then you just upload the particular file, and then you click the submit and that's it.
Right, so each student will be given three chances, so maximum is three, you can only submit three times, yeah?
So please make sure that you check carefully before you do the submission.
Any questions?
Right, so if not, then this the announcement, just to be clear.
Okay, then next, let's continue on with our lecture.
So in previous lecture, actually we introduced very quickly the general steps in the JPEG encoder.
So let's do a quick recap before we dive into where we left off last time.
Okay, so what we have is that, Jane speaking, even the image is very common that we convert this image into the YCBCR format.
Okay, so you have the Y channel, CB and CR channel, right?
Okay, and then typically it's in a 420 chroma subsampling.
Okay, so that means for the CB and CR, every 2x2 pixel block, you only keep one CB and one CR.
So this will study a bit more when we come to the M-Pack compression.
Okay, and then afterwards we know we'll partition this particular image into multiple 8x8 pixel block.
This is what we have.
Okay, and then we'll perform DCT, right?
So in this DCT is known as a 2D DCT, but moving forward, we'll just call it DCT because it's understood
that we are referring to 2D DCT.
So when you perform the DCT for every 8x8 pixel block, after you perform the 2D DCT, you're going to get 8x8 coefficient.
So 8x8 DCT coefficient here.
Right, and afterwards we're going to perform quantization to quantize this 8x8 DCT coefficient into 8x8 quantized DCT coefficient.
So the reason why we need to perform this quantization, as explained in previous lecture, is quite simple.
It's because we are using finite number of bits to represent this image.
So once you are using a finite number of bits, that means you have a finite number of levels that you can represent.
So therefore we need to perform quantization.
So this is where we stop in previous lecture when we come to the steps of this quantization.
So that's why we are now going to continue.
So in order to perform this quantization, we need to use a quantization table.
Now let's look into the quantization steps now.
Right, so in last week we mentioned that we will try to explain how do we perform the quantization first before we come back to the slides to further elaborate on some of the points.
So let's do that.
So if you remember in last week, we mentioned that when we want to perform quantization, the idea is quite straightforward.
So this is the DCT quantize, this is a DCT coefficient.
So you remember just now, you have the 8x8 pixel block after you perform the DCT.
This is the 8x8 DCT coefficient.
Right, so therefore this is your 8x8 DCT coefficient.
So when you perform quantization, you need to make use of a quantization table.
So this is the quantization table here.
So how you perform quantization is actually very straightforward.
It's an element by element quantization.
So what it means is that you take this value, for example, you divide by the corresponding value here, and then you round to the nearest integer.
So for example, 120 divided by 10 is 12.
Round to the nearest integer is still 12.
Right, but if you, for example, have this particular number, which is 40, you divide by 15.
And if you round to the nearest integer, you will see that it's actually 3.
Right, so which is, therefore each of the element here, you divide by the corresponding entry in your quantization table.
And then you round to the nearest integer, you'll get this quantized DCT coefficient here.
Okay, so the values in this particular quantization table here, each of these particular value, we can either call it value, or sometimes we call it step size.
Right, you refer to the same thing.
So in previous lecture, I actually asked you these questions here.
Right, no, if you observe this particular quantization table, what do you notice?
Yeah, so I didn't, some of you point out in last lecture, you'll notice that this particular quantization table is valued, it's not even.
So the value was stuck to increase horizontally, vertically and diagonally.
Right, you can see the values here are small and the value near this range are large.
So can some of you still remember what is the reason we do that?
Remember I mentioned that there are two reasons why we do that.
Why do we design the quantization table in such a way that the values near these top left corners are small and the values near these corners are large?
Why?
Anyone?
You can still remember?
Yeah, to reduce the error, but why is it by design?
This way you can reduce the error.
Yes?
Ah, okay, so yeah, I guess what you're trying to say is that, right, from last lecture, we know that given an 8 by 8 pixel block, right, because pixel values,
because of the property of spatial redundancy, the pixel value tends to change slowly in the pixel domain.
So once you perform DCT, right, that means the energy will be packed into the low AC corner, right?
So this is known as the energy compaction.
That means, now most of the DCT coefficient near this top left corner, or corresponding to the low AC regions, are large.
You can see the value here, they are large here, right?
So therefore, to reduce the quantization error, right, because most of the values here are large, to reduce the quantization error, okay,
that correspond to this large value here, right, we'll use a small step size, because the smaller the step size,
that means we know that the smaller the quantization error will be.
Okay, so that's the one of the reason, okay, because the DCT coefficient near this corner, or the low AC coefficient, have large value.
Therefore, to reduce the quantization error, therefore we use a small step size here.
So that's one, the first reason.
What's the second reason?
Okay, exactly, because human visual systems are more sensitive to changes or distortion or error at low frequency component,
and this is a low frequency component.
That means any small changes in the quantization error or values here would actually introduce more perceptual difference to your eye.
So therefore, because humans are more sensitive to no coefficient near this corner, so therefore, by using the same argument,
we should reduce the error caused by the quantization here.
Hence, we should use a small step size here.
Okay, so these are the two reasons why the quantization table was designed in this particular manner.
So with that basic understanding, now we can go back to the explanation here.
So the quantization, as I mentioned, because we're using a finite number of bits to represent the image,
so therefore we need to perform quantization, so that you can only represent with a finite number of levels,
so as to map the continuous value into a finite number of discrete values.
So in order to do that, we'll be using the quantization table.
So from the earlier operation, you'll see that we need a quantization table to perform the quantization.
So when you perform quantization, it's clear that information loss will occur, because it's a many to one mapping now.
So therefore, information loss will occur during the quantization.
Right, okay, so next, the properties of the quantization table.
So just now we have spent a bit of time to explain about some of the properties.
So okay, we know that human is more sensitive to the DC and low AC coefficient, right?
So we have just explained about it.
So therefore, more emphasis should be taken in quantizing this DC and low AC coefficient.
So what do we mean by more emphasis?
More emphasis means that we should try to make sure that there's less quantization error near this region.
So less quantization error means that we should have a smaller value or step size near those regions.
Okay, so therefore, we'll use a smaller step size or quantization value to quantize those DC and low AC coefficient to reduce the quantization error.
So just now, we spent quite a bit of time to explain about the reason.
Okay, and further, we know that the step size and all the value in the quantization table is a compromise between the level of compression and information loss.
So what it means is that for this particular step size in the quantization table,
if you increase the value or if you increase the step size, what will happen?
From the quantization error perspective, right?
So suppose this particular quantization table, if all these values here will increase this value,
so if it increases value, what would be its impact in terms of the quantization error?
The error would increase or decrease.
For example, instead of 10 here, if I increase it to 20,
do you think you'll introduce more quantization error or less quantization error?
More, right?
So larger step size means that you'll introduce more quantization error.
Okay, but if you do that, what would be the potential advantage?
So for example, if you increase the step size here, you know the price you have to pay is now, you'll introduce more quantization error.
That means later on, your reconstructed images would be not as good.
So for example, initially given an image, you partition it into numerous 8x8 pixel blocks.
So each of the pixel blocks, you do the transformation to get the 8x8 DCT coefficient.
And afterwards, you perform the quantization, then you get your quantized DCT coefficient.
So if you use a large step size in the quantization table here, that means actually you introduce more error in your quantized DCT coefficient.
So that is the downside.
But what could be the potential advantage of doing that if you want to use a large quantization step size in the table?
Are there any potential advantages if you increase the step size?
Surely there must be some advantage.
If there's no advantage, then people will just put the step size all equal to one, or they don't perform quantization at all, or they just do a quantization with a step size of one already.
So surely you must have a reasonable value here.
It cannot be overly small.
So what's the advantage if you increase the step size?
So if you increase the step size, what will happen is that you are going to get a lot of...
This quantized value is going to be smaller, generally speaking, smaller.
And in particular, you're going to get a lot of zero near this corner here.
Because to start off, your DCT coefficient near this corner is already small.
This is an exaggeration.
Usually there will be some value here.
But start off is already small.
If you divide by a large step size, that means these values are likely going to have a lot of zero.
So when you have a lot of zero bunch together, a subsequent technique known as a run-length coding is going to compress it more effectively.
Therefore, what it means is that if you use the largest step size, you are going to get more zero near this high AC coefficient.
And therefore, your subsequent run-length coding is going to compress it better.
And your file size is going to become smaller.
So therefore, to summarize, if you use a larger step size, the price you have to pay is that your reconstructed image may not be as good now.
Because you have more quantization error.
But the advantage that you have is now your file size is much smaller.
Or in other words, its compression ratio is higher.
So therefore, it's actually a trade-off.
You can see that the step size of the value in the quantization table is a compromise or a trade-off between the level of compression and the information loss.
So let's just repeat one more time.
If you use a large step size, the information loss will be large or small.
If you use a large step size, the information loss or the quantization error will be large or small.
But your level of compression now will be high or low.
If you use a large step size, your level of compression will be...
Level of compression or the compression ratio means how much you can compress it.
It's going to be high, right?
If you use a large compression ratio, that means your AC coefficient is going to be...
Lots of zero. That means the subsequent run-line coding can compress it into much smaller file size.
Therefore, your compression ratio is going to be large or your level of compression.
You can compress it into a much smaller file size.
Okay?
So now if you do the reverse, if you use a small step size...
Suppose if we use a small step size in your quantization table, the information loss now will be...
Large or small.
If you use a small step size, the information loss will be small.
But your level of compression will be small as well because now you cannot compress it that well.
Okay?
Right?
Okay.
So therefore it's actually a compromise.
You have to choose a suitable value to balance between these two factors.
Right?
Okay.
So now, mathematically, how do we represent quantization?
So we can see that the quantization is illustrated using this formula.
So first of all, this FUV here is a DCT coefficient.
Okay?
And then this QUV here is the quantization...
The value in the quantization table.
Right?
And then this F cap here is your quantized DCT coefficient.
So essentially what you see is that you take your DCT coefficient,
you divide that by the quantization value in your quantization table element by element,
you round to the nearest integer, and then you obtain your quantized DCT coefficient.
Right?
So that's pretty much the equation that described the process that we have explained earlier on.
Okay.
So because for an image, typically we change it into YCBCR domain.
So you have the luminance component as well as the chrominance component here.
So for the luminance component, this is a typical quantization table that we use.
And for the chrominance, CB and CR component, these are the typical quantization table that we use.
How do you obtain these two quantizations is that when the people, the chip hack,
working group that designed this particular quantization table,
they try out many different types of images and find out this particular quantization table
seems to work well.
Right?
So that's why they decided to adopt this two default quantization table.
All right?
Okay.
So this process, we just explained how do we perform the quantization.
Right.
Okay.
So next we are going to compare or study the effects of this particular quantization now.
See, suppose we have this well-known Lina image.
I think some of you know where this Lina image come from.
Right?
Anyone know where this Lina image come from?
So this is a very well-known image from an image processing perspective.
Actually, this particular image initially come from a magazine.
Yeah, it come from a very well-known magazine.
Right?
You all can go and find out which magazine it is.
Right.
Okay.
By current standard, it's nothing.
So anyway, this is a very well-known image called Lina, right?
From the image compression, image processing perspective.
So now if you look at some, one of this 8x8 pixel block here.
So let's look at this particular 8x8 pixel block here.
And this particular 8x8 pixel block here is coming from a smooth region.
All right?
It's a region that smooth or has low frequency content.
So if you look, if you zoom in and look at this 8x8 pixel value here, right?
Using Fij to represent, you can see this is the pixel block here.
So the value change very slowly.
So this has, this is, we can call it a smooth region,
or it has low frequency content because the value change very slowly.
Right?
Okay.
So next assuming that we perform DCT on this 8x8 pixel block,
then we'll get this 8x8 DCT coefficient here.
So if you look at this 8x8 DCT coefficient,
we can see that the energy is actually packed on this top left corner now.
So energy is defined as each of the value you squared.
So it's quite obvious that now energy is packed to this low AC coefficient or top left corner.
And then for this high AC coefficient, you can see the values are smooth.
Okay?
Right?
So next, okay, so you can see this is a smooth image of pixel block here.
So next we perform the quantization.
So how do we perform the quantization?
What it means is that we take this particular 8x8 pixel block, right?
We look at, okay, we use this quantization table.
We take the corresponding value.
For example, this value here, 515 divided by this value 16,
and round to the nearest integer.
Okay?
And then we'll get the first value here.
And then if you repeat that, you take your second DCT coefficient 65,
you divide by the corresponding quantization values or step size at the corresponding position.
You round to the nearest integer, then you'll get this second value here.
Okay?
So you repeat that, then you're complete and you obtain your quantized DCT coefficient.
So once you obtain your quantized DCT coefficient,
then actually there's a further, no steps for you to perform the compression using entropy encoding.
Okay?
But that one, we assume that, no, we are not going to look into it at the moment.
We just assume that you can actually continue with the compression
and then finally obtain a compressed image or bit stream.
So now you have a compressed image already.
So now if you want to do the reverse, you want to decompress or reconstruct the image,
then we have to do the reverse of performing the inverse entropy encoding.
Right?
And then once we reach that particular stage,
then the next thing is that we need to do the inverse quantization.
Okay?
Right?
So we need to do the inverse quantization.
So during the quantization step, what we do is that we take the quantization,
this is a DCT coefficient.
We divide by the corresponding value in the quantization table,
we round to the nearest integer.
So that is a forward quantization.
So in the inverse quantization, right, so what we do is that we take this,
we multiply with the corresponding value in your quantization table to obtain this de-quantized
decantization.
So it's quite straightforward.
Right?
During quantization, you divide during the de-quantization, you multiply.
Okay?
So therefore for each of these particular values here,
you multiply with the corresponding quantization values in the quantization table,
and then you obtain this de-quantized DCT coefficient.
All right?
So once you have this de-quantized DCT coefficient,
and after works what you can do is that you can perform the inverse DCT to construct the
reconstructed pixel block already.
So you can see, right, one is that you have the forward path which is doing the encoding,
right, to obtain your bitstream.
The other is doing the reverse, which is trying to perform the decoding,
which is to reconstruct your pixel block.
So therefore now, this is your reconstructed pixel block.
Okay?
So you start off with this particular pixel block.
And then this is your reconstructed pixel block.
If you take the difference between them, right, so this is the arrow.
So this arrow is a difference between your original pixel block
minus your reconstructed pixel block.
Okay?
So this is the pixel blocks here.
So what can you observe from this particular arrow?
So you notice that most of these values here are actually quite small.
Right?
That means actually, you know, your compression has performed quite well because, right,
given original image, you do the compression, okay, to compress into the bitstream.
And after works, you do the reverse to reconstruct your pixel block.
You'll notice that your original pixel block and your reconstructed or decompressed pixel
blocks are arrows are actually very small.
Right?
So therefore what it means is that, you know, for JPEG or Technic, it can actually compress
this kind of a smooth pixel block quite well.
Okay?
Now let's look at a second example.
This second example now is that we are going to look at this particular 8x8 pixel block here now.
So this particular 8x8 pixel block now is coming from what we know as a texture region.
Okay?
Texture.
Right?
That means actually, there's a certain pattern or in other words, there are high frequency
components.
That means the pixel value changed very quickly.
So this is the 8x8 pixel block now.
So if you zoom in and show the pixel distribution of this 8x8 pixel block,
you can see this is how it looks like.
Okay?
The pixel value changed quite quickly.
Right?
So after you perform the DCT, right, you will see that this is our DCT-KVCN here.
Okay.
So if you observe this particular DCT-KVCN here, as compared to the DCT-KVCN for just now
the earlier smooth block, what do you observe?
What's the difference?
The DCT-KVCN for a smooth pixel block versus the DCT-KVCN for a texture pixel block.
What do you notice?
The high frequency component, the values are,
okay, for this texture region, the high AC-KVCN here, the values are lower or larger as compared to
larger, right, larger compared to the, just on the smooth block.
So if you compare, if I can just show you one more time, so you can see this is the DCT-KVCN
for the smooth block.
You can see most of the energy now is packed to this corner already.
Okay?
The values at this high AC-KVCN are actually small.
Right?
As compared to now, this is the texture block.
You can see actually for this high AC-KVCN here, actually the values are larger.
So the reason is, the question is why?
Why is that for a texture pixel block, right, for a texture block like this?
Somehow this high AC-KVCN's, their values are not so large.
I mean, for this pixel block, the high AC-KVCN's, their values are large.
Or in other words, the energy compaction properly is not so good for texture region.
What is the reason?
If you remember, right, when we study about this DCT transform, what is the assumption
for this particular properties of energy compaction property to be valid?
DCT, we say that it can actually perform energy compaction, pack the energy into a small number
of kVCN.
But that's under the assumption that what?
Under what assumption?
In the original pixel domain, the pixel values are changing slowly, right?
So the pixel values are changing slowly.
Okay, so which is true just now for the smooth region?
But for the texture pixel block like this, because the pixel values are changing very quickly,
therefore actually it has high energy contained.
That's why, you know, this particular high AC-KVCN's, their values are larger.
So in other words, the energy compaction properties is not so well exhibited in this
texture region, because the assumption that the pixel values change very slowly is not
correct here now.
Okay, we say that for most of the images, if you look at a small pixel region,
usually the pixel value changes slowly, but there are some exceptions.
For example, an exception is this texture region.
So anyway, yeah, so this is the comparison.
So next if we continue, so we have this DCT-KVCN, we see that for texture region,
the AC-KVCN's, the values are also larger.
Okay, afterwards we perform the quantization.
We make use of a quantization table.
We repeat what we've described.
So you'll see that this is your quantized DCT-KVCN.
All right, okay.
So you come to this stage already, and afterwards you continue on to compress it into a small file
size.
So next you want to do the reverse of reconstructing the image now.
So you do the reverse of the entropy encoding, and afterwards you need to perform.
When you come to this stage, the fault stage is the quantization.
So the decoder stage would then be decantization or inverse quantization.
So you just take this, you multiply with the corresponding value in the quantization table,
you'll get your decantized DCT-KVCN.
Right, and afterwards you perform the inverse DCT.
This is your reconstructed pixel block.
So now you take the difference between your original pixel block
and your reconstructed pixel block, you'll see that this is the error.
Okay, so now if you compare the errors for the smooth region, okay, versus the error for the
texture region, you can see that, right, the error for the texture region is much larger now.
Okay, so these are all the observations that we will know, right, when we perform JPEG compression,
it's impact on different types of pixel block.
Jane speaking, for smooth region, it can compress it well, right, the error will be smaller,
but for a texture region, it doesn't work so well, because it does not satisfy the assumption that,
you know, the pixel value changes slowly.
Okay, right, okay, so now we come to this point that let's try to do a simple exercise to see
whether you understand what I've been talking about.
Right, okay, so for this exercise, it says that in a new image compression scheme,
a student would like to follow similar steps in the baseline JPEG to perform grayscale image
compression.
Okay, however, the student proposed to partition the image into multiple 4x4 pixel block,
perform 4x4 DCT for each block, and follow by the corresponding quantization and entropy
encoding.
So part one, it asks you to briefly describe a mean similarity and a mean difference between the
basis functions of the DCT used in this new compression scheme, and the one used in baseline
JPEG.
Okay, so I think we have covered just now the, you know, this basis function in the previous
lecture, and in the past 30 minutes or so, we also spent some time to talk about the quantization.
Right, okay, so now it's probably time for you to take a pause, think about it, and then afterwards
you'll go through the answers together.
Yeah, so by the way, all these are past year exam questions, so I include it here so that you
can go through it in the lecture and you also know what to expect in the exam.
Okay, so yeah, at least we have some time to think about it.
So any suggestion? What do you think is the similarity between the basis function for this
new scheme, which is a 4x4 block scheme versus the JPEG?
Right, so first of all, for JPEG, what is the pixel block that we partitioned into?
It's an 8x8, right? So for JPEG, given an image, we partitioned into numerous 8x8 pixel blocks,
but for this current scheme, it's a 4x4 pixel block, even an image, we partitioned into 4x4 pixel
block. Okay, so now one is 4x4, JPEG is 8x8. So in terms of their basis function, can you at least
explain, for example, we can start with the difference. The difference is much easier to
explain. What's the difference? There are actually quite a number of them, but just give me one,
the obvious one. In terms of the JPEG 8x8, how many DCT basis functions do you have? How many
different types? How many? 64, right? So if you remember, yeah, for JPEG, right, so you have 64
different types of basis functions, but for 4x4 pixel blocks, how many different types do you have?
16, huh? So you can see.
Yeah, okay, so this is for the 4x4 pixel block, right? So the types of basis function that you
have is 16 of them, and this is the DCT. Sorry, this is the JPEG, you have 64. So the number of
DCT basis function is 16 versus 64. So that's one, the difference. In terms of similarity, what you
can notice is that if you look at both the basis function for this 4x4 DCT and for this 8x8 DCT,
you can see that as you move in the horizontal direction, in the vertical direction, or in the
diagonal direction, the spatial frequency start to increase. Yeah, how fast the pattern changes
start to increase. So that is the common similarity between these two different sets of
basis functions. So that could be the, you can list it out as the difference and similarity.
So therefore you can see similarity is that both basis functions have an increasing horizontal,
horizontal, vertical, and diagonal spatial frequency. Okay, so that's the similarity.
And for the difference for this particular scheme, because it's used for 4x4 DCT, so you have 16
different types of basis function. As opposed to JPEG, which use 8x8 DCT, which you have 64
different types of basis function. So therefore we have this one similarity and one difference
between these two basis functions for these two. Right, okay, so next let's move on to the next
part of the questions.
All right, okay, so next part of the question is ask, okay, ask you to write down a suitable
quantization table for this new compression scheme. Briefly justify your answer. So I'll give you
one moment to think about for this new scheme, which is based on 4x4, you know, partitioned image
into 4x4 pixel block. What could be a suitable quantization table? I'll give you one moment
to think about it, and then we'll go through the answer together.
Okay.
Okay, all right, so at least I have some time to think about it. So what do you think are the
key properties, right, when you try to write down the quantization table for this new scheme?
What should be the size of this quantization table? It should be.
Sorry, a bit louder. The size of the quantization table should be what?
4x4, huh? And then what are some basic rule of thumb when you write down the quantization table?
Birth the value horizontally, vertically, and diagonally in the increasing horizontal,
vertical, and diagonal direction. The value should be increasing or decreasing,
increasing, right? So these are two basic properties for you to write down the quantization table.
Okay, so therefore one possible answer would be like this.
So a possible quantization table could be like this, right? So the key information,
as I mentioned, it should be first of all 4x4 in terms of dimension, and in terms of the value as
you move increasing horizontal spatial frequency, vertical, and the diagonal spatial frequency,
you can see the value will start to increase in all this direction based on what we have discussed
before. Okay, so so long as you follow this principle, whatever answer you provide, I'll give you
full mark so long as you follow that principle. Okay, so the explanation is that the quantization
table should be 4x4 with increasing step size in the horizontal, vertical, and diagonal direction.
Right, so the reason is, you know, this is to reduce the quantization error, okay, for the DC
and low AC coefficient, right, as the DCT coefficients are larger. So this one is the first reason
we mentioned. And also second reason is because humans are more sensitive to distortion, error
or distortion in this region. So therefore we also need to make sure that, you know, the step size
near these regions are smaller. So that's exactly what we have discussed, you know, for the past,
no 30 minutes or so. Okay, any questions?
Right, so if not, then this answer again will be available from tomorrow on works, so there's no
need for you to copy. All right, okay, so now we have actually completed the quantization. So next
we are going to continue on. So the next thing that we are going to do now is that after we have
performed the quantization, the next step that we are going to do is we are going to do the
entropy encoding here. So the entropy encoding actually will be consisting of four key steps.
The first step is known as a vectoring or zigzag scanning, right, so later on we will see what is
a zigzag scanning. And afterwards we are going to perform differential encoding, right, or is also
known as a differential pulse code modulation for the DC coefficient, right, okay. And then for the
AC coefficient, we are going to use the run-land coding. And then finally all this is we are going
to put it through the half-moon coding. So anyway, this is just the general steps in the next few
slides we are going to explain each of these steps a bit more in detail. Right, okay, so you can see
all these four steps here. The first step that you have to do is a vectoring or zigzag scanning,
right. So the objective of this particular zig, okay, maybe let's look at what this zigzag scanning
is first. So this zigzag scanning is like this. So just now what we have is that we have performed
the quantization already. So now we have this particular quantized DCT coefficient. So for this
particular quantized DCT coefficient, it's actually a matrix or a 2D array. So we want to convict it
into a vector. So we want to convert this particular matrix into a vector, okay. So when we convert
this matrix into a vector, right, okay, there's a few different ways we can do it, right. So the way
we are going to do it in this case is that we are going to start off with this DC coefficient,
and we are going to collect or convert this matrix into this vector in this way here. We are going
to scan through the coefficient in this particular manner, okay. Right. So afterwards then the first
value here is the DC coefficient, and the rest of the 63 coefficients are the AC coefficients here.
Right. So this is the example. After, for example, we perform this zigzag scanning here.
But the question is that why do we want to scan the coefficient in this particular manner?
Now what's the logic behind it? Why do we want to scan the DC coefficient in this particular fashion?
So the reason why we want to do it in this way is because if you remember, the first coefficient
is a DC coefficient, and these are the low AC coefficient, and these are the high AC coefficient.
And now based on the properties of the energy compaction, as well as the designs of your quantization
table, we know that near this AC coefficients here, you are going to get lots of value, which is zero.
Right. Because to start off with the, your quantize, your DC coefficient near this corner is already
small, and then you divide by a very large step size. That means you're going to get lots of zeros
near this high AC coefficient. So therefore, these orders of scanning will try to group
a lots of the zeros together. Okay. So therefore, by scanning through the DCT coefficient,
quantized DCT coefficient in this manner, a lot of the value zero here can be grouped together.
So this will facilitate the subsequent, no, running coding later. Right. Okay. So that's the basic
idea. We try to group the low AC coefficient together and the high AC coefficient together,
and the high AC coefficient because there are lots of zero. Right. So it will make your subsequent
run-land coding more effective. Okay. So that's the basic idea. So this process is known as a ZIXX
scanning. Right. So it converts this quantized 2D matrix into one D vector here. So the objective
is to exploit the presence of lots of zeros in the quantized matrix, particularly near this high
AC coefficient here. Okay. So that's what we do. So once we have done that, then your subsequent
vectors here, usually, no, towards the later part, you are going to get lots of zeros here.
Okay. So now the next thing is that after ZIXX scanning now, we are going to consider the DC
coefficients and the AC coefficient separately. So the DC coefficients, we are going to use a
differential coding or the predictive coding to do the compressions here. So you can see that
the DC coefficient is treated separately from the rest of the 63 AC coefficient. Right. And what's
the meaning of the DC coefficient? So if you remember in our previous last week's exercise,
no, we do try to calculate the DC coefficient. We say that the DC coefficient is an indication of the
average brightness or intensity of the pixel block. Okay. So the DC coefficient reflects the
average brightness or intensity of the pixel block here. Right. So the DC coefficients are
encoded using differential coding or predictive coding. So what it means is that, suppose if we
look at this, this is the first pixel block. Okay. 8 by 8 pixel block. And you have another 8 by 8
pixel block next to it. So for these two pixel blocks, each of them you are going to perform just
now the process of DCT transform quantization, ZIXX scanning. Right. And then you're going to get
this block, your give rise to a 64 dimensional factor. This block, you're going to give rise to
64 dimensional vector. And then for the two DC coefficient between them, we are going to use
a predictive coding to represent it. But why do we want to use predictive coding or differential
coding? What's the logic behind it? So when you use a differential coding, right, it's based on
the idea if these two values are the two DC value. Okay. For these two blocks, their values are very
similar or very different. Okay. When the values are very similar, right, it's actually good to use
predictive coding to encode it. Because the idea of predictive coding is that instead of representing
each of these values individually, we calculate their difference. So if these two values are very
similar and we calculate their difference, then the difference is very small. And if the difference
is very small, that means you can, you only need to use a small number of bits to represent them.
And hence you can achieve the compression. Right. So in short, the reason why we use the
differential coding or predictive coding to encode the difference between these two DC
coefficient is because each of the DC coefficient is an indication of how bright this block is
compared to the neighboring blocks. And we know that given a particular image, if you partition it
into many, many pixel blocks, for two consecutive pixel blocks, do you think their brightness are
going to be very similar to each other? It is, right? So if you look at, you know, just look at my
shirt, if you look at two consecutive pixel blocks, their average brightness or intensity is going to
be very similar. If they are very similar, that means their corresponding DC values are going to
be very similar. If they are corresponding DC value is very similar, that means we can use
predictive coding, right, to take this DC value minus this, this, the following DC value and the
arrow will be very small. And when the arrow is very small, you only need to use a small number
of bits to represent it. So therefore it's actually a good idea to use a differential of
predictive coding to code the DC coefficient. Okay. So that's the basic idea. So the difference,
which is also known as a prediction arrow between the DC coefficients of the current block and the
previous block is encoded. Okay. Based on what I've just explained. Okay. So the reason is because,
okay, as I mentioned, differential coding is used as the average brightness or intensity between two,
no consecutive blocks are very similar. Okay. So that's the basic idea for the DC coefficient. We
use differential coding to code it. Right. Next, we have the running coding now. So early on,
you can see that. Okay. So this particular DC coefficient, for example, this current block,
this is the DC coefficient. Just now we mentioned if you have another block, that means you have
another factor. So this DC coefficient and the DC coefficient for the two blocks, we use a differential
coding to code it. Right. So now we are going to look at this, the rest of the 63 AC coefficient.
So for this AC coefficient, how are we going to encode it? So the technique we are going to use
is known as a run name coding or run name encoding. You refer to the same thing. So
for the AC coefficient, we are going to use run name coding or run name encoding. Right.
Sometimes you use coding. Sometimes you use encoding. This works. It's interchangeable. So
there's no difference. Okay. So the AC coefficients are going to be encoded using run name encoding.
Right. So the running encoding, it exploit the presence of a large number of zeros in the
AC values by trying to group the zeros together. So earlier on, if you remember, when you do the
zigzag scanning, right, okay, at the later part, you're going to get many, many zeros. So these
zeros can be grouped together. Okay. Together. So that's what's trying to say by trying to
exploit the presence of a large number of zeros in the AC coefficient here. So this running coding
actually has a unique syntax. So running coding, the syntax is actually the use, you know, a pass
of values. So for running coding, actually, it consists of strings of pairs. That means there's
many different strings of pairs here. So each of the pairs in this particular
running coding, it consists of two values, skip and value here. So skip means that, right, the
number of zeros you are going to encounter before you see the number of zero you are going to
experience before you see the first non-zero value, right? Because we know that when we scan the AC
coefficient, that's many, many, many, zero there. Right. So how we are going to encode it is we are
going to use many different pairs like this or strings of pairs. For each of this particular pair,
this skip value means that how many, in this current value, how many zeros are you going to
experience first before you encounter the first non-zero value? So the number of zeros that
you encounter is known as a skip. So you can see the number of zeros in this current run. Okay.
And then this value here is the first non-zero value that you encounter. So therefore, for example,
when you scan the rest of the 63 AC coefficient, first, the first run, maybe, you know, you see,
for example, three zero, right? Then you are going to have three, which represent the three zero.
And then the first non-zero value that you encounter, then you have one pair. Okay. And
afterwards, you continue to see how many zero you encounter. Okay. So the number of zero you
encounter is called skip. And then the first non-zero value you encounter is that you encounter
is called value. So you are going to get many skip value pairs, skip value pairs, skip value pairs
until at the end, when the rest of the values are all zero, we have a unique symbol called zero,
comma, zero. Okay. Which indicate the rest of the AC coefficients are all zero already.
Okay. So these are some of the details and text. Actually, you don't have to
know the detail, but I just roughly tell you this is how they do it. Okay. So for running coding,
right, it's going to be represented as a string. Okay. Of this skip value pair. Okay. Each of
the skip value pairs, the number of zero encounter and the first non-zero value that you have.
Okay. So that's the running coding. And then after finally, right, once you have for the
DC coefficient, we have used just now the differential coding, the AC coefficient, right,
we use a running coding to reduce it into a strings of many skip value pair. Right. So
the next thing is that we notice that, for example, for this DC coefficient after predictive coding,
as well as a running coding, right, this particular pattern of the skip value pair patterns that you
see, some pattern occur more often than the others. So if some pattern occur more often than
the others, then the logical way for you to do it is the next step to further compress is to use
an entropy encoding. So Huffman coding, as we have studied in the previous lecture, right,
is a common entropy encoding technique. So that's why we use it. So, okay, the explanation is given
here. So after differential coding and the running coding, some patterns occur more often than the
others. Some values or some patterns occur more often than the others. So therefore, entropy
coding such as Huffman coding is then used to compress the symbol based on what we study in
the first week's lecture. So the ideas of Huffman coding to recap is that, okay, for more commonly
seen pattern or more frequent pattern, you use the shorter code works to represent. And for the
less common pattern, you use a longer code work to represent it. Okay. So therefore, high compression
can be achieved by replacing frequent pattern with shorter code work and vice versa. Okay. So
Huffman coding is used on both the differential coding and the running coding.
Right. Okay. So next, this slide here shows the, you know, the image quality versus the number of
DCT component that we have. So if you remember in the particular, in last week's lecture, we talked
about the DCT coefficients, right? So there's DCT coefficients here. Okay. So, right, for example,
this particular diagram shows that if this is your original pixel block, if you only keep one DCT
coefficient, that means you only keep the DC coefficient, right, then when you try to perform
the image reconstruction, you only give the average intensity of this image. Right. Okay. But if you
start to increase the number of DCT coefficient that we have, right, by scanning through the first
few AC, by keeping the DC plus the first few AC coefficient. Okay. But keeping a small number of
this particular DCT coefficient, you can start to see your reconstructed pixel block start to
improve significantly already. And then if you use up to 12 DCT coefficient, you can see your
reconstructed pixel block or image becoming better and better. Okay. So therefore, what it means is
that for this DCT here, you only need to keep a small number, right, because of this energy
compaction probability, you, energy compaction property, you only need to use a small number of
DCT coefficient for you to be able to reconstruct your pixel block more effectively. Okay.
Right. Okay. So just now in the previous slide, we say that, okay, so so far, what have you done,
right? We have given a particular image, we partitioned into numerous 8 by 8 pixel blocks.
Each of the pixel blocks, we let it go through the DCT transform, right? Okay. And then each of the
DCT coefficient, we let it go through the quantization to obtain the quantized DCT coefficient.
All right. Okay. And afterwards we go through a zigzag scanning to convert it into a 64-dimensional
vector. The DC coefficient, because different blocks are similar, we use differential coding.
For the AC coefficient, we use the running coding, right? And afterwards, this DC and AC, we let it
go through the entropy and coding such as half-moon coding, right? So this is what we have now.
So one up to this stage now, the last thing that you need to do is you need to pack all this
information right into a particular JPEG syntax, right? Okay. So therefore, the last step is we
need to do the frame building here. So JPEG have a certain form of syntax to define how do you pack
those information. So JPEG define the syntax for the bitstream, right? For this image. So the
rule of this particular frame builder is to capture all those information that we have extracted,
format it properly based on what JPEG can understand and then put it into this bitstream.
So therefore, this go to capture all the information, right, from this image into a
certain format that JPEG can understand, right? So then that's the end of the story. Okay.
So therefore, if you have a quick look at this, right, so we pretty much cover all of them already.
So yeah, let's just do a quick recap. We have the original image typically we convert into YCBCR
color space. And then for this CB and CR, usually we perform some chroma sub sampling. So that means
for example, a two by two pixel block usually will only keep one CB and we keep one CR here.
Okay. And then for this image, we are going to partition into numerous eight by eight pixel block.
Okay. Each of them will go through a DCT to get the DCT coefficient.
Each pixel block will go through a quantization to get the quantized DCT coefficient.
So in the process of performing this quantization, we need a quantization table
that we have just explained. So this particular quantized DCT coefficient, we're going to use
just now the zigzag scanning by performing that, right, we'll convert into the vector.
So the first value is a DC value. The rest of the 63 values are the AC value. So
the DC value, we are going to go through the differential pulse code modulation,
which is also the differential coding. Okay. And afterwards, because some pattern occur more than
the others, we use the entropy coding such as halfman coding to perform the compression.
And for this AC coefficient, because there are lots of zero, okay,
we need, so we'll exploit the halfman, sorry, the running coding and code it. And the output
is that some of those pattern, the skip value pairs are more often. That's why again, we exploit
entropy coding to compress it. Okay. So in order to use this coding, we need a coding table,
for example, a halfman table that has been trained in advance. And then finally, all this information,
like the tables, the pattern that you obtain, you're going to pack into your JPEG bitstream here.
So you have the data here. You have some header, some control information, and then you have this
table that contain all the table information. So this completes the JPEG encoding process.
Right. Okay. So now if you look at this JPEG bitstream, so JPEG bitstream is just now the final
file or the bitstream that we have. So the bitstream structure is organized in this way.
So at the highest level, you have a start of an image. All right. So these are the, you know,
the header or the control information. And this frame is like the data in the image. And this frame
can further be divided into a few scans here. So even a particular JPEG image, you know,
it can be divided into a few scan. So a few scan is usually referring to a few lines of
eight by eight pixel block. So that's a meaning of a scan. Right. And then in one scan, for example,
a few lines of eight by eight pixel block, it can be further divided into a few different segments.
So a few segments is actually, you know, a few eight by eight pixel block is arranged together.
That's called a segment. And afterwards beneath each segment, then you have the eight by eight
pixel block. So this is how JPEG organized their bitstream.
Okay. So now we have studied the forward transform. That means given an image, we go through all
this process, we can get the bitstream. So now from this bitstream or the JPEG image that you
store in, for example, your mobile phone, if you want to know display the image back, right, so this
is known as the decompression. Okay. So right. Therefore now we want to look at the reverse,
which is the JPEG decoder. So JPEG decoder means that you have a JPEG file or the bitstream,
right? After you go through this JPEG decoder, you want to reconstruct your or decompress an image.
Okay. So therefore this JPEG decoder is exactly the reverse of the JPEG encoder that we have studied.
So right. The flow is like this. We have the JPEG bitstream or image. We let it go through the
frame decoder. So it extracts some information, right? So it extracts some control information
and also extract all the tables. So just now you can see we have the
halfman table. We have the quantization table and some control information.
So we extract those information. And the next thing is that, right? So the reverse of just now
the JPEG encoding, we'll see the reverse, the first reverse process that we need to do the
halfman decoding. Okay. So after the halfman decoding, we have the DC component and we have
the AC component. So the DC component, we need to now go through the differential decoding.
The AC component, we need to let it go through the ground length decoding. So the reverse of
what they are experienced. So once we have the DC and the AC coefficient, we need to organize them
properly into the matrix form. And then we need to let it go through the decantization or the
inverse quantization. Okay. Right. And afterwards, we need to let it go through the inverse DCT.
Right. And then finally, right, we need to let it go through the image builder to make sure that
all the eight by eight pixel block are arranged properly. And then finally, you will have your
reconstructed image. Okay. So that's basically the reverse of it. So now, early on from diagram,
I already explained the steps. So let's just look at the right up here for this JPEG decoder.
So JPEG decoder extract the control information and the table and then pass to the image builder,
as mentioned. So the first thing you need to do is you need to go through the halfman decoder,
right, to extract DC and the AC component. Right. So and then the DC component need to go through
the differential decoding, right, differential decoding to get the DC coefficient. And the AC
component need to let it pass through the running coding to get the AC coefficient. Right. So afterwards,
you need to rearrange it into the matrix format. And then we need to let it go through the inverse
quantization or decantization. Right. So once you obtain the decantized coefficient,
we need to let it go through the inverse DC to get your original pixel block. And after
works, you need to arrange all this pixel block properly. And then you will be able to obtain
your original image. Okay. So that's pretty much that. Okay. So now with that, so we can go through
simple exercise. Actually this exercise is just like what we have just explained.
So you can see, for example, one of the sample pass here question, it asks you to draw a simple
block diagram of the baseline, JPEG decoder, and then clearly label all the key components in the
diagram. All right. Actually we just covered it. But if you want, you can just know, close it and
then think for one moment whether you can still highlight some of the blocks here. Okay. I'll
give you just one moment and then we'll, I'll just show you the answer.
Yes.
Yeah. There are some.
Most of the time they have some, some, how should I say, standard protocols are either in terms of
padding or some way to manage that. But those are actually some, I would say it's a secondary issue.
You can do some padding. Either you impose some constraint on the number of pixels,
which is a multiple of eight, or you can do some padding.
All right. Okay. So therefore for the answer, yeah, it's actually quite.
All right. Okay. Let me see.
Okay. So the answer is actually this diagram that we have just shown you a little bit earlier.
So in the exam, what you need to do is simply just, no, sketch this diagram and label all
the components properly. Yeah. So since I've just explained a little bit earlier, so I'll not go through
it again here.
All right. Okay. So now we have actually covered part two. So in this part here, we actually
studied the following. So we look at some term and concept and trophy encoding. And then we talk
about the basic of image and video compression. We look into the general transform base coding
or compression. Now that we spend some time to explain about the properties of DCT, especially
from the perspective of change of basis. And then we spend some time to discuss about the
JPEG standards. Yeah. Okay. So that's pretty much part two. I think it's probably time we take a
short break. Right. So let's take a short break until eight and then we'll resume at eight PM.
Okay.
You are welcome to read up from these references or any sources that you can find from the
internet.
Right, so the outline for part three is that, first of all, we are going to look at some
video coding as well as standards.
And in particular, we'll be focusing on the MPEG as well as the H.26X series of the video
compression standard, because these are the dominant video compression standards.
And then finally, we'll be looking at some new emerging coding standards.
Okay, so that's the plan for part three.
Right, so first, we are going to look at video coding and standards.
So we are going to understand some of the basic theory.
Oh, sorry.
Okay, maybe let me just quickly run through one more time.
Right, okay, so part three is on video compression and standard.
Okay, so these are some references.
Right, any questions?
Just read up from them or from the internet.
Okay, so these are outlines.
So first of all, we'll be looking at some video coding and standard.
And then we'll be looking at these two types of video compression standard MPEG series
as well as the H.26X series of standard.
And then we'll be looking at some emerging direction.
Okay, so next we'll be touching on this video coding and standard as some of the basic theory behind it.
Right, so first we'll be trying to cover some of the basic concepts of video compression.
Right, okay, before that, let me just play a short video, right, to kind of warm yourself up a bit.
Starting 8th September, grab 99% off breaking deals on Shoppe.
Okay, so we'll be looking at some of the basic concepts of video compression.
Okay, so first we'll be looking at some of the basic concepts of video compression.
Okay, so anyway it's a long video, so hope that this part of the lecture will be as lively as this.
Okay, but probably Laili not.
Okay, so anyway, for video compression, a lot of them, even though there are some basic underlying techniques behind it,
but there's also lots of more standard based issue.
So anyway, we'll try to make this lecture a bit more interesting by trying to carving some of the more intuition behind video compression
rather than focusing a lot on the syntax.
So we'll try to explain the idea behind it rather than focus on the syntax.
Right, okay, so in order to continue with the video compression, let's do a quick recap of some of the redundancy that exists in the video.
Right, so as you can remember, video is nothing but a sequence of frame that you play very quickly and based on the human vision persistent,
it will give the impression of the smooth motion.
Right, so there's a basic idea behind this video.
And of course, also there's an audio expect to it.
Okay, so now in a video, it exists a lot of redundant information.
That's why when we are trying to perform video compression, our key objective is to remove this redundancy or extra unnecessary information from the video.
So what are some of the redundancy that exists in a video?
Right, so let's do a quick recap.
So the first redundancy that we have is a spatial redundancy.
By now, after study about the JPEG standard, you should be quite familiar with this concept already.
So spatial redundancy means that given a particular image, in particular, if you look at a small pixel neighborhood, the pixel values tend to change very slowly.
So if the pixel value changes very slowly, that means there's lots of redundant information.
Rather than representing each pixel value, actually you can think of some better way to represent it.
So that's the basic idea of the spatial redundancy.
So spatial redundancy refers to the statistical corrosion.
So corrosion can be interpreted as a similarity or relatedness between pixels in an image or more specifically within a small pixel neighborhood.
Okay, so because these types of redundancy exist within a single frame, so that's why it's also known as intraframe redundancy.
So for example, if you look at one of these small pixel neighborhoods here, it's quite clear that the pixel values are very similar to each other.
So there's lots of redundant information.
So when we perform video compression, we should try to remove this redundancy.
So the next redundancy is known as a temporal redundancy.
So if you remember, temporal redundancy refers to time-based redundancy.
So in this particular example here, a video is actually a sequence of frames that change very slowly.
So if you look at these three frames in a video, so if you look at a small, for example, pixel corresponding pixel location,
you can see that the pixel values are very similar across different frames.
And for different frames, this is along the time axis.
So therefore there's lots of redundancy in the time axis.
So therefore it's known as the temporal redundancy.
So temporal redundancy refers to the statistical correlation or similarity or relatedness between pixels from successive frames,
for example, successive frames, in a particular position, for example.
So because this type of redundancy exists across different frames,
so therefore it's also known as an interframe redundancy.
It's a redundant information that exists across different frames, hence interframe.
Right, okay, so the third type of redundancy that has to do with a human visual system,
which is known as a psycho-visual redundancy here.
So in particular, we have the frequency masking here.
So the frequency masking says that humans are more sensitive to any changes or distortion or noise in low-frequency component
as compared to high-frequency component.
So if you take these particular two images here, right, so for example, if you look at these particular sky regions here,
right, if there's some noise or some distortion, maybe for example in the form of having a dot here or a bird here,
our eye can actually spot this thing quite readily.
That means if there's some distortion or some change, actually our eyes can spot changes in the low AC component quite readily.
So this is as opposed to this image here.
So you can see this image has lots of texture or high AC component.
So if you have a small inset here, actually our eyes cannot spot it so readily.
So it's just how human visual system works, okay.
So this particular observation is known as a frequency masking.
So it says that human is less sensitive to noise or distortion in high-frequency component, okay, and vice versa.
Vice versa means that now human is more sensitive to noise and distortion in low-frequency component, okay.
So this is known as a frequency masking, right, and then next is the color masking.
So color masking we have mentioned a number of times already.
So human is more sensitive to the luminance or the brightness component as compared to the chrominance or the color component.
So therefore human is more sensitive to the luminance or brightness component as compared to the chrominance or the color component.
So when we are trying to perform video compression, actually the objective is we are trying to exploit all this redundancy that exists either within the frame,
or across the frame that has to do with a human visual system and how we represent the code to perform the compression.
So that's a basic underlying idea.
So therefore how do we perform video compression?
How do we compress the video?
So we are going to exploit all the redundancy that we have just explained.
So by removing the spatial redundancy, by reducing the temporal redundancy, and by exploiting the cycle visual redundancy.
So in the following slides you'll see no different strategy to do that.
So in real life, there's actually many, many different video compression standard, but all of these standards, their goal is the same, which is to reduce these types of redundancy.
So on top of that, we also want to improve the coding efficiency.
That means how we represent the big pattern.
So some of the things that we have studied before, including for example, the Hartman coding, right, the differential or predictive coding.
These two refer to the same, or for example, one length coding that we have studied in JPEG.
So these are the two key strategies we are going to use to perform video compression.
Okay, start on here.
Press the wrong button.
Okay, so next let's look at what's the structures of a video.
So as we have mentioned before, a video is nothing but a sequence of frames.
So you have a sequence of frames here.
So for this sequence of frames, very often we are going to organize it into multiple what we know as a group of pictures.
So video is a sequence of frames.
So we are going to organize it into numerous group of pictures, which is also known as a GOP.
So we are going to organize it into numerous GOP, right?
Okay, and then if you look at each of these particular picture, right?
So picture, in the context of video compression, we can call it image, we can call it picture, we can call it frame.
They're all referred to the same thing.
Okay, so if you look at these single pictures here, you can see this picture of this frame can be divided into a few different slices.
So just now in JPEG compression, we also see this slice structure.
So these different slices.
And then for each of the slice here, right, it's going to be further divided into a few macro block.
So each of these is a macro block.
Okay, so this macro block is a little bit different from the JPEG.
So for a macro block, it consists of one 16 by 16 pixel block of wide channel, one 8 by 8 pixel block of CB, and one 8 by 8 pixel block of CR.
So in other words, the macro block structures that you have here in video compression, right, it consists of four 8 by 8 pixel block of wide channel,
which is the luminance channel, one 8 by 8 pixel block of CB, and one 8 by 8 pixel block of CR.
So you can see here, okay, you have one, two, three, four, four 8 by 8 pixel block of luminance or wide channel, one CB and one CR channel.
So this is known as a macro block here, okay, in video compression.
So now, right, there's an alternative way of looking at this particular video structure.
So you have this particular video sequence, which is what's being shown here.
So this video sequence can be divided into numerous GOP, group of pictures like this.
So numerous GOP, right, and then you have some header information.
Okay, so which are some control information here.
Under GOP, right, so you can see this is one GOP.
Under one GOP, you have a few different pictures of frames here.
So one GOP, you have different pictures.
And then under one picture, you can be divided into a few different slices.
For example, a few different slices, okay.
And under one slice, you can have multiple macro blocks.
Okay, so you can see there are many different macro blocks.
Okay, and then under each macro block, it can be divided into six blocks here, which is this six blocks here.
Okay, four luminance blocks, one CB and one CR.
So you have six blocks here.
And then for each of the blocks here, right, it will consist of the DC component, which is using a differential coding and the AC component, which is just now the ground link coding.
Yeah, so actually for lots of the video compression, it also exploit what we have learned in the JPEG compression.
So therefore, right, you can see that there are some certain similarity with respect to what you have learned in the JPEG.
And that will be bring forward to the video compression as well.
Right, okay, so let's look at this macro block a little bit closer.
So a macro block consists of things like this.
So you can see you have four 8x8 pixel blocks of wide channel, one 8x8 pixel block of CB and one 8x8 pixel block of CR.
So you can see one macro block has four 8x8 pixels of wide channel.
So Y is the luminance, one CB and one CR.
So this 4x8 pixel block you can also see is equivalent to a 16x16 this Y component.
Y is the luminance.
Okay, and the corresponding 8x8 CB and CR component here.
Right, okay, so we have explained this a few times already.
So a macro block has four luminance blocks, one, two, three, four, and two prominence block, one CB and one CR.
So this is the basic building block for the DCT operations and motion compensation in video compression.
So subsequently we were talking about, you know, this is DCT operations as well as motion compensation.
Right, it's going to be based on this structure.
Okay.
Right, okay, so next let's look at what's the basic idea in video compression.
So the main idea in video compression actually is centered on two things.
You have the motion estimation and motion compensation.
So what is motion estimation and motion compensation?
So if you think about it for one moment, a video is actually a sequence of frames.
Okay, a sequence of frames.
And each of these frames are very similar to each other.
So like what we mentioned just now the interframe redundancy.
So therefore, instead of trying to, you know, represent each of this particular pixel value,
what you can do is that for each of the frame, we can partition it into numerous macro block.
Okay, we can partition it into numerous macro block like what we have explained earlier on.
And afterwards, suppose this is the current frame.
Okay, this is the current frame that we want to compress or include.
We partition it into numerous macro block.
Okay, suppose this is a current macro block that we want to compress right in our current frame.
So this current macro block that we want to compress in this current frame will compare to the previous reference frame.
Okay, so we'll compare with the previous reference frame and try to see where is the most similar block or the best match block.
Right, so the process of trying to find out the most similar block is known as a motion estimation.
You want to find out where it is, the most similar block.
So suppose this is your current frame, this is your reference frame.
So you try to find, okay, this current macro block here, you try to find the positions of the most similar block.
Suppose you find the most, the best match block is here, then this relative offset, you know, how much you move from this position to this position.
This is known as a motion factor.
Okay, the relative displacement is known as a motion factor.
So the process of finding the best match block is motion estimation.
And afterwards, once you found the best match block and your current block that you want to encode, you take their difference.
Then this is known as the motion compensation.
You try to find the prediction error.
So why we want to do that as mentioned many times is because for a video, if you just imagine your hand, this current video of the hand in this current frame, it may be here.
In the next frame or the previous frame, it may be just a little bit, it's very, very similar to it.
So therefore, very likely you can find a best match block quite readily.
Okay, so therefore, this is the main ideas in video compression.
It consists of motion compensation estimation, which is trying to predict the motion factor, right, the position of the best match block.
And then motion compensation, which is you're trying to find a small difference between your actual macro block.
That means the current block you want to compress as well as the predicted, that means the best match block that you have found earlier.
Okay, right, so we can easily understand this motion estimation and compensation from this figure.
So again, just imagine, for example, this is the current frame that you want to compress.
Right, so this is the current frame you want to compress.
The first thing that you do is you partition it into numerous macro blocks.
So each of these is actually a macro block here.
Now, suppose if we look at this current macro block, you want to compress this current macro block.
So what we do is that we look at the previous reference frame.
Okay, because this frame, your current frame and the previous reference frame should be very similar.
Okay, so standard at this particular positions here, standard at this particular position, you're going to define a such a frame.
You're going to define a such window.
Okay, your search window is where you're trying to find this best match block.
So standard at this current position here, right in the previous reference frame at the same center position, you define a search window.
And afterwards, you try to find what is the positions of the most similar block or best match block.
Suppose after you scan through all the positions, you find that the most similar block is this block here.
Then the relative offset from this standard here to this particular standard here, this is known as the motion factor here.
Okay, so this is the motion factor.
This is the most similar block or the best match block here.
So this particular process of trying to find out the positions of the most similar block is known as motion estimation.
So after you have found this match, best match block, you can see this block here, the current block you're trying to compress and the best match block.
If you look at it, there's still a small difference.
Yeah, because if you imagine it's still a video.
So even if you found a block, which is most similar, there's still a small difference.
So therefore you need to take the difference between your current block and the best match block, right?
You take that difference.
So this particular process of taking the difference is known as motion compensation.
Okay, so these two concepts here.
Right, okay, so let's continue on.
Right, so in many video compression, there's also these ideas of intraframe and the interframe compressions here.
Right, so you can see that for many video compression techniques such as MPEC or H.26 series of compression,
they make use of both the intraframe as well as the interframe compression.
So what is intraframe compression?
So as the name suggests, intraframe compression means it's a compression within the frame.
Okay, it's a compression within the frame.
So typically given a particular video, right?
For example, just now we say a video can be divided into many GOP structures, many group of picture structures.
So now if you look at one GOP structure, right?
So you look at one GOP structure, there's a few different frame types.
So later on we are going to see, right, there's a few different frame types here.
So some of the frame types, right?
For example, in the context of MPEC 1, right?
So in the context of MPEC 1, the GOP structure actually has three frame types.
The i-frame, the p-frame as well as the b-frame that we are going to study shortly.
So for the i-frame, right?
So i-frame stands for intra-coded frame.
That means we are going to compress this frame independently, just like it's a JPEG image.
Okay, so for this GOP structure, there's an i-frame, there's a p-frame, and then there's a b-frame in between.
So for i-frame, we are going to compress it independently just like JPEG images.
So these types of frames, because we are going to compress it independently, right?
It does not depend on other frame.
So it's known as an intra-frame compression.
So therefore, for some of the frames in the video, we will consider some of these frames just like they are steel images, like in a JPEG image, right?
So for example, the i-frames in the MPEC, we are going to compress it independently, okay?
Right, so because we compress it independently, we treat it just like it's an image.
So the goal is to reduce the spatial redundancy just like in the MPEC compression.
So it will use a technique which is very similar to the JPEG compression that we have studied earlier on.
So this is known as the intra-frame compression.
Okay, so the next types of frames that we have is known as the inter-frame compression.
So the inter-frame compression, as the name suggests, the means is a compression that exists across a frame.
So when it's across a frame, actually it's based on the idea of the motion, estimation and compensation that we have just studied.
Right, so for inter-frame compression, it makes use of the correlation across the temporal domain, right?
So for example, in the context of MPEC standard, right, we have the P-frame and B-frame here, which we'll study shortly.
So for P-frame and B-frame in MPEC, it actually right, perform inter-frame compression, okay?
You look at two, you look at, for example, this current frame that you want to compress, you compare with the previous reference frame,
you try to find the positions of the best match block, you calculate the difference.
So which is the motion, estimation, compensation we just introduced, yeah?
So when you are using, you know, across two different frames, we call inter-frame compression.
So therefore, for many video compression standard, they usually, you know, leverage on both intra-frame compression as well as inter-frame compression.
So for inter-frame compression, because you are utilizing the correlation across two different frames in the temporal domain,
so the goal is to reduce temporal redundancy, the similarity across different frames, right?
And it makes use of the technique of a motion, estimation, and compensation technique that we have just introduced a short while ago.
Right, okay, so the next thing is that we are going to look at, you know, this, you know, the color space.
So similar to JPEC, for MPEC, typically the color space we are going to use is the YCBCR color space.
So if you look at this particular image here, right, okay.
So anyway, the luminance sometimes, short form we just called Luma, okay, chrominance sometimes we just called Chroma, okay?
So this is a short form here, right?
So for this MPEC, for video compression, right, most of the time we will convert the color space into YCBCR color space here, right?
So if you look at, for example, this image here is in the RGB color space here.
So if we convert it into the YCBCR color space, you can see this is the Y channel.
This is the CB and this is the CR channels here, right?
Okay, so you can see that actually our eyes are more sensitive to this particular Y channel and less sensitive to this CB and CR channel, right?
So because our eyes are less sensitive to this CB and CR channel, so if you want to perform compression, what can we do?
Since our eyes, number one is that, okay, why do we want to represent this video in YCBCR color space?
Why?
Why is it common for us to convert the color space for video into YCBCR color space for compression?
I think we actually kind of very briefly touched on this in one of the earlier lecture.
So the reason why we commonly represent an image in this YCBCR color space is that, right?
Because our eyes are more sensitive to the Y channel and less sensitive to the CB and CR channel.
That means once we convert the color space into this particular representation, there's a very intuitive and very logical way on how we can perform the compression now.
Because compression means that we want to compress using as few bits as possible, right?
If we can represent this image in this YCBCR color space and we already know once we represent in this color space, our eyes are sensitive to this,
but our eyes are not sensitive to this CB and CR.
Therefore, there's a very natural scheme which is that means we don't have to keep all the pixels in the CB and CR channel, right?
Since our eyes are not so sensitive to it, right?
So we can drop some of the pixels in the CB and CR channel.
So the reason why we can drop is by dropping it, it hardly makes any difference to how we perceive this video, right?
So that's why once we are in this space here, we can simply only keep a small number of subsets of pixels in this CB and CR channel.
So this particular process is known as a chroma subsampling.
That means we only perform subsampling for some of the pixels in the CB and CR channel.
So that's the ideas of chroma subsampling.
So it turns out that actually there's also a few different ways, a few different strategies we can decide what are the chroma pixels we want to keep.
So therefore, there's a few different subsampling format.
So let's look at some of the common subsampling format.
So the first subsampling format is known as a 444, right?
So there's no need for you to interpret whether there's a mathematical kind of interpretation behind it.
There's no need to. Just remember there's this structure.
444 correspond to this 422 correspond to this format and so on and so forth.
So pretty much 444 chroma subsampling means that you do not perform any subsampling at all, right?
So if you look at these particular examples here, so right, actually, right, you have one wide channel here.
So for 444, that means the wide channel, we keep all the eight pixels here.
In this particular case, we are showing a two by four pixel block.
So for 444, we keep all the wide channel pixels.
And then these blocks here, actually, the interpretation of this U plus B means that you have one U block and you have one V block.
So let's take a shortcut and show them together.
But actually, you have one two by four U block and one two by four V block here.
So that means we keep all the U block pixels and we keep all the V block pixels.
So now if you have those three two by four pixel block, we put them together in the RGB.
This is how it looks like.
Okay. So this is if you use a 444, that means we do not do any subsampling.
So the next subsampling that we have is the 422 chroma subsampling.
So for the 422 chroma subsampling, right, for the wide channel, again, because our eyes are sensitive to it, so we keep all the pixel.
So we keep all the pixel value.
Now, okay, for the U channel, just remember you have one block, which is corresponding to U and the other block, which is corresponding to V.
So actually, there are two blocks there.
Right. So for 422 chroma subsampling, what you do is that for every two horizontal CB, okay, this U and V actually is very similar to CB and CR.
So we just interpret U and V and CB and CR.
They are the same in this context here.
So for every two horizontal U pixel or CB pixel, we only keep one.
Okay. That means we drop the other one.
We only keep, for every two horizontal pixel, we only keep one U, okay, or two horizontal pixel, we only keep one U or we only keep one CB here.
And likewise, for the CR or the V channel, every two horizontal pixel, we only keep one.
That means you actually drops half of the pixel in the U and V channel, or the CB and CR channel already.
Okay. So now if you put those three blocks together, why U and V together, this is how it looks like after you have performed a 422 chroma subsampling.
Okay.
Right. So the next one is that, okay, the other well-known subsampling format is known as a 420.
So for 420, that means the Y channel, we keep all the pixel.
Right. For this U and V, if we consider the U block here, right, every two by two pixel block, we only keep one.
One U pixel. Every two by two pixel block, we only keep one U pixel.
And then likewise for V, every two by two pixel block, we only keep one V pixel.
Every two by two pixel block, we only keep one V pixels here.
So now if we have these three blocks together, we put them together.
This is how a 420 chroma subsample pixel will look like if we change it to the RGB representations here.
Okay.
Right. And then next, the next one is the 411 chroma subsampling.
So for 411 chroma subsampling, what we have is again, the Y channel, we keep all the pixel.
And then for each of the U and V, every four horizontal pixel, we only keep one U.
Okay. And every four horizontal pixel, we only keep one V pixel.
So if we put them together, this is how it looks like.
Okay. So these are the, a few common chroma subsampling format that we have.
So you can see for 422 and 411, it involves horizontal subsampling.
Every two pixel, you keep one or every four pixel, you keep one.
Okay. And then for 420, it involves a horizontal and vertical subsampling.
Every two by two pixel block, you only keep one.
So if you look at now, if you look at this chroma subsampling format, you notice that, okay,
this original pixel block and then this, another three chroma subsampling blocks are,
it looks kind of different now.
But earlier on, you know, we mentioned that our eyes are not so sensitive to it.
So by right, if you perform some chroma subsampling, you know,
your eye cannot tell the difference between them.
So, so how do we explain, explain this?
By right, it should be something like, because our eyes are not so sensitive to this chroma channel,
so we can drop some of the pixels, right?
So by right, what it means is that, you know, after you perform this subsampling, right,
this pixel block should visually look similar to this original pixel block, right,
that you do not drop any pixel.
But if you look at it, actually it looks kind of different.
Okay, so actually, yeah, the thing is like this, because if you are talking about, for example, a TV,
you know, a TV nowadays, a big TV actually has many, many pixels, right?
So now we are more like, you know, we really, really zoom in to look at a small pixel block,
and you can tell the difference.
But if you zoom out, because there are so many pixels there, right,
actually from our visual perspective, right, you can hardly tell them apart, okay?
So the reason why you can tell them apart now is because you zoom in and look at it so closely.
But once you zoom out, right, there are millions of pixels.
Actually from the visual perception perspective, you can hardly tell them apart, okay?
Right, okay, so therefore the basic idea of chroma subsampling,
I think we have spent some time to talk about it.
The basic idea is human is more sensitive to the luminous component than the chroma component.
So in order to achieve compression, that means to try to, you know, keep as few pixels as possible, right?
The chroma component can be subsampled, or in other words, some of the pixels can be dropped, okay?
So if you perform 422 chroma subsampling, that means every two horizontal Y-sampled,
we only keep one CB, one CB and one CR pixel, right?
If we use, for example, the 420 chroma subsampling,
for every 2x2Y-sampled, we only keep one CB and one CR sample.
So based on what we have explained.
Right, okay, so next I'm going to play you a very short video to explain the basic principles of video coding.
So again, with some, you know, animation and visualization,
sometimes it's easier for you to understand than just simply using the words that I've described.
Okay, so let me just play this short video for you.
If you watch videos on the web, you use video codecs.
But what exactly is a video codec?
Codecs reduce large videos to more manageable sizes. This is called compression.
Without codecs, serving video on the web would be almost impossible.
Uncompressed or raw video simply requires too much data to transmit over even the fastest networks.
For example, a 5 minute mobile video without compression uses over 3 gigabytes of data.
A 5 minute HD video uses over 25 gigabytes.
Files this large would take many hours to download to your computer for playback.
On a mobile connection, they take weeks.
So how does a codec shrink all that data to something that you can play on your device in seconds?
Codecs use sophisticated algorithms to work their magic.
But you don't need to know what a discrete cosine transform or entropy encoder is to understand the basics.
The first thing to keep in mind is that digital videos are sequences of pictures called frames,
much like the frames in conventional movie film.
In most web video, there are about 30 frames per second of video.
Because there are so many pictures per second of video, the picture in each frame varies only slightly from the frames before it and those after it.
Codecs work by removing similarities in the uncompressed frames,
keeping only the differences and coding the differences as symbols.
After all the redundancies are removed, the resulting data, called the encoded bitstream,
uses far less data than the original uncompressed source.
There are two parts to a codec, an encoder and a decoder.
The encoder compresses the video stream into a binary encoded bitstream.
The decoder restores the encoded bitstream back into sequential pictures or frames or playback.
The encoding process results in some loss of the original video's quality.
One test of a codec's quality is measuring the size of that loss.
On the decoding side, simplicity and speed are perhaps the most important qualities of a codec.
After all, a decoder isn't much use if no one's computer is powerful enough to run it.
So that's a brief introduction to the world of video codecs.
Next time you watch a video on the web, you'll know something about the amazing technology that makes it possible.
Okay, so that's a quick introduction and visualizations of the video coding or compression.
Next, we're going to start off with explaining the basics of the MPEG compression now.
The approach we're going to talk about this video compression is that we'll be focusing our attention on, for example, one of the MPEG standard.
For example, MPEG 1 standard.
So we'll explain the MPEG 1 standard a bit more in detail.
And then after works, we are going to explain for the subsequent different compression standard like MPEG 2, MPEG 4, Hitch.264, and so on and so forth,
and see what is the difference between them.
Because the matter of fact is that there are many video compression standards there.
If we try to explain all the compression standard in detail, after a while,
many of you are going to lose interest because it's just like a lot of reputation and redundancy and so on.
So therefore, the approach that we are going to use when we are trying to explain this video compression is that we will start off with the early video compression standard.
We'll explain a bit more in detail.
And afterwards, for the subsequent more recent video standard, we'll try to explain for each iterations of a standard what is the improvement that was introduced.
So it will be more concise and it's also easier for you to learn rather than trying to file all the repetitions.
So that's why we'll start with the MPEG standard because when you study about video compression, this is the most common standard we start with.
So the objective of the MPEG 1 is to perform video compression.
So we try to encode or compress the video signal here.
So by now, you probably already know that for MPEG standard, it's actually set similar to the earlier general video compression standard.
It will be based on DCT coding.
So we'll be using DCT and then it will also be using the motion estimation and compensation.
So the idea that we have introduced.
So for the DCT coding, the objective is to reduce the intraference redundancy.
So earlier on, if you remember, when we given a particular video, there'll be some frame that you encode it independently without reference to any other frame.
So we encode it independently just like an IFrame or like a JPEG image.
So for those types of frames here, we'll be using the DCT coding.
And our goal is to remove the intra frame redundancy within the frame itself.
And then for some frame, you'll be comparing the similarity across two different frames.
So for those frames, the goal is to remove the interframe redundancy.
So the technique that we'll be using is the motion estimation and compensation that we have introduced.
So this is a recap.
So for MPEG, they'll also use this macro block structure, which consists of four 8x8 blocks of wide channel,
one 8x8 block of CB and one 8x8 blocks of CR.
So you can see you have one luminance component and then you have two chromium components, CB and CR, and it's using 420 chroma subsampling.
So if you recall, just now for the 420 chroma subsampling, every 2x2 wide sample, you only keep one CB and you keep one CR.
So therefore, in terms of structure, it will be like this.
Four 8x8 blocks of wide channel, one 8x8 blocks of CB and one 8x8 blocks of CR.
Using this chroma subsampling strategy.
So next, we are going to explain about this MPEG video structure a little bit more in detail now.
So first, you have a video sequence.
This video sequence can be organized into multiple GOP structures, group of picture, GOP1, GOP2 and so on and so forth.
So if you look at one GOP structure, if you zoom it in, you can see that it has an i-frame, it has p-frame and then it has b-frame in between.
Actually, there's a small error here.
For one GOP structure, you only have one i-frame.
So this line here actually should be stopping until this b here.
This line should only be stopping until this b.
So for one GOP, you would have one i-frame, which is intra-coated frame.
You encode it independently.
You have some p-frame, which is you encode with respect to the previous reference frame.
And then you have some b-frame, which is you encode with respect to the previous and the following reference frame.
So anyway, we'll talk a little bit more about this later on.
But in short, one GOP, as you know now, is that you have i-frame, you have p-frame, as well as you have b-frame.
So we'll explain each of these frame type a little bit more closely later.
So now if you look at each of these particular frames here, either ip or b-frames here, it can be further divided into different slices.
For example, this slice number one, this slice number two.
And in each slice, it can be further partitioned into numerous macro blocks and b.
And each macro block will consist of just now, we say 4A by 8, y block, 1A by 8, CB and 1A by 8, CR.
So all together it will be 6A by 8 pixel blocks.
So that's the basic organizations of the MPEG video, how it looks like.
So now we are going to zoom in to look at the GOP structures now.
GOP stands for group of pictures here.
So if you zoom in and look at one GOP structure here, so in one GOP structure, you have one i-frame.
You can have a few p-frames and then you have some b-frames in between here.
So what is i-frame here?
So i-frame stands for infra-coded frame.
That means it's a frame type that you encode independently by itself, just like JPEG standard.
So this is the i-frame here.
So the next frame type that we have is known as a p-frame.
So p-frames stands for predictive coded frame.
So for predictive coded frame, when you want to encode it, you have to compare with respect to the previous reference frame.
For example, if you want to encode this p-frame, you need to refer to the previous reference frame here.
If you want to encode this p-frame here, you need to refer to the previous reference frame or anchor frame here.
So your reference frame can either be i-frame or it can be p-frame.
So because now you are comparing this frame with respect to the previous reference frame, so it's an interframe now.
It's an interframe redundant, interframe compression.
So when you are performing the interframe compression, that means you need to perform motion, estimation and compensation.
So you can see there's a motion compensation here.
You have a motion compensation here.
So this is the p-frame.
So the third frame type that you have is a b-frame here.
So this b-frame refers to bi-directional frame here.
So bi-directional frame here means that if you want to encode this b-frame here, you need to compare with respect to the previous reference frame and the following reference frame.
In this case here, for example, if you look at this example here, the previous reference frame is the i-frame and the following reference frame is p-frame here.
So you need to compare your b-frame with respect to this previous and the following reference frame to do the compression.
So likewise for this b-frame here, if you want to encode or compare this b-frame, you need to compare respect to this i-frame and this p-frame here.
So these are the three important frame types in MPEG-1 standard here.
So because for b-frame, you are comparing with respect to the previous and the following reference frame, it's known as bi-directional motion compensation.
You compare with before and you compare with after.
Okay, so next with the figure, we have very briefly explained.
So now we can further elaborate a little bit about this GOP structure here.
You can see a video sequence is divided into numerous GOP structures.
So a video, you can partition it into numerous GOP.
So for each GOP, you may have these three video types, i-frame.
So i-frame stands for intra-coded frame, p-frame stands for predicted coded frame, and b-frame stands for bi-directional coded frame.
So i, p, and b-frame.
So next we are going to look at each of these particular frame type a bit more in detail now.
So i-frame.
So i-frame, as we mentioned, we encode it independently just like JPEG here.
So it's coded without reference to any other frame.
The wide CB and CR blocks are coded independently just like JPEG that you have studied.
Okay, so this part should be straightforward.
Next we'll look at p-frame and b-frame here.
So for p-frame and b-frame, actually because when you encode it, you compare with some other reference frame.
So because you compare with some other reference frame, it's known as inter-coded, right?
Because it's inter between two frames.
So it's inter-coded or sometimes also known as inter-plation frame here.
Okay, so p-frames are coded using motion estimation and compensation, right?
From the previous angle frame.
So the previous angle frame can be i-frame or it can be p-frame just like what we see here.
Okay, if you want to encode this p-frame, it has to compare with the previous reference or angle frame.
And this reference or angle frame can either be i-frame or p-frame.
Okay, and then b-frames are encoded using prediction from either the past, future or both angle frame.
So for b-frame, for b-frame here, for example, this b-frame, you are going to compare with the past as well as the future angle frame.
Okay, so you are going to do three comparisons.
You're going to compare with the previous reference frame, the following reference frame, and you're going to take the average of them.
So we are going to see a bit more about how do we encode each of these frames a bit more in detail later.
So you can see p-frames encoded using prediction from the past, from the future or both.
Okay, so this is the MPEG-1 display encoding order.
So suppose we have a video, right?
So in this video here, we have these particular different frames here.
So this is showing the GOP structures here.
So in terms of the display format, when you are trying to display frame by frame, right, the structure is like this.
Firstly, you have the i-frame, and then you have some p-frame, okay, and then you have some b-frame in between.
So this is when you display the video, when you play a video playback, this is how the frame will be played.
i, bb, p, bb, p, bb.
This i here is actually belonging to the next GOP structure.
Okay, yeah, so this is how if you play a video, it will be shown.
But when you are trying to perform the coding and transmission, say suppose when, you know, this video you have already compressed it,
and when you want to transmit different frame information to the receiver end.
So how we encode and how we transmit it is a little bit different from how we display it.
So what we do is that first of all, we will be transmitting this i-frame first.
And then afterwards, we will be transmitting the p-frame and afterwards, we'll be transmitting the two b-frames in between.
And then next, we will be transmitting the next p-frame, and then we will be transmitting these two b-frames in between.
And then, you know, so on and so forth.
So the question is that why do we want to do it in this way?
So when we're doing the coding and the transmission,
why is it that we transmit the iframe first,
followed by P, and then followed by the B in between?
So what's the reason?
Okay, so in order to answer the questions,
I just asked the self, right?
Okay, suppose you are at the receiver side.
Okay, once you transmit this,
but suppose if you receive this iframe, the first iframe,
do you think you can decode it?
Can you decode it?
You can, right?
Because iframe is, no, when you try to decode it
or reconstruct a frame,
it does not refer to any other frame.
That means you can reconstruct this iframe directly.
Now, say suppose, suppose for one moment, right?
If we decide, say, okay, we transmit this b-frame.
Suppose we don't follow this order.
Suppose a second frame, you try to be smart,
you say that, okay, I'm going to transmit b-frame.
Okay, after I transmit the first iframe,
suppose I transmit the b-frame.
Suppose if we transmit the b-frame,
and at the receiver side,
once you receive this b-frame,
do you think you'll be able to decode it?
Will you be able to reconstruct this b-frame?
The answer is yes or no?
No, right?
Why?
Because in order to reconstruct this b-frame,
you need both the previous reference of anchor frame i
as well as the following anchor frame p.
So therefore, even if I transmit b-frame,
there's nothing I can do.
I still have to wait for the p-frame to arrive first.
Because in order to reconstruct this b-frame,
you need to know the knowledge of iframe and p-frame.
So because of that simple logic,
that means we must transmit iframe first,
which it can decode or reconstruct independently.
And after works, you'll transmit this p-frame,
because this p-frame will depend
on the previous reference frame iframe.
So only after I've reconstructed this iframe here,
I'll be able to reconstruct the p-frame.
So therefore, we will transmit the p-frame second.
And after works, only after I get the iframe and the p-frame,
then I can transmit the two b-frame in between.
Because this two b-frame will depend
on the previous iframe and the following p-frame
before it can decode.
So that's why due to that logic,
this is the order you need to transmit your video.
Right.
So next, let's spend a bit of time
to talk about the design issues in the GOP structure.
So based on what you've studied now,
so what frame type in the GOP structure do you think
will have the largest and the smallest compression ratio
and why?
So now you have three different frame type iframe,
p-frame, and b-frame.
So out of these three frame type,
which one do you think will have the highest compression ratio?
So if you remember, the definition of compression ratio
means that it's a storage requirement.
OK, compression ratio is defined as the storage requirement
for original data or uncompressed data
over the data storage requirement for a compressed data.
That means the higher the compression ratio,
the smaller you can compress the frame
into smaller file size.
So based on that, which one do you
think will have the highest compression ratio?
OK, I hear someone say b-frame, right?
So why b-frame will have the highest compression ratio?
So generally speaking, you have iframe, p-frame, and b-frame.
So iframe actually is based on intra-frame compression.
That means it's like a JPEG-based approach.
So you have to compress all the blocks within a frame.
So this iframe is intra-frame.
And p-frame and b-frame is actually
inter-frame compression.
That means they are trying to compare the similarity across two
frames.
So generally speaking, for video, because we know that for video,
each frame must be very similar.
So therefore, when you look at different frames,
there are lots of similarity.
So when you're looking at different frames,
There's lots of redundancy across different frames.
So therefore, generally speaking,
techniques that leverage or frame type that
make use of inter-frame compression,
you'll be able to compress it into a smaller file size.
So therefore, what it means is that p-frame and b-frame
would have higher compression than iframe,
because it's based on inter-frame redundancy.
So therefore, p and b, their compression ratio
will be greater than i, because across different frames,
they are very similar.
So they will be able to compress it
into a much smaller file size.
So we know p and b compression ratio is greater than i.
But now the next question is between p and b.
Which one will have a smaller compression ratio?
So p-frame, if this is a p-frame,
it only leveraged on one previous frame
to perform the compression.
But for b-frame, suppose this is a current b-frame,
you'll compare the previous reference frame
and the following reference frame
to perform the compression.
So therefore, do you think p-frame or do you think b-frame
has a higher chance of finding a more similar matching block?
Which one will have a higher chance
of finding a more similar matching block?
It should be.
b-frame, right?
Because p-frame only rely on one frame.
But b-frame, it can look at the previous as well as the following.
So therefore, if you are looking at this particular b-frame
here, you partition it into numerous macro blocks.
So for this current macro block that you
want to compress under the b-frame,
you can refer to the previous reference frame
as well as the flowing reference frame.
So the chances of you finding a best matched block
is much higher.
If you can find a best matched block much higher,
that means subsequently due to the motion compensation,
the error between them is much smaller.
If the error is smaller, then intuitively,
you probably are likely going to compress it better.
So therefore, the compression ratio
in terms of the IP and b-frame here,
b-frame will have the highest compression ratio,
followed by p-frame, followed by i-frame.
So that's this particular question here.
So anyway, this one, I will not give you the answer
since it's a discussion.
I think you should be able to follow it.
So the next thing is how do you choose
the suitable GOP structures here?
So these GOP structures refer to, for example,
how big this particular size should be.
Actually, in this case, you refer to n is equal to 9.
So this n is equal to 9 is actually your GOP structures
here.
n is equal to 9 is a GOP structure.
You can see 1, 2, 3, 1, 2, 3, 1, 2, 3.
So this GOP structure, GOP size is n is equal to 9.
So this is actually a design parameter.
You can choose a small GOP structure, GOP size,
or you can choose a large GOP size.
But usually, there must be a trade-off.
Otherwise, people will just keep choosing a very long one
or a very short one.
So that must be a trade-off.
So what is a trade-off?
So how do we choose a suitable GOP size?
So what is the potential impact of this GOP size?
If you choose, for example, a very large GOP size,
if you choose a large GOP size, what
will be the potential advantage?
If you choose a very large GOP size,
that means the chances of you having B-frame is higher
or lower.
The percentage or the proportion of B-frame
will be higher or lower.
Higher, right?
So if the proportion of the B-frame will be higher,
so from earlier on, we know that B-frame has higher compression
ratio, right?
So if you have more B-frame, and each B-frame
has higher compression ratio, that means overall,
you will be able to make this video,
the final file size will be larger or smaller.
Smaller, right?
So therefore, if you choose a large GOP structure,
that means the number of iframes that you have
will be higher in terms of proportion.
And because we know that B-frame has higher compression
ratio, that means overall, your file size will be smaller.
So if you choose large GOP structure,
your compression ratio will be higher,
and your file size will be smaller.
But what's the price you have to pay?
I mean, surely there must be some disadvantage, right?
Otherwise, people just choose as big as possible
the GOP structure already.
There must be a price that you have to pay.
So what's the price you have to pay?
Sorry?
Ah, yeah, OK, that's exactly the point.
So if you think about this video compression techniques,
for example, for P-frame and B-frame,
it's inter-frame compression.
That means when you want to compress one frame,
you refer to the previous reference frame.
You want to compress one frame for P-frame and B-frame.
You refer to the previous reference frame.
So what it means is that in the process of encoding
or due to transmission or whatever error,
when there's an error occurring in one frame,
say, suppose an error occurring in this P-frame
due to some packet loss or due to some issue,
this particular error is going to keep propagating.
It's going to keep propagating.
So how do you stop this error from being propagated continuously?
You need to have an i-frame to stop.
So i-frame is like start afresh.
We start things afresh.
So therefore, if you choose a very large GOP structure,
you run this risk that, no, if error occur,
it's going to propagate for a long time.
So therefore, you cannot choose a GOP to be overly long.
Otherwise, when the error occur, this error propagation
is going to be very long.
So therefore, you may want to choose.
If you choose a large GOP structure,
the advantage is that your compression ratio will be high.
You'll compress into small file size.
But the price you have to pay is now the error propagation.
Potentially, it's much longer now.
So that's the shortcoming.
So that's the trade-off between these two issues.
So yeah, probably I'll just very quickly talk
about this motion, estimation and compensation.
So this motion, estimation and compensation,
I think the idea we already mentioned
is quite clear.
So we are trying to leverage on the temporal redundancy,
because we know that for consecutive frames in the videos,
they're very similar.
So if between different frames are very similar,
then we are just trying to find the best match block,
take their difference, and then encode it.
So in video, not every frame needs
to be coded independently.
Many of the frame, like P frame and B frame,
that we've studied before, we are going to code it in the frame.
So therefore, the idea is that we
are going to take the difference between our current frame
and the previous reference frame.
We take their difference, we encode their difference.
And because these two, your current block
and the previous reference blocks are very similar,
so if they are very similar, that means
that difference is very small.
And if it is very small, that means
it's very easy for you to do the compression now.
Because if between your current macro block
and your best match block, if you take their difference,
or the prediction error is very small,
when they are very small, you only need very small number
of bits represented.
So therefore, then it's very suitable for compression.
So for this type of technique, what we have probably mentioned
too many times already, is leveraging
a motion estimation and compensation.
So motion estimation means try to find the positions
of the motion factor.
Motion compensation is try to predict
the difference between your current macro block
and the best match block, the small error.
So this particular figure shows how we do that.
So when we want to perform motion estimation,
so what we do is that suppose we start off
with a particular current frame,
this is the frame that we want to compress,
we partition into numerous macro blocks.
So each of these is a macro block.
Suppose now this is a current macro block
that we want to compress.
So what we do now is that we look
at the previous reference frame.
Okay, one of the previous reference frame.
Standard at this particular positions here,
we are going to define a search window here.
Okay, we are going to define this search window.
So this search window has a size of two P plus one
by two P plus one.
So we are going to check each of this particular position
in this particular search window.
So we are going to look at all the positions
to find the positions of the best match block
or most similar block.
Okay, so the process of trying to find out
within this particular search window here,
which position has the most similar block is known as,
this process is known as motion.
The position, the process of trying to find out
the best match block in the previous reference frame
is known as motion.
Estimation, right?
Okay, it's known as motion estimation.
So suppose you go through this search window,
you find that this is the positions
of the best match block.
Okay, then afterwards the offset between this position
to the position of the best match block,
this is known as the motion factor.
Okay, so it's the relative offset.
So this is known as the motion factor here.
So once you found this motion,
okay, you found the best match block,
you take your current macro block
that you want to compress,
minus your best match block.
So this best match block sometimes is also known
as a predicted block.
Okay, so you take the difference,
then you have this prediction error.
So this prediction error is in the form of a matrix,
and usually their values should be very small.
Okay, right?
So you take the difference between your current block
you want to compress and your best match block,
the process of taking the difference is known
as motion compensation.
Okay, so motion vector, motion vector search
is limited to the immediate neighborhood.
So for example, this search window here.
So both horizontal and vertical displacement
in the range of minus P to P,
if you are talking about from this position minus P
and minus from minus P to P,
both vertically and horizontally,
then you'll give rise to a search window
of two P plus one times two P plus one.
Okay, so quite easy to understand.
Right, okay, so these equations actually just shows
how do we calculate the more exact calculations
of trying to perform the motion estimation.
So the idea is actually quite simple.
In order to perform this motion estimation,
we need to calculate the difference
between two macro block, all right?
So pretty much what it means is that,
okay, so we have this current macro block
that we want to compress, all right?
This current macro block.
And afterwards, we are going,
and then, okay, so this current frame,
we partitioned into numerous macro block.
Suppose this is a current macro block we want to compress.
So, okay, we refer to the previous reference frame.
Okay, standard at this position,
we define a search window, right?
So in afterwards, we just try to, you know,
move this particular macro block
because behind there's a reference image.
So you try to move this particular reference block,
and at each position, you try to find the difference.
But how do we define the difference?
The difference is defined as this
mean absolute difference, MAD here, okay?
So this mean absolute difference, okay?
At this particular position,
I and J is defined as the offset, all right?
And you try to find which position is it, okay?
So I and J is offset here.
So you can see this particular term here is actually,
no, the pixels in your current macro block
that you want to compress.
So this is the current macro block
that you want to compress,
which is defined as this macro block, okay?
And this term here is actually the positions,
the pixels in the macro block of the reference frame.
That means, no, at each of center,
at each of these positions here.
So at each of this particular position,
for example, you have a macro block, okay?
So you have the current macro block
that you want to compress,
and at different position, the corresponding macro block.
Okay, so you take their difference, okay?
Absolute value, right?
So these two summation is to check,
no, all the particular macro block size,
all the macro block size.
So the macro block size,
suppose we assume it to be n in this case.
So you check all the pixel values in the macro block size,
okay?
You take their absolute difference,
you sum up over all the pixels in the macro block size,
and then you divide by n squared to take the mean, okay?
Take the mean.
So therefore, then by calculating this,
you will be able to find the MAED at different position.
So this MAED is a way to measure
which position give you the smallest error.
Okay, and then afterwards, right by now,
you have at this different I and J position,
each of them will give you one MAED.
So therefore, the best match block will be the one
that give you the smallest error.
So therefore, the motion factor, which is defined as UV,
is trying to find which of this MAED has the smallest value.
Okay, so therefore, the motion factor
is among these different sets of I and J,
the one that give you the smallest error, okay?
Within this particular search window.
So that is pretty much the meaning of motion estimation.
So this video here just show you simple visualizations
of, you know, right?
You can see if you define each of this
particular macro block here,
you have some small arrow here.
So this small arrow just, you know,
kind of indicate, right?
Okay, where is the relative motion factor, right?
And also the length of it will indicate, you know,
how much is the relative offset that you have, okay?
All right, okay, so, okay, we'll probably,
just stop here today,
but I'll just play you a very short video
before you go just one or two minutes,
so it should be fast.
Okay, I know that there are many of you
who are traveling from China,
so I'll just play a very short song,
just about one, two minutes.
Let's go.
I'm not sure what's the point of this
I don't know what's the point of this