Okay, so we'll come back to the lecture.
So before we start, just a quick reminder.
So for next Thursday, it's actually a public holiday in Singapore.
It's a depart valley.
So there's actually no lecture on next Thursday.
So we'll arrange a make-up instead.
So the make-up will be on November 9, 9am to 12 noon, right, using the provided Zoom
link.
Okay, so just to recap, next Thursday there's no lecture because of public holiday.
So we'll do the make-up on 9th of November, 9am to 12 noon.
So that's the first announcement.
And then the second thing is all of you are aware that today we're going to have the quiz.
So for the quiz, I just want to highlight one thing, which is the sitting arrangement.
Because this class is actually very big.
There's 517 students.
So in order to later on facilitate our checking collections of the answer scripts and also
to check the attendance, we have divided this LT into the following sector.
So for students with serial number 1 to 100, I believe you should know what is your serial
number.
So the serial number is the one that's reflected in this class list.
So just check your serial number.
For those students seated from 1 to 100, please try to sit in these sections here, which is
those three sections, 1, 2, 3.
And then the student 101 to 200 is the central 3 section, 1, 2, 3.
Okay, 201 to 300 is this 3 section, 1, 2, 3.
Okay, 301 to 410 is this central, this 2 sector.
And then 411 to 517 is sitting here.
So later on, please try to sit according to this that will make our later on the attendance
taking as well as the collection of the script much more efficient.
Okay, because at the end, no, we have to collect out a script, make sure the number is agreed
before I can let you go.
So later on, please make sure that you sit according to this arrangement.
So for today, we are going to have about one hour of lecture from 630 to around 730.
And afterwards, I'll give you a break and then you can come back at around 750 to get
seated and then we'll start to distribute the question paper and so on.
And we'll start the CREZ 8 o'clock show.
Right, okay, so that's the arrangement for today.
So next, let's continue on with the lecture.
So today we are going to start with a part five, which is on video analysis and understanding.
So given here are some of the references.
There are actually many references here are just some of the listed one, right?
If you want to learn more about it, you're welcome to read these references.
Okay, so for part five, pretty much these are the topics we are going to cover.
So the main focus is on video analysis and understanding.
So we want to understand what's happening in the video.
So we have a few selected tasks.
Video understanding is very broad.
There's many, many things.
So we are going to look at a few selected representative use case and application.
So the first one is object detection tracking.
So we want to detect the object and then we want to track the movement.
Second one is the pose estimation.
So you want to be able to detect the key points or the skeletons of a human.
Okay, and afterwards, the third task that we'll be looking at is a video or human action
recognition.
So we want to understand the actions of the person.
Right, so first, let's look at the first use case, which is on the object detection.
Right, so under the object detection, we'll be looking at the following topics.
So first of all, we'll give a quick introduction of what is the object detection.
And afterwards, we'll look at some of the broad categories of object detection techniques,
which include two stage detectors, one stage detector, lightweight detectors, as well as
some new and emerging methods.
Right, okay, so what is the objective of the object detection?
From the name itself, you already know.
Pretty much, is that suppose you're given a particular image and video, you want to
detect various, you know, object of interest.
So right, you want to detect, for example, in this image here, you want to detect all
the vagus, for example, the cars, the persons and so on.
So therefore, you need to actually find a bounding box.
You want, you need to find the bounding box for each of these objects.
And afterwards, you need to provide the label.
That means you need to perform classification.
What is this bounding box corresponding to?
What category is this?
Right, so therefore, the objective of object detection is you need to predict the object
classes in the image and video.
And then you need to localize them using some bounding boxes as being seen here.
Right, so you need to detect as many as know they are in the image and video.
So it's both a regression and classification task.
Regression is because you need to find the location of the bounding box.
So you need to regress a bounding box to find where this particular object of interest is.
And then classification is that once you found a bounding box, you need to tell what category
it belongs to.
So therefore, it's also a classification task.
Right, so what are, why is this object detection important?
It's because it's a very important early kind of task for some downstream application.
It's a very important upstream task to support downstream application.
So for example, object tracking, if you want to track the object movement, you need to
be able to detect the object first.
Right, post estimation, for example, there are many persons in this particular video,
you want to be able to detect the post for individual person, then you need to be able
to detect all the persons first.
Okay, action recognition, right?
If you want to understand the actions of a person, you need to identify or detect where
the person is.
So these are some selected application that you can see is some closely coupled downstream
application for object detection.
Right, so object detection has many, many real world applications.
Right, so early on we have since, for example, autonomous driving, you need to be able to
detect all the vehicles, the track sign, the pedestrian and so on and so forth.
Right, okay, another important one is the videos of lens and monitoring.
You want to, for example, monitor in an airport whether someone is doing something suspicious.
Right, so these are just some sample applications.
Right, okay, so as indicated earlier, so autonomous driving is one kind of a very popular object
detection application, where you need to be able to detect all the vehicles as well as
traffic sign, traffic lights and so on.
Okay, so let's have a quick look at the brief history and milestones of object detection.
So in early years, right, you can see the turning point is this AlexNet.
So when we study about CNN, if you remember, AlexNet appeared in 2012.
So this is one of the networks that actually demonstrate that this deep neural network
can actually outperform human handcrafted approach.
So this is actually a turning point, AlexNet.
Prior to this AlexNet, most of the methods is actually handcrafted methods.
So in early years, for example, there's some very well-known object detection methods such
as VLLJONS, which is trying to detect the face, deformable part models, okay, histogram
of gradient.
So these are all well-known handcrafted techniques to detect objects.
But after AlexNet, right, then the emergence of deep learning methods appear.
So but broadly speaking, it can be divided into two broad categories.
The first one is two-stage detectors.
Namely when you want to perform object detection, you divide into two steps or two stages.
First you try to detect some possible kind of a region proposal.
What is the likely region you have the object?
And afterwards they perform the classification.
So if you do that, that is known as two-stage detectors.
So some of the well-known two-stage detectors include, for example, RCNN, FASLA RCNN, MAS
RCNN.
So these are some well-known two-stage detectors.
As opposed to two-stage detector, you have one-stage detector.
So one-stage detector means that you try to perform the regression and classification
in one go.
You do not need to propose what are the likely regions that the object may exist.
So that's why it's known as one-stage detectors.
So these are some of the well-known one-stage detectors, including, for example, YOLO SSD,
single-shot detectors, RetinaNet, and so on.
So today we're going to very briefly introduce some of these object detectors.
So what are some of the challenges in object detection?
So if you are new to this topic, you're taught that object detection should be relatively
straightforward.
But it turned out that object detection people still continue to perform research on it because
there are some challenges.
So some of the key challenges in object detection include different imaging conditions.
So for example, the object that you have can be from different viewpoint.
Same object, if you look at it from different viewpoint, you still need to detect it's the
same object.
Scale, whether it's small or big, lighting, whether it's bright or dark, whether there
are some background clutter, whether part of the object is occluded.
So these are all challenges in object detection algorithm.
So another important consideration is computational efficiency.
You want to be able to compute very efficiently with least amount of computation.
So this is particularly important in some application, whereas they are energy constrained
or memory constrained or power constrained.
So therefore there's another challenge.
The other popular topic is the close world versus open world problem.
So close world problem is that if you have already predefined a certain categories of
objects that you need to detect, then it's a close world problem.
For example, in autonomous driving, you may probably have already predefined.
You need to detect different types of vehicles, persons, traffic lights, traffic signs, and so on.
So as opposed to that open world means that we know that in real life it's not possible
for you to predefine all the possible objects.
So therefore in real life there will be some objects that you do not know in advance.
So how do we handle those problems?
So those are known as open world problems object detection.
Right?
So in order to study this object detection, we need to leverage on some data set.
As in any deep learning algorithm, you need the data set, you need the method.
So therefore we need some data set to support object detection.
So these are some common object data sets.
So the first one is the MSCoco, it's stand for Microsoft Common Objects in Context.
So this is the popular data set to support object detection.
Next one is ImageNet, and afterwards a Google Open Images.
So these are some popular data set that is used to train object detector as well as evaluate
its performance.
So this table here give a quick summary.
So you have different types of object detector.
The number of classes that it has in the data set range from 80 to 600.
So the data is partitioned into training, validation, and testing data set here.
So for the training data set you can see the partition.
For different data set, you have a different number of images, total number of objects,
and per image what is the average number of objects inside.
So this table just give you a quick overview of this important data set.
So if we go just slightly a bit more info on this MSCoco data set.
So earlier we already mentioned it's an important benchmark data set for training and evaluation
of object detection.
So it has 80 categories and more than 200 cases of training images.
So one thing that you notice is that if you try to plot the number of images versus the
number of the classes that you have, you can see you have this particular well-known long
tail problem.
That means there are some categories you have lots of training data, but there are lots
of categories you have very few training data.
So this is a data imbalance problem or long tail problems here.
So long tail problem is a practical problem that we need to solve when we want to perform
object detection.
Otherwise, our developed algorithm will tends to detect categories that are more commonly
seen.
So this is for example an illustration of the challenge that we need to address in object
detection.
Another one, ImageNet.
So ImageNet we have looked at it before.
It consists of 1000 image categories.
But out of that 200 category is used for object detection with more than 500 cases of images.
So this is the ImageNet.
So next one is the Google Open Image.
It has 1.9 million images, 16 million bounding blocks, and it consists of 600 categories.
So again, all these are just some basic information to let you have a certain feeling.
So the next thing is that before we go in and look at different types of object detection
algorithm, we need to understand what are some common performance matrix.
How do we measure whether an object detection is performing well or not?
So one of the most common performance matrix is known as the mean average precision or
MAP here.
So MAP sometimes is also loosely called AP, average precision.
So more accurately it should be called mean average precision.
But sometimes some paper or some books, they just loosely called AP.
But actually they are referring to the same thing.
So this MAP is a matrix to evaluate the performance, the accuracy of your object detection algorithm.
So in order to measure this particular performance, you need to define a particular parameter
known as intersection over unit or IOU.
So what is the meaning of this IOU?
You can see from this particular figure, this is the meaning of the IOU.
Suppose when you want to evaluate the performance of object detection algorithm, so you have
some ground truth object.
For example, I have a monitor in front.
So the ground truth is this particular monitor.
So we have the ground truth.
And then if you run our object detection algorithm, then you will come out with a bounding box,
detected bounding box.
So now we have a ground truth.
We have the ground truth, bounding box, and then we have a detected bounding box or predicted
bounding box based on our algorithm.
So obviously the closer they overlap, that means the better your detection algorithm is.
But how do we measure it?
So one way is using this IOU.
So IOU is actually intersection over unit.
So the name itself already tells you that.
For example, you have this is the ground truth object.
This is your detected or predicted bounding box here.
So intersection means that the intersection of this area, union means that the union of
this area.
So the ratios of this area, intersection area over this union area is defined as the IOU.
So this IOU, obviously the larger the IOU, that means the closer it would have to be
together.
So therefore typically when we want to decide whether a prediction is correct or not, our
prediction is considered as true positive if the IOU is greater than a threshold.
So true positive means that, for example, there's a ground truth here.
There's a ground truth object.
And then you predicted this bounding box.
Actually the IOU between your ground truth and predicted bounding box, if it's greater
than a chosen IOU, then we say that actually it's a true positive.
That means because there's an object and we actually detect it.
So it's a true positive.
So we interpret a particular detection to be true positive if the IOU is greater than
a chosen threshold.
And then it's forced that negative if our IOU is less than a threshold.
For example, if this is the bounding box, this is a ground truth.
In our detected bounding box is very far away.
That means our intersection over union is very small.
So in those cases, when our IOU is less than a certain predefined threshold, then we say
it's a false positive.
Because even though we thought there's an object there, but it's too far away from the
ground truth.
It's a false positive.
We think it's a positive, but it's actually false.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now these particular issues of IOU, this threshold here is actually very tricky.
So how exactly do you choose?
What is the most representative IOU?
Because you can choose many different values.
So it turns out that there's some common choices of this threshold.
So one of them is called AP50 or AP.5.
So AP.5 means now we choose our threshold to be equal to 0.5.
But if you just choose a single value of 0.5, it's still a little bit arbitrary.
So therefore there are some people who argue that instead of using one single threshold
value, why not we have a sequence of threshold values?
So it'll be more meaningful.
So that's why we have this particular MAP that's defined by a cocoa.
So MAP cocoa here.
So MAP cocoa is also defined as AP starting from 0.5 to 0.95 with a step size of 0.05
here.
So what it means is that you calculate the MAP at 0.5, at 0.55 and all the way to 0.95
and then you take the average over these 10 terms here.
So the advantage of using these kinds of the performance matrix is that it's less sensitive
to the threshold value you choose.
It's more representative.
So therefore this is a common performance matrix.
So next we are going to spend a little bit of time to explain how do we calculate the
MAP here.
So mean average position, how do we calculate?
So MAP is calculated by finding the AP for each category and then take average over
different classes.
So suppose in this particular image you have a few different categories.
You have person, you have cars and so on.
So we try to find the average position for each different category.
For example for person category, for car category and so on.
And afterwards we take the average over this different category.
So that's why we find the AP for each classes or each category and then we take the average
over this different category here.
So early on as I mentioned, some people actually loosely call this MAP as AP but more precisely
it should be MAP.
But some people actually just use it loosely.
So the assume that from the discussion is clear because you are taking average over different
category of objects.
So therefore it should be MAP.
So how do we calculate this MAP here?
So in order to calculate the MAP, for example now you have an object detection algorithm.
You want to find the MAP for your algorithm.
So how do you do it?
So first of all, you run your algorithm and then you try to predict or generate all these
object bounding boxes.
So suppose you have a particular image.
You want to detect all the objects in this particular image.
Suppose you have different cars, vans and vehicles or so on.
So what you do is you run your algorithm and then you try to obtain all these bounding
boxes for different categories here.
So you predict the bounding boxes as well as the label, whether it's a car, whether
it's a van, whether it's a person using a model here.
And afterwards you need to calculate some of the matrix of values in what's known as
the confusion matrix here.
So in this confusion matrix, three of the popular matrix is a true positive, four positive
and four negative.
So what's the meaning of this true positive here?
So true positive means that if your ground truth is there's an object and your algorithm
managed to detect this object, such that its IOU is greater than the threshold, then we
say that we managed to detect it.
So we call it true positive.
We do a positive prediction and it's correct.
It's true.
So it's true positive.
Force negative is, for example, if you have this particular object here and your prediction
is very far away, it's very far away.
Either the overlapping is very little or it's very far away.
So what it means is that you do a prediction here.
You do a prediction here.
But this prediction is actually not accurate because it's too far from the ground truth.
So this is known as the force positive.
So you can see we think it's positive.
We think we detect by force.
So force positive.
The next one is the force negative.
So force negative means that negative means that you do not think there's an object there,
but actually there's an object there.
So suppose if you have your ground truth, there's an object there, but you do not think
there's an object.
You do not do a prediction on this.
Then it's called force negative.
You think it's negative.
You think there's no object there, but it's incorrect.
So force negative here.
So based on these three parameters, then we can calculate the precision versus the precision
and recall matrix here.
So what is precision and recall?
So the precision, let's look at precision here.
So the precision is defined as the number of true positive over the total number of
prediction.
So if you, for example, in this image, you make 10 prediction.
Okay.
Out of these 10 prediction, how many of them is true positive?
Suppose there is six, then it's six over 10.
Then your precision is six over 10.
Okay.
On the other hand, recall is defined as true positive over ground truth.
So suppose in this particular image, again, there are 10, say suppose there are 20 objects.
But for out of these 20 objects, you only manage to say, get six correct true positive.
Then your recall is out.
20 ground truth, you only manage to retrieve or recall six.
So therefore, this is the definitions of the recall.
So true positive divided by ground truth.
Ground truth is the true positive plus false negative, and prediction is true positive
plus false positive.
So this is the equation for you to calculate the recall and the precision.
So therefore, you can calculate the recall and precision.
And then finally, if you want to find the average precision for the current category,
it's actually the area under the curve.
So usually you'll be able to plot this graph, precision versus recall.
So by changing this different threshold value, you'll be able to obtain this precision versus
recall graph here.
So the AP average precision is defined as area under the graph.
So for a threshold of 0.5, this is how the graph would look like, 0.7 and 0.9.
You can see, right, if you increase the threshold from 0.5 to 0.7, so 0.5 means that it can
be a bit loose.
Even though it's not exactly very close match, you still consider it to be correct.
But if IOU is 0.9, or threshold chosen is 0.9, then it's very tight.
Your prediction and the ground truth need to be almost the same before you can consider
it to be correct.
So that's why you can see that this graph will look something like this.
The area under the graph is much smaller.
So therefore, average precision AP is defined as the area under the graph for one category.
So now for each category, you can repeat the exercise.
Afterwards, then MAP is defined as the average precision over all the classes.
So once you have, for example, this formula here, once you have found the AP for one category,
you sum up over all the categories divided by the total number category, then this is
your mean average precision MAP.
So apart from MAP, another important performance matrix is a floating point operation.
After your fully trained algorithm, if you give a sample, for example, an image, how
much of the floating point operation you need to perform before you can arrive at your detection
of prediction.
So this floating point, the number of aromatic operation like summation, multiplication is
known as the floating point operations here.
So floating point operation is a matrix to evaluate the computational complexity.
Obviously, you want it to be as, for good algorithm, you want it to be as small as possible.
So it's how many operations is required to run a single instance for a model.
So imagine the total number of floating point operation, which includes, for example, addition,
subtraction, multiplication, division, and so on for a single forward pass.
So this will reflect the detection time for different model.
Obviously, the less flocks that you have, the faster you'll be able to do your inference.
That means your model will be able to run much faster and ideally, we want it to be
real time or close to real time.
Okay, so next we are going to look at some object detector category.
So the main object detector category can be divided into a few, one stage detector and
two stage detector and the lightweight detector.
So what's the idea of this one stage versus a two stage detector?
So for example, if you look at this image here, so a two stage detector traditionally
actually is started from this two stage detector.
So the two stage detector means that you have this particular image.
You let it go through, for example, a CNN network to extract the feature.
So at this point here now, you will have some feature.
Afterward, you let it go through a region proposal network or a proposal generator here.
So the goal of this proposal generator is to try to predict some bounding boxes that likely
the object may be inside.
So you'll try to, from this particular feature here, you'll try to predict some likely boxes
that contain the object and also what is the likelihood.
So objectness classification, what's the likelihood that there's an object there.
And afterwards, this information will be reflected here.
You'll indicate, for example, this dotted line here, this is the likely region that some object exists.
So afterwards, you crop up the corresponding region, you extract the feature, you let it
go through a smaller network such as a CNN and then you try to classify which category
it belongs to.
And then you further refine the bounding box because your initial bounding box may not
be so accurate, so you can further do some fine adjustment.
So this is the idea of two-stage detector.
Your stage one is to have a region proposal network to come out with the proposed region.
And then your second stage is then to perform classification.
So this is known as a two-stage detector.
As opposed to that, for one-stage detector, it's quite straightforward.
So you have a network, you have an image, go through a network.
And afterwards, you'll go through two different head network here.
One is to perform regression to find the region and then the second is to find out what category
it belongs to for this region.
So there's no need for you to introduce this proposed region.
So that's why it's known as the one-stage detector.
So we are going to look at, first of all, two-stage detectors.
So as explained early on, for two-stage detector, we use techniques such as a region proposal
network to propose possible object region.
So we try to go through a network to detect some possible object regions here.
So some of the popular methods include, for example, faster RCNN or mass RCNN.
So until five, 10 years ago, these are relatively popular methods.
Others you have this special spatial pyramid networks or feature pyramid.
So all these fall under two-stage detector methods here.
So compared to one-stage method, two-stage method in the past or older methods tends
to be more accurate.
But the shortcoming is that they tend to be slower.
So traditionally, for two-stage method, it's more accurate, but it also requires more time
and computation.
So among the two-stage detector, region-based convolutional neural network or RCNN series
of detector was quite well known in the early stage of object detection.
So this series of object detector known as the RCNN, we have the RCNN, faster RCNN,
and mass RCNN.
So these are all closely related.
And it was the earlier very representative two-stage object detection methods.
So we are going to first of all look at the original region-based RCNN methods here.
So this is the basic ideas of RCNN.
So first you have an input image.
So if you remember, for these types of methods, since it's a two-stage method, so you need
to propose some region proposal.
So you'll use some technique to propose different possible regions.
So for this RCNN, they try to propose close to 2,000 region proposed region.
So that's why you can see it's actually going to be very slow because you need to propose
up to 2,000 possible candidates.
So this obviously is very slow.
But anyway, suppose you take one of these proposed regions, you warp it, you do a reshipping
of this particular region, and afterwards you let it go through a RCNN network to extract
some feature.
So to extract some feature that is representative of this region.
And then afterwards, during the earlier time, they used a support pattern machine to perform
the classification.
So that was an earlier method.
So anyway, summary of this method is it generates a large number of regions, 2,000, around 2,000,
and then extract feature from each region.
So you can see for each region, we extract some feature using CNN.
And then afterwards, with each region, it will classify using support factor machine,
SPM, which was the older classifier method before deep learning become more popular.
And then afterwards, it goes through a few different iterations, and then we have a more
popular one, which is known as the faster RCNN.
So the idea of faster RCNN actually is very similar to the original RCNN, but it just
makes some improvement.
So the basic principle is still the same.
Given an image, you let it go through some convolutional layer to extract some feature.
So from this feature map here, based on this feature map here, you'll come out with some
using a region proposal network to propose some possible region, whereas the object map
here.
And then afterwards, you use the ROI pooling.
That means you only pull out this region that correspond to the region of interest.
And then for each of these regions of interest, you try to perform classification and regression
to find out what the object is.
So you just use a more efficient way of performing this region proposal.
So this idea introduced a region proposal network known as the RPN.
So this RPN makes use of the same features as compared to the detection branch.
So you can see this is the initial network.
You extract some feature.
So your region proposal network is leveraging on these features here, which is used for
the detection.
So therefore, you do not need additional computation.
You do not need a lot of additional computation.
So it's shared the convolutional feature from the detection branch.
It shares these common features here.
So therefore, it would reduce the number of cores.
So this RPN will predict the boundary, the bounding box, as well as no objectness score.
That means how likely there's an object inside this proposed region.
So this particular slide shows the performance of using a faster RCNM.
So this is an earlier method, but it's actually still performing quite well for this faster RCNM.
So if you do a quick comparison of different types of methods here, you can see your original
RCNM is much slower because they need to detect up to 2,000 proposed regions.
As compared to after a few iterations, the faster RCNM is already a lot more efficient
and faster than the original RCNM.
So we can see therefore, is there's a continuous improvement.
So now we actually very clearly explained about the key principles of a two-stage detector.
And also we go through some of the most representative two-stage detector, which is RCNM.
Next, we are going to move on to the one-stage detectors.
So one-stage detector, as I mentioned to you earlier, that means you try to predict
the bounding box and the category directly.
So one-stage detector try to regress, that means find the bounding box and then classify
which category from the feature map directly.
So among them, some of the most representative methods is YOLO, SSD, Centenet, Ephesian deck
and so on and so forth.
So compared to the two-stage detector, one-stage detector, it tends to be faster.
And for older methods, actually the one-stage detector, the performance is not as good as
two-stage, but in recent years, actually this one-stage detector, especially YOLO,
is becoming more and more popular.
So nowadays when people use this object detector, almost YOLO is their first choice, because
it's fast and it's performing better and better now.
So there was a trend that this one-stage detector, object detector is kind of dominated
by this YOLO detector in recent years.
So that's why we are going to spend a bit of time to look at this YOLO detector.
So YOLO stands for You Only Look Once Detectors.
So there's many iterations ready starting from YOLO V1, V2, V3 and so on and so forth.
And this year, actually YOLO V10 came out already.
So there's already 10 iterations of this YOLO.
So each of these particular iterations of YOLO suggests some improvement.
So that's why we are not going to go into the detail of each iteration, but rather look
at some high-level features of the general architectures of YOLO.
So the YOLO architecture, generally speaking, can be described by this.
So first, if an input image, it will go through the backbone network to extract some features.
So this can be, for example, your CNN network to extract different features.
You can also see that, visualize that this particular feature actually is extracting
kind of features in different scale, from bigger to smaller.
So it's some convolutional network, for example, to extract features of different scale.
So this is known as the backbone network is to perform the feature extractions for different
scale because when you want to do object detection, sometimes the object is small, sometimes
the object is big, so you need to be able to handle objects with different scale.
And then afterwards, we have this head network here.
So this head network now will perform the upscaling.
So we'll make it bigger.
So it's a little bit like a unit structure here.
So initially, we extract features and become smaller and smaller scale.
And afterwards, we up-sample it, taking some feature laterally to extract better and better
features at different scale.
And afterwards, this feature at different scale is put into a head network to perform
the regression and classification, to predict these objects of potentially different scale,
so that the head network is used to predict the classes as well as the bounding boxes.
So this is a very crude high-level overview of YOLO series detectors.
Right.
OK, so YOLO detector currently is the state of the object detector, one of the best.
OK, so in recent year, you can see, for example, YOLO 7 is in 2022, YOLO 8 is 23, and this
year alone, we have YOLO 9 and YOLO 10.
Right.
So it's progressing very quickly.
So if you look at the performance matrix here, so we have already studied about this
Cocoa AP.
Right.
So just now we mentioned about this Cocoa AP.
So obviously, the larger the value is, the better your detection algorithm is.
So therefore, for a good algorithm, you want the AP to be high, and we want the latency,
right, the time for you to generate the result to be short.
So therefore, a graph in this region will be good.
So you can see this is YOLO V10 as compared to the earlier iterations of the YOLO.
OK.
So this graph is, progressively, is becoming better and better.
So next, this graph shows the performance of the, again, AP, Cocoa AP versus the number
of parameters, your network parameter.
Obviously we want a smaller parameter is better.
So therefore, right, you want it to be in this region again.
Again, you can see YOLO V10 is getting better.
Right.
So this slide here shows comparison.
Actually, frankly speaking, when I look at it, I can hardly tell any difference because
all trees are performing quite well now.
But anyway, just to give you a few.
Yeah.
So these are the three YOLO recent YOLO factors of the AP.
OK.
So the next types of detector we want to look at is a lightweight detector.
So what is a lightweight detector?
So lightweight detector is used for resource-limited devices.
For example, you may want to have some camera that is powered by a battery and sitting at
some remote corner.
Right.
OK.
So therefore, for those kind of devices, you want it to be lightweight, you want it
to be efficient.
Right.
OK.
So lightweight detectors, generally speaking, is small, is fast, and is efficient.
So some of the representative methods, for example, include MobileNet V2-based SSD.
Right.
So MobileNet V2, and when we study CNN before, we know that actually it's one of those very
compact networks.
OK.
And if you combine with this SSD single-shot detector, then it actually has a name called
MediaPart.
Right.
OK.
So this is the representative methods of a lightweight detector.
Other methods include, for example, ShafferNet, SqueezeNet, and so on.
So the advantage of this is they are very fast, they are very efficient, but the disadvantage
is, as you can think, as you can see, it cannot be good all the time.
So the disadvantage is it's not as accurate.
Right.
OK.
So let's look at, take one of the examples, for example, MobileNet, to see how does it
make it more efficient and lightweight.
So MobileNet is a very representative method, right, that, you know, leverage on some, exploit
some properties to perform convolution, to make it more efficient.
So it makes use of a technique known as a depth-wise separable convolution, to reduce
the computation.
So what is a depth-wise separable convolution?
So if you look at, for example, this particular case here, so typically in normal convolution,
right, when you want to perform a convolution, so you will need a filter or kernel of dk
by dk, for example, 3 by 3, yeah, 3 by 3 here.
And then this m here is a number of the channel.
So if you want to perform a convolution to generate one output channel, you need dk by
dk, right, OK, for example, 3 by 3, and then you need to have this m, which is the depth
of your input channel.
So in order to generate one output channel, you need one of this filter, right, to apply
across the whole, you know, image domain.
So therefore, if you want to generate an output filter, then you need n of these numbers of
filters here.
So you can see these are the number of parameters as well as the corresponding computation that
you need to perform, yeah, if you are using traditional CNN network.
So as opposed to that, actually, right, for mobile net, it break it into two parts here.
One is that depth-wise convolution filter, right, so this filter here actually corresponds
to, you know, each of the small filter, each depth or each slices, OK, so this 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, actually you can kind of think about this one slices at each of these parts here,
OK, and then afterwards you have a point-wise convolution.
So you will then convolve it at each, you know, point, OK, so therefore, for mobile
net, actually, it performed this depth-wise separable convolution, which is divided into
depth-wise convolution and a point-wise convolution.
So depth-wise convolution is to apply a single filter to each input channel, and point-wise
convolution is then applied one by one convolution.
So the easiest way to understand this is by looking at this particular diagram here.
So suppose you have a particular input volume here, so this different color refers to different
channel, right, so, right, if you want to perform this depth-wise separable convolution,
first of all is we perform depth-wise convolution.
So depth-wise convolution means that, for example, you take the first filter, right,
this small filter here, right, you only, you apply this convolution only to this one channel,
OK, you apply the convolution to one channel, and you generate the output.
And afterwards you take the second filter, one slice of the, you know, this filter, and
then you perform convolution, depth-wise convolution, on the second channel to generate the output.
So you use all these different depth-wise filters, you perform convolution on each channel,
right, then you generate the output here.
So this output you arranged it as before, and then now at each position here you perform
one by one convolution.
So one by one means that actually it's just one value, thick, OK, one value, but don't
forget there's actually a depth dimension, right, so therefore you just put this particular
one by one at each position, you perform the convolution, then you generate one value here.
So if you take this, you move it across the whole volume, then you are going to generate
one channel, so this corresponds to one filter.
So next, if you make use of the next point-wise filter, you repeat the same operation, then
you generate the next channel.
So you can see by doing that, by performing this depth-wise separable convolution, right,
the number of parameters you can visualize quite easily, right, so this is original CNN,
the number of parameters, and they are corresponding computation versus this depth-wise separable,
right, so this is only one by one, OK, and this is only one slide.
So the number of parameters that's required and computation that's required has been reduced
significantly.
OK, so that's one of the representative methods.
So the next thing we are going to look at is some new and emerging techniques.
So the new emerging techniques that we are going to look at is this Srin transformer
here.
So some of you have probably heard about this Srin transformer.
So what is this Srin transformer?
So Srin transformer is a popular recent image classification and object detection method,
so it can be used to perform image classification or object detection or segmentation here.
So it's served as a general purpose backbone for computer vision, so, right, just like
the VIT that we have studied in the previous lecture, given the image, you partition it
into different patches, and for each of the patches, by going through the transformer
encoder,
you can progressively extract better and better feature for each of the patches, right, by
using the self-attention.
You try to find, OK, for this kind of patch, what is the contributions of other patches
to work sit so that you can get better and better context factor representation for the
particular image patch?
Those are VIT.
So for Srin transformer is performing similar growth as well.
It can serve as a general purpose backbone for computer vision, right, and it can also
achieve this hierarchical feature map that we'll see later, right.
So let's look at, first of all, what's the basic principles of this Srin transformer
here?
So the basic principles of Srin transformer is, right, in order to understand, first of
all, let's look at this VIT, right.
So VIT, if you remember, what we have is that even a particular image, we partition it
into numerous, OK, image patches.
So each of the image patches is 16 by 60, yeah, and afterwards, right, we convert each
of these patches into a vector, and then afterwards we perform, we let go through a transformer
encoder, right.
So for each of these particular token or vector embeddings here, we try to look at the contributions
of all the other patches to work so that you can generate better feature representation
at the next encoder layer, OK.
So you repeat this numerous time, right, such that after each of the encoder layer, your
feature representation at each of the patches becoming better and better, become more and
more representative because you are extracting information from the neighboring patches.
So this is the key ideas of the VIT.
But what is the price you have to pay?
What is one of the key drawbacks of this VIT?
What is the key drawbacks of VIT?
So the key shortcomings of VIT is actually there are two.
Number one is that when you are trying to, for example, find these particular feature
vectors here through the self-attention, you need to find the relationship of all the patches,
the contributions of all the patches, respect to this current patch here.
So that means you need to look at the relationship between this, but the attention of all the
patches with respect to this current patch, right.
OK, and you can think about it, this is very time consuming.
So therefore, number one is that if you use VIT, it's very time consuming.
That's number one.
Number two is that for VIT, they use the patch size of 16 by 16.
And this 16 by 16 is a bit too big.
The resolution is too low.
So therefore, it may not be able to support some applications such as, for example, if
you need to perform some dense task such as segmentation, it may not be able to do it
up because it's too big.
Each of the blocks is too big.
Right, so to address that, people propose this string transformer here.
So this string transformer here, what they do is that first of all, for each of these
particular small regions of patches, it's actually 4 by 4.
So they partition this particular patch of region into 4 by 4.
So you have this 4 by 4 here.
So afterwards, at the initial level, when you want to calculate the cell attention,
you only calculate the cell attention between this window, this red region here, this is
the window.
Let me see, if we want to find the features for this particular current patch, you only
find its self attention respect to this particular window here.
Likewise for this, only with respect to this window.
So therefore, by restricting the attention to a smaller region, you do not need to find
the attention of those patches which are far away.
So therefore, you reduce the number of attention that you need to compute.
So by doing that, because you only calculate the attention between the particular region,
therefore it's faster.
So that's number one.
Number two is that, you can see in the early layers, it's 4 by 4.
The patch is 4 by 4.
So actually, the resolution is much higher.
It's a very high resolution.
And afterwards, in the next layer, we'll take each 2 by 2 patch, we combine them.
We combine them, we do a patch merging to become now 8 by 8.
So now, for each of these, patch now is 8 by 8.
You can see this 4 now is merged into 1.
And afterwards, to find the better feature in this region, you perform the self-attention
across all these patches here.
So again, you only calculate the attention across this small window.
So therefore, you can improve the computational efficiency.
And then finally, if we continue, so for this 2 by 2 patch you combine, then you reach here.
So therefore, there are two things that has been achieved.
Number one is that by only looking at the attention within the particular window, you
reduce the computation of time.
Number two is that initially, we use a small patch, and afterwards, we progressively merge
it.
So you will have a feature with different hierarchical representation, different scheme.
So that's the basic idea.
So we can see that it says that the Swin transformer, a built hierarchical feature, you can see
feature with different resolution by merging image patches.
So each of these initially, every 2 by 2 block, when you go to a higher level, you merge
them.
Every 2 by 2 block, you merge it.
And then in deeper layer, it has a linear computational complexity because it only consider the attention
within this window.
It doesn't need to consider the patches in all the other window.
Okay.
Right, okay.
Because it only, yeah, it has linear computational complexity due to the computation of self-attention
only within each local window.
So each local window.
Right, so it can serve as a general purpose backbone, as I mentioned to you before, and
it can perform dense reclamation because some of the patches are very small, high resolution,
so you can do very dense tasks such as object detection.
Right, so as opposed this previous vision transformer that we explained in the previous
lectures, right, okay, that only has single low resolution, 16 by 16, and it has quadratic
computation, right, respect to input image because for each patch, you need to find
the attention for all the patches in the image.
So these are the key difference between scene transformer and vision transformer.
Okay, so let me just go through one or two more slides quickly.
Right, okay, so this is the basic architectures, right, so this diagram just now we have already
explained.
Right, so the basic idea architecture of the scene transformer is that it will split
the input RGB image into non-overlapping 4 by 4 patch.
So given a particular image, you partition it into, okay, numerous 4 by 4 patches like
this.
Okay.
Right, and then afterwards you will have this a scene transformer block for learning.
So how does it work?
Let me see.
Yeah, so maybe let me just simply use this diagram to explain the high level intuition
before we come back to the complete architectures here.
So the basic idea of this scene transformer block, right, so is this.
So this is a scene transformer block here.
So this scene transformer block can be further divided into this, okay, window-based multi-hate
style attention, okay.
And this shifted window-based multi-hate style attention.
So this part here is actually the window-based multi-hate style attention, okay.
And this part here is the shifted window-based multi-hate style attention.
So this part here, if you look at this, you will see that this is something very similar
to the VIT structure.
Yeah, so it's just similar to the VIT structures that you have seen before, okay.
However, they introduce this window.
So this is what it means.
They introduce this different window.
So VIT, they will consider the whole thing as a single image.
But for scene transformer, you will partition it into different window here, okay.
So therefore we can see it's a window-based multi-hate style attention.
In layer L, a regular window partition scheme is adopted.
For example, in this illustration, we partition it into four different window.
And the style attention is computed only within this window.
So as opposed to the traditional VIT, traditional VIT you may need to, if you want to find the
attention for this patch, you may need to look at the attention with respect to all
the patches in the image.
But scene transformer, we divide them into different window, yeah, so that we only need
to look at the self-attentions of all the patches within this window, okay.
So likewise for this.
So this is what we do for this window-based style attention in order to calculate the next
layer better feature.
We only look at attention for this window here.
But if you simply look at attention for this window here, there's a shot coming, which
is some of the, for example, patches here may not be able to leverage on the information
from patches from the other window, right.
So therefore how do we do it?
How we solve this problem is we introduce this shifted window-based style attention.
So after this layer, in the next layer, our window partition is shifted.
So instead of like this, now this window here, we move it to the middle, okay.
We move it, this window here, we move it to the middle.
And then this part here and this part is actually wrapped around, okay.
It's wrapped around.
So this and this is more like wrapped around, this and this is wrapped around, and this fall
is actually kind of like tube, they are wrapped around.
So therefore, now your window here, right, for example, this patch here you can find
is attention respect to some patches in the other corner.
So therefore you encourage information exchange across different window rather than just simply
using a single window, okay.
So that's the basic idea.
So the basic idea of scene transformer is that given an image, we partition it into different
window, right, and we only calculate the attention within the window.
And then afterwards we use the shifted window to ensure that, you know, the attention can,
can be exchanged across different window rather than a fixed window.
Because if you use a fixed window, you know, we can never leverage on information of the
other patches across different window.
So once we have that understanding, now let's look at this particular diagram again.
So this diagram just now, this is actually the scene transformer block that we mentioned,
right.
So therefore you look at the attention in one window, and then afterwards you look at
the attention of the shifted window, right, okay.
So this part here, and this particular part just now we have already explained in the
previous slides here.
So this is the architectures of the scene transformer block.
So first of all, we have an image which is a H type times width times three, right, is
a color image.
So we partition it into numerous patches.
So each patch is actually four by four by three.
Dimension is four by four by three.
So four by four by three, four times four times three is actually 48.
So therefore after we perform this partition, right, okay, each of the patch now would
have 48 dimension effectors.
And then because we are using four by four patch, so the number of patches, okay, vertically,
horizontally now is H divided by four times W divided by four.
So this is the total number of patches after you perform the partitioning into four by
four, okay, four by four, right, okay.
And afterwards we will do the linear embedding.
We will project, we use a matrix to project this 48 dimensional vector, each of them,
48 dimensional vector, into C dimensional vector.
So this C value can be chosen, right, based on different types of model that you have,
okay.
So this is the linear embedding.
And afterwards you let it go through this string transformer block, which is this part
here.
So which is you try to find the cell attention, no, within the window.
And afterwards you try to find the attention across shifted window, right.
So you repeat it a number of times.
So once you have done that, so at the end of this is you have a better feature representation
already.
But next we want to move on to the next layer.
So we do the patch emerging now.
So this patch emerging means that now every two by two patches from here, we merge it
into one, okay.
So every two by two patches, we merge it into one, okay.
So you merge it into one, you can see that now, right, the size now will be H divided
by eight by W divided by eight.
So it's H over eight times H over eight, right.
So when you merge them, initially the dimension is C, but if you merge four of them, then
it becomes 4C.
But this 4C will let it go through a matrix to project it to 2C, right.
So the vector now will be reduced, right.
And afterwards, so now you have this number of patches.
Each one is of dimension 2C.
You let it go through this string transformer block to perform, you know, the feature extraction
through the cell attention, window base and shifted window base, you'll get better feature,
right.
So you repeat this number of times until finally, right, you have no different patches.
This number of patches now, right, the number of patches now you have is smaller, right.
But each of this particular vector would have a better representation than the original
vector.
Then this particular output, then you can subsequently use it for either the purpose
of classification, no segmentation or detection and so on.
Right, okay.
So this is the last slide I'm going to see.
So if you use string transformer to perform segmentation, you can see these are the results.
So string transformer is actually a very popular methods.
All right.
So okay, so I think, yeah, I'll probably just, okay, probably this slide's here.
So yeah, so this particular site shows that, all right, the performance of the average
precision over the number of year of release.
So you can see of course, more recent years, yeah, the methods are actually becoming better
and better.
Right, so this diagram shows the AP versus the frame per second.
So ideally, you want the frame per second to be as fast as possible and you want your
AP to be as high as possible.
So this is the good region to be in.
So for two-stage method, sorry, frame per second, we want it to be large.
Okay, AP wanted to be high.
So this is the corner.
Okay, this is the corner we wanted.
So for two-stage method, they tend to be slow, right, so that's here.
First-stage method, right, some of them here, some can be quite fast and lightweight methods.
So this is one of the lightweight methods.
It just give you a few.
Right, okay, we'll stop today, right.
So yeah, I'll give you a break.
Please come back at maybe 7.55, right, so that we can start the piece at 8.
Okay.
Student, as I mentioned a number again, make sure that you check your name, right, and see
what is the serial number.
Okay.
So later on, once you receive the questions ro Priorit, you must the first thing you
must do is write down the serial number.
Okay.
Your full name as far as the calculation number.
Right.
do. This serial number is very important because later on we need to tell you. Okay, and then
there will be some questions with some spaces so you can write your answer in the given
spaces. Okay, and then at the bottom there are some reserved spaces for you to write
your answer. Please make sure that you write your answer here so that again is to make
the marking easier. If I see your answer is correct, usually I'll just put a tick and
you will get a full mark for that. But if I don't see the answer then I have to look
for it then you know I'm not going to be so happy already. So please make sure that make
it easier for you and also make it easier for me. There are some spaces at the bottom
that you're supposed to write down the answer. Please do that. So the paper actually consists
of two pieces, right? So two pieces, one, two, three, two pieces with four sides here. So
there are three questions, right? At the bottom of question three and at the end there are
still some empty spaces. So if you need a bit more space to do the calculation you can
use that. But the important thing is that there are some reserved spaces for each of
the part. Write your answer there. Okay, and also for this quiz there's no early dismissal.
There's only 40 minutes. So once it starts you can only leave once, no we dismiss you
after the quiz is over since it's a very short quiz. So therefore if any one of you
need to use a toilet now please do that. We have very limited main power and then we
need to take attendance very quickly so that we will not be able to entertain that you
want to go to the toilet or you want to leave early. No early dismissal. If you finish just
take a nap, right? 40 minutes very fast. Okay. And then the last thing is that please
sit according to this sitting arrangement. Again because your class is very big, right?
If you don't sit according to this attendance, later on it's going to make our attendance
taken, taking very cumbersome and it's also going to take a long time for us to know,
check that the number agreed. Okay, are you all seated according to this arrangement because
I don't know. Let me just have a show of head. One to 100 is a sit number one to 100. If
your sit serial number is one to 100 please raise your hand. Okay. Looks reasonable.
Please follow this. 101 to 200. Okay. Alright. Looks alright. Okay. 201 to 300. Okay. 301
to 410. Okay. Yeah. 411 to 517. Okay. Yeah. Thanks. So yeah. I think it looks reasonable.
Yeah. But there are some students who do that. So.
So.
Okay, so student, please.
Once you receive the question paper,
don't start answering yet,
you can write your name,
matriculation number,
and your serial number.
Right?
So in case if you forgot your serial number,
later on, there'll be some student assistant
who walk around to take attendance.
You can also check right from the list.
Yeah?
The list is here.
So the student assistant who hand out the question
also have the list.
You can also check your attendance there.
Right?
Okay, so make sure you write down
the serial number,
your name,
extra-esmetriculation number.
Right?
It's a closed book quiz,
so on your table,
you can only have the question booklet
or the answer booklet calculator writing material.
Right?
If you want some additional pieces of paper
for calculation, it's okay.
But no reading material.
Mobile phone, please switch off.
And also take out your student matriculation ID.
Okay, who doesn't have the question paper yet?
If you have not, please raise your hand.
Student, please speed up the part.
Okay.
Student assistant at the top corner, there's, right?
Okay, who has not have a copy of the paper,
please raise your hand.
Right, this section, there's a lot.
Please hand out.
Help.
Okay, sorry, which section, please sit according to this.
Yeah, one, oh.
Yeah, just sit according to this.
One, nine, nine is this, middle section.
Okay, who else?
Right, okay, this corner.
Okay, who else who has not have the question paper yet?
Right, so everyone have it already, huh?
Ready, huh?
Right, okay, so we started a little bit late,
so now the clock behind is 8.02.
So anyway, we'll finish, I'll give you a bit more time.
We'll finish at 8.45, all right, based on the clock behind.
So I'll give you extra three minutes.
Right, you can start now, we'll finish at 8.45,
based on the clock behind.
Okay, you can start now.
Blue pen?
Huh?
Can we use blue pen?
Blue pen for?
To answer the question.
Blue pen, yeah?
Yeah.
Blue pen.
You know we just forgot to mean for theask me, so,
yes, some 1939 sorry.
For new student, please sit according
Anybody else just picked up the
Nong and said a
student assistant, right? You can start taking the attendance now.
you
student, can I just have your attention for one moment? For question 3, yeah, 3B, question 3B, right? Okay, there's a small typo here, right? The question is that a single
name, right?
it's not can, it's just a very minor thing.
it's more proper to be
okay?
so, yeah, just make sure that, take note that the order of the works are short.
yeah
okay?
okay,
ready?
Okay, class, just a quick reminder.
Yeah, very important, you must make sure you write down a serial number, name,
medication number. As I mentioned, there is some space for you to do the calculation.
Very important, you must write your final answer in the given spaces for each question.
Question one, okay, question two, please make sure you write your final answer in the allocated space.
Right, for question three, just write down your answer in the spaces given.
If you need some extra spaces to do your calculation, page three and page four is also okay.
But if you use those spaces, please clearly indicate that you are using page three or page four.
But most importantly, your final answer should be given in the given spaces.
Okay?
Thank you.
Is it done?
Still there, assistant three and four?
Are you done already?
Three and four.
Thank you.
Okay, student assistant number six, where are you?
Number six.
Have you given me the name list?
And also, student, you have not hali your number, right down the sub-total, right, for your case.
Those who have not written, please come to the front.
Thank you.
Where is student number nine, the mark list?
Student number nine.
Can all the student assistants please come to the front?
Thank you.
Please stop writing. Student assistant, please try to collect the answer strip under your
care and make sure that the number of answer strips you collect agree with the number on
your list. For the other students, please remain seated. Don't leave yet. We need to
tell you the answer strip before we let you go. So once it's made, please remain seated.
You
you