Ven.
Okay, we'll come back.
Can you just check?
Because this is the new LTA for me to conduct here.
So I also want to see whether the arrangement is most optimal for a lecture.
So those students at the back, can you see the screen in front?
Is the screen over there switch on?
It's also on this view screen.
Is that also on?
Okay, then that's good.
Okay.
The screen's all turned on.
So we'll come back to the lecture.
So I've actually posted part three of the lecture notes already, so you can proceed to the course
side to download it.
On top of that, I've also posted this assignment one, home assignment one.
Right, okay, so you can actually go to the course side.
You can come to the assignment.
Okay, so I just want to very quickly share with you regarding some of the information
for the assignment and also some of the things that you need to be careful of.
Right, okay, so as I mentioned, I already posted the two announcements.
One is regarding the CA one, and then the homework home assignment.
The second one is regarding the lecture note part three.
Right, so for the assignment, when you are ready and you want to submit your assignment,
what you need to do is you need to go to the course side, and then you click on this particular
button called assignment.
Okay, so just click on the button.
So when you click on the button, you'll come to this particular page here.
Right, so in the page, you'll see that there's a few instructions.
Number one is to submit only a single soft copy PDF file.
Right, so in the past, we have students who submit, for one such assignment, they submit
a few multiple files, and this is going to create problems because when we download the
file, sometimes you only download one file.
Right, so if you split your assignment into a few parts, it's going to make marking very
complicated, and also sometimes we may even miss some of the files.
Right, because you have to bear in mind that there's about more than 500 of you.
Okay, so therefore when you submit, please submit only one single soft copy PDF file.
Right, only one file.
Okay, don't submit multiple files.
Okay, so through this particular course side, okay, like this particular link that I mentioned,
so that that line is 4th of October.
Right, so you have more than four weeks to do that.
Okay, and then when you submit your file, please name your file, right, using this name.
Okay.
So name your submitted file using surname underscore given name underscore metriclation
number.
Okay, so for example, if your name is Tan Yiming, right, so then it's Tan underscore
Yiming underscore your metriclation number and dot PDF.
Okay, so please follow this particular naming strictly because in the past, sometimes I even
have to take like couple of hours to sort out some of the file.
Some students didn't follow the instruction.
They just simply use whatever name it is and we will download.
We do not know who make the submission, right, which this particular submission is coming
from which student and we need to take a long time to trace it.
So this is going to be very cumbersome.
So please make sure that you follow this particular naming terminology strictly.
Okay, right, so that when I download it, I have all the files ready and I can just proceed
to do the marking, right, instead of trying to file, you know, this particular submission
is coming from which student.
Right, in addition to that, also make sure that you write your full name, okay, as well
as metriclation number on the first page of your submitted assignment, right.
Okay, so this is especially true for sometimes students, they don't follow this name, right,
and then we do not know who make the submission.
Sometimes some students is called, you know, assignment one and I don't know where it
does come from.
So, you know, at the last case scenario, at least I can look at the first page to find
who, you know, this assignment belongs to.
Okay, right, and then the last point is that late submission and noncompliance of the instruction
may be penalized, right.
So if you don't follow this instruction, you can be penalized.
Yeah, because in the past, yeah, I actually took one day just to figure out, you know,
this assignment because there are quite a large number of students who don't follow
the instruction.
Take me a long time really to find out where the files is coming, who make the submission.
Okay, so if you don't follow the instruction, you may be penalized, right.
So this mainly to make sure that you follow this instruction.
Okay, so after going through the instruction, the next is that the assignment is actually
given in this tab here.
So you can just click on this tab and then you'll be able to see the assignment, right.
So in this CA1 home assignment, you can see these instructions are exactly the same as
what I've gone through.
So the assignment itself have two questions.
The first question is asking you to do some calculations of the DCT manually.
So don't use a program like MATLAB to calculate.
You have to do it by hand.
Okay, so yeah, so this is the first question.
The second question is that actually I asked you to write a short kind of abstract or a
report, right.
So the particular abstract or report is centered on generative AI in video signal processing,
right.
Generative AI in image of video signal processing.
Okay, so you'll do some studies yourself, right.
And then afterwards, you're supposed to write this short report.
So the report is one page, okay, using time in romance, font 11 and single column, right.
So I don't expect you to write a very long report.
Just a short report will do, right.
If you read up some material, right, sometimes you have some references, right, just include
the references, no, at, no, as a separate page.
Okay, so this reference page will not be counted, right.
So this individual homework assignment, so do not plagiarize and do not use generative
AI.
The topic is on generative AI, so don't, don't showcase a skills of generative AI.
You can use it as a research, right.
You can, you know, go use it as a research tool, but ultimately when you write, you have
to write in your own works.
Yeah, I'm going to do some, you know, try out different combinations of the question
in the chap GPT.
So once your answer come out, I'll roughly know, right, or at least I guess I'm sense
whether you're just copying from, you know, chat GPT directly.
So long story short, right, don't copy from your friend and don't copy from, you know,
generative AI, you know, directly.
Okay, you must understand and write in your own works.
Okay, so conduct research brainstorming and explain your own thought.
Right, so this pretty much, okay, first assignment, right, any questions so far?
Right, so if there's no question, but you want to do the submissions, say, suppose you
have a complete birth of this exercises and you want to do the submission, it's actually
quite straightforward.
You just come to this particular link and you click on it.
Right, so once you click on it, you will bring you to this particular page here.
Right, so this page will ask you to create submission, upload the file and add some
comment, but the only thing you need to do is just simply upload the file.
So upload one single PDF file that I mentioned to you.
Okay, so there's two question, question one and question two, right, you can probably
create a work document.
Yeah, so for example, question one, we got it, we require you to write some equation.
So if you find it is easier for you to write on some paper, you can do that.
And afterwards you can take picture or you can scan it.
Right, and then afterwards you copy into a work document.
And then the second question, second part of the questions you can type up.
So it's in a work document and afterwards you just convert it into the PDF format.
So I, it doesn't matter which way you use.
So long as at the end, you can only submit one PDF file, don't submit multiple file, only
one single PDF file.
So you just need to click on this upload button.
You can see that right then you just browse your local file and then you just
upload it.
And once you're done, you just click the submit button.
Okay, so also please make sure that you check your answer, no, uh, carefully and
also make sure that you check your name, the name of the file, uh, properly because
there's only certain number of times you can submit because we do want too many
multiple submission.
So actually I'm quite, uh, linear already.
So for each student, you are given three chance to submit.
Okay.
So once you use up those three times, there's no more, uh, submission anymore.
Right.
So make sure that you check carefully before you do the submission.
Okay.
Is everyone clear about this assignment?
All right.
Okay.
Good.
Then we are done with this particular assignment already.
Okay.
So next, uh, next topic we're going to cover today is, uh, DCT, district,
cosine transform, right?
So, um, what is DCT?
Actually, there's a few way you can interpret it.
One way you can interpret is, is just a simply, uh, kind of mathematical operation.
Yeah.
So you can interpret this DCT operation is a transformation that involves some
mathematical mapping or transformation.
So later on in the lectures, I'll also try to, uh, provide another interpretation
or intuition on DCT from the basis perspective.
Right.
So first of all, let's try to look at, uh, from the mathematical viewpoint.
How do we perform a DCT or district cosine transform?
So for example, given a particular, uh, pixel block, right?
In our context here, this is, uh, either, uh, you know, main matrix or a pixel block here.
So you have this particular, uh, pixel block, right?
We call it Sij.
So the subscript is i and j.
Okay.
So this I refer to the number of row and j refer to the number of column.
So I here and j here.
Right.
Okay.
And then afterwards, when you perform to the DCT, right, what you obtain is SUV.
So this SUV is known as a DCT transform.
So it's a transform.
Right.
You can see the substrate is you and V.
So the row now is the index is you, right?
The column index now is V in the transform index.
Okay.
Right.
So how do we perform this particular transformation?
You can actually interpret this particular mathematical operation using this formula here.
Right.
So if you look at this particular formula in first glance, if this is the first time you
encountered, it may look a little bit complicated, but actually it's not that much.
It's not really that complicated.
Later on, we're going to go through one exercise together using hand and then you will have
a certain, uh, appreciation and understanding of the, uh, formula here.
So, but if you look at the first glance of this equations here, you can see, first of
all, we have this Sij here.
The entry is here.
Right.
So this is the pixel value.
And afterwards we go through these two, uh, no cost function.
That's why it's called district cosine transform.
Okay.
So it's cosine transform because we're using this particular cost functions here.
And afterwards you perform a double summation, right?
Running from I to N is equal to one.
So in terms of, okay, first, uh, yeah, I, I from one to N plus one, uh, N minus one is
the number of row and J from zero to M minus one is a number of column here,
column index.
So you do a double summation and afterwards you also multiply with these two functions
here.
So these two functions here is defined by these expressions here.
So when the K value is equal to zero, right, then this particular function will take the
value of one over, uh, you know, square root one over N, take a square root and for
other values running from N to N, uh, minus one, right?
This half RK will be taking these particular functions here.
So in this particular equations here, this big N here referred to the dimensions of the,
uh, pixel block or image block.
Right.
Okay.
So, right.
So we have a quick look at this equation.
As I mentioned later on, we're going to go through one exercise together to see how do
we, uh, use this formula to, uh, perform this T.
Right.
But first, why do we want to perform DCT here?
So DCT is a very popular transform used in, uh, many transform based image compression.
So transform based image compression method, as I explained in the previous lecture, is
a class of method that you take an image, right?
Okay.
Typically, but you partition it into numerous pixel block and for each of the pixel block,
you transform it into the transform domain.
So the reason why you want to take a pixel block and transform it into a transform domain
is because the transform CREDCN in the transform domain contains some good property that you
can exploit to perform compression.
So that's the high level, uh, explanation that I explained to you in a last lecture.
So therefore among all these different, so there's many different way you can do this
transformation.
So among them, to DDCT is one of the most popular transform use and it's actually used in a
JPEG compression as well as impact compression.
So the reason why, specifically the reason why it can, no, it has this good property is
because it can offer the energy compact, uh, energy compaction for transform CREDCN.
So if you remember, what's energy compaction?
So the energy compaction means that, for example, initially if you have a particular
pixel block here, right?
So in the original pixel block, you do not know which pixel values are larger.
So therefore you do not know where the energy is located in a particular given image.
Because if you think about giving a particular image, energy is defined by the pixel value
you squared.
Okay.
The value is squared.
So if you think about a general pixel block, for example, N by N pixel block state, 4 by 4
or 8 by 8 pixel block, right?
Usually given a typical pixel block, you will not know which pixel value is larger in advance.
So you do not know in general, given, for example, an N by N pixel block where the energy
is located in the spatial domain.
But once you perform the transformation into the transform domain, the energy will be packed
into a small number of quivicin.
Right?
So later on, we are going to see how DCT is able to achieve that.
But at this stage, just try to understand that DCT has this good property that it can
perform energy compaction.
It can take this particular pixel block, once it's transformed into the transform quivicin,
the energy will be packed into a small number of quivicin.
That means only a small number of quivicin will have large magnitude.
The other quivicin will have low magnitude.
Okay, so that's the first good property of DCT.
The second good property of DCT is that it can offer redundancy reduction.
Right?
So this redundancy reduction actually I explained in the previous lecture.
So I mentioned that if you look at the original pixel block, if you know this current pixel
value, do you think you more or less know the pixel value surrounding it?
Do you know or do not know?
In the original pixel domain or image domain.
If you know this pixel value, do you think more or less you know the pixel value around it?
Yes.
So what is this property?
This is known as the spatial redundancy.
So this spatial redundancy says that if you know this, given a small image neighborhood,
the pixel value tends to be very similar to each other.
That means if you know this pixel value, likely you also know the pixel value.
Pixel value surrounding it.
And from the compression perspective, this is no good because that means there's lots of redundant
extra unnecessary information.
Yeah.
So therefore, once you have this particular image in the pixel book, in the, we have this
pixel block in the original image domain, it has lots of redundant information.
Okay.
So once we perform the transformation, such as using DCT in your transform quivicin, in your
transform domain for the transform quivicin, if you know this pixel value, if you know this
transform quivicin, do you think you know the transform quivicin next to it?
If you know this DCT quivicin, do you think you know the DCT quivicin next to it?
Or roughly you can guess what this?
The answer is actually no.
Yeah.
In the transform domain, knowing this DCT quivicin, hardly tell you anything about the DCT quivicin
around it.
So this is known as the reductions of the redundancy.
So why is this good in the compression perspective?
The reason why it's good in the compression perspective is that you already remove lots of
redundant information in the transform domain.
Right.
So at this stage, I will just make this high level explanation.
So later on, we are going to go through one or two examples and we will try to explain this
concept again when we have some concrete example.
So it's probably easier to understand.
Right.
Okay.
So what are the advantages of using DCT?
It will give you good compression results.
That's why many compression standard deploy it.
Okay.
The basis functions are fixed and not image dependent.
Right.
So this particular basis function at this stage, you may not know what this.
So later on, we are going to look at the further explanation and then later on, we can come back
and do look at it.
But at this stage, just a step it that for DCT, one of the advantages that the basis function is fixed.
All right.
So that means you always use the same sets of basis function, no matter what your image is.
Right.
So it's fixed and it does not depend on what kind of image you use to perform the compression.
Okay.
So later on, we'll explain this a bit more.
So at this stage, we'll just leave it as it is.
But the disadvantage of DCT is that the compression is not as effective or as efficient as some other
transforms such as a KLT.
Right.
So KLT is a covenant transform which actually can perform the compression better.
But of course, KLT also has its own limitation.
So the main limitations of KLT is that it's image dependent.
That means depending on what types of images you are using, you have to train different model for
different types of images.
So that means it's image dependent.
That's why no KLT also have a, even though its performance is better, but it suffer from some limitation as well.
That's why when you talk about the trade off, DCT overall is still better because it does not
depend on what kind of images you're trying to compress.
You can always apply it.
Right.
Okay.
So the next thing we're going to explain is no, uh, this legal function.
So I'm quite sure all of you, when you are young, right, you have played this legal function before.
Right.
So the next thing is that we are going to explain this KLT from the perspective of legal function or basis function.
So the reason why here I call it legal function is that this legal function is like the basis function that we are going to
introduce later when we try to explain, uh, this DCT.
Right.
Okay.
So let's look at, you know, the relationship between a transform and basis function.
Right.
So a transform can always be described as a change of basis function.
So when we are performing, uh, a transformation, for example, given the pixel block, when you perform the
transformation such as a DCT, right, to obtain the transform, actually it involves a change of the perspective or a
change of basis function.
Right.
So therefore transform can be think of a change of basis function.
So transform involves a change of perspective on the image signal.
So this, uh, transform or this basis function actually can be also be interpreted as a change of perspective or how you look
at the signal.
Okay.
So the basis function is actually similar to the legal function that I've shown you in the previous slide.
So we are going to see a little bit more about this.
Right.
Okay.
So before that, now we are going to introduce the basis function or image for four by four DCT.
So the, when you say four by four DCT, that means the pixel block that we have is a four by four pixel block.
So we have a four by four pixel block.
Right.
Then we'll perform this particular transformation that we have would then be a four by four DCT.
So you have a four by four pixel block.
After you perform a four by four DCT, you'll get the four by four transform.
Right.
So in order to do this particular transformation, actually it also involves a change of basis function.
So that's why next we are going to introduce, you know, the basis function for this four by four DCT here.
Right.
So these are the sets of basis function or basis image for four by four DCT.
So this legal, this basis function you can also look at interpret it as if each of this is actually a types of legal function.
So each of this is a type of legal function, just like what we've seen here.
Okay.
So each of this image of functions here is a types of legal function.
And how do we interpret this legal functions here?
Right.
Okay.
So how we interpret it is that, okay, when the color is white or bright, that means this value is larger.
When the color is dark or black, the means of value is smaller.
Okay.
So now if you look at the first legal function, the first types of legal function that we have or basis function that you have here, you can see it's actually uniform.
So uniform means that right for this piece of legal function is actually flat.
Okay.
Right.
Actually, this piece of legal functions here, it consists of four by four element here, four by four element.
Okay.
Four by four element here.
Right.
And when the color is same color, that means this piece of legal function, four by four kind of size of legal function is actually flat.
Okay.
So next, these types of legal function here, right, you can see, right.
If you take a knife and you cut it horizontally, right, this color is brighter than this value is larger.
This color is darker than this, the value is smaller.
So imagine if you take a knife and you cut through it horizontally, then actually the profiles of this particular legal function is large and small.
Okay.
Large and small.
Right.
Okay.
And then this one, likewise, if you take a knife and you cut horizontally, you can see it's large, small, small, large.
And afterwards, if you take this one, you cut it is a large, small, large, small.
All right.
So you can see that as you move horizontally, right, initially your legal function is flat.
Okay.
But the next one that you have now start to change, start to kind of change.
Right.
And the more you move in this direction, horizontally, the pattern become faster and faster.
Okay.
The fluctuation become faster and faster.
So therefore this legal function, you can see as you move in the horizontal direction, it has increasing horizontal spatial frequency.
If you recall in last lecture, we say spatial frequency is in the space based domain, how fast the pixel value change.
Yeah.
So therefore this is what we have here.
As you move it horizontally, you can see initially it's flat, change slowly and then progressively change faster and faster as you move in this direction.
So likewise, vertically, you can use the same interpretation.
Initially it's flat.
Okay.
Now if you look at this one, you take a knife and you cut it vertically.
You can see now this part is large, this part small.
That means it's large and small.
Okay.
And then if you take this one, you cut through it is large, small, small, large.
So that means if you move down this vertically, the legal function that you have initially is flat and then vertically it become initially changed slowly, but progressively change faster and faster.
Okay.
So this is the legal function.
So if you move in this direction, that means it's in a diagonal direction.
The pattern become changed faster and faster.
Right.
So this is the legal function.
Or more properly, the proper term is called the basis function or the basis image when you are using a four by four DCT.
Okay.
So you have 16 different sets of legal function.
Yeah.
You have 16 of these different legal functions, 16 different types.
Okay.
16 different types of legal function.
So let me see.
This 16 different types of legal function.
Right.
Each of these legal function is actually has actually four, four by four element like this.
Okay.
So that is actually the legal function for DCT.
So next we are going to see how when we are performing DCT, it involves a change of basis function.
Right.
So that's the next thing we're going to do.
Okay.
But before that, maybe let me just continue for one more slide.
So just now the one that we show here is a four by four DCT.
Transform.
Now, if we use the, if you try to look at the basis function image for a by a DCT, so a by a DCT means that now, right?
The original pixel block now is partitioned into eight by eight pixel block.
So when you're a by a pixel block, when you perform a DCT transform, then it's a eight by eight DCT transform.
Right.
And your output will be eight by eight DCT transform crazy.
Okay.
And in the process of changing a eight by eight pixel block into an eight by eight transform crazy.
You will be using this new sets of legal function now.
So this new sets of legal function.
Now you can see, actually there are 64 of them.
Okay.
Eight by eight.
So there's 64 different types of legal function.
So the first legal function that you have here, right?
You can see if you look at this particular pattern here is the same value.
It's constant value.
That means it's actually a flat piece of function.
Right.
So your first legal function is very simple.
It's just a flat piece.
So the second legal function, right?
You can see if you take a knife and cut through it, you can see this part is large.
This part is small.
So therefore that means it's large and small.
Okay.
And then we'll just take one or two more.
Right.
If you take this one here, if you cut through it, you can see this is large small, large, so large, small, large.
So as you move progressively along the horizontal direction, you can see initially it's flat.
Now afterwards, it changes slowly.
Now afterwards, it changes faster and changes faster and faster.
So as you move in this particular direction, you can see the types of legal functions that you have
actually changed faster and faster in the horizontal direction.
Okay.
So by the same token, we can also interpret vertically this way.
So we'll just go through a few one.
Right.
So if you look at this one, we call it vertically, you can see this is large, this region small.
So it's actually large and small.
Okay.
And this particular piece, if you cut through it is large, small, large.
So as you move down the number, the, this particular row index, you can see the vertical spatial frequency
initially is flat.
Change slowly, change faster and change faster and faster.
Okay.
So these are the 64.
Pieces of legal function for 8 by 8 DCT transfer.
Okay.
So at this stage, you may not have a good appreciation of what this legal function is.
So that's what we are trying to explain to you next using an example.
Right.
To let you to have a better appreciation of what this basis function is.
All right.
Okay.
So first of all, let's imagine that.
Right.
Imagine that suppose, no, right.
First of all, we'll start with a 4 by 4 pixel block, right?
Because this is something that is a bit smaller.
It's easier for you to appreciate and understand.
Right.
Suppose we start off with a, no, a 4 by 4 pixel block here.
So, right.
So we're going to start with a 4 by 4 pixel block here.
No, a 4 by 4 pixel block here.
So, right.
Okay.
So this pixel blocks here, you can see, I do not show all the pixel value because I
don't want it to look too complicated.
I only show the first few pixel values here.
So we have a 4 by 4 pixel block.
Okay.
And the pixel value at this top corner is actually 2, 1, 3, 4.
There are some other values somewhere there, but I do not show it.
All right.
I only show the top left corner, the 4 pixel values here.
So we have a 4 by 4 pixel block and the top left corner value here is 2, 1, 3, 4.
There are some other values here, which is not being shown.
Okay.
So now the task that I'm going to give it to you now is that, suppose now you are in
no kindergarten.
So in a kindergarten, you are given a simple sets of legal functions.
Just imagine for one moment, you are given a simple sets of legal function.
These single sets of legal function actually consist of 16 different types of pieces of
legal function.
Okay.
There are 16 different types of pieces of legal function.
So the first types of legal function that you have here is, looks like this.
Okay.
It has a value 1 at this particular corner here and 0 everywhere else.
Can you visualize it?
Right.
So the first types of legal function has this single value at this corner here and the rest of the
values here, 15 values are all 0.
So the second types of legal function that you have here, it has a value 1 here at this corner
and the rest of the values, okay, rest of the 15 values are 0.
Okay.
And then there are some others here.
I do not show it, but now if you move on to the fifth one here, right, this sets of legal
function has a value 1 here and is 0 everywhere else.
Okay.
So these six types of the legal function here, right, it has a value 1 here and the rest are,
all of them are 0.
So can you spend one moment and visualize how this legal function looks like?
First of all, this is the legal function that you have in kindergarten.
So very similar.
It's very simple.
You have 16 of them, right?
One, two, three, four, one, two, three, four, one, two, three, four, one, two, three, four.
You have 16 different types of legal function.
Okay.
So the first types of legal function that you have has a value 1 at this corner.
The rest are all 0.
The second types of legal function here has a value 1 here and the rest are all 0.
Right.
There's a third one here.
You can kind of imagine the third one is having, you know, at the particular position, it's
1 and the rest is all 0.
Okay.
And now you have, if you go through, you come down to the fifth one here, it has a value 1 here
and the rest are all 0.
So now can you visualize these 16 different types of legal function?
You can, right?
Okay.
So the now, the task that I want to give it to you now is that, okay, now you understand
you have these 16 different types of legal function.
And for each of these types of legal function, you can use as many as you want.
Okay.
You can use as many as you want.
Now the task I'm going to give it to you is that suppose I tell you that, you know, I have a
particular 4x4 pixel block that looks like this with this two value, with the top value here
being 2, 1, 3, 4.
So the task I give it to you now is that, okay, please use the legal function that I
given you just now and try to stack them together such that you can reconstruct
this particular 4x4 pixel block.
Do you all understand the question or the task I asked you to do?
Right?
Okay.
So good.
If you understand the task I asked you to do now is that, okay, so now we want to reconstruct
this particular pixel block using these 16 different sets of legal functions.
So now the question is how many of these types of legal function do I need to use to reconstruct
this particular pixel block?
How many of these legal functions do I need to use?
These types of legal functions here that looks like this.
How many do I need to use in order to reconstruct this pixel block?
Two, right?
Why is it two?
It's not because I write two here.
Right?
You can see it's two because, right, okay, you can see this particular pixel block that we have
has a value two here, right?
All right.
And the only types of legal function that can contribute to this particular positions here
is actually this type, right?
So therefore this is the only types of legal function that has a non-zero value at this corner.
Okay.
So now if this is a legal function, if you want to get a value of two, that means we need
two pieces of this kind of legal function such that when we stack on top of it, okay,
this value will be one plus one, okay, and it will become two, right?
It's quite simple to understand.
Next, how many of these types of legal functions is required
for you to reconstruct this pixel block?
One, right?
It's quite, again, quite easy to understand.
The only types of legal function that is non-zero at this position here is this one.
So therefore whatever value that is being shown here, you need to use it, okay?
So it's one pieces.
Right?
So the other two, I'll just skip it.
Now let's look at this the fifth one already.
So how many types of legal function, this type of legal function is required
for you to reconstruct this pixel block?
How many?
All right.
I think some of you definitely know.
Okay, some of you show me a bit shy, just show me three.
Right?
Okay, it's three.
Okay.
So the reason why it's three is because, right, if you look at this,
but this position here, this is the only legal function, okay?
That has non-zero value at this position.
All the others are zeros at this position.
So therefore only one that you can use to reconstruct this particular pixel block is this.
So therefore you need three of these types of legal function to reconstruct this.
Okay?
So by the same token, by now you can see already, right?
How many of these types of legal functions is required to reconstruct this pixel block is actually four.
Okay?
Using the same argument.
Right?
Okay.
So this, you can see here, what we have learned is that in kindergarten,
you have this 16 different types of legal function.
Right?
So in order to reconstruct this particular pixel block here, okay?
This particular pixel block, the numbers of the types, the numbers of legal functions that
you need for each of these legal functions is simply the pixel values on this four by four
pixel block.
So therefore this particular first sets of legal function is actually very intuitive.
It's, that's why it's known as the kindergarten kind of legal function because it's very intuitive.
Right?
With this particular legal function, how many pieces you need for you to reconstruct is simply given by the pixel value.
Okay?
So these sets of legal function, one, two, three, four, just now the 16 different sets of legal function,
these sets of legal function is known as the basis function or the basis image and is the most basic one.
Okay?
So therefore you just learn the first sets of basis image or basis function.
It's very simple.
Right?
That's why it's very intuitive.
So this 16 different types is the first sets of legal function or basis function or basis images you have learned.
Okay?
Right?
So now next we are going to learn another more complicated sets of legal function or basis function or image.
So what's the second sets of the more complex legal function that we have?
The second sets of more complex legal function that we have now is the DCT, the DCT basis function or legal function.
So if you remember, this is the four by four DCT basis function or image or legal function that I've explained to you a short moment ago.
So you can see for this new set of legal function now is a lot more complicated now because now you're in university.
So the legal function you're going to play with is a lot more complicated.
So now you have this second set of these legal functions here.
Right?
So if you remember the interpretation, this one means that it's flat.
Okay?
This type of legal function means that large and small horizontally.
And if you move in this direction here, that means it's changing faster and faster horizontally.
And if you move down this particular direction here, that means your legal function now is changing faster and faster vertically.
Okay?
And in this direction is faster and faster diagonally.
So now imagine that you have these new sets of legal function now, 16 of them.
And you can use as many of each of these legal function you want to stack them together.
So the task, what's the new task now?
The new task is that you are given the same pixel block.
So you can see that it's the same pixel block as before.
But right, you are asked, okay, in order to reconstruct this pixel block.
Okay?
How many of this legal function?
Actually, how many of each of this legal function do you need to stack them together,
such that you can reconstruct this pixel block?
Okay?
So that's the question.
Do you understand the task that you have?
Yeah?
So you can see now it's not so simple as your previous kindergarten legal function.
Right?
Your legal function now is a lot more complex now.
Okay?
So let's see.
Right?
We have the same pixel block as before.
Let's say that how many of this legal function, right, this type of legal function that's
required to reconstruct this pixel block?
Suppose at first glance, you can't tell, right?
Because it's very complicated.
Let's say that the number of this type of legal function that's required for you to
reconstruct this pixel block, let's call it S00.
Okay?
For one moment, let's say it's S00.
We do not know how to find yet, but let's call it S00.
And how many of these types of legal function is required to reconstruct this?
Okay?
So this here corresponds to this.
This one here corresponds to this legal function.
So how many of this legal function is required to reconstruct this?
Suppose I call S01.
Okay?
So by the same token, there's one more here, one more here.
Next, this one here.
So how many of these types of legal function is required to reconstruct this?
Okay?
So this block here is this.
Right?
The number here I call S10 now.
Okay?
So this is this legal function here.
Now it's S11 and so on and so forth.
Okay?
So it turned out that, right?
This number, this, the number of each of this legal function that is required for you to
reconstruct this pixel block.
What is this number?
How?
Okay.
So this S00, S01, S02, S10, S11.
This number here, do you want to take a guess what are all these capabilities here?
Right?
So it turned out that the number of this, each of these types of legal function,
that's required for you to add up, to stack together to reconstruct this particular pixel
block can be obtained by simply, you know, performing the 2D DCT.
So therefore, for example, your original pixel block 2134 here, after you perform the 2D DCT,
right, the DCT coefficient that you have here, this coefficient we call S00,
this coefficient we call S01 and so on and so forth.
This coefficient now is S10, this one is S11 and so on and so forth.
Right?
So if you take a pixel block, right, 4x4 pixel block, you perform a 4x4 2D DCT, then you are,
you know, you'll get the 4x4 DCT coefficient.
So these are the 4x4 DCT coefficient and each of the DCT coefficient, actually behind the
scene, each of this particular DCT coefficient actually implies how many of this corresponding
legal function that is required for you to stack together to reconstruct your pixel block.
Okay, so therefore, this is the second interpretation on performing DCT.
So you can see now performing DCT, actually the signal that you are dealing with is the same
signal. Okay, this, the signal or the pixel blocks that you're dealing with is the same pixel block,
but you are using different sets of legal function to reconstruct it.
Okay, so in kindergarten, you're using these simple sets of legal functions.
So this is the first basis function, right, or legal function.
In university now, you are using these new sets of legal function, right, but the task is still
the same. So you can see essentially it's the same problem, even a pixel block, you want to use
these sets of legal function or basis function, or you want to use a more complex sets of legal
function to represent the same, this pixel block. So that's why this is known as transformation.
It's a change of basis function. It's a change of perspective on how you represent the signal,
right? So it's a change of perspective, right, or change of how you represent the signal using
different legal function or basis function, right? So therefore, this is the second interpretation of
how we perform DCT, right? But what is important about this, right? So why do we need to have this
levels of understanding? Because you could just simply interpret it as a mathematical operation.
So now the next question I want to ask you is that, right, suppose you have these particular
blocks here, okay? Right? Do you think you need more of these types of legal function
or more of these type of legal function to reconstruct a typical 4 by 4 pixel block, right?
So suppose you have a 4 by 4 pixel block here, right? Do you think you need more of these types
of legal function or do you think you need more of this type of legal function in order to reconstruct
a typical 4 by 4 pixel block, right? So if you think that you need more of these types of legal
function, okay, we call it A. If you think that we need more of these types of legal function,
we call it B. So can I have a show of hand? Who thinks it's A, right? If you think you need more
of these types of legal function to reconstruct this pixel block, just raise your hand. Let me
get a few. Probably I only see one, two, very, very few hands, right? If you feel that we need
more of this type of legal function to build this pixel block, raise your hand. Let me get a few.
But okay, actually the second one is more. Yeah. Okay, so which one is correct? Actually,
the answer is A. You need more of this type of legal function than this type of legal function
to reconstruct a typical 4 by 4 pixel block. But now the question is why? Given a typical 4 by 4
pixel block, why do we need more of this type of legal function than this type of legal function to
reconstruct it? Anyone? So the answer actually come down to one of the redundancy that I mentioned
many times so far, since lecture one until today, I actually repeated quite a couple of times. So
in image domain, there's one very basic redundancy. What's that?
What's the redundancy that you feel is maybe relevant to this issue that we are talking about?
Anyone?
It's actually the spatial redundancy. Spatial redundancy tells us what. It says that for
a general image, if you look at small pixel neighbourhood, the pixel values tend to be very
similar to each other for most image patches. So if given a small image neighbourhood such as a 4
by 4 pixel block that you have, the pixel values tend to be very similar to each other. If the
pixel values tend to be very, very similar to each other, that means its frequency is very low or its
change is very slow, right? It's changed slowly. So if even a typical 4 by 4 pixel block, the pixel
value changes very slowly, therefore you probably need more of this kind of legal function because
this kind of legal function corresponds to the legal function which changes slowly, right?
These are the legal functions which change very quickly. So therefore this is the high level
intuition. So for a typical 4 by 4 pixel block, usually you need more of this type of legal function
than this type of legal function to reconstruct it because our pixel value changes slowly.
So what it means now is that if you need more of this type of legal function than this type of
legal function, that means the DCT coefficient near this corner here will be larger or smaller.
The DCT coefficient near this corner here will be large or small,
will be large, right? Because you need more of this type of legal function, right? If you need
more of this type of legal function, that means the coefficients here S00, S01, S10, S11 will be
larger, right? And earlier we have just mentioned that this S00, S01, S11, all this coefficient is
nothing but your DCT coefficient, okay? So therefore even a typical 4 by 4 pixel block,
if you need more of this type of legal function, that means the coefficients near this top corner
will be larger. If the coefficient near this top corner will be larger, right? That means we know
the DCT coefficient near these values will be larger, okay? And the DCT coefficient near this
corner will be smaller, okay? In other words, you need less of this type of legal function,
that means the coefficient near this corner will be smaller, that means the value near this corner
will be smaller. So now you can see, right, why we have this energy compaction properties of DCT,
because the DCT coefficient now, even a typical 4 by 4 pixel block, after you perform the DCT
transform, you can see that the coefficient near this corner will be very large and the coefficient
near this corner will be very small, right? Because the coefficient near this corner is very large
and energy is defined as each of the coefficient or each of the pixel value you squared. So now you
can see now, because these values are large, these values are very small, so now the energy is packed
to this small number of coefficient. So this is exactly the properties of energy compaction.
So let me just repeat one more time. If you look at this particular 4 by 4 pixel block, right,
even a typical 4 by 4 pixel block, do you know which pixel will have large value
in advance? A typical 4 by 4 pixel block. You do not know which pixel will be large or which
will be small. That means you do not know where the energy will be distributed, right? But after
you perform 2 d d c t, you can see that the energy now is packed at this coefficient, right? So if
the coefficient energy is packed at this coefficient, that means now we can develop some strategy,
right, to represent this coefficient more effectively, okay? Right? So that means we can
dedicate more resources for us to help to encode coefficient near this corner, and the coefficient
near the rest of the corner, because their values are small, so we probably do not have to spare
as much attention on it. So this is the basic properties of the energy compaction. So therefore,
these properties of energy compaction, you can explain it quite readily using this change of
basis function. But if you use a formula just now that we showed, actually it is not immediately
clear. So that is why one of the advantages of trying to explain this using this basis function
here, okay? So we have just explained why d c t actually can offer energy compaction
through this change of basis function now. Okay, the second important properties that we
mentioned for d c t is we say that it can reduce the redundancy reduction. So what it means is that,
right? If you look at, for example, this 4x4 pixel block, if you know this pixel value, do you
know, do you think more or less you know the pixel value around it? I know I asked many, quite a
number of times already, but I just want to drive home the message so that all of you understand
what we are saying because we are not just studying about d c t. This concept is actually,
it's an important concept used in every type of transform, not just d c t. Right? So if you
know this particular pixel value, do you think you more or less know the pixel value around it?
Yes, right? Okay. So this is due to spatial redundancy. So, and from the compression perspective,
this is not good. From the compression perspective, this is not good because you have lots of redundant,
extra unnecessary information that exists among your pixel value. Right? And we need to remove
this redundancy. So now after you perform the transformation, okay, you have all this different
d c t coefficient now. So the same question now is that if you know this d c t coefficient,
do you think you know the d c t coefficient around it?
No, right? So I hope you get the gist of what I'm trying to say. Right?
In after you perform d c t, right, knowing this particular d c t coefficient doesn't tell you
much about the d c t coefficient around it. And this is good from the compression perspective
because you have removed a lot of the extra unnecessary redundant information. If there's
still some redundant information, that means you should continue to remove it. But after you
perform the transformation, once it's in the transform domain, okay, knowing this coefficient
doesn't tell you much about the coefficient next to it. That means you have removed a lot of
an extra unnecessary information and you have removed the redundancy. Okay? Right? Okay. So I
know that we have spent quite a fair bit of time explaining about this, but this is actually,
as I mentioned, if you are starting many different types of transform, not just for d c t,
for d f t, you know, discrete Fourier transform, discrete wavelet transform,
you know, for many different types of transform, actually the basic
concept behind is the same. It says that you are using different sets of
this basis function or legal function now. So if you can understand this particular point,
that means you have a good or at least learn something quite useful today. Right?
Okay. So now we are ready to do one exercise now. Okay. So this exercise says that, huh?
Okay. Right. Two d d c t of an n by n data matrix is given by this equation, right? So this is
actually what I've shown you earlier on, right, in the previous slides. And it says that, okay,
use this equation to calculate the two d d c of the following four by four pixel block.
Right? So, yeah, I know that I've not really explained the detail exactly how to calculate,
but just, you know, try to see, right, you can think about how we can manipulate this
particular equation to solve this problem for one moment. Yeah. And then we'll try to go through
the answer together shortly. So I'll give you just one moment to think about it. And afterwards,
I'll go through the answer together.
Okay.
So, yeah, well, if you have not learned about this before, this will look, you know, at first
quite daunting, right? But actually, there's a systematic way to solve it. So for this,
you know, how to find the two d d c t, we are going to introduce two different approaches
of it. So the first approach that we are going to show is this in this exercise here. Right? So
before that, let me just quickly show you the
right. Okay. So let me just try to go through with you the, you know, the early step to solve
this particular problem. Right? Okay. So in order to, again, there's no need for you to,
you know, download or copy this answer, I'll make it available tomorrow. Right? So after tomorrow,
you can download it. Right? Okay. So first of all, we have this particular given formula.
All right? So this two d d c t. So the first thing that we look at is that if you look at this
particular first inner summation here is respect to this index j. So though, therefore those terms
that is independent of j, we can bring it out of the inner summation. So we bring up this term,
which is independent of j outside of this inner summation. Right? So we bring it out here. Okay.
And then this particular r, r, v here, actually we can bring it inward to this particular some
outer summation. So in other, we can just simply rewrite a little bit to obtain this particular
form here. So this form is obtained from this form here. So now if you look at this particular
inner term here, so this particular inner term here, you can see that is that okay, you have the
coefficient, you multiply with this particular costum, and you sum it up with the index j running
from zero to n minus one. So previously, if you remember j in i index is row index, j is the
column index. So if you sum it from zero to n minus one, that means actually you're performing
this particular computation row by row. Okay. So this particular equation is known as the
1d dct. So therefore this particular term here, you can interpret as performing 1d dct row by row.
Okay. So if you, given a particular pixel block, if you perform the 1d dct row by row,
okay, then the intermediate result that you obtain, suppose we call fiv here. Okay. You can see the
index now has been changed in terms of j index now has been changing to v because we've operated 1d
dct row by row now. Okay. So this particular result, suppose we intermediate result, we call fiv,
then now this term here can be represented as fiv now. So now if you look at this particular
term again, you can see that this particular term, for those of you who have studied dct before,
you'll recognize that this actually 1d dct column by column. Right. So again, you have this intermediate
result, you multiply with this particular custom, you sum it from zero to n minus one. Right. i is the
this particular row index. So that means you're performing your 1d dct column by column now.
Right. So if you do that, then this result will be, you know, what you obtain will be the 2d dct.
So in short, therefore, a 2d dct can be computed using a two-stage 1d dct. So the first stage is
performing this. Right. So the first stage is that performing the 1d dct row by row. Okay. And the
second stage is performing the 1d dct column by column. So therefore, when you want to calculate
a 2d dct, of course, there are many different way you can do it. This one of the most classical
way of doing the 1d dct through a two-stage 1d dct decomposition here. Right. So if you look at
this particular process here, essentially it's equivalent to this. Right. So you can see,
suppose you have, you know, fix a block, you want to calculate, right, is, you want to calculate
is 2d dct. So the index is i and j. i is the row index. j is the column index. Right. In the dct
coefficient here, right, the row index is u, the column index is v. Right. So this is a 2d dct.
So just now the process that we mentioned just now to decompose a 2d dct into two 1-stage 1d
dct is that, first of all, for each of this particular row, okay, you perform 1d dct row by row.
If you do that, then you'll obtain your intermediate result, which is we call FIV. Yeah.
So afterwards, right, once you take this, you obtain this intermediate result, you perform the
1d dct column by column, then you obtain your final 2d dct. So that's essentially the main idea of
what we need to do. Okay. So let's continue. Right. So these two equations here is essentially
shown in just now the slide. You perform 1d dct row by row, you get the intermediate result,
and afterwards you perform 1d dct column by column. Right. So that's what we will do here.
Right. Okay. So now let's look at this particular, so these are the two equations here. Right. And
in these equations here, n refer to the size of the pixel block. Right. So in our example,
it's a 4 by 4 pixel block. That means this big n is equal to 4. Right. So therefore, right,
we substitute for this a 4 by 4 2d dct. We let n be equal to 4. We substitute into these two
equations. So therefore, now you can see for the 4 by 4 2d dct, the first stage now, when you
substitute n is equal to 4 into this formula, you'll be able to obtain this. Okay. And when
you substitute n is equal to 4 into the second formula, this is what you have. So now it can
be reduced more concretely into these two equations now. Okay. So let's continue. So now
we have these two, you know, this particular pixel block here. Right. So this particular pixel
block, you can see it's 4 by 4 pixel block here. Right. So now if you want to perform 1d dct
row by row in the first stage, so the first stage is to perform the 1d dc row by row. So,
right, you can see the first row. Okay. The index that we use here, the index is actually starting
from zero. So therefore, for example, the row and the column index is zero, one, two, three.
The column index is also zero, one, two, three. So the index start from zero. Okay. So now we can
see the first row and the fourth row here because it's all zero. So after you perform
1d dct is also zero. Right. So those two rows, then you don't have to do any calculation.
Yeah. But the second row that you have, so you can see the first and fourth row,
if you perform the 1d dct, right, you can see they're all zero. Next, if you look at the second and
the third row, so let's look at, for example, the second row first. So if you look at the second row
here, right, so you can see the row index is actually one. Okay. Because we start with a zero
index here. So the second row, S1J is zero, 10, 10, zero, which is this particular row here.
This particular row here. So now we'll substitute this particular zero, 10, 10, zero into this
equations here. So we'll expand out this particular summation, but we'll expand out this summation.
So if you expand out the summations here, right, you'll see that this is what you have. You can go
back and verify. Right. So if you expand out this particular summations here, right, and you
substitute in just now, this rows of value, this is what you're going to obtain here. Okay.
The first stage 1d dct. Okay. So now this is the formula. So the next thing is that, right,
okay. So this is general 1d dct for the second row. So in this formula here, we can see that V,
right, is actually the column index. And this V value can run from zero, one, two, three.
So therefore we need to substitute in different values of V into this formula. So if you let V be
equal to zero, the substituted in, you're simplified, your C is 10. Right. Okay. And afterwards you let
V be equal to one, V be equal to two, V be equal to three. If you plug it into this particular
expression and simplify, you'll see that its value is 10, zero, minus 10, zero. So therefore your
result of performing 1d dct for the second row after you have done the calculation is 10, zero,
minus 10, zero. Okay. So we have actually obtained the 1d dct for this particular
second row already. So because third row is the same as the second row, so therefore
you will expect that the third row will have the same 1d dct as the second row. So you can just
write down the answer directly. So therefore after you have performed the 1d dct, no, first stage
1d dct row by row, this is the intermediate result that you obtained. Okay. FIV. So once you obtain
this 1d dct, right, after first stage, what is the second stage? The second stage is you have to
perform the 1d dct column by column. Right. Okay. Of course, this is a simple example. Right. So if
you look at now, this particular column here, zero, 10, 10, zero. So this zero, 10, 10, zero
is just like the first row that we have just now, zero, 10. I said this zero, 10, 10, zero is row.
Okay. In this case here, zero, 10, 10, zero is column, but you have already found the 1d dct
just now for this row. Okay. And this is the result. So if you are now interpreting it column-wise,
you expect you'll be obtaining the same 1d dct in a column direction. So therefore,
without even doing the calculation, yeah, you can see that the 1d dct for this column now,
okay, would be, okay. So because the first column here is this value, all right. And just now from
our row-wise operation, you can see when the row is this, this is this 1d dct. Now your column
is the same as your row structure. The value is the same. So if you perform the 1d dct, you
will expect it to have the same result as before. Okay. Which is, you can see just now the result is
10, zero, minus 10, zero. So in this case here now is 10, zero, minus 10, zero, but except in
column-wise now. Okay. So now you have obtained the 1d dct for this. And next the 1d dct for this.
So the 1d dct for this, if you look at column-wise, this column and this column only differ by a
negative sign. So therefore, you expect the 1d dct column-wise would have a negative sign in front.
Okay. So this is the first column. This is the third column. You'll notice that differ by a negative
sign. So therefore, you expect the resultant 1d dct to have a negative sign in front as well. So this
become minus 10. This become 10. Okay. So now for the second and the fourth column, because this
are all zero. So the output is also zero after 1d dct. So therefore, by completing it, you'll be able
to write down the 1d dct for the first column, for the third column, and the other two columns is zero.
So this is the 1d dct after, sorry, the 2d dct already. Okay. Because you perform the 1d dct
row-wise and afterwards column-wise.
All right. Okay. So let's continue. Right. Okay. There's actually a part b. So part b says that
based on your result in part a, calculate the 2d dct of the following pixel block b.
Right. So this is the pixel block b. It asked you to calculate the 2d dct for this particular
pixel block b. Right. So I'll give you a bit of time to think about it and then we'll go through the
answers together. So let me also put the answers side by side.
Okay. So just now for part a, this is 2d dct. Right. So for part b, right, you are supposed to make
use of your result in the earlier part to found is the 2d dct. Right. For this pixel block.
So I'll give you a bit of time to think about it and then we'll go through the answers together.
Okay.
Okay. So anyone has any suggestion? How do we solve it?
Okay. So if you compare this pixel block b and this pixel block a, what is the relationship between them?
Okay. Can we express b in terms of some simple expressions of a?
Okay.
Can we? Yes. You take the a and after works. So first of all, you have a uniform pixel block.
Right. And this uniform pixel block should be 20 throughout. Right.
Okay. And then after works the minus half of a. Right. Okay. So that's actually exactly right.
So therefore, right, in order to solve this problem, you can observe that b is actually
consists of this pixel blocks of all 20 minus half a. Right. So you can just observe it quite
readily. So now if you want to find the 2d dct of b, so the 2d dct of b is a 2d dct of this
pixel block minus the 2d dct of this. Okay. So next, what is the 2d dct of this particular
pixel block? So this is the question. What is the 2d dct of this particular pixel block?
So in order to answer the questions, right.
Okay. So in order to answer the questions, we will need to look at, okay, for example,
if you consider a 1d dct and this 1d dct right, consists of values of 10, 10, 10, 10. So this
sequence of values of 10, 10, 10, 10, if you perform the 1d dct, 1d dct, if the values are all
the same 10, 10, 10, 10, when you perform the 1d dct, the first coefficient that we have, we call
it the dc coefficient, dc coefficient. The rest of the coefficients that we have, we call it the ac
coefficient, right, ac coefficient. So when your values are constant, right, then is ac
coefficients are all 0 because ac, this word ac, come from this term alternating current. I think
many of you have studied in your, you know, in your bachelor degree before, right. So alternating
current means it's fluctuating. So if all your values are the same, that means all the rest of
the ac values are 0. So these are the properties of dct. Without doing any calculation, you will
know right away, okay. If all the values are the same, that means it's constant, there's no change,
then we can write down right away the rest of the ac coefficients are 0. So on top of that,
okay, this coefficient here is known as a dc coefficient. So dc is a direct current. So the
dc coefficients here is actually the double, the average intensity or brightness of this particular
row here. So the average values here is 10, right. So double is 20. So therefore the dc coefficient
is double the average, okay, intensity or pixel values of this value here. So the average here,
you can see quite clearly is 10. So when you double it is 20. So therefore these are basic
properties of the dct. If you have a constant value here, we know the ac coefficients are 0.
We know the dc coefficients is double the average, okay. So therefore write this one, we can write
down as 20, 0, 0, 0. So now let's look at this particular pixel block now. So if you do the one
dct for this particular row here, 20, 20, 20, 20, what do you think will be the resulting one dct?
If you take 20, 20, 20, 20, right, this row, we take this one dct, what will be the value?
It will be 40, 0, 0, 0, right. So therefore if you perform this in the first stage,
first stage which is we process it row by row, we process it row by row, this row will give you
the one dct will be 40, 0, 0, 0, correct. Second row will also be 40, 0, 0, 0. Third row 40, 0, 0.
Last row 40, 0, 0, 0. So now after the first stage, okay, only your first column is 40,
the rest are all 0, correct. So what's the second stage? Second stage is you need to
perform the one dct column by column. So the first column is 40, 40, 40, 40. So after you perform
the one dct column wise will become 80, 0, 0, 0. So the first column now will be 80, 0, 0, 0.
So the rest of the three columns we already see earlier, they are all 0. So therefore performing
one dct will also be 0. So therefore by looking at this pixel block, you can write down the two dct
directly, okay. We can write down the answer directly, okay. And a is already obtained,
the one dct from the previous questions already. So therefore doing some simple manipulation,
you'll see this is the result, right? Okay. So this is the, yeah, so this is the one d,
okay. So for this exercise, for this particular exercise here,
all right, okay. All right, so I think, yeah, probably this is a good time to take a short
break. But before the break actually, yeah, so the other day, last week my wife actually
come to me and yeah, she say that she saw lots of this videos on toying and, you know, the video,
he said, she told me that she know how to beat this particular monster already. So I think by now
all of you should know, right? And according to what I heard, no, this particular monster kill many
new players and many new players spend hours to try to beat this particular big head monster. So
anyway, yeah, let me just play this. Okay, we will see the, in case some of you still do not know.
All right. Okay, I will not play the whole video, right? But I hope my wife really know what she
said. Okay, so the next one is that, right? So just about half an hour or one hour ago before
the lecture, I actually use a chat GPT, the Dali Tree, no, to try to generate this, the
Wukong in NTU, right? So this is what Wukong in NTU looks like, right, according to the interpretation.
Right, okay, so we think a short break will come back at 8.15, right? Let's come back at 8.15.
Okay, so let's continue. So in the first half of the lecture, we explain about the basic definitions
of the 2-DDCT formula, and then we show how we can perform 2-DDCT by changing it into a 2-stage 1-DDCT.
So there's actually an alternative way of calculating the 2-DDCT, which is through the
matrix implementation or multiplication. So that's why we are going to now look at the second approach
to calculate the 2-DDCT, right? Okay, so we can see that previously the factorizations of the 2-DDCT,
the previous example, into the 1-DDCT, this particular process actually can be also be
implemented using this matrix multiplication, right? So therefore, if you want to calculate 2-DDCT,
you can also use the matrix multiplication to perform it. So in these equations here,
this is your pixel block, okay? For example, our earlier example, this is the 4x4 pixel block,
right? So this t here is a DCT matrix, okay? So this t is a DCT matrix, right? So you can see it's t
multiply with your pixel block and multiply with this t transpose. This is a transpose here.
So by performing this matrix multiplication, then you'll obtain your 2-DDCT transform.
Right? Okay, so and now if you look at this particular DCT matrix a little bit closer,
so you can see this tij here, i is actually the row index, j is a column index. So tij actually
just refers to different values in this particular DCT matrix. So the, right, so now if you look at
this DCT matrix here, when i is equal to zero, that means for the first row, okay? So for the first
row, they all have the same value, which is one over root n. n is the size of the pixel block. For
example, 4x4 or 8x8. If it's 4x4, then n is equal to 4. If it's 8x8 pixel block, then n is equal to 8.
So this is for the first row. And for all the other subsequent rows, okay, is given by this
particular expressions here. Okay, right, so again, i is actually the row index,
j is actually the column index. So you just need to remember it. And the block size is n by n.
So, right, let's look at one particular example here. Okay, so if you look at the case, if you are
performing an 8x8 DCT transform, then n is equal to 8, right? So if you plug this n is equal to 8
into this previous formula and simplify a little bit, then this is the expressions you are going to
obtain. So now if you look at i is equal to zero, so this is the i index, this is the j index here.
So when i is equal to zero, it refers to the first row. So that means now the first row will have
all the same value here. And this row here is corresponding to when i is equal to 1.
So when i is equal to 1, right, then we have to use this formula. Okay, so for this row,
when i is equal to 1, we have to use this formula and we let i be equal to 1 into here.
Then you can see this row here is defined by half cos 2j plus 1 multiplied by pi divided by 16.
Okay, this row here. And then now for all the different values here is with respect to j index
now. So j is equal to zero, j is equal to 1, j is equal to 2, and so on and so forth. So when j is
equal to zero, you put it here, you can see it's actually half cos, okay, pi over 16. When j is
equal to 1, this particular column here, when j is equal to 1, you can see this is 3 pi over 16.
So 3 pi over 16. So by the same token, you'll be able to actually write down all the coefficients in
this DCT matrix by using this formula. Right, okay, so just now we have actually mentioned that
if you can write down this DCT matrix, or if you are provided with the DCT matrix,
then to calculate the DCT coefficient, right, is simply by this matrix multiplication,
T multiplied by the pixel block multiplied by T transpose. Now, for example, if you are given
this particular DCT coefficient, if you want to obtain the pixel block, how do we do it?
So what we can do is that, right, we perform, you know, inverse transform, okay, we multiply
free multiply with T transpose on both sides, then this will become, you know, T inverse
multiplied by T, we multiply with T inverse on both sides, then this will become 1. So we have
a T inverse here, and we multiply with T transpose inverse here, then we'll have this term here.
So anyway, because the matrix T is orthogonal, right, actually you can go home and verify quite
readily, because this DCT matrix is orthogonal. So orthogonal means that, you know, T multiplied
with T transpose, right, T multiplied with T transpose is the same as T transpose multiplied
by T, which is equal to identity, or in other words, T transpose is equal to T inverse, okay.
So because this DCT matrix that we have just studied satisfied this particular condition,
therefore actually just now, you know, from the earlier equation, by multiplying with the inverse
on both sides, you can readily show that, okay, if you are given the DCT coefficient,
and if you want to obtain the pixel block, you just need to perform this multiplication,
which is T transpose multiplied with your DCT coefficient, multiplied with a T will give you
the pixel block, okay. So now we have a simple relationship to do the transform in both the
forework as well as the inverse direction now, okay. So with that now, we are ready to, you know,
solve this particular, we'll solve this problem. So this question says that a 2D DCT
of an n by n pixel block is given here, okay, right, which is what we have just gone through just
now, okay. So determine the 2D DCT matrix T, 4 by 4 pixel block, ground your answer to
4 decimal places, okay. So I'll give you one moment to familiarize yourself with, you know,
to write down the DCT matrix given the formula, okay. So I'll give you a bit of time to try it out.
Okay.
Okay. So yeah, at least you have some time to think about it. So let's try to go through the
answers together.
Okay.
Okay. So pretty much, right, as I mentioned here, right, what you need to do now is that in this
case, because it's a 4 by 4 pixel block, right. So, okay, because it's a 4 by 4 pixel blocks here.
So what you need to do is simply let m be equal to 4 into this formula. So the first row now is
actually 1 over 2, right. So square root of 4 is 2. So it's 1 over 2. So first row is actually
0.5 here, right. Then the second row, no, you just let, for example, this i is equal to 1 is this
row, i is equal to 2, i is equal to 2, 3. So for i is equal to 1, then the first row is that you have
2 over 4, which is 1 over root 2, okay. And then cos, right, 2j plus 1pi divided by 8 here, right.
And then you substitute in different values of j, right. You'll be able to write this thing down.
So anyway, I'll not, you can go home and verify yourself, right, to make sure you know how to
evaluate this. So by doing that, you'll be able to write down this particular DCT matrix, okay.
So once you've calculated the DCT matrix next, it says that basically you result in part A1,
calculate the 2-D DCT of the following pixel block A, and round your answer to the 3 nearest
decimal places, okay. So again, I'll give you a bit of time to, you know, to try it out,
and then we'll go through the answers together.
Okay, so you probably have some time to think about it. So how do we find the
the DCT transform.
How do we do it?
So the 2D DCT, the DCT coefficient should be equal to,
is a matrix multiplication.
So what's a matrix multiplication?
It should be, what's our first matrix?
What's our first matrix?
T, right?
And then multiply with A,
and then multiply with T transpose, yeah?
So we have, the matrix A is already given, right?
And then the T transpose, I mean the, sorry,
the DCT matrix is also given.
So pretty much is reduced into a,
matrix multiplication problem, right?
Okay, so you can see the 2D DCT of A, right?
Is T, A, T transpose, yeah?
So now, okay, so this is your matrix A,
this is your matrix T that you have found from earlier, right?
So T transpose just means that, no,
the row become column, okay?
The row become column.
So now you have these three matrix, yeah?
You just need to do some multiplication,
and if you are careful, at the end,
you'll find the DCT coefficient.
So this is the 2D DCT coefficient of the pixel block A, right?
So are there any questions?
Right, so if not, then let's continue.
Okay, so now we have the basic tools, right?
We have studied about DCT transform,
and also we know some basic properties of image.
So next we are going to look into the
JPEG image compression standard, right?
So let's look at some of the key observations
that help us to design JPEG compression.
So the first observation is that we notice that
the image content changed relatively slowly
across the image, for example, within an eight by eight
pixel block.
So this is pretty much the spatial redundancy
that we mentioned before, right?
So if even a particular image, especially if you look
at a small pixel neighborhood, such as the eight by eight
pixel neighborhood, right, the pixel values
tend to change very slowly, right?
Okay, so this is just the nature of the images, right?
So if the pixel values tend to change very slowly,
what kind of things can we do to exploit
this particular property in order to help?
Suppose you want to develop some algorithm
or some standard to help us to perform image compression,
yeah, okay, and we know that small pixel neighborhood,
such as an eight by eight pixel neighborhood,
tends to change very slowly.
Given a small eight by eight pixel neighborhood,
the value tends to change very slowly.
So what are the things that you have learned so far, right?
What kind of clue or some suggestion or some strategy
for us to help to perform the compression?
Actually, we just studied a few minutes ago.
So what it means now is that if you know the pixel
neighborhoods change very slowly,
then what it would suggest to you is that perhaps
you can consider to use some transform,
such as DCT for you to transform the image
in the original kind of pixel domain
into the transform domain.
Because once the pixels are transformed
into the DCT coefficient, right?
The coefficient is actually packed
over a small number of coefficient,
which is known as the energy compaction.
So once we know that the energy is actually packed
into a small number of KVC,
then we can subsequently develop some strategy
to help to compress it more effectively.
So therefore, the answer to the first question is that,
then we can consider to, for example,
deploy some transform, okay?
Especially in the context of JPEG is DCT transform, okay?
So the answer to the first question is that,
therefore we should leverage on DCT transform
to help us to perform energy compaction, right?
So that's the answer to the first question.
So the second observation is that,
human are less sensitive to distortion
in high spatial frequency component
than low frequency component.
So this observation is like what we mentioned
in lecture one, right?
So high spatial frequency component means that,
the pixel value change very quickly.
Low frequency component means
that the pixel value change very slowly.
So if you remember the example that I mentioned is that,
if I'm eating dinner and if my shirt,
you notice that I always like to wear this plain shirt,
if there's a spot, for example, a white spot here,
every one of you can see it quite readily
because our eyes are very sensitive to any changes
or distortion in low frequency component.
This black patch here is low frequency component,
because the pixel value change slowly.
So when there's any change or any distortion
or any noise in low frequency component,
our human visual system can spot that quite readily.
So this is opposed to, for example,
if I'm wearing a shirt that has lots of stripes,
vertical and horizontal stripes.
And if there's a spot here,
in other words, if there's a distortion or noise,
your eye cannot spot it so readily.
So this to explain that our eyes are less sensitive
to any noise or distortion in high frequency component,
but our eyes are more sensitive to distortion
in low frequency component.
So based on the particular observation,
how do we design our JPEG?
So earlier on, okay, if we look at just now
the example that we have.
Here we go.
The DCT coefficients, all right,
this is known as a DC coefficient,
and this is known as a low AC coefficient,
and this is known as a high AC coefficient, right?
So from the context of the DCT coefficient here,
this value is known as a DC, okay, DC, direct current,
right, these regions here are known as a low AC,
these regions are known as a high AC.
So the reason why it's known as a low AC and high AC
is because if you look at this underlying legal function,
low AC means that the patterns are changing,
they are corresponding legal function is changing slowly.
High AC coefficient means that the underlying legal functions
are changing much faster.
So that's the low AC and the high AC coefficient.
So because our eyes are, actually our eyes are more sensitive
to distortion in low frequency component, right,
and the low frequency component actually is in this region.
High frequency component, right,
correspond to the high AC coefficients here.
So therefore what it means is that we should actually
dedicate more resources, right,
to represent or to encode this DC and low AC coefficient.
Okay, so therefore question number two is that,
since our eyes are more sensitive to, you know,
any changes or distortion in this low AC coefficient
as compared to high AC, high AC coefficient,
therefore we should dedicate more resources
to encode this low AC coefficient.
Right, so this is just the first card,
no it's the first time I'm trying to introduce this concept,
but later on there are some slides
and then each of this concept will be further explained
and reinforced, right, okay.
Right, okay, so the second question is that,
no, right, so how does it define this, a JPEG design?
That means the answer to the question is that
we'll dedicate more resources to try to represent
the low AC coefficients here, right,
and this is done through a quantization matrix
that you're going to study later, okay.
So the last observation is that human is more sensitive
to luminance, okay, or the intensity component
as compared to the color or the chrominance component.
So how does this affect the JPEG design?
All right, again, this observation we know,
human is more sensitive to the brightness
or the luminance component
as compared to the chrominance component.
So how can we use this knowledge
to help us to perform compression?
So what we can do is that because our human
is more sensitive to the luminance
than the chrominance component,
that means we can drop some pixel value
from the chrominance component.
Since our eyes are less sensitive about color,
that means we can drop some of the pixel value
from the color component, right.
By doing that, we'll reduce the number of bits
that we need to compress or store, right,
but it makes very little perceptual difference to our eye, okay.
So that's the answer.
So the answer to this question is by dropping some
of the pixels from the color or the chrominance component,
and this particular process is known as trauma subsampling,
okay, but again, we'll also study later, right.
So anyway, we just want to provide some high level
kind of observation from our observation,
then we develop some strategy
to help us to perform the compression.
Right, okay, so now with that,
we'll try to give some high level kind of
a fact-share information to describe about JPEG.
So JPEG, all of you know,
is a very popular image compression standard, okay.
It can handle both lossy and lossy compression, okay.
Right, so the compression ratio typically is
from 10 to one to 20 to one,
that means you can compress the file size
into one, you know, one 10 of it,
or 120 of the original file size here.
So there's a four modes of operation,
which is known as a sequential DCT mode,
progressive DCT mode, lossless mode, and hierarchical mode.
So there's these four different modes
of JPEG compression, but for this course,
we'll only be focusing on this sequential DCT mode here.
So this sequential DCT mode is also known
as a baseline JPEG, right.
It's also known as a baseline JPEG,
and is one of the most popular and important mode
among these four modes of JPEGs here.
So therefore for this course,
we'll be focusing on sequential DCT mode, right,
and is also known as a baseline JPEG, right.
So for this course, we'll study about this mode only.
Right, okay, so what are the main stages
in a baseline JPEG here?
So for baseline JPEG,
it can be divided into the following steps.
First, you have the image of block processing,
okay, followed by DCT transform,
followed by quantization, entropy coding,
and frame building.
So moving forward from now, this juncture on work,
every time we talk about DCT,
we are referring to 2D DCT,
because I don't want to keep repeating 2D DCT,
2D DCT, you know that we're dealing with images.
So definitely the DCT is a 2D DCT.
So sometimes we're just simply,
in shock, we just call it DCT, okay.
Right, okay, so this is the general overviews
of the JPEG encoder.
So if you remember, the ideas of the encoder
means that you have an original image, right.
So after you go through this encoder,
it will compress it into a smaller file size of bit stream.
So this is the ideas of the encoder,
right, in the context of compressions here.
So therefore, JPEG encoder,
the goal of this JPEG encoder is,
even an input image, right,
your output is actually a compressed image of bit stream.
So this is a compressed image of bit stream here, right.
So let's look at how do we do that.
So first of all, this particular image,
if you remember, right,
we mentioned that typically for JPEG compression,
even an image will try to convict into
YCBCR representation.
So can you remember,
why do we want to convict into the YCBCR representation?
For example, given RGB image,
it's quite common that you convert it into the YCBCR color space,
or color model, but why?
Why?
Because once it's expressed or converted
into this YCBCR color space,
we know that our eye is more sensitive
to the luminance component, Y,
and less sensitive to the chrominance component,
or the color component, CB and CR.
So since our eyes are less sensitive
to the CB and CR component,
that means we can perform some subsampling,
chroma subsampling,
that means we can drop some pixels
in the CB and CR component or channel.
So that's why you can see that
this particular first channel is actually your Y channel.
This CB, the next two channels is a CB and CR here.
You can see actually the number of pixels
that it has is smaller.
So for example, this every four by four Y channel pixel block,
you only have one CB and one CR.
That means you actually only keep a small subsets
of the CB and CR pixel.
Why is it you can do that?
The reason why we can do that is
because our eyes are less sensitive
to the CB and CR component.
So therefore we can afford to drop it
and you will make little perception difference to our eye.
So that's why very often we convert it
into Y CB, CR color space,
and we can afford to drop some of the pixels
from the CB and the CR channel.
So once you have this particular image here now,
so the next thing is that we try to partition
into eight by eight pixel block.
So for JPEG image, given a particular image,
we'll try to partition into numerous eight by eight
pixel block, okay?
But for the Y as well as CB and CR channel, okay?
So therefore after this, you have eight by eight,
numerous eight by eight pixel block,
and we use this notation FIJ to represent
this numerous eight by eight pixel block.
So the next thing is that we are going to let it go
through the DCT transform for each of this block.
So if it's an eight by eight pixel block,
after you perform the DCT, what you obtain
is a eight by eight DCT coefficient, okay?
So it's a eight by eight DCT coefficient.
Now we use FUV to denote it, right?
Okay, FUV, capital FUV to denote it.
So the next step that we're going to do
is that we are going to perform quantization.
So each of this step later on,
we are going to have some slides to further explain it.
So this is the first time we're explaining
the key steps that are more due in the JPEG encoder.
So the next steps that we are going to do
is that we have a quantization here.
So if you remember, what's the objective of the quantization?
So the objective of the quantization is that
because we are representing images using computer,
and computer only have a finite number of bits.
So when you have a finite number of bits,
that means you only can represent finite levels,
finite number of levels.
Therefore, you must perform quantization.
So therefore, we'll perform the quantizations here.
In order to perform the quantization,
we'll be using a quantization table
that we'll explain the process later.
So anyway, after you have performed the quantization,
so for each block now,
we have a quantized DCT coefficient now.
So you can see we use F cap,
there's a cap on top to denote
is a quantized DCT coefficient.
So this quantized DCT coefficient now
is going to go through a process known as a zigzag scanning.
So zigzag scanning.
So zigzag scanning is a way to convert 2D matrix
into a vector.
So later on, we'll see more about it.
But anyway, is to convert this particular matrix
into a vector.
So once you convert into the vector,
the first value is a DC coefficient.
So the DC coefficient will let it go through a DPCM,
differential pulse code modulation,
which is a differential coding.
Again, we'll study a bit more about it.
So for the DC coefficient,
we use a differential coding to encode it.
And for the AC coefficient,
we'll let it go through a run length coding.
Again, later on, we'll learn more about it.
Here it's just to introduce to you
the general blocks of all the steps.
Okay, so now once you have this differential coding
and the running coding,
the output you are going to pass through
an entropy coding.
So the output here,
because when you look at this output here,
some pattern occur more often than the others.
So once you know that some patterns occur more often
than the others, right away, when it comes to your mind,
you know you have to use techniques
such as entropy encoding.
So this is exactly what we are going to do here.
So we are going to use this entropy encoding
to encode this DC coefficient and the AC coefficient.
And to do that,
you will be using a particular,
you know, code work or coding table
that has been generated earlier.
Okay, so finally, all this information
is going to pack into the data in the bit stream, right?
You also have the header information
and the table information, right?
So this will be packed into your JPEG bit stream.
Then it can either be stored or it can be transmitted.
So that's a general overview of the JPEG encoder.
Right, okay, so now once we have understood
the general overview,
we are going to look at each of these particular steps
a bit more in detail now.
So the first steps that we have
is to perform the image partitioning.
So the ideal image partitioning is quite intuitive.
That means given a particular image,
we try to partition it into numerous eight by eight
pixel block.
So we partition it into numerous eight by eight
Right, okay, and then afterwards,
okay, if you look at further a little bit more
about this image here,
actually, even though in JPEG compression,
we tend to use this YCVCR color space
or color model more often,
but actually for JPEG,
it can also handle other types of color images as well,
such as monochrome, that means a grayscale image,
color lookup table,
it can also handle RGB image, right?
It can handle YCVCR,
but by far, YCVCR is the most commonly used color space
if you want to perform JPEG compression, right?
So either way,
no matter which is the mode you're using,
what you are going to do
is that you're going to partition it into numerous
eight by eight pixel block here.
So each of this eight by eight pixel block here now,
so you are going to take this image,
you partition it into numerous eight by eight pixel block.
So each of this particular pixel block now
is going to be passed to your DCT transform, okay?
So it's very simple,
give it an image,
you just partition it into numerous eight by eight pixel block.
So each of the pixel block now,
you are going to pass it through DCT, okay?
So therefore, the next step is that
we are going to let it go through the DCT here now.
So the DCT is applied to each of the pixel blocks here.
So if you look at this particular equations here,
this equations is actually,
just slightly right of just now the DCT transform equation
that we have learned in the first half of the lecture.
So we just let it go through the DCT transform,
we have this particular eight by eight pixel block,
after you go through this transform,
then you'll get your eight by eight DCT coefficient, okay?
Right, so a recap,
why do you want to do this two-DDCT?
By now you should know,
the reason why we want to do the two-DDCT
is because it has some good property.
So exactly what are the good properties?
So what are the good properties for that DCT can offer?
Can you still remember?
Number one, it offer energy compaction, right?
Number two, it reduce the correlation
between the coefficient or it perform this
redundancy reductions here.
All right, okay, so the reason why we want to perform
the DCT is it convert the image data into a form,
which is the DCT transform coefficient,
which is more suitable for compression.
That means it has some property
that we can exploit to perform compression, right?
So by now we know two-DDCT offer energy compaction, right?
So given a particular pixel block,
it try to, once you have the transform coefficient,
the energy is packed to the top left corner.
The reason why it's packed to the top left corner by now
is because we know that the number of legal function
that you use is more slowly changing.
So number two is that offer redundancy reduction
by reducing the correlation between transform coefficient.
That means in a transform coefficient now,
knowing this DCT coefficient doesn't really tell you much
about the surrounding DCT coefficient.
That means you already remove the correlation.
Correlation means similarity, okay, or relatedness.
So once you remove all this similarity and relatedness,
that means there's no extra unnecessary information
in your transform domain.
So from the context of compression, this is good.
Right, okay, so this is the recaps
of the JPEG DCT basis function.
So in our previous lecture,
we start off with a four by four pixel block
because four by four pixel block is actually much easier
for you to understand and visualize.
But for JPEG because they are using eight by eight
pixel block.
So if they're using eight by eight pixel block,
then the corresponding legal function
and basis function looks like this.
So if you remember, you have eight by eight,
16 different types of legal function.
Okay, so the interpretation,
actually I've explained to you before.
Right, okay, so next we are going to,
just try to look at this particular process,
especially the change of basis in the DCT now.
Right, okay, so when you're trying to perform DCT
for the JPEG compression,
so first of all, given an image,
you partition it into numerous eight by eight pixel block.
So therefore what we have now is that the input
is the eight by eight pixel block here.
So after you perform DCT,
what you'll obtain is an eight by eight DCT coefficient here.
Right, so eight by eight pixel block,
after you calculate the DCT,
you'll get the eight by eight DCT coefficient.
So this particular process, if you want,
you can think of it as just a mathematical process.
Just now using a formula, using MATLAB, using Python,
actually you can just use the pixel block
and you can generate this DCT coefficient.
But earlier on in the first half of the lecture,
we tried to also introduce the concepts of basis function
so that you have a better understanding
and appreciation of what is happening, okay?
So therefore an alternative interpretations
of when you perform the DCT transform
is this particular question here, right,
which is when you are performing DCT,
it involves a change of perspective
or now you are trying to represent this pixel block
using these new sets of legal function.
So these new sets of legal function,
you can see there are 64 different types
of this legal function, right?
So these 64 different types of legal function,
each type you can have as many pieces as you want.
Right, so now the questions,
when you are performing the DCT transform for JPEG
can be put in this way.
If you are given an eight by eight pixel block,
how many of this legal function, right,
and how many of this legal function,
actually how many of each of the legal function
that you need to stack them together
to reconstruct this pixel block.
So the number of this legal function that's required
is your, this DCT coefficient.
The number of these types of legal function that's required
for you to reconstruct this pixel block
is this DCT coefficient, okay?
So the number of this type of legal function
that's required for you to reconstruct this pixel block
is given by the corresponding DCT coefficient.
So by doing that, you'll be able to interpret
what's the meaning of each of this DCT coefficient,
which is the number of this legal function,
which is required for you to stack them together
to reconstruct your pixel block.
Now, okay, just to make sure that you wanna understand,
right, okay, so do you think you need more
of this type of legal function,
or you need more of this type of legal function?
So if you need more of this type of legal function,
the answer is A.
If you need more of this type of legal function,
the answer is B.
So who thinks it's A?
Okay, who thinks it's B?
Okay, good, everyone learn.
Right, so now we know that we need more
of this type of legal function
than this type of legal function.
Why?
Because given an 8 by 8 pixel block,
which is a small neighborhood,
pixel value generally tends to change slowly.
So if we change slowly,
that means we need more of this type of legal function
than this type of legal function.
If we need more of this type of legal function,
that means the coefficient near this corner will be large,
and the coefficient near this corner will be small.
But so if the coefficient near this corner is large,
then we can actually come up with a strategy
to try to provide more emphasis to encode
or to represent coefficient near this corner.
Since the value is large,
if it's large, we need to pay more attention to it.
And also as I mentioned,
this coefficient is known as DC,
and the rest of the 63 coefficient
are known as the AC coefficient.
Right, okay, so this is another visualization.
So this visualization is now,
for example, these are now the DCT coefficients here.
So actually it's the same story,
it's just trying to explain it in some slightly different way
and also have some graphics to help you to appreciate.
So right, if you have the DCT coefficient,
so what it means is that suppose it starts
with a eight by eight pixel block,
after you perform the DCT transform,
this is your eight by eight DCT coefficient.
So the eight by eight DCT coefficient,
the first value actually means that
how many of this block is required.
So you can see this block is actually a flat block.
So this DCT coefficient means that
how many of this Lego function is required.
Now you can see this Lego function is,
if you cut through it horizontally,
it's actually look like that.
So there's a 3D view,
a bit easier for you to appreciate.
Right, so let's just take one more.
How many, for example, this DCT coefficient,
so this DCT coefficient means that
how many of this Lego function is required
for you to stack together
to reconstruct the original pixel block.
So this one here, the underlying Lego function
is if you take a knife,
you cut vertically, it's changing like this.
So this is exactly what we have explained before,
but now they use some 3D visualization
to help you to appreciate and understand a little bit more.
Right, okay, so yeah, we'll just continue.
So for example, if you take a particular pixel block,
for example, now this is the pixel block,
eight by eight pixel block.
If you look at this pixel value,
so these are some pixel values here.
The reason why you have some negative value
is because probably they minus some average value
or something first.
They do some pre-processing first.
So anyway, this is the eight by eight pixel block
from the image, and this is the corresponding value.
So you can see brighter value corresponding
to larger value, okay?
Yeah, and then darker value corresponding
to a smaller value here.
So now, for example, if you have this pixel block,
when you perform 2D DCT, right,
what you obtain is the coefficient
will look something like this.
For example, this is your DCT coefficients here.
So what you notice is that the coefficient
near these corners here, the magnitude is larger.
The coefficient near these corners here,
the magnitude is smaller.
So this is exactly what I've tried to explain before.
And because energy is defined as each coefficient squared,
so therefore you can see energy is actually
packed at this corner, okay?
And this region here, energy is very small, right?
So you can see therefore these corners here,
the value is much larger, okay?
So therefore you can see in the original pixel domain,
you do not know where the energy is distributed
because you do not know how the pixel block looks like.
But if you perform DCT now,
we know that energy is packed
into this top corner coefficient.
So therefore now we have a good way to, you know,
to exploit, to perform compression by concentrating
our emphasis on this coefficient near this corner.
Right, this corner, not so important
because their values are small.
So we can just enum most of the,
and we have come up with some strategy
to put more emphasis to this top corner.
So let's continue.
Right, okay, so, right, yeah,
this is just one more example.
For example, this is actually your DCT coefficients here.
Right, so DCT coefficient.
So for example, this coefficient means
that how many of this Lego function,
this coefficient, DCT coefficient means
how many of this Lego function,
this coefficient means how many of this Lego function
is required for you to reconstruct
your original pixel block.
Again, we repeat this message a number of times
so that you can fully appreciate and understand it, yeah?
In the context of JPEG.
So in JPEG, this is exactly what happened.
Right, okay, so now let's look at, for example,
this particular image here.
So if you have this image, if you remember,
we partitioned into numerous A by A pixel blocks.
Suppose you take this current pixel block here.
So you take this pixel block, this is how it looks like.
Okay, this is corresponding, you know, pixel value.
So if you perform 2D DCT, right,
so you can see this is a DCT coefficient,
values near these corners are much larger,
generally speaking, the value near this corner.
So this is energy compaction, right?
So if you use a color bar to make it easier to visualize,
yellow color means that the magnitude are larger.
Okay, so now you can see now the energy is packed
to this top left corner.
Right, okay, so now with the understanding,
we can proceed a bit more now.
Okay, so next, right, so this is your original
A by A pixel block.
After you perform the DCT transform,
you'll get the 8 by 8 DCT coefficient.
So early on, we already see this first coefficient
is known as the DC coefficient.
The rest of the 63 coefficient are known as the AC coefficient.
So in particular, the AC coefficient near this region,
we call it low AC coefficient.
The AC coefficient near this region,
we call it the high AC coefficient, right?
Because of what we mentioned before, right?
So near this, the coefficient near here,
the underlying legal function is changing much slowly, right?
The AC coefficient near this corner,
the underlying legal function is changing much faster.
So therefore, we call this low AC coefficient,
we call this high AC coefficient here.
And if you look at this coefficient,
if you move it horizontally, right?
If you move in this direction here, right?
The coefficient shows increasing horizontal spatial frequency.
Right, that means if you move in this direction,
if you remember initially it's flat,
it changes slowly, it changes faster and faster.
So this is the increasing horizontal spatial frequency.
Right, if you look at this coefficient,
if you move down here,
this is increasing vertical spatial frequency.
All right?
Okay, so we'll probably just look at the quantization next.
So for quantization, early on as I mentioned,
because we're using computer to represent,
so we only have a finite number of bits
to represent the DCT coefficient, all right?
So because we only have a finite number of bits,
therefore we must perform quantization.
So quantization is required to map the continuous value
into the discrete value.
So how do we perform this quantization?
In order to perform the quantization,
we'll be using a quantization table, right?
So whenever we use quantization,
we know that some information is lost,
just like what we have studied before
in previous lecture, quantization,
because it's a many to one mapping,
I mean some information will be lost.
So information lost will occur during quantization.
Right, okay, so next let's look at this quantization table.
So before that, let's look at how do we perform
the quantization.
So we just skip a few steps forward
and afterwards we'll come back to the previous slides.
Okay, so right, this is our DCT coefficient here.
So if you remember, we have a A by A prixer block
after we perform the DCT transform.
Suppose for one moment this is our DCT coefficient here.
Yeah, it's highly simplified here,
but this is the DCT coefficient here, right?
Okay, so in order to perform quantization,
we need to make use of this,
what's known as a quantization table.
So this is a quantization table here, right?
So this quantization table here, right?
When we perform quantization,
what we do is we perform an element by element quantization.
We take this particular value here,
we divide by this quantization step size
and we round to the nearest integer, okay?
So for example, 120 divided by 10 will give you 12, right?
So 12 is exact integer, so we can just write down as 12.
Right, but if for example we have 40, right?
We divide that by this 15 here, right?
And then if we round to the nearest integer,
you'll see that it's three.
So in other words, right,
when we perform quantization,
it's an element by element operation.
You take the value, you divide by the corresponding value
or step size in the quantization table,
you round it to the nearest integer.
So this particular operation is given here.
You have your DCT coefficient,
you divide by the corresponding quantization value
or step size, you round to the nearest integer
and then you have the quantized DCT coefficient, okay?
So the process actually is simple.
But if we spend one moment here
to look at this particular quantization table, right?
So this is the quantization, a sample quantization table,
right, a sample quantization table.
What do you notice about this sample quantization table?
What do you notice?
Is that a certain pattern for this quantization table?
Do you notice certain pattern for this quantization table?
You'll see that the values near this DC
and low AC coefficients, yeah.
Okay, this value inside, we call it value
or sometimes we call it step size.
It refers to the same thing.
So you can see that this value near the low AC coefficients,
their values are small or large.
Their values, okay, as compared to here,
these values are small or large, small, right?
Okay, so the step size of the quantization value
near this high AC coefficients, their values are large, right?
Okay, now the question is why?
Why do we have a quantization table
such that the step size near these corners are small
but the step size near these corners are large?
Right, if you can answer this question,
then we can finish the class today.
I know some of you are already just waiting
for the goal signal, right?
So why do you think the step size here is smaller
and the step size here is larger?
I'm sorry, say something, I can't hear clearly.
Okay, so I guess what you're trying to say
is that because the DC and low AC coefficients are large
and these high AC coefficients are already very small.
So therefore, right, because the values here are large
in order to reduce the quantization error,
because we know most of the values here are large.
So if you want to reduce the quantization error
that is being incurred, we must use small step size here
because the larger the step size,
the more loss you are going to introduce, correct?
So therefore, since this values,
most of the values are focused on at this corner,
we must use small step size here
so that we'll introduce much lesser quantization error.
Okay, I think this is, yeah, it makes sense.
And this corner here,
because the values are already very small,
so it doesn't matter, we can use a larger value, right?
Okay, so that is the first reason.
Actually, there's one more reason.
So the first reason is because the value near this
low AC coefficients are large,
so therefore to reduce quantization error,
we should use small step size here.
Right, what's the second reason?
Why we want to use small steps size here?
It's because our human visual systems
is more sensitive to just now, low AC or high.
Our human visual system is more sensitive
to changes or distortion in low AC or high AC coefficient.
Low AC, right?
So that means our eyes are more sensitive to any changes
or any distortion in this low AC coefficient.
If our eyes are more sensitive to any changes
or quantization error in this low AC coefficient,
then we better make sure that we use a smaller step size
to make sure that we do not introduce so much distortion.
In our, this low AC coefficient.
So these are the two reasons why
we designed the quantization table in this way.
Okay, I think we'll finish the class today.
We'll continue next week.
So next week we'll be here again.
Thank you.