you
.
So, welcome back. Let's continue with today's lecture. So,
today, if we can move a bit faster, probably we'll skip the
break in between so that we can finish the class a little bit
earlier. Okay. So, the next topic that we are going to talk
about is how do we adapt and fine tune the foundation model.
So, we are going to talk about the foundation model.
We are going to talk about the foundation model.
Foundation model, usually we train with a diverse large-scale
data to train it so that it will
acquire some cover general capability. But very often, when
you want to subsequently adapt it for some downstream
application, you will need to do the fine tuning. So, if you
are downstream application, you may be have a small data set
. So, this particular process is then known as the fine tuning
or adaptation. So, you can see this is the high-level idea.
So, if you take the example of an LLM, large-language model, it's
a type of foundation model. So, we'll start with, for example,
a large-scale diverse data. We will use it to train our LLM.
So, this LLM, because it's trained using diverse large-scale
data, so it usually has strong capability. But we want to
further customize it for our downstream application. So, what
we can use then will be, for example, a customized
knowledge data set to do the fine tuning, to fine-tune our
network so that it can be customized for our use case. So,
that's a general idea. So, fine-tuning is a process of
updating some parameters in our pre-trained model, such as
the foundation model, for some downstream application. For
example, you could have an LLM, which is a large-scale kind of
general application, such as a LLMA. But you may have a use
case in your certain company or your factory. You want to be
able to ask some questions regarding to the manual for
your factory. So, it's customized for this particular
factory. So, therefore, in those kind of cases, then you can
use your factory manual to fine-tune your pre-trained LLM,
or foundation model, for your conversation or
querying in for your factory application. So, the pre-trained
model, as mentioned, it contains vast and diverse
knowledge because it's trained using a large-scale data. But it
may lack certain specialization. For example, the case we
mentioned, for the case of a certain factory, you may want to
be able to handle those specific use cases for your factory.
So, fine-tuning will address this particular gap by adapting
your large foundation model to learn from your domain-specific
data, such as, like I mentioned, the Q&A or the manual for
your factory setting, so that it can handle the target
application more effectively. Right, okay. So, what are the
process of performing a fine-tuning? Right, okay. So, the
first thing is that you need to do some data preparation. Just
make sure that the data that you have is properly clean, is
formatted based on the standard format, and then, if
necessary, you may want to do some data augmentation. Right, so
this is the first stage. You do the data preparation. And
afterwards, you need to choose
a suitable
model.
So, you may want to choose a suitable
model. Right, so currently, there's lots of models out
there. Some are closed models, some are open models. Right, so
you may want to choose a suitable model that matches your
needs. So, this could include things like
what's the size of the model, what kind of data it has been
used for pre-training, and also the performance. So, these
are some of the considerations that you need to consider,
right, what type of pre-trained model you're going to use. Okay,
and afterwards, you need to choose a suitable method to do
the fine-tuning. So, in the next few slides, we'll spend a
little bit of time to look at what are some common ways to
do the fine-tuning.
So, in the next few slides, we'll spend a little bit of time
to look at what are some common ways of fine-tuning a
foundation model. Right, okay, so once you have done that,
then you need to do the validation. Right, so after the
fine-tuning, you want to test it on your validation data set
to see the performance. So, this is the set, the
validation, so you need to evaluate your fine-tune model
on the validation data set to see its performance. Right, and
if you notice that the performance is not good, then you
may need to go through this process again to do the
model iteration. Right, you need to do it a few times until
you get satisfactory performance. So, once that, then
you're ready to deploy it. Right, so you can deploy your
fine-tune model to the real-world application. So, this is
the kind of standard pipeline, right, on the fine-tuning of
a foundation model and their deployment.
Okay, so next, we are going to spend some time to very
quickly talk about some common fine-tuning or adaptation
techniques. So, the type of fine-tuning or adaptation
technique we're going to look at will be the adapter
tuning, okay, a low-rank adaptation, and then quantized
low-rank adaptation. So, this is improved versions of the
low-rank. Okay, and then the prefix tuning, and then
finally the prompt tuning. Right, so these are a few
broad categories of tuning or adaptation techniques that
we are going to look at.
Okay.
Right, okay, so the first approach we are going to use is
the adapter tuning. So, adapter tuning actually refers to
broadcast technique, right, which you are, that is used to
fine-tune your large pre-tuned foundation model. So,
typically, you will try to introduce some small network
in your original foundation model. So, instead of, you
know, fine-tuning all the parameters in your foundation
model, you are going to propose a small network, and then
you are only going to train and update, right, this
particular small network, which is known as the adapter.
Because if you think about it, right, foundation model
actually is very large. There are lots of parameters.
And if you want to train a large foundation model, number
one is very expensive computationally, and also you
require lots of data. So, therefore, right, for many of
us, we don't have the capacity, right, or the money to do
the fine-tuning of the whole foundation model. So,
therefore, typically what we do is that we introduce some
small network, and we will only try to train this small
network, right, that work jointly together with the large
foundation model. So, that's the high-level principle.
So, we'll introduce adapter. So, adapter is just a small
network, and there's different strategy for us to
introduce this adapter network, and then only train this
adapter network here. Okay, so the key objective is, you
know, you will reduce the computational resources, right,
and also it's useful for cases when for your downstream
cases you only have limited data, right. So, those are the
cases. For adapted tuning, it's useful for limited
computational resources and labelled data, right, which is
for most of us, right. Okay, so what are the some key steps
and adapter tuning? So, first of all, the key steps is that
you need to introduce some small network. So, this small
network is also known as the adapter. So, we need to introduce
some small network or known as the adapter, right, that work
jointly with our foundation model. So, in the next few slides,
we are going to see, right, what are some common strategies for
us to introduce this small network here. Alright, and then
afterwards, as mentioned earlier on, during the fine-tuning
steps, only this adapter or small network would be trained.
So, you don't have to train the whole foundation model, but you
only train this small adapter networks here, right. So, by
doing that, you can reduce the number of parameters that need
to be updated because your adapter is small, right. So, you only
need to train adapter, that means you only need to update
small number of parameters, and then for the obvious reason,
this will reduce the computational time as well as storage
and also the required data. So, this slide here shows some
of the possible way how do we introduce the adapter and then
train our adapter network together with the foundation model.
Right, so there's a few common strategies, right. So, the first
strategy is known as the prefix tuning. So, for these
illustrations here, we are assuming that the foundation model
that we are using is a transformer-based model, right. So,
when you see this diagram, you can see this transformer, okay,
which is shown in blue color is frozen. That means during our
subsequent downstream fine tuning or adaptation of the model,
right, this foundation model is frozen. That means we do not
update the parameter, okay. And the small network that we have
here, for example, this prefix here, these are the parameter
or network that we will train, okay. So, the first approach is
known as a prefix tuning. So, the prefix tuning, as the name
suggests, is that you introduce a prefix, right, prefix before
the particular foundation model, which is in the form of a
transformer. So, we introduce a prefix and then we only train
this prefix here, okay. So, this prefix you can also
broadly interpret as like a prompt that you use in language,
LLM. You know, in LLM, very often you need to introduce
some prompt to your LLM to generate the output. But this
particular prompt or prefix in this context is something that
we can train, right. So, that, you know, when we train this
particular prefix, we can use it to target our desired output
for our target application. So, this is the first approach
which is known as a prefix tuning. So, the next approach is
known as a LORRA. Okay, so anyway, we are going to spend,
you know, a few slides talking about each of these methods a
bit more in detail. So, the next one is a LORRA. So, LORRA,
what it does is that you have first of all a large
pretrained model. So, this is a large pretrained model. So, what
we propose to do is that we introduce two small
matrices, A and B, all right. And then we'll use,
when we do this fine tuning, we'll only train this small
network here, A and B to update the parameter. And this branch is
in parallel. So, in other words, right, when we are doing the fine tuning, we are only
training this small network. Okay, so this small network will
provide the delta update so that it can fine-tune your knowledge
in your foundation model. Okay, so this is LORRA. Okay, so the
next one is a series adapter. So, as the name suggests series,
you can see that means we try to put our adapter in series
configuration with our foundation model. For example, this is our
transformer here. In this case here, we can potentially introduce
an adapter here. Okay, we can introduce an adapter here which is in series.
Right in this structure you can see in series here. And this adapter
is a small network. It could be, for example, in the form of
two linear layers and with a non-linearity
in between. So, an example of this adapter could be a
small network like this. Okay, so this is known as a series adapter. So,
you introduce some adapter in series with your
conventional transformer network. Okay, but more
commonly what you have is a parallel adapter. So, what you have is your
this foundation model which is a transformer. And then you introduce some small
network adapter which is in parallel. So, you can see
this structure here actually is also kind of similar to the LORRA. So, LORRA
is actually a form of a parallel adapter which
is similar to this. Right, so as I mentioned, adapter is
just a small network. So, a sample adapter could be, for example, just consists
of two FC layers with a non-linearity in between. Just like this.
Okay, so these are a few broad categories of the adapter.
Right, and then later on we are going to look at
each of these approach a little bit more in detail.
Right, okay, so the first approach we are going to look at is the LORRA.
Right, so LORRA stands for low-rank adaptation.
Okay, you can see this is a low-rank adaptation here.
So, later on you are going to see why it's called a low-rank adaptation here.
But first of all, we are going to look at some basic idea and then after a week, so look at
the diagram to have a better understanding. So, LORRA is
an efficient fine-tuning approach. So, you can do the fine-tuning quite
effectively. Okay, so it's an efficient fine-tuning method
for foundation model such as LLM. Okay, so
some of the advantages, it has low computational
overhead as well as a parameter update. So, later on you will see why that's the case.
So, an example is that, for example, if you have a chat GPTT,
this is a GPT3. Initially,
GPT3 has 175 billion of parameter.
If you want to fine-tune using Adam Automizer for the whole
parameter in this LLM, so this
is very expensive. Now, instead of doing that, if you decide to use LORRA
approach to do the fine-tuning, you'll see that
in terms of GPU memory requirement, it will be reduced
by three times and in terms of trainable parameter, it will be reduced
by 10,000 times. So, in short,
it will reduce the number of parameters that need to be trained very significantly.
So, how does it do that?
So, in order to do that, okay, so these are the steps of the LORRA,
but before that, maybe we can look at the diagram first to get
a certain sense of how this LORRA work before we come back to look at
the steps of LORRA.
So, this diagram here shows the key steps involved in
fine-tuning of a foundation model using LORRA here.
Okay, so for example, you can see this part here is actually
for a transformer which serves as, for example, your foundation model.
Okay, so what we can do is that, for example, we can introduce
a particular parallel adapter called LORRA here.
So, this is the LORRA here. So, this LORRA here would be
something that we want to fine-tune for our downstream target application.
Right, okay, so let's zoom into these particular
steps here a little bit more in detail here. So, if you look into here,
so what you have is that first of all, suppose your input to this particular
network here, okay, we call it a vector of dimension
x, yeah, a vector of dimension x, sorry, a vector x of
dimension d, right, a vector x of dimension d. So,
if we go through the standard kind of foundation model
right, then what you'll do is that you'll go through this pre-trained parameter and then you
will generate the output here, right, so this is your pre-trained
model, okay, the foundation model. So, what we'll do is that for LORRA
we are going to introduce two smaller matrices, okay,
right, here it's called WA and WB, but it
can also be A and B here. So, these are the two
matrices that we are going to introduce. So, later on what we are going to do
is that we are only going to train this small network here, right, this
small networks, these two matrices, okay, these two matrices
are two matrices with low
dimension, okay, so, or low
rank here. So, these are the two networks that we are going, or matrix that we are going to train,
and then the output of this network will go through
this particular network that we train and then you will generate the output
and then the output from this part which is from the
pre-trained model as well as from your fine-tune model
that wouldn't be added, okay, to generate the output. So, this output
you will then compare with your target output for your target
kind of downstream application and then whatever error that you have would then be
back propagate to only update this parameter only,
okay, so this is the only network, so this LORRA adapter
here is the only network that need to be trained and this part here
is consists of the products of two matrices
that has a lower rank or dimension, okay, that's why it's called
low rank decomposition here. So, next
if we look into this a little bit more in detail, so if we zoom in
this part, okay, of the network here, you'll see this is how it looks like,
okay, so this is your foundation
model, okay, right, it's a very big matrix W here,
right, suppose if you have an input vector, okay, X of dimension D,
right, so after you multiply with this particular matrix, then your output
is actually a vector of dimension K, right, so what we
do now is that if you think about it, if you want to do the fine-tuning
by brute force, that means you have to fine-tune all
the parameter in this particular network here, but if you want to fine-tune
all the parameter in this particular matrix W
is very expensive because the size is very, very big,
so therefore as opposed to using the brute force to train all the
parameter here, right, we propose this as a smaller network here,
so this particular smaller network consists of two matrixes
A and B here, the notation sometimes
is sometimes they call it W, A, W, B, sometimes they call it simply A or B,
but they refer to the same thing, okay, so you have
so this is the adapter under Laura here, so you have this matrix
A and this matrix B here, so you can see this matrix A here, the dimension
is actually D by R, so this R is the rank of the
matrix and typically this values of R is very small, okay, it's
very small, okay, so likewise the second matrix B
is K by R, again this R here is very small
value, so therefore you can kind of think about it, if your value R is very small,
that means now these two matrixes is actually very thin matrix,
so therefore the number of parameters that is required
to train these two matrixes is much smaller, right, but in terms of storage
as well as the training, as well as the data required to train this,
so by doing that, right, therefore you can reduce the
number of parameters that need to be trained, okay, and then whatever
your downstream application, the target
that you want to achieve or fine tune can be updated by
training this matrix but keep this big matrix frozen,
okay, so that's the high level ideas of Laura,
okay, so next let's go back to
these are the key steps and ideas of Laura, right, so
Laura is, so the key steps are using Laura to
train our foundation model, first is that again we need to choose a suitable
pre-trained foundation model, right, and then afterwards we need to
choose a suitable layer for us to do the adaptation, so the adaptation that you
can do can be for example in the self-attention layer or in the
FC layer, right, so it could be a few places that you want to do the
adaptation, right, so some common layer could be the attention
layer in the transformer or the FC layer, okay, afterwards
we will introduce two low-rank matrices, okay,
for low-rank decompositions here, right, so for each of the layer
that you decided to do the fine tuning, you will introduce two low-rank
matrices A and B, right, okay, that will approximate the
update of the changes that you need to make to the original matrix that be,
so you can see this, the view here is the original matrix from your foundation
model and this small network is actually the products
of two low-rank matrix A and B, okay, right, so initially
it's supposed to be one big matrix but a matrix but you decompose it into
two products of two low-rank matrixes
A and B here, so that's why it's known as a low-rank decomposition,
a matrix is decomposed into the products of two
low-rank matrices and then therefore when you do
the fine tuning for your target application, right, so this
the view is frozen, we only update these two small matrices,
okay, A and B, right, so the output now
is actually coming from your foundation model as well as
these two, the products of these two matrices, okay,
so this is your new output now, okay, and afterwards you can then
introduce these two low-rank matrices and afterwards
you can fine tune the model, right, so fine tune the model means that
you freeze this foundation, the original weight matrix, you
only update these two matrices, right, okay, so just like
what is being shown here, so during your fine tuning
for your target Douser application, you present some, your new data
you have your desired output, okay, Y cap, you compare them
and then you get the error and then you back propagate to update
these two matrices, okay, A and B only
right, okay, and afterwards
once it's fully trained, right, then afterwards you can
evaluate the performance of your adapted model, okay, and afterwards if necessary
you can do some optimization, right, which involve
for example hyper parameter tuning, so this hyper parameter
tuning could be, for example, you may want to change the value of this R
right, to see what kind of value is a suitable value for you
to achieve the goal, yeah, among other things,
okay, and afterwards you evaluate your model, right, once your model
is performance satisfactory, then you proceed to deploy and monitor
its performance, so that's a basic idea of Lora,
so this is the key equation that defines the Lora, okay,
okay, so next we'll move on to Quantize Lora
or QLora
okay, for some of you if you have
look at this before, you are probably familiar or you have encountered this
QLora before, so QLora is just a more efficient way
of performing Lora, okay, so it's a more efficient way
of finding a tuning of foundation more than Lora
so it use a few different tricks, right, so that as the name suggests number one
use the quantization and then also it use other things
like trying to perform the double quantization, right,
also use some digital, more intelligent ways of representing
the information using the integer for representation
and some memory swap operation that we'll see later, right,
so QLora actually combined Lora, the one that we have seen
before with the quantization, right, to
optimize the performance, okay, so QLora
as I mentioned is using Lora as a baseline method to improve
and this Lora is a parameter if you see a fine tuning method
as mentioned earlier on, right, so you add a small
trainable network that has a small number of parameters
while keeping the original weight of the foundation
model frozen, okay, so this slide here
shows some of the key difference
between the original fine tuning
the Lora as well as the QLora here, right, so this figure here shows
that, okay, so this full fine tuning means that assuming that if you do not
use any adapter at all, you have a foundation model and you decide
to fine tune all the weights in your foundation model directly
by brute force, so this is this visualizations here
so in that case, for example, your foundation model, your base model
typically you use 16 bits representant and currently foundation
this transformer is one of the most popular
model use in FM, okay, so right, typically
if you want to train this particular base model or foundation
model, your optimizer, right, need to have a larger, more
precise representation, so for foundation model usually we use
16 bits but for your optimizer usually we use 32 bits
to store the more accurate information to do the training, right, so
therefore if you use a brute force, you can see that, right, the number of parameters
that you need to train is quite a lot, right, and then
this, you know, the storage, the kind of
weight, right, the parameter that you need to store to train your foundation
model is also quite big, you can see it as illustrated by this
big box which means there are lots of parameters that need to be stored
to do the training, so as opposed to that for
Laura, just now we say that, okay, so what we need to do is we only
need to introduce those small networks, A times B, alright, okay, so
those two small matrices, A times B, the storage
that's required is much smaller, okay, so therefore it's much smaller
the number of parameters that need to be trained is much smaller here,
okay, so when we want to fine tune this particular
foundation model here, so what we do is we don't train this foundation model
directly, the foundation model is frozen, but we only train this
small adapter, so this is a small adapter that needs to be trained, and because
an adapter is much smaller, that means the storage that you need to do
for your optimizer is also smaller here, okay, so this is
the ideas of Laura, for Qlora it actually
improved upon this Laura, so what it does is that first of all
it introduced a four-bit representation, so as opposed
to six-bit, now it used the four-bit representation, so that's the first
improvement with respect to Laura, okay, so the second one is that
in the process of performing these steps here, perform what is known as
double quantization to further reduce the number of parameters,
alright, so shortly we'll see, and then finally, they also
have this memory management scheme that they find, for example
if this particular memory in this GPU is going to
overflow, then we'll swap some of the memory into the CPU from
the operation perspective, right, so this is the basic difference
between Qlora and Laura, okay, so let's look at the key
ideas of this Qlora, so as mentioned Qlora
actually works, it's based on Laura, okay, but it just suggests
a few further improvements, so the first improvement is the
four-bit normal float representation, known as the MF4,
okay, so we'll see later on, so this is a new data
structure that make it more suitable for data which is
following certain distribution, for example the data that you have
what it may be following certain normal distribution, that means
certain kind of central value occur more often than the others, so
it leverage on this particular property to design a new
data type which is known as the MF4,
right, okay, second is that it also make use of a double quantization,
so right, when you use this Qlora,
first of all you will be using some quantization constant
to quantize Qlora, and then for this quantization constant
you further perform quantization on it, alright, so it's a more
intelligent way of performing the quantization known as
the double quantization, so this will allow it to reduce the
memory footprint, okay, and then third
is that it have this page optimizer that allow
the memory swap between the GPU and the CPU
more effectively, okay, so these are the four, three key
properties of Qlora, okay, so
let's look at the first one, the four-bit normal float representations
here, right, so you can see that for most of the parameters
that you are trying to find Qlora update, typically it doesn't
occur uniformly, right, it's not uniformly distributed,
but rather the more the parameter distribution is actually
Gaussian distribution or normal distribution that looks like this,
okay, so therefore as opposed to the traditional way
of performing the quantization or representations
of the four-bit numbers, right, so traditionally
if you want to represent a certain number
using a four-bit number, what you'll do is that you'll divide this particular
bin equally or evenly like this, okay,
but you can see that this particular approach is probably not
so suitable for data, right, that has
Gaussian or normal distribution, because we know that for normal distribution
most of the data is going to be occurring near this range here,
okay, near this range here, so if we use that evenly
spaced kind of bucket of bin, right, then you'll see that, right,
so these bins here are going to be underutilized, yeah,
but whereas the bins here actually is just too big, so you cannot provide
sufficient detail, so therefore instead of that, right,
for this particular case here, what they do is that they try to change
the size of the bucket based on the probability, okay, so we can
see now the bucket size here is that for this range of
the value which the probability occurrence is much smaller,
it decided to use a larger bin, right, for this range of the
value where as you can see the probability is much larger, it decided to use a smaller
bin so that you can provide more resolution, right,
for those range of value, but that is
going to happen more often, so that's a basic idea, right,
so they adjust the size of the bin based on the probability
whereas this data is going to occur, which is normally near
the central of your normal distribution, okay, so
this four bin normal float data type representation,
right, the high level idea is going to encode number only for bits,
okay, so it's an optimal quantization technique like what
I mentioned before to represent those normally
distributed data, right, and it will supposedly give better
results than the typical evenly spaced
four bits representation, right, so that's the first
improvement of this Q-Lorah, right, the second
one is that it uses a technique known as a double quantization, right, so
when we try to, because in order to reduce the number of parameter that need to
be stored, right, so this Q-Lorah, they perform quantization, so
they use some quantization parameter to quantize this KPC, right, this
value, it has divided by the quantization parameter, so
this quantization parameter or constant
is further quantized again, right, so it's quantized twice,
so this is a technique to further reduce the parameter,
okay, so double quantization treats the quantization constant
of the first quantization as input to the second quantization,
in other words, it just performs quantization twice, so by doing that
it can reduce the number of parameter storage further,
okay, right, so there are some detail which also
involve partition the model parameter into smaller blocks
for further quantization, but I think there's no need for us to go into
too much details here, for those of you interested, you
can go into that a bit more, right, okay, so the
third improvement is the page optimizer that I mentioned, so sometimes
when your GPU is kind of memory is almost full, then
you will sort some of the memory with the CPU, so
you perform the automatic page-to-page transfer between the CPU and the
GPU, when your GPU is kind of, the memory is
full and almost running out of memory, okay, so it's a management
kind of a process, okay, so
right, so far we have actually introduced about the
general ideas of adapter, okay, right, so we have also introduced
about Lora and Qura, so the next thing we are going to look at it
is the prefix tuning, so as mentioned
earlier on, the idea of prefix tuning is quite simple, that means prefix
tuning means that you are going to introduce some
learnable tokens or embeddings in front of your foundation model, so this
is a foundation model, you are going to introduce some learnable
embedding or tokens, right, known as a prefix before your network, so
you are going to use this way to help to provide
some information, right, to your network, because you know your foundation
model is actually very large and you do want to touch it
because it's too expensive, so many different ways are thinking of different
ways to introduce a small network
to achieve the goal of only training this small network,
so earlier on we already see this foundation model, there are people who try to
put some adapter in series, okay, known as a series adapter,
there are also, this is a foundation model, there are also method which is trying to put
some small network in parallel, okay, this is called a parallel
adapter, so among them, for example, Lora and Qura
actually is based on this idea that you put
parallel adapter, so there are also some other people who think that, okay, this is a foundation model, if I cannot
change this foundation model, maybe one way that I can do is that I can
modify or train the prefix that we put
into this particular foundation model, so this is the idea that's coming from,
yeah, so probably by putting in some prefix and
train the prefix, such that this prefix can then
modify your target output for your downstream application, this is one way
that we can achieve the fine tuning, so that's a basic high level
idea, okay, so prefix tuning is a technique to train
FM, right, by
prepending, that means we add in some information in front, okay, by
prepending a sequence of learnable vectors, so this learnable
vectors is also known as embedding or prefix
to the model, okay, so therefore by doing that we can
modify the input representation,
right, okay, so we modify the input representation
because now this prefix is interpreted as an input to
your foundation model, right, so we train this particular small
prefix, all right, without touching the foundation model, so
we modify this input representation, prefix is part of the input
rather than modify the internal representation
of the foundation model, okay, so this will make it into a lightweight
and efficient technique, okay, so before that maybe
again is what we can do is that we can use this figure to very quickly visualize
what is the basic principles of prefix tuning
and afterwards we'll go back to the slides to look at the steps.
Okay, so this particular diagram is showing that, right, suppose if you want to
we have a foundation model and suppose now
we have three downstream applications, one is to do the
table text, the other is summarization and the other
is the kind of a translation, suppose if you're a foundation model
and you have these three downstream applications, if you use the
brute force approach to retrain your foundation model
fully, that is very cumbersome, so
this is the illustration I was trying to say, suppose if you take this particular
foundation model and you try to find it fully
for three different target downstream applications, then you need
to have three different copies of the fine-tuned
or adapted foundation model for three different applications,
right, so this is not very, you know, kind of efficient
because fine-tuning of the foundation model is already very
expensive and you need to keep a few different copies of
your fine-tuned foundation model for different downstream applications,
so not very efficient, so how do we do that using the prefix tuning
so what we do in the prefix tuning is that we have this particular
foundation model, we do not touch, the structure we do not touch, what we do
is that now for different downstream application, right
table to text summarization or translation, similar to this
we just train this prefix here, so this prefix are actually
some vectors or some embedding that you can train,
together with the small network connections here, so
these are small embedding
of vectors together with the network that you can train for each downstream
application, so therefore for this downstream application, table to text, you only
need to train this prefix, okay, for the second application
you only need to train this prefix and the third application you only need to train
the other prefix, so therefore by doing that you'll be able to
reduce the amount of training as well as storage
because most of this particular small network that you are training, the prefix
is going to be used jointly with a single
foundation model that's frozen, okay, so that's a basic advantage
as well as the idea, right, in prefix tuning, you
can see also this prefix now is serving as part of the input representation,
so it's training of this input representation rather than
the parameters in this foundation model,
okay, so with that basic understanding, let's look at the key steps in the prefix
tuning, so first of all you're going to introduce the sequence of learnable vectors of
prefix, like just now the one that we've shown, right, so this prefix are
additional tokens, okay, you can call it token, vectors,
embeddings, right, okay, that is added to
the original input tokens, right, so now this particular input
sequence now will include this new prefix that we've introduced
in addition to the original, right, tokens that you use to train
your network, okay, right, so this will allow
the prefix, right, the information in front that is used to
inference the model internal representation to generate the output, so that
this output now can compare with the output of your downstream
application, right, to get the error and this error can then be back-brokered
to train your prefix, okay, so during
training, right, during the fine tuning, only the prefix embedding is
trained, the rest of the model parameter in the foundation model is frozen,
right, so this prefix can learn task-specific feature that help
the model to adapt, like what's being shown here, right, so depending on
different application, this prefix here, right, can be fine-tuned
to customize for specific downstream application.
Okay, so next, after we have introduced
the prefix tuning, so this prompt tuning is actually very similar
to prefix tuning, right, so prompt, I mean for many of you
you have learned LLM before, you know that when you want to use that LLM
you usually need to provide a prompt or a question
to prompt this particular LLM to respond, so this
prompt tuning therefore, idea-wise is actually very similar to the prefix tuning,
except for this prompt tuning is a little bit more flexible, this prompt
tuning can be either in the form of some language text or it can
be also be in the form of LLM, you know,
embedding similar to the prefix tuning, but idea-wise is very similar.
Yeah, so this idea
of prompt tuning actually is very similar to prefix tuning, right, so
okay, so this figure on the left is just trying to show that, right,
if you use a brute force and you try to train your
LLM, you know, I mean you try to fine-tune
your whole LLM, right, so this is very expensive, okay, and this
is actually not the way we usually do it in our
kind of downstream application, but rather
for prompt tuning, we keep this pre-trained foundation model frozen,
this LLM is a language model, which is a type of foundation model,
but we only introduce this prompt here, and then we only fine-tune
these prompts here, right, so this prompt is actually a sequence of
embedding or token or vectors similar to prefix tuning,
yeah, except it can be a bit more flexible, right, so you can see the idea
is very similar to the prefix tuning,
right, so okay, with that visualization, next we can look at the
information here, it's a technique used to use prompt to
guide the model's behavior, so this is the prompt here, so this prompt
here is actually a sequence of vectors or a sequence of
embedding or, you know, a sequence of prompts, right, so whichever way
you prefer to use it term, okay, so this prompt
can either be some static, which is some fixed text,
all right, or it can be dynamic, which is some learnable embedding,
so if it's a learnable embedding, that is just like the prefix learning
that I've introduced to you before, right, so do you fine-tuning
these prompt embedding are trained similar to prefix tuning, right,
whereas the parameter in your foundation model is frozen, okay,
so yeah, we also again, we only modify
the model's input to guide its response without changing
the foundation model internal parameter, right, so the
difference compared to the prefix tuning is that, prefix tuning
right, we assume that
we only use the learnable vectors or embedding, but for
prompt, it can either be text prompt or learnable
embedding, so actually, right, in short, this prefix tuning and prompt
tuning, conceptually, they are just almost the same, yeah, it's just that
prompt tuning is a little bit more broader, it can include
either text or it can be including some
learnable vectors or embeddings, yeah,
right, okay, so yeah, so
basically just now, we have introduced a few broad categories of how do we fine-tune
a foundation model, right, such as LLM, so in section one
we covered the following, okay, we covered the current state of the art
based on a foundation model and how do we adapt or fine-tune a foundation
model, okay, so next we're going to move on to
section two, which is on LLM
okay, so under this, we are going to cover the following, first a quick introduction
of LLM, right, and then afterwards we introduce what is BERC, okay, what is
GPT, some well-known LLM as well as some recent emerging
training, right, so what is LLM, I think all of
you know that, what is LLM, so LLM is a type of foundation model, but specifically
it's an AI model that handle, you know,
human language, so it's an AI model that can understand, generate
and manipulate human language, right, okay,
so what are some of the key features of LLM, right, so we know that for
LLM is a large scale, a massive scale
that means you train with a large number of data and also this information
is captured in a large model, right, that has billions
of parameters, okay, so therefore it's actually massive scale
right, that has a large parameter and also
train with a large number of data so that it can acquire
a good understanding of various linguistic
tasks, okay, so the training, by now you should know, training is
trained using a large number of data, right, okay,
so once it's fully trained,
it has many capabilities as some of you already know, since you have been
dealing with this LLM before, so it has strong capability, it can
handle various tasks such as translation, summarization,
no, sentiment analysis and so on and so forth, so it has very strong capability
and because of this capability, it's used in many different applications
right, so many applications that you have seen before, chat box,
conversation, so on and so forth, but it also
has some challenges like what we mentioned before, for example bias,
so it will be bias based on what kind of data it's being trained on, if the data
is for example trained on Western kind of language, then it will be
bias to work stuff, okay, misuse, sometimes
it can be useful, no,
purpose which is not suitable and also the impact, right, nowadays for example,
this LLM can be extended to coding, right, so that it can affect
potentially the life of the programmer, so I think
a few weeks ago actually I heard
an interview by the NVIDIA CEO, I think Janice Nguong,
so actually he mentioned that, right, actually one of the interviewer
should be now, nowadays
trained people to be the programmer, actually the CEO
NVIDIA CEO, his answer is not to train anyone
learning programming any further in the future, because in the future
programming is going to be a tool that everyone can do,
so you just indicate what you want to achieve and then
with these LLM types of tools, it can generate the code automatically,
it's just like I remember when I was in early years
when I just do my bachelor's degree, we have to learn how to
write the codes for the web page, I remember one of my internship is with
Sintel, and we have to write all those codes, how to generate
password and so on, but nowadays a lot of those things you actually don't have to do it anymore,
you just have to tell them what you want to achieve, the code will be generated in the background,
so anyway we don't know, so this are
lots of potential societal impact on this, for example LLM
and more generally speaking for foundation model.
This slide shows some of the popular timelines
of LLM, you can just browse through yourself to see
are there anyone that you are not familiar with.
But for this course we are going to introduce a few important
ones, so first of all we are going to learn this bulk, so this
bulk stands for bi-directional encoder
representation from transformer, so this particular bulk
is actually dealing with the representation of the
text, so given some works that you have,
can you come up with some vector representation that can
describe this works very well, by taking into consideration
for example the relationship between other works,
their contribution towards this work. So pretty much this part
of the model is even the input token
or works, we want to generate some
factors that is a good representation of all this input
work or token.
So bulk is actually an NLP model
developed by some facts information first, so it's an NLP
model developed by Google around 2018.
So it's actually the transformer encoder, if you remember
transformer we have the encoder and we have the decoder part.
So bulk is actually corresponding to the encoder part of
the transformer. And then it also has the
bi-directional self-attention, that means when you look at this particular
works here, it's actually getting the information from the works
in the past as well as works in the future, so therefore
it's bi-directional. So it has the bi-directional self-attention.
So from what we know from the
transformer already, because of that it can understand or it can
obtain the context information, it can get the information of
all the other works that contribute to this kind of work.
It can then generalise some contextualised work embedding
that is given some work after you go through this transformer encoder
a few times, you'll be able to get a vector that is a good representation
that contains the context. So this context means that meaning
of the other works. So it can
generate a contextualised work embeddings of vectors.
So there's a few different versions, so two important
versions is the base version as well as the large version, with this
number of parameters. And then subsequently there's further improvement, so sometimes
you'll see various types of bulk. So these are some further
improvements that build upon the original bulk.
Right, so let's look at the bulk and GBT, because these
are the two very early AI models that were developed
after the transformer came up. So if you can recall
this is our transformer. So this part here
corresponds to the bulk. The encoder of the
transformer corresponds to the bulk and the decoder of
the transformer corresponds to the GBT series of data.
So bulk is for representation, that means given some
input tokens of works you want to generate vectors that can represent it
representation. And GBT is mainly focused on
generation. So given for example a work can you generate
the next work and generate the next work and so on and so forth. So its focus is on
generation. So next we are going to
look at this bulk training very quickly.
Right, okay, so the training of the bulk actually
involves two stages. The first stage is that you want to
pre-train this bulk so that it can understand the language.
So once you have understood the language structure or reasoning
then in your stage two you will then use your pre-train model
you'll do some fine tuning for some downstream application.
So that's what we have seen for many different use cases. So stage
one is to do the training. Stage two is to fine tune your
pre-train model for some downstream application.
So this is the pre-training stage.
So later on we will explain this particular
pre-training as well as the fine tuning a little bit more in detail.
But pretty much it's a two stage process. Stage one
is we do the pre-training. So this particular pre-training
is that we will provide some input tokens
and then we'll have some output target
and we'll train it such that at the end of this training here
right, you're given this particular input here, you will have
some good vector representation. So this is the
objective of the stage one which is the pre-train
your bulk. So once you have already pre-trained your bulk
here, that means this network in between here would have learned a good
understanding of the human language. And after
works, the next step is for the fine tuning then we take this pre-train
model here. So depending on what kind of application that we
have, whether it's like some question answering,
trying to file a sentiment analysis or whether these
two sentences has some relationship, we can
then use it to fine tune the network for some subsequent
downstream application. So these are two key steps.
Let's probably
see.
So let's look at the first step here.
How do we do this pre-training here? So how do we do this pre-training here?
There's actually two tasks involved in doing the pre-training of the bulk.
Number one is that you can see that for this pre-training
here, the input is unlabeled sentences of
sentence A and B.
That means actually from the general text that you have, because you're going to take the
training from the general corpus, you're going to get
sometimes some sentences which are actually together
or sentences which are not together. That means it's two consecutive
sentences or not consecutive sentences. So you have
this particular sentence A and B. If these sentences A and B
are next to each other, then we have this particular
next sentence prediction and SP is the next
sentence prediction. So depending on right from the corpus that
you obtain, whether these two sentences are together or not together, then
you can train this next sentence prediction to be either 0 or 1.
So this is one way you can train so that you can
let this particular network learns the
linguistic understanding about how the human language looks
like. So that's one thing. The second thing is that you also have this particular
masking here. Masking here means that some of this particular
works here actually will mask it.
Our goal is that we want to predict this mask length
this particular mask
here. So for example, we hide one of this work. We
want to train our network so that it can predict what is this
missing work. This is called the masking. So therefore there's these two
tasks that we train at the same time. First is this
mask language model, which is this part here. When there
are some work that we purposely hide, can we predict this work?
Mask language model. The second task it do is
that when two sentences are together, we want to train this
network so that it can predict whether two sentences are together
or not. So by doing that, actually it will train your
network, your bug model to learn to
get better vector representation as compared to your original token.
So when you get better vector representation, it also means that at the same
time you also train this underlying network
model in this model here, which is our transformer. So this is the
training steps here. So next, right
with that quick introduction, let's look at
what do we do in the pre-training. First we'll be using
unsupervised or self-supervised learning. Self-supervised or unsupervised learning
in this case, it means that you don't have any person to go
and provide the annotation. But rather this information, this
data is taken from some generous sources and corpus
and then just by looking at it, because in a lot of text you already
have all the works as well as the sentences. So
you can just simply take this information without external
annotator to provide the annotation, you can start to do the training already. So this
particular steps is known as a self-supervised. Okay, right
because you do not need external annotator to provide the annotation.
From the text instead you obtain,
you already have this supervisory signal.
So the goal is to learn language structure and context. So early
on I mentioned there are two tasks. The first one is known as the mass language
model, MLM here. So the mass language model, the goal is
that we'll hide some of the works in our input and we
want to train this network to use its surrounding context
to predict this mass work. So by using the surrounding
context to predict what is this mass work, that means you
force the model to learn the context or the relationship between the works.
Okay, right so you'll try to predict the mass work from the
surrounding works. Okay, so therefore you achieve some context learning.
Okay, so the second task is a next sentence prediction, NSP.
So you'll try to predict whether a sentence follows another in a text pair.
Alright, okay, so again by doing that you'll force this
particular bulk to learn the
language structure, to learn the logical context between sentences.
So bulk training could be leveraging on Wikipedia
or some book, Coppers, which is a large number of data
in the early model of training. Okay, so
next let's spend a bit more time to talk a little bit more about this
bulk input representations here. So for this bulk input
representations here, so first of all you have this particular
okay, so the input here actually consists of a few things. Number one
is that you have this bulk token
embedding here, okay, this part here. Alright, so
this token embedding is just like what we have studied before for the
transformer, which is given some token
embedding, you'll use a vector to represent it. Okay, so this is the part
and more specifically the token embedding scheme that they use is known
as a work piece, which consists of a 30,000
vocabulary. So therefore given some works that you have,
you'll use the vector to represent them. So after
work, right, you know that just like what we have studied before for the
transformer, the position is also important. So you also
need to include the position embedding, which is in the form of
vector. So you, therefore the positions of each of these works
right in the sentences is important. So we have this particular
position embedding which is indicated, which are actually vectors
right that indicate the positions of each works in this right
up. Okay, and then finally we also have an extra part which is known as
a segment embedding. So this segment embedding is just simply to
indicate whether it's sentence one, sentence two, sentence three, and so on and so
forth. Okay, so these are the three pieces of information. Right, so for
the input, therefore you need to have this token embedding, you need to have a vector
to represent this token of works. Right, you have
a segment embedding, which is a sentence numbering, whether it's for example
this part here is sentence A, this part is a sentence B,
you need to indicate which sentence it is. And then finally you also
need to indicate the positions of each of the works. Yeah, so this
is the position embedding. So therefore for your input representation
it consists of these three parts.
Right, okay, so yeah,
this is still a bit more detailed about the pre-training. So during
the, this the, okay, the next sentence prediction we already
mentioned to you, right, so if the two sentences are together
then, no, for example, you should predicate as one. If the two sentences are not
together, you should predicate as zero. So we know that based on that
we can actually calculate the error between the prediction and our
ground truth. We can use this particular error to go and do the
propagation to train it. Right, so this particular part of the diagram is to show
how do you do the prediction or training for this
mass language model. Right, which is one of the work we must do, but we want
to use the context to predicate. Okay, so what we have is that
right, during the training, right, suppose at one stage here you have some
vectors here and afterwards, right, you let it go through
a linear layer to project it to 30
dimensional vectors. Alright, okay, and then you let it go through a
softmax to become the probability. And then this probability
would then compare to your ground truth because when you take
the sentence, you already know what should be the work
basis. So therefore, you have this ground truth here. So this
ground truth is the one hot vector. Suppose if it's no m, then
all the values here is zero, zero, zero. m is one, the rest are all zero.
So you can compare your ground truth with your prediction to get the
error. And afterwards, this error can then be backpropagate to train
your model as well. Okay, so this is the training involved is the
mass language model. Okay, so by doing that
right, by doing that, then we can train
our bulk model. So once it's fully trained, then next we want to use it
for the downstream applications already. So once fully trained,
we'll take this particular back network here, right, and then we'll
use it for the fine tuning of the downstream
application. Right, so let's look at, you know, the fine tuning for some specific
downstream tasks. Right, so again, we'll use a supervised
okay, we'll use a supervised learning. Right, so that means
it will add a task specific module after the last encoder layer so that it can
map, right, to the target output here. So for example,
this downstream task that you have now, right, in the bulk initially
they have some specific tasks. Some of them could be, for example,
right, you have a question, for example, this squad here. So this squad
is actually a data set coming from Stanford. So what it does is that
right, it asks a question, okay, and then this answer is
actually lying inside a paragraph. Okay, it asks the question, and
the answer is actually in a paragraph here. So you can actually indicate where
is the starting point and the ending point of this answer in this
paragraph here. So that's the problem statements here. So for example,
if you want to, you know, take this pre-trained model
and then update or fine-tune it for your downstream
squad kind of a problem statement, which is you give it a question.
The answer is actually lying within the paragraph and you just
indicate where is the starting position and the ending
positions in this paragraph that contain the answer. Okay,
so if you want to do that, so what you need to do is that
in this particular fine-tuning task, you take this model here,
you just introduce a small network here, okay, which could
be for example a few layers of MLP here,
right, okay, to predict the starting point and the ending point.
So therefore you can see internally is the same, but we just introduce a small network here.
Right, okay, so doing the fine-tuning
would present it with for example question one, paragraph one, and then
the start and end for
this first training data, okay, and then you get the
loss and then you're used to train this network here. And afterwards you present
the second question, second paragraph, and then
the desire output for the start and
end. And afterwards you can get the error, you can then train this small network here.
Okay, so that's a basic idea, right, so you can use
supervised learning, you add a task-specific module which is
here, okay, after the last encoded layer, so you can see this
the last encoded layer, so after the last encoded layer, so that you can learn,
okay, you can train this small network here. Okay, so the
example here is the question-answer task, right, which is this
squat here, right, so you will train two extra vectors here, right, so you want to
train this start and end vectors here. To mask the beginning
and end of the answer from this paragraph, okay, you have a question here
that and the answer is lying inside this paragraph as I mentioned,
right, so you want to indicate where's the starting point and the ending point in this paragraph
that contain the answer, yeah. Okay, so
yeah, this idea can then be extended to many different
language kind of tasks, for example, sentiment analysis, text summarization, and so on and so forth,
but we will not go into the detail.
Right, okay, so in terms of performance evaluation, therefore your pre-trained
model, you can then use it for many subsequent tasks, so
a lot of this task has to do with the human language understanding,
right, okay, that either is involving image
pair, right, or a single sentence, right, so I think
this is a little bit more in detail, probably we don't have to go into the details
up. Suffice to say that once you have this
book, you have trained it, right, you take this pre-trained model, you can
then do the fine-tuning for the downstream task, and the downstream task
typically involves designing a small network at the
last layer to do the training of the small network.
Okay, right, so this
general language understanding task as well as the
standard question answering data set, so these are some data set that you can
use to train the performance of your trained
book model, okay, right, so we will not go into some of these details, so
each of these diagram here is just showing some of the
downstream tasks, how you define it, okay, probably
I'll just take one more, for example, one of these is a sentiment analysis, so if you
present an input sentence, right, your output here, see
here, you train a network to classify whether, what kind of sentiment
this sentence is, is it positive, negative, or neutral,
right, so you just train a small network here to do the prediction, okay,
so others I will probably would not go into it.
All right, okay, so it's a piece to say that, you know, at the
time when it was proposed, actually this book that will actually outperform
many other different networks at the time, right,
okay, so we have actually looked at the,
just now the book, next we are going to look at GPT, so
generative between transformer, right, so this is the, in the, like, the early
stage of GPT, of us we know that GPT have gone through many different iterations,
right, okay, so this diagram again, so
earlier we have already looked at book, so this is focusing on representation,
so next we'll look at the GPT, which is focusing on the generation,
right, so the basic idea of GPT, actually we
have already studied before, which is, you know, during the training, right, you just
want to use, you know, okay, so when you take the text for the
scopers, you already have structures of different works, yeah, you have different works here,
so the GPT idea is very simple, you just use the current
works that have been generated, okay, for example you have a few generated works, you
put into your decoder and then you try to predict what is the
next work that is going to come out, okay, so that's the basic
ideas of the GPT, yeah, so GPT is an AI
model, right, okay, it's trained on a vast amount of
text, right, okay, so elaboration, self-supervised
learning, just like what I mentioned before, because the information that
you obtain already contain this superficially information, because you already
have, you know, the structure of the works, so you can use, you know,
the works that you obtain from the scopers, any
coppers to do the training without any external annotator here,
right, so you leverage self-supervised learning to train large amount,
to use large amount unlabeled data to train
your large language model, right, so it can be used for many tasks like generation,
translation and so on, right, it's focusing on the
transformed decoder expects here, right, so the coppers that used to do
the training, for example Wikipedia coppers, right, so
the pre-training is quite simple, right, it's pretty much as I
mentioned during the transformer, which is you try, even some
works that you have already predicted, use it to predict the next work,
right, so once you predict the next work, right, and then use the following to predict the flowing
works, yeah, so this is what we mentioned before, a few times
we explained about the transformer, so you try to predict the next
token or works from the previous sequence of tokens that you have predicted
so far, okay, right, so this is the general
pre-training, so for the fine-tuning stage, once you have actually
you know, have a pre-trained GPT
model, you can then actually use it to do the fine-tuning,
so for the fine-tuning what you can do is that you can come up with some task-specific
prompts, okay, for the model to learn, yeah, so once you have for example a trained
GPT here, you can ask it some questions, for example
the case that we mentioned before is the factory
suppose you have a GPT which is initially trained for a
broad-based kind of application, but now you have a company which says that
I don't really care so much about the general GPT, I want you to be able to
develop a model that can answer the questions for the operations of
my factory, yeah, so what you can do then is that you can take this pre-trained
model, right, okay, so you can, during the fine-tuning
what you can do is that you can ask some specific questions for your
operations of factory, for example how do I fix this machine A,
so how do I fix this machine A, you can then put in as a prompt
and then your output here would be your target answer
from your manual, for example in your company or in your factory you have
some, you know with this question you have a standard answer, right, so you can
then present the standard answer and then you can then fine-tune your network
here, right, your pre-trained model already, yeah, you can
either, you know, you can either fine-tune the whole model or you
can use techniques such as we have mentioned before like the adapter to only
train a small network to do the fine-tuning, okay, but the general
idea is this, yeah, so during the fine-tuning you can use some
task-specific prompt, right, depending on your use case, right, you
can use your target output and then you can train your network by, for example, introducing
some adapter to do that, okay,
so right, therefore, right, so this part here summarized what we have
mentioned before, right, so in terms of the recent developments of the
LLM, so first we have the BERT-based series which is a
representation and some variation arising of it, we also
have those models that focus on the generation, especially GPT series,
okay, and then there's also some model which is
actually training jointly between the transformer and
decoder, okay, for example, T5, so you have three broad categories
of the LLM architecture, one is focusing on the encoder
only, such as BERT, alright, okay, so
just now, for example, BERT we already covered, for the pre-training the focus on
mass language modeling or next sentence prediction, so
it is good for classification types of application, so the second
class of the AI model focusing on the decoder side of the
transformer only, which is for generation, such as GPT, so
they are training, pre-training mainly focus on the next work or token
prediction, right, so it's good for generalization tasks
okay, and generally speaking for this GPT actually
it can achieve better generalization after the pre-train
okay, there are also some AI models that look at both
the encoder and transformer training of them together, right, such as
T5, T5 refers to text to text transfer transformer
okay, right, so the pre-training is that you provide some
input as a text and then you use some output as a text as well, for example
the most common one is language translation, your English, your input
could be French and your output is English, so this, no, for
this model you'll be training your transformer as your encoder
and the decoder at the same time, so therefore it can also
be involving the encoder and decoder training together
as well, so this type of task is suitable for applications such as
machine translation
okay, so with that, next let's move on to some well-known LLM here
right, okay, so there are quite a number of well-known LLM
probably the most famous one is GPT, so GPT4O is one of the recent one but
not the newest one because it gets come out so quickly, so
GPT4O right, is one of the well-known LLM models, so it's right, so we'll just
go through the facture information quickly, so it's developed by OpenAI
so you can see the number of parameters, more than 175 billion, so it's a very big model
right, you can access it through API call, so you call this
your batch processor data, you call the API and then you return the result
if you want to run it for your experiment, okay, it released in May 24th
right, so there's a previous iterations of the GPT,
alright, okay, so it has stronger multimodal capability now
okay, and it can also respond in real time, I mean for those
of you who have seen the video before, you can see it's quite, it responds very quickly
right, okay, so another popular M that we have is LLMA, LLMA3
right, it's actually a more recent version as well, so it's developed by Meta
alright, which is the company by Facebook and Instagram, so the parameter again
you can see is very big, okay, there's a few different version, right, with large number of parameters
right, so one good thing about LLMA is open access, that means you can actually download it
and you can try out for your own experiment, okay, released in April 24th
right, so there's a previous iteration, so the performance is probably as good
as GPT for, but it's at a lower cost, right, so you can install it on your local system
right, yeah, so which is good, and also it partially
address the privacy concern because you can download the model, you can actually do the training
in your local machine, so you don't always have to upload your data through the cloud
right, because there are some privacy concerns, okay, so it's actually ideal for AI researcher
to do this performance, right, you can adapt it right, as well as open source
right, so therefore LLMA is actually quite popular open source LLMA model
right, the other one is a Germany which is by Google, right, so I think these are some
factual information, there's a few different variations, right, okay, released in April 24th
right, previously it's known as BAC, right, but they rename it into this Germany
right, okay, so there's a few different models for different use cases, right, it can handle various things
like image, audio, voice and so on, right, okay, so next we'll just look at chat GPT a little bit more
right, so this chat GPT 4.0 right, is for a more natural human computer interaction
right, so your input can now be not just voice, it can be text, it can be image, it can be video and so on
right, likewise the output can also be that, not just simply no text, it can be text, it can be image, it can be so on
right, okay, so it's a single end-to-end model that handle different modality, you can see that the response time is quite fast
that's why for those of you who have seen the demo before, it's as if you're talking to another person
right, actually I've seen some video on Xiao Hongsu before, they put two models of the GPT and then they're talking to each other
which is actually, I think probably some of you have seen before, which is quite interesting, it's like two person talking nonsense
but actually it makes sense as well, they're talking to each other
right, okay, so it improves on other non-English language, that means you can handle other languages as well
okay, so it's quite good, right, achieve good vision and audio understanding
right, okay, so for those of you who have not seen some of this, the capability of GPT 4.0, here I'll just play you a few short video clips
to let you be impressed by currently what GPT can do, right, or overall this LLM and foundation model can do
so let me just play the video
hey, so guess what, I've got a huge interview coming up and I really would love your help preparing for it
that's fantastic news, I'd be thrilled to help you get ready, what's the interview for and how can we start preparing?
it's a software engineering role and I was thinking you could do kind of a rapid-fire mock interview
okay, maybe let me just input the cat fit
maybe ask me three questions and at the end you can give me some feedback
great idea, let's dive straight in, first question, can you tell me about a challenging technical problem you solved in your previous projects and how you approached it?
yeah, well at my previous company we were developing an app, originally it was on one platform
but then when we supported another platform we had to find a way to synchronize the data across both platforms
so we had to build a synchronization engine to handle that and we ended up open sourcing it and it was useful for a lot of other projects
that sounds like a really impactful project, especially since it went open sourcing benefited others
now for the second question, how do you typically approach learning a new programming language or technology?
yeah, it's a great question, I think the best way to learn any new technology is to just start using it
starting with small projects and building up from there, I think I've learned a lot that way
hands-on experience is definitely a solid approach, now for the third and final
go on
sure thing, how do you handle tight deadlines or pressure when working on a project?
I think the key there is prioritization, you know I think taking the time up front to be really clear about what's important and what can wait will make a big difference
absolutely, prioritizing tasks effectively can make a huge difference under tight deadlines, great answers
your responses show a solid mix of technical skill and thoughtful approach
for feedback, I'd say you did an excellent job concisely explaining your experiences and approach
just remember to keep your examples as relevant as possible to the job you're applying for
anything else you'd like to practice or go over?
no, I think that's it but any other constructive feedback, I want to really make sure I'm ready here
you've got a strong foundation and I can see your thoughtful and your responses, just a couple of things to find too
first, in your answers, try to weave in specific examples that highlight your skills and achievements
especially those relevant to the job you're applying for, this will make your responses more memorable and impactful
second, be concise but thorough, it's a balancing act but the goal is to give enough detail to be informative without overloading the interviewer with information
I see, I see, anything about my body language, was my delivery okay?
your body language was generally positive and engaging, you maintained good eye contact and seemed attentive which is great
one note though, try to avoid touching your face too much, it can be distracting and might give off signs of nervousness
overall, you came across as thoughtful and focused which is exactly what you want
okay, I think I'm ready, thank you
hey, I'm writing a story, I'm gonna...
okay, so you can see currently you can use as a tool to really help you to rehearse for interview
you can also have this particular vision, kind of thing to see whether you're facial expressions, whether you appear to be confident and so on
so it's actually quite good nowadays, I think as most of you probably already know
and I want you to see something like...
okay, so the next one is actually, you can also use GPT to solve some maths problem
right, so probably this one I also played, but the rest probably I'll just let you...
hey, I invited myself and my son Imran here to try out some of their new technology
so we're curious about how good it might be at tutoring someone in math on Khan Academy
so let's get it started, it's loading up
alright, we sure can see our screen
actually, in this form...
hello there, I'm here with my son and I'd love you to tutor him on this math problem
but don't give him the answer, you can ask questions and nudge him in the right direction
but I really want to make sure he understands it himself
and he's here in the room so you can talk to him directly
of course, I'd be happy to help
let's look at the problems together
can you first identify which sides of the triangle are the opposite adjacent antipotenuse relative to angle alpha?
alright, so I'm pretty sure this is the angle alpha right here, right?
ficked, current's cracked
now, looking at the triangle, which side do you think is the hypotenuse?
um...
remember the hypotenuse?
I'm not totally sure, I think it might be this one but I really am not sure, this side AC
you're close, actually side AC is called the adjacent side to the angle alpha
the hypotenuse is the longest side of a right triangle and is directly opposite the right angle
can you find which one is the hypotenuse?
oh, okay, I see, so I think the hypotenuse is this really long side from A to B
would that be correct?
exactly, well done
now that you've identified the hypotenuse, can you identify which side is the opposite side to angle alpha?
okay, well, I mean you told me earlier that this was the adjacent side
and I know that's the hypotenuse so I'm guessing that this side BC is the opposite side
great, the dexon, that's absolutely correct
now that you've identified all the sides, relative...
okay, so I guess from the short video clip you already can sense that nowadays they are really good
they can handle, no, this not just language, they can handle vision, they can handle codes and many different aspects
right?
angle alpha
alright, okay, so the next video is about coding
so again, I'll just play a short segment of the clip and then just give a few about what it can do as a coding assistant
so let me take out a computer for this
okay, so I'm gonna open the chatGPT desktop app like Mira was talking about before
okay, and to give a bit of background of what's going on, so here we have a computer and on the screen we have some code
and then the chatGPT voice app is on the right
so chatGPT will be able to hear me but it can't see anything on the screen
so I'm gonna highlight the code, command see it and then that will send it to chatGPT
and then I'm gonna talk about the code to chatGPT
hey chatGPT
hey there, how's it going?
yeah, it's going really well, I was wondering if you could help me with a coding problem today
of course, I'd love to help you out
what's the coding problem you're dealing with?
okay, I'm gonna share with you some code, one second
sure thing, take your time
okay, so I just shared some code with you
could you give me a really brief one sentence description of what's going on in the code?
this code fetches daily weather data for a specific location and time period
smooths the temperature data using a rolling average
annotates a significant weather event on the resulting plot
and then displays the plot with the average, minimum and maximum temperatures over the year
awesome, thanks so much
and in the code there's this function foo
can you describe to me what the plot would look like if I had versus didn't have this function?
sure, the function foo xy takes in a data frame x containing temperature data
and a window size y for calculating the rolling mean
it smooths the average temperature, minimum temperature and maximum temperature columns
by applying a rolling mean over the specified window
with the foo function, the plot would show smoother temperature lines
because the rolling mean reduces the noise or fluctuations in the data
awesome, thanks so much, so yeah, I definitely will want to apply this function
and so I'm gonna generate the plot and then show it to you, give me one second
absolutely, take your time, I'm excited to see the plot when you're ready
yeah, so so far chatGPT has only been able to see the code
and now I'm gonna run it and then I'll use the vision capability
okay, so again from this statement video you can see that right now
this note is actually progressing by lips and bounce very quickly
these are the chatGPT
okay, so in addition to that you can also use any of this
foundation model to do a text to image generation
just provide some text, right, it can generate various kind of image
and even now this, you can start to generate videos like some of you probably heard about the Sora
a few months ago, yeah
okay, so this slide shows the performance of some of the popular LLM models
right, so you can see for different tasks and then for different LLM models
yeah, they are performing actually quite well
okay, and then next we'll look at some of the emerging train
so yeah, so this is the more recent versions of the, this is the open AI model called O1
right, so it can be used to do some reasoning, coding again
so again I'll play a short segment of this more recent versions of open AI models to perform reasoning
the first of the problem I would like to show is an interesting like common sense reasoning thing
that all the previous type of LLM models didn't do that great
which is about physics and about physical objects in the relationship
the problem reads assuming the laws of physics on Earth
a small strawberry is put in a normal cup and the cup is placed upside down on a table
someone then takes the cup and puts it inside the microwave
where is the strawberry and explains the reasoning behind it
it's a simple problem every human will know straight away what is the answer
but it's something that language models are struggling a little bit
and then we can see how does this model do it
and you can also like a little bit have a glimpse on what is happening in the head of the model
and we also get a pretty nice answer of like you know what happened
why it happened in this particular scenario
the model needed to spend a little bit more time thinking about it
and analyzing what it actually happened there
the model has a bit of a harder time thinking
especially about like scenarios involving physical objects
and you need a little bit more time thinking for that
okay so it's a short video that talks about open AI reasoning
the first of the problem
okay so next one is a short video about a more recent version of the coding
alright so the example I'm going to show is writing a code for visualization
so I sometimes teach a class on transformers
which is a technology behind models like chat pt
and when you give a sentence to chat pt
it has to understand the relationship between the words and so on
so it's a sequence of words and you just have to model that
and transformers utilize what's called a self-attention to model that
so I always thought okay if I can visualize a self-attention mechanism
and with some interactive components to it it would be really great
I just don't have the skills to do that so let's ask our new model
O1 Preview to help me out on that
so I just typed in this command and see how the model does
so unlike the previous models like GPT-40
it will think before outputting an answer
so it started thinking
as it's thinking let me show you what are some of these requirements
I'm giving a bunch of requirements to think through
so first one is like use an example sentence the quick brown fox
and second one is like when hovering over a token visualizes edges
whose thickness is proportional to the attention score
and that means if the two words are more relevant
then have a thicker edges and so on
so the one common failure in most of the existing models
is that when you give a lot of the instructions to follow
it can miss one of them
just like humans can miss one of them if you give too many of them at once
so because this reasoning model can think very slowly and carefully
it can go through each requirement in depth
and that reduces the chance of missing the instruction
so this output code let me copy paste this into a terminal
so I'm going to use the editor of 2024
so Vim HTML
so I'm just going to paste this thing into that
and save it up
and on the browser I'll just try to open this up
and you can see that when I hover over this thing
it shows the arrows
and then quick and brown and so on
and when I hover out of it it goes away
so that's a correctly rendered version of it
and when I click on it it shows the attention scores
as I asked for
and maybe there's a little bit of rendering like it's overlapping
but other than that it's actually much better than what I could have done
yeah so this model did really nicely
I think this can be a really useful tool for me to come up with a bunch of
different visualisation tools for my new teaching sessions
okay so let's continue on as I mentioned
today we'll probably try to push through all the content
so that we can have an early dismissal
rather than having a break in between
we can probably leave a bit earlier
so in recent year one emerging trend is that now we are going to put all these
different aspects to the multi-model
text, image, video, different kind of sensing modality and so on
so in recent year this is a very active research area known as a multi-model LOM
so you can see just in recent year for example 2004
how many different models has been developed
so what is a multi-model LOM?
so it's a model that is capable of understanding on generating different data modality
text, image, audio, video and so on
so it will leverage on multi-model input and output
so both input and output that is working on include different types of modality
that we have mentioned just now
and then it also supports cross-model understanding
for example sometimes if you just simply use a text alone to try to understand image it may not be sufficient
so you need to have text, you need to have image or video
to ensure a more complete understanding
so and also to make sure that across different modality
the text and the image that align and you can understand them properly
so cross-model understanding means that you allow the model to link information across different modality
for example between text and image
so because now you have a different modality
so you will be training with a diverse set of data
text, image and so on
so further because you are training across different modality, different sensing and so on
you now will have a more complete understanding
and context understanding of the content you are trying to look at
so as opposed to single model approach
now you have a better model understanding
so the applications of multi-modal LLM there are a lot of visual question answering
for example you give an image and you can ask a question
for example how many cats are there in this image
or what is the cat doing to the dog
so give an image, you can ask a question and then they will answer it
image captioning, give an image you want to generate a caption
text to image or image to the text generation
audio visual processing
so there are many many possible applications
so some of the multi-modal LLM that you have is
ChagGPT4 is one of them
Lava and many others as shown in the figure
so I will probably just play one last video
to give kind of a quick introduction of what is this
an emerging multi-modal LLM
our network issues slowing down your business growth
Meta AI is back again with an exciting new model job
the LLMA DIMIT point 2 model series
this marks Meta AI's first open source multi-modal model
and it's available in two variants
11 billion and 90 billion parameters
LLMA 3.2 is actually designed as a drop in replacement for LLMA 3.1
but its performance surpasses expectations
current benchmarks show that the LLMA 3.2 is outperforming both
Claw 3 haiku as well as the GPT4 Omni Mini
across various benchmark tests
now the open source community is quickly closing the gap in my opinion
and it's just great to see because we're slowly seeing these new models
outpace even closed source models
these models are optimized for speed and accuracy
excelling in tasks like image captioning, visual question answering
and even image text retrieval
in this demo video you can see that with the LLMA 3.2 model
analyzing and categorizing data from receipts accurately
which displays them afterwards in a table
and this is something where LLMA 3.2 truly shines at
so essentially they release four models
you have the featuring vision LLM's
which are the 11 billion and 90 billion parameter models
and the lightweight text only models
which are the 1 billion and 3 billion optimized models
and they basically are optimized for edge and mobile devices
and they both actually support 128k tokens
which is excelling in tasks like summarization and instruction following
and they're actually optimized for various sorts of processors
now the LLMA 3.2 vision model surpasses closed source alternatives
in image understanding which we'll take a look at in a bit
and it could be fine tuned using torch tune
and right now it's actually available on Huggingface, demos
you have it on together, AI
and you can actually install this locally
which is something that I'll showcase as we go further into the video
now during their evaluations they were able to easily showcase
how the LLMA 3.2 vision models are highly competitive
with top models like the Cloud3 Haiku model
as well as the GPT4 Omni Mini
and you can see that it excels exceptionally well
in categories like image recognition
as well as within vision understanding
the 3 billion parameter model is something that actually
probably posited here is a bit more technical
so those of you if you are interested in the emerging trains
of this multi-model LLMA
please go ahead to watch the video, the link is already provided in the lecture notes
right, okay, so therefore for Section 2 actually we covered the flowing introduction
and we spent some time talking about BERT, GPT
and then we covered very briefly some well-known LLMA
and then finally the emerging train
so for Part 6, right, so these are the two key topics that we covered
Number 1 is foundation model
Number 2 is the large language model
alright, so that will conclude the lectures
but before I let you go there's a few things I just want to very quickly mention
right, okay, so
right, this exam pointer
actually it's not like I'm going to tell you what
it's going to come out in the exam
right, but rather, okay, let me
yeah, I don't want to disappoint some of you
but okay, so anyway, these are just kind of things to tell you
what are the things you should do or what are the things you should not do
alright, okay, I see that's up the percentage of students who come in today
seems to be higher than usual
maybe you are trying to anticipate this part
but okay, so anyway
right, let me just give a few quick high-level kind of descriptions
so far for this course there's two CAs
right, so CA1 is on homework assignment
actually I've marked quite a number of the
this assignment one already
actually most of you are doing very well
that's why, because I see that
for CA1, most of you are doing quite well
that's why for CA2, I started to be a little bit more tricky
but as I mentioned in the previous class
yeah, I received some feedback
so in terms of marking, I will make it a bit more flexible
and also I can do some adjustment
but I've actually marked quite some percentage of the CA2
which is the quiz already
so based on those I've marked for birth
currently I have looked, the average is above 70
so which is actually considered as quite good already
it's quite close to last year's average for the CA
so therefore in short what I'm trying to tell you is that
don't worry too much about the CA
right, so actually so far based on the certain percentage of the marking that I've done
actually the average is above 70
so therefore I don't think of an issue
another thing I also probably kind of want to highlight to you
is that some of you may not know
actually what happened is that in NTU we have some moderation process
so what it means is that if the exam and the course is easy
if the score is very high
then usually they will try to moderate down
that means they will reduce the mark
on the other hand, if a certain course is difficult
and the average is lower
then usually during the moderation process
actually it's organized by school
will then adjust the mark accordingly
so therefore usually you don't have to worry too much about the score
because you will usually do some moderation
so that your grade is reasonable
so that part I just want to highlight to you
because I think maybe a few of you
not too many but a few of you are a little bit concerned about it
but I think so far based on what I've seen it's okay
so the next thing is that in terms of now
because we are coming to the end
so we need to start to prepare for the exams
so for the exams there are four questions
so these four questions are going to be spread across the whole course
so for our course, you know that there are two key topics in this course
the first part is on coding
which is the image and video coding
the second part is on video understanding
so we talk about AI models
and also some of the subsequent things like
understanding of the video
as well as for example what we learn in this foundation model and so on
actually the coverage, it can fall under all these topics
okay so and another thing to...
which is coming to this point here
because last year, even last semester
this particular course there was another lecture
which is there are some visiting lecture
so last semester actually for this course
there are some visiting lecture which teach some of the subject which is not examined
and two semesters before there's actually another lecture
which teach some other material as well
so all in all in short what I'm trying to say is that
so therefore if you look at some past exam questions
so it may not be exactly the best indicator
because as I mentioned
this is actually only the first semester I teach the whole course
in the past there are always some other lecture which teach some other things
so in short
okay for the preparation I would still strongly encourage you
encourage you to look at the past year exam paper
but when you look at the past exam paper you can look at the content
if those questions are something that you feel you have learned before
then it's likely covered by me
then it should be okay
but if you see some question which is totally clueless
they have never seen it before
likely it was covered by someone else
in those cases you can just safely ignore those questions
so therefore when you refer to the past exam question
it may not be a fully indicator
it may not be a perfect indicator
but you can look at the question
if those questions are something that you look familiar with
then those are questions previously stepped by me
and those are probably something you can refer to
but if those questions are something totally you have not seen
then you can ignore them
so therefore what I'm trying to say is that
when you refer to past year exam question
please use it with your own judgement
because the teaching team and the content has been modified before
but more importantly is that you can refer to the exercises that are prepared in this course
those exercises are still important
so in terms of the exam type questions
there will be some calculation question
and there will be some description questions
so I cannot remember the
probably it's like around 60-40 that kind of range
I cannot remember the exact amount
but there's a good mixture of them
maybe like 60% calculation
or 40% description
something around that I cannot remember the detail
50-50 or 60-40
so therefore there's a reasonable amount of calculation question
and then there will be some description questions
so for calculation question
I think we have gone through some sample example
in the lecture
so those are still things you can practice and try out
but having said that because for exam
just like actually for the quiz
the school actually will have a certain expectation on us
we cannot have everyone doing very well
because if everyone is doing very well
the school is going to come and ask me why everyone is doing so well
then after work they will just press down the mark
it doesn't make any difference
but the only problem now is that you cannot differentiate between stronger student
and probably more average student
so therefore in short
what I'm trying to tell you is that for the exam paper
there are always going to be some part which is more difficult
it's for sure there will be some part which is more difficult
so if you see there are some more difficult questions
just try your best to write something
don't leave anything blank
because if you leave it blank
there's nothing much we can do
I cannot give you a mark for blank space
but so just write something
even if you cannot really stop it just write something
and also as I mentioned
there will always be some reasonable question
some which is easier
some which is a little bit more difficult
so I mentioned already calculation and description question
the ratio is probably about 60, 40, that kind of thing
or 50, 50 I can't remember
so in the description type of question
actually we have already gone through some sample example in the lecture
so sometimes it's quite common you will get this kind of question
briefly describe or state clearly whether A or B is better
state yes or no
the kind of thing
so a lot of this or list the state the kind of thing
a lot of these questions are supposed to be concise
so please don't write long answer
just write to the point
you know that for this course
your class is very big there's 500 something
and we have a short time to do the marking
so we have to mark very quickly
so therefore the more concise the answer is
just write to the point
the faster I mark and usually tends to be
more my mood will be better if I see
concise answer and the answer is there rather than
three points and then you write a long paragraph
then my mood will not be so good
so long sorry short
just try to be concise and to the point
again there's many exercises that I've shared with you
you can look at those sample answers that I've provided
so lots of them is just quite concise and to the point
okay
yeah so for the description question
very often sometimes they ask me to ask you to
for example you know describe briefly
sometimes you may ask you to draw a diagram
sometimes you may ask you to list certain things
so these are some common I mean some possible questions
yeah so that is similar to what you have seen
in the sample practice questions
in the class if you refer to some past questions
you will also see something similar
so this part is just some do's and don'ts
so yeah please do that
write clearly
be concise and to the point
don't write very long
good thing about Chinese students
Chinese students tends to be quite concise
and to the point
okay so yeah this part
initially I am thinking if possible you may want to draw some
bounding box around the final answer
because sometimes when you do the marking
some students working can become very messy
and then you don't really see where the answer is
if you can just draw a small bounding box at your final answer
that will make my marking easier
and usually
if I can mark it your script easier I tend to be a bit more lenient
right
okay next start a new questions on the new page
for example if this question one has three parts
one A one B one okay one A is here
from here to here one B is here
and then when you have question two please start on the new page
don't try to put two questions on the same page
because it will make our marking very cumbersome
yeah so whenever you have a new question just write on the new page
yeah because as I mentioned
our school has certain guidelines on how we do the marking
when you put question one and two on the same page
it will make our marking a lot messy
and also for the person who do the checking
right so these are what the things you should not do
don't overwrite don't write too much really don't write too much
right don't mix your answer so when I say don't interfere
or mix your answer means that for example you have this question one
A one B and one C here don't suddenly
insert your question two A here yeah
because usually when we do the marking we mark it question by question
we mark all question one first
and afterwards we mark question two
so sometimes if I mark question one
if I do the marking I put a tick here tick here tick here tick here
then after marking I will talk this page I already marked
so when I by the time I mark question two
this part may be missed yeah
usually it will not happen we'll do the checking very carefully
yeah but it just means that it is going to make it a bit harder for us to do the marking
yeah so please try not to do that
okay so yeah any other questions you want to ask
regarding the exams
any questions
right so if not then probably just the last thing
yeah okay I think this one everyone knows already right
yeah so yeah Li Ziqi just come back right so if you feel really stressed
yeah go and watch a little bit of her video
that probably will distress you
yeah okay I will not play her video you should know like
she has how many one billion views already in the past few days
yeah so okay so anyway this is another
this is another kind of YouTube channel sometimes I watch right
if I feel a little bit stressed but okay yeah probably I will just skip this
yeah another thing is that for the exam yeah you know what's this right
yeah yeah so anyway this is
right okay so at least for the exam perspective
don't do this alright don't overly relax yourself
okay right and also people feel that no yeah
okay anyway for Chinese you should know what it means
okay and then finally I wish you all the best right in your exam right and I hope to see you again
maybe next semester right okay as I mentioned for the exam don't worry too much
because if the paper is hard definitely we are going to do some moderation
and yeah the practice question is still useful yeah and
for each question definitely there will be some part which is a little bit difficult
so yeah just be mentally prepared okay right last
opportunity any questions right so if not I see you
bye bye thank you
you