Communication off-camera
This is going to be fun.
.
All right.
Okay.
Right, so good evening, class.
Right.
This is the first time I'm here in such a big LT
and see many of our students here.
So it's really a very big LT.
Right, okay.
So welcome to this course,
E6427, Video Signal Processing.
Right.
So I'm actually Prof Yab.
I'm going to be the instructor for this course.
Right, so given here is my contact information.
So should you have any question,
you're welcome to drop me an email
and then we can talk about that.
Okay.
Can you all hear?
Oh, yeah, sorry.
Okay, right.
Let's probably do it one more time.
So welcome to E6427, Video Signal Processing.
Right, so I'm Prof Yab.
I'm going to be the instructor for this course.
So given here is my contact information.
So should there be any question
that you would like to ask regarding this course,
you can drop me an email.
For the past one week or so,
there are many, many emails.
I think I receive about six
or seven hundred applications
for the projects. So actually,
I'm overwhelmed with the email for the past
few weeks. So for those
students, if you write in
during this period and if I do not
respond, please try to be understanding
because there are just too many
email applications for the
projects for the past one week or so.
Okay, but moving forward, yeah,
when you write in, I'll definitely respond to you.
Okay, so this is the
course outline for
this particular course. So it's divided
into six parts. So
first of all, the first thing we are going to look at
is the introduction and basics.
Before I continue, can I just check
the students at the back? Can you all hear me?
Okay, great.
Okay, and then
part two, we are going to look at image
compression and JPEG standard.
Okay, and then part three, we'll be looking
at video compression and standards.
And then afterwards, part four
we'll be moving on to some AI
models and architectures.
Okay, and then part five, we'll be
looking at some video analysis
and understanding. And then finally,
part six, we'll be looking at some emerging
topics and image and video processing.
So that's a general overview
of the course.
So you can see pretty much
the earlier part tends to be
more focusing on
compression, so video
compression. And the
second half of the
course tends to be more on
AI and then the video analytics.
So these are the two
key focus for this particular
course.
Okay, so for this course, there are
some references. Of course, nowadays
you can make use of different
tools to help you to do the learning.
You should try to make use
of all the tools, which include, for example,
usual ones like Google's.
You should also use the
chat.gbt and other
resources like Quora and
also some traditional textbooks.
So by all means, if you have any
questions regarding the course,
make use of all the resources out there
to help you to do the learning.
But of course, if you are using tools
like chat.gbt, you have to be
a little bit more careful because the content
that's being presented may not
be 100% accurate.
Right, okay, so this slide is the
standard slide that the school actually
suggests us to include, which is just to
remind you that the materials
in the slides are copyrighted by
respective publishers and authors.
And the slides should only be
used for your own personal studies.
So no
part of the slides should be recorded, reproduced
or distributed without the
permission of the author.
So the reason why we have this is that
I mean for some of you, probably you already
know, right,
there are some students who actually
go and record
the material and then afterwards sell
it online. Right? There are some
websites like Course Hero,
actually you can find the lecture notes,
the exercises, the
assignment as well as the solution online.
So therefore we do not encourage
you all to record it.
So it's to stop that.
Okay.
Right, so for many of you,
this is probably one of the most
important things you would like to look at for
a course. So for this course, in terms
of the assessment, it's pretty
standard throughout for
MSc courses. So the
first component is examination.
So examination will account for
60%.
So it consists of
four questions. So you have to answer
all the four questions and
it will be closed book. Okay? So it's a
closed book examination at the end
of the semester.
In addition to that, there's also
this continuous assessment.
So continuous assessment is 40%.
It will consist of
two CA. So the first
one is homework assignment.
So this homework assignment, I plan to
release it around week five
or week six around that time.
So it will be a homework assignment
which is 20%.
And the second component is
quiz, which will account for
another 20%. So this
quiz will likely occur around
week 11 or week 12.
So once it's a little bit closer,
I will inform you regarding the quiz
arrangement.
So far, are there any questions?
Do you hear any echo?
The sound quality is okay.
Okay, so next
we'll move on to part one on the
introduction of this
course here. So this, today's
lecture is pretty much on introduction
so you can more like sit back and relax.
Yeah, and then after
the introduction, then we'll formally move into
the more technical part
of the course. But the first part
will be mainly on introduction
and basics.
Right, so in part one, these
are the topics we are going to cover. So
first of all, we are going to introduce
the basic concept about image
and video. So what are actually images
and videos? And then we'll be looking
at some selected different topics
of video signal processing and application.
Because if you think about
video, right, video signal
processing, actually the title itself is very
broad. It can cover many,
many different aspects of video signal
processing. It's a very broad
topic. But as I
mentioned, for this particular course
there will be two key focus that we'll be
focusing on. One is the coding
and compression, okay, and communication.
The second one is on
the analysis and analytics
and understanding. So these are the
two key focus for
this particular course here.
Okay, so in the first part,
as I mentioned, the first
important part will be on the
image and video standard. So
we'll be talking about different types
of compression, such as
we'll start off with image compression,
and afterwards we'll move on to video
compression. So in the process
of introducing this compression
techniques, we'll also introduce
some standards that you
probably have heard of, such as
JPEG image compression,
video compression, you probably heard about
MPEG as well as H.26x
series of compression.
So those are the topics
we're going to cover in the first
part of the course.
Afterwards we'll move on to the second part,
where we'll be talking about video
analysis and understanding.
So in order to do that, we'll try to introduce
some AI models.
So we'll first of all try to cover
concepts such as linear classifier,
convolutional
neural network, recurrent neural
network, LSTM,
and then transformer, and then probably
some of the relevant concepts.
So we'll try to introduce those basic
AI models first, and afterwards we'll
proceed to look at some sample video
analytics application,
such as object
detection, multiple object
tracking, post estimation,
action recognition in
videos. So those are the topics we'll cover.
And then finally, under the
emerging topics, we'll try
to cover some recent trends.
So specifically, we'll
probably be talking about some large language
model, and also some
foundation models, in the
context of video analytics.
So that's a general overview
of this particular course here.
So first,
let's look at the image and video
basics.
So what is an image? I think most of you
should be familiar with image
already. So an image is nothing
but if you think about it, it's actually a two-dimensional
array, or a matrix
of pixel elements.
So you have a two-dimensional array
of small elements here.
So each of the smallest elements is
known as a pixel. So pixels stand
for picture element.
So image is an important media
for us to convey the information.
So we need to store it,
we need to process, and we need to present
it. So that's the basic
understanding of what an image is.
So it's represented by a two-dimensional
matrix, or
two-dimensional array of pixels here.
So for example, you can see this is an
image. So this image
consists of different rows
of pixels here.
So each of the basic elements is a pixel.
So there are many
different popular image formats,
such as JPEG,
which stands for Joint Photographic Expert Group,
and then
TIFF, TAC, Image File Format,
BMP, Bitmap Format, and so on.
So for this course, we'll spend
some time to talk about
the techniques for image compression,
as well as the underlying principle
for JPEG image compression.
So that's
the basic
parts regarding the image
compression that we're going to study.
And then before
we continue, as I mentioned
for this lecture, we are going to
talk about some of the basics to
make sure that everyone has a common understanding
and is familiar with
the terms that we are using.
So first of all, we're going
to introduce the concept of pixels and resolution.
So I believe everyone
should understand what a pixel is.
So pixels
represent picture elements.
So it's the smallest element in
a digital image. So if you look
at this particular image here,
it consists of a two-dimensional
array or matrix of
pixels.
So if you zoom in
these parts of the image, if you zoom in
in, then you can see each of these
pixels a lot more clearly.
So each of these particular elements here
is known as a pixel, which is
the picture element.
So another associated
concept with image
is resolution. So what is the meaning
of resolution? Resolution means the number
of pixels in the image. So there's
a few different ways you can express
the number of pixels in the image.
You can simply express
it in terms of the total pixel count.
For example, you can say that this particular
image is 10 megapixel.
That means this image actually
consists of 10 megapixels
of pixels. Or it
can be expressed as width times
height. For example,
for first
total pixel count, for example, if you say an image
can be 5 megapixels.
In terms of, you can
also express it as width times height.
An example is 640 by
480. So what it means is that
you have the number, the row
is 640 and the height
is 480.
So this is the dimension of your image.
Another way of
expressing this resolution
in the context of printing and
scanning is this pixel
per inch, or PPI.
So for example, when you say that you are trying
to print a certain document, you need
to indicate how many pixels per inch.
In one inch of space,
how many pixels can you squeeze it?
So these are different ways for you
to express the resolution.
So you can see this resolution
pretty much is trying to reflect
the ability for you
to distinguish or
differentiate fine details in an image.
So if you look at this small image and you
zoom it in, clearly, if
you have a higher resolution, that means
you can pack more information into it.
That means you will be able to see a lot more details.
So that is the
basic idea of resolution.
So the next term that we are going to introduce
is bit depth or color depth.
So what is bit depth and color depth?
So bit depth or color depth is the number
of bits used to represent
each pixel.
So if you look at these images
here, there are three types of images
here. So the first one is a binary
image.
So you can see binary image because it consists of
either, you know, the color can
only be either black or
white. So if it's black or white,
that means how many bits do you
need to represent it?
If it's for a binary
image, it only can have
two colors, which is either black or white.
So if it's either black or white, how many
bits do you need to represent each pixel?
One,
because it can only have two possible values.
So therefore, for binary images
like this, you only need to have one bit
represented, okay? Because it's either
black or white.
So the next time is a grayscale images.
So these are examples of grayscale
images. So these are probably like
your grandparents' generations of
photos or my
mother's generation of photos.
So these are the grayscale images here.
So very often, we use
eight bits represented.
So if we use eight bits to represent it,
that means how many possible
gray levels or tones can
it show?
For each pixel?
Sorry?
256,
so it's two to the power of eight
because for each bit
you can have two possible values. So two
times two times two, you times it
eight times, then it's two to the power of eight,
which is 256
possible gray
level. So this is a
this image here is an example
of grayscale images here.
And if you zoom in this more
pixel blocks here,
you can see this is the examples of grayscale
images. For grayscale
images and binary image, it
only consists of one channel
or one component.
So for this binary
or grayscale image, it only has
one channel
or one component.
So and then for each component,
if you zoom it in, just now
we already know if we use eight bits
to represent it, that means you can have
256 gray
level. So this 256
gray level typically we represent
from zero to 255.
So zero to 255.
And if it's smaller, if the
value is smaller, that means it's darker.
If the value is larger, that means
it's brighter. So you can see for example,
for smaller value
each byte 51 here is actually
corresponds to darker pixel.
And if the value is larger such as
177,
it corresponds to brighter pixel.
So that's the
basic understanding.
So the next types of image that we have
is color images. So this color image
is very common. That's what we see every
day. So this is an example
of the color image.
So if you look at this particular
color image, again it consists of
different pixels here.
Each of these is actually a
pixel. And each of
this pixel will consist of a triplet
of value. That means it has three values
here. Triplets of value. So each
of these pixels here would have red,
green and blue. So for example,
these pixels here will consist of
red, green and blue. So it has three
channels. So red,
green and blue are referred
to as three channels or
three components.
So typically,
because each of these
channels or components,
we use eight bits to represent it.
So therefore, each pixel now
can be represented as three times
eight, which is 24 bits.
So that is the
basic visualizations
of how we represent different
types of images.
So the next thing we are going to
look at is some
column color
spaces. So what are color
spaces? So just now, the color
image that we've shown, we know that
color image, again, consists
of a two-dimensional array or
matrix of pixels. And for each
pixel, it can be shown
as triplets of value.
The example that was shown is red,
green and blue. RGB.
But this particular way of representing
the color image is not
the only way. So there are actually
many different ways you can represent
color images. So different
ways of representing color images
are known as color
spaces or color model.
So there's many different ways
you can represent colors,
images.
And this is known as color spaces.
So this particular figure
shows some of the examples.
For example, red, green, blue is one
common color space.
HSI hue saturation
intensity is another common
color space. And later on,
you're going to see why CBCR
is also another common color
space. We are going to
look at each of these color spaces
and also talk about why,
in some cases, we want to use this color
space, and in some cases, we use
another color space.
So let's try to look at,
first of all, color
images again. So color images
can be expressed in terms of different color
spaces, as I mentioned. There's many different
ways you can express the color.
So some of the common color space
is RGB. For example,
the image that we have just now earlier on
shown is RGB images.
HSI is another popular
one, and why CBCR
is another popular one. So this
why CBCR color space is
commonly used in standards
such as image and video
compression and TV transmission.
So these are the color space that's commonly
used in those applications
here. So if you look at RGB
color space, you can see
the color is represented by
triplets. Now we say each pixel has three
values. So these three values
are triplets of value as
red, green and blue, RGB.
So if you look at
this particular
color model
here, I think this is some color
model that you probably, for most students,
you study in secondary school.
So you have the primary color,
which is red,
green and blue. So if you
add red and green, you'll
get yellow, red and blue you'll get
magenta, and then green
and blue you'll get cyan. And if
you add these three colors, you'll get a white
color. So this is the standard
additive color model
that you study in secondary school.
So another
visualizations of this particular primary
color, we can also visualize it in terms
of a color cube. So we visualize
it in the color cube, then red,
this axis is red,
this axis is green, and
this axis is blue here.
So red will take the values of
1, 0, 0.
Green is 0, 1, 0.
And blue is 0, 0, 1.
So it's like the unit values along
this axis here.
And then as we have seen,
red plus green will give you yellow.
So this corner will be yellow.
Red and blue
will be magenta. This corner will be
magenta, and blue and green,
this corner will be cyan.
And if you add up these three colors, then this
particular diagonal, the corner
will be the white color. So
this particular corner will be
white color, and if the value is
0, 0, 0, then it's black color.
So if you draw a line to connect
the black to the white, this
will correspond to the grayscale
representation.
So this is the representation
of the RGB color cube.
So a little bit more
about the RGB
images. So earlier on
we mentioned, typically we represent
as 24 bits color images.
So if you look at this particular
color image, you
divide into three different channels.
You have the red channel, green channel,
and the blue channel. So an image,
typically, a color image, if you
represent in terms of RGB color,
images, that means there's three
channels, and then each of these channels you can
actually separate them. Then
this is what you're going to get, these three channels
here. Okay, so you can
see that each pixel has three
components, red, green, and blue, you already know.
And then for each component, for each
pixel, we use eight bits to represent
it. Right, so therefore
for each channel, because we use
eight bits, that means it has two
56 tones,
and the value that it represents is
from 0 to 255.
And if the color is black,
it's 000, and it's white,
it's 255, 255,
255, in terms of the
color representation.
And also, if you look at this
particular image, if you break it into the
three channels, you can see
for example this red channel here,
this area that corresponds to
the red color, when you
look at the red channel here,
the value is actually
brighter or whiter.
That's because how we represent this
color is that, as we
have mentioned before, if the value
is larger, it's whiter
or it's brighter. And if the value
is smaller, it's darker
or blacker. So therefore,
if you look at the red channel, because the
red channel actually reflects the red
component, so this region
corresponds to the red component
here. So that's why their values
are larger, and because
their values are larger, they are indicated
as brighter.
Other regions that, for example,
doesn't contain that much red color,
it will be
darker.
So if you now look at the green channel,
you can see these regions here contain the
green channel, so that's why
their value is larger and
hence a little bit brighter.
And then finally, for this particular
image, you can see because there's hardly any
blue component, so therefore
if you look at the blue channel, most of them
are dark, which indicate
that their value is very small,
that means not much blue component.
Okay, so just now we have introduced
one very common color space,
which is RGB color space.
So the next class of color
space that we are going to
show is the YUV,
YIQ and YCBCR color space.
So this
color space is another scheme
to represent color images.
So for this particular color
images, that means actually the images
will be represented by three different
channels again. But this
three different channels now will be
the Y channel, if you look
at this YUV
channel, that means this three channel will be
represented by Y channel,
U channel and V channel
now. So this is another
way of representing
the color image.
And YIQ and YCBCR
are actually just a very
similar to YUV,
they are just a small variation, slightly
different.
So pretty much, as I've
already explained, YIQ
and YCBCR
are small variations of
YUV channel, color
space. Therefore, typically we consider
them as more or less the same.
So among this color space,
for example, if we use the YUV
as the example here,
this Y channel corresponds
to luminance channel. So
luminance means the brightness part,
the black and white, the
brightness part.
So the luminance is actually
the brightness part or the black and white
parts of the image.
And then the UV actually
corresponds to the chrominance part.
So this UV refers to the
chrominance part. So chrominance
means it's the color part of the image.
Okay, color part of the
image.
So, this,
why do we want to, in some cases,
represent an image or
video in terms of YUV,
YIQ or YCBCR
color space? For example,
in video broadcasting,
typically we use these types
of color space, YUV,
YIQ,
and for JPEG and image,
JPEG and
MPEG compression, we use YCBCR.
So why do we want
to use this kind of color space
in video broadcasting
or
compression? So here the
answer is, it makes good
use of the bandwidth. But what exactly
does that mean?
Okay.
I mean, for example, in
this
video broadcasting,
you can choose to represent
your image and video as RGB.
But if you do that,
when you want to do the transmission,
it's not so efficient.
As compared to if you decided
to change this color space
from RGB to
YCBCR or
YUV color space.
So when you represent the image and
video using YUV
color space, and then when you do
the transmission,
we can do it in a more efficient
manner. So anyone
has any idea why is that the case?
Yes.
Okay.
So,
yeah, what
you're trying to explain is more
like the temporal
correlation.
Okay, the similarity
across different frames,
yeah, when you're trying to
do the transmission.
Okay, so in the context of
compression, because each
frames, okay, consecutive frames
are very similar, so you
only need to encode the small difference.
I believe that's what you are coming from.
But still, it does not
clearly explain what's the difference.
Why? I mean, for,
if you represent the image as RGB
or YCBCR,
okay, now I mean both of them,
you can also
leverage on the similarity
or the inter-frame
correlation for you to help to perform
the compression. But it still
doesn't really quite explain why
one color space is better
than the other color space.
Any other
thought?
Okay, so one of the reasons why in
the context of video transmission,
okay, compression and then
TV transmissions, why we
want to represent the color in these
types of YCBCR color spaces,
is that once we convert
the color space from RGB
into this YCBCR,
YUV color space,
for example, this white part
just now we mentioned, it corresponds to
the luminance part,
which is the brightness component.
And this UV corresponds
to the chrominance part, which is the
color component. So the next
thing that you need to know is the
how human viscous system works.
Our human viscous systems
are, right in our eye, there's actually
two types of cell, rot and cone.
Probably if you
can still remember what you
study in the secondary school biology.
You know our human eye,
the retina, actually has
two types of
this light
kind of sensitive cell that
can perceive the light. One is a rot,
the other is a cone.
So one of them is sensitive to
the color component,
the other is sensitive to the brightness
component. That's why
in the
middle of the night,
if you wake up and when you go to the
toilet, actually what you can see
is a gray color. You cannot
see the color, but you can see only the
grayscale, the brightness.
That's because our eyes are more sensitive
to the luminance
component. So all in all,
what I'm trying to say is that for human
viscous system, actually our eye is
more sensitive to the luminance component
as compared to the
chrominance component, or the color
component. So because our eyes
are more sensitive
to the luminance component
and less sensitive to the chrominance
component, that means
we can afford to throw away
some of the information
in the chrominance component.
Because it makes very little difference
to us. So traditionally,
because we know that, for example,
for video transmission,
it requires lots of bandwidth.
So bandwidth is very expensive.
So therefore, you want to reduce
the number of bits that you want to
transmit. Okay. And then
it's very logical now,
if our eyes are more sensitive to the
white channel, or white
component, then we should keep
all the information in white. And
if our eyes are less sensitive
to the chrominance component,
then we can afford to throw
away some of the information, by
dropping away some of the pixels.
Okay. So therefore, in short,
what I'm trying to say is that, now,
if you represent your image and
video into this kind of
color space, there's a very
simple strategy for you to
reduce the number of
bits that you need to transmit over
the channel.
For example, doing
the TV transmission. What you need to do
is keep all the white channel, drop
some of, or sub-sample,
or drop some of the information from your
chrominance component. So that's
why this particular color space
is a lot easier for
you to decide what to do, as opposed
to RGB. So, for example,
if your video is RGB,
you cannot, no, there's no
very clear strategy. Now, if you want
to drop some pixel, what are the pixel
you want to drop, or what are the channel you want
to drop? It's not so clear cut.
Okay. So that is the reason.
So, because of that,
this color space is commonly used in TV
industry and video compression.
So, for example, YUV
is used in this PAL and
CCAM TV standard.
YQ is used
in NTSC, and YCBCR
is commonly used in JPEG and
MPEG compression. So, later
on, when we study about JPEG and
MPEG compression, we'll be mainly dealing
with this color space here.
And then for
different color space, RGB,
and this, okay, in this particular
table, it shows the conversion
between RGB and YQ.
So, you can actually just do a simple
conversion by some matrix
multiplication to convert from one
color space to another color space.
Okay. So,
the next thing we want to very quickly
touch on is CODAC.
So, does
any one of you know what this company
is, CODAC?
Anyone
know CODAC?
Camera.
Okay, long time ago, right? What you heard is
long time ago. Actually, I still remember
when I was a young kid,
my brother bought
the first kind of camera.
Yeah. So, at the time, I was very
excited. You have to take this
camera, and then you actually have to
think very carefully exactly
what is the photo you want to capture.
Because every photo, once you click it,
you capture it. It's already
one film that's been
taken already. So,
it's very expensive, it's very precious.
Unlike nowadays, when you have
mobile phone, you can just keep taking photo.
You don't like, you just delete. But in the past,
the photos are actually
using this kind of
camera is using from
this kind of
analog film for you to take
the photo. So, this company,
CODAC, used to be a very big
company, very, very important. When people talk about
camera, they just think of CODAC.
So, it's just a very big
company. So, in
the past, it's actually very dominant.
But, later
on, because they make
lots of money from this firm,
analog firm that you have. But
later on, when time starts to change,
this digital photography
and digital camera
and filming start to appear, actually
CODAC is
very resistant to
changing.
The reason is quite straightforward,
because they are making so much money from making
this firm. So, when there's a new
technology appearing,
digital camera, so they are very
resistant to
switch from analog camera to digital
camera. Whereas,
other companies such as
Fuji, actually they manage
to do the transition much
more quicker. So, in short, this
particular slide is trying to show
that sometimes you have to
move on with technology.
When technology changes,
you just have to follow. Otherwise,
you'll become obsolete.
So, this particular
heading here, CODAC moment,
so in the past, there's a very well-known
advertisement. When you want to take a
photo, we call it a CODAC
moment. That means you are taking a photo.
So, that's why they call it a
CODAC moment. So, anyway,
CODAC kind of went bankrupt
around
2012, which is about
13 years ago.
Alright, so the next thing we are going to
quickly do is, we are going
to look at how do we capture
information,
this image and video information
from camera. So, we are going
to spend a bit of time to talk about
camera, how to perform
data acquisition.
Right, so in order to do that, I actually have
a very short video to explain
to you how a camera
works, how does it capture
lights from the
imaging source and convert it into
a digital image.
Right, okay. So, let
me just play this video for you.
Okay, let me just do some adjustment first. This echo is very strong here.
This program contains experiments which are performed by professionals. These tests are dangerous and may involve the use of hazardous materials. They should not be performed or imitated under any circumstances.
It's all about light.
The digital camera.
It's revolutionized photography
by transforming light into
electricity. Everything
is there to draw in light. From
the camera's buttons, controls
and dials down to the lenses.
What the digital camera
does with light is what makes it
so revolutionary.
It turns
light into electrical charges
that become the image captured on the screen.
Light particles or photons
leave the source, bounce
off the subject and
enter the camera through a series of
lenses.
The photons then follow a designated
path on their way from photon
to photo.
A series of lenses allows the
photographer to capture the clearest image
possible.
This lens diaphragm is what
controls the amount of light that the photographer
allows in through the camera's opening
or aperture.
After crossing
the diaphragm, the lenses
and entering the aperture,
the light bounces off a mirror and
heads for the viewfinder.
Before it gets there, the light is flipped
over as it passes through a prism.
That's so the image seen in the viewfinder is
right side up.
If the photographer likes the
image, time to press the shutter
button.
The mirror lifts and the light rushes in.
For a fraction of a second,
the light is not heading in the direction
of the viewfinder.
But for the very heart of the digital camera,
the image sensor.
The duration of this fraction
of a second depends on the shutter
that opens just long enough to
expose the sensor to light.
Now, to the real heart of this
digital revolution, the element
that captures the image,
the image sensor. A tightly
structured grid made up of
extremely tiny light sensors.
When the photons hit the light sensor,
they are absorbed by the semiconductor
material it's made of.
For each photon absorbed,
the light sensor emits an electric particle
called an electron.
The photon's
energy transfers to the electron.
That's the electrical charge.
The brighter the image,
the stronger the electrical charge is.
So each electrical charge
has a different intensity. A circuit
board then converts the different intensities
into computer language.
They represent millions of tiny colored
dots that make up a photo.
The pixels.
The more pixels
in a picture, the better the
resolution.
Okay.
So this is a new system.
I'm not too sure why the
echo is so strong.
Yeah. Okay. So we'll try to work with it.
Okay.
So let's see.
So this is a new system.
Okay.
So let's see.
Okay. So we'll try to work with it
for the time being.
So this particular video just shows you
how we can actually,
the lights from the imaging source
can be converted into a particular
image or video.
It's because you have a sensor.
And then for a particular sensor,
image sensor in the camera,
actually it consists of many different
elements. And these elements can actually
then convert the light or the photons
into electric charges.
And these electric charges can then be converted
into some binary representation,
which is the pixels.
Okay. So this particular slide shows
the signal flows of a digital camera.
So let's have a quick look at
how the signal flow looks like.
So first of all, you have some subjects.
So the light will be collected by this
lens here. So the lens will collect the light.
Okay. And then it will hit this particular
CCD. So this CCD is a
types of image sensor.
So there are a few common types of
image sensor. CCD
is one of them. Right. CMOS
is another one. Right. So this particular
CCD here, right,
from the video that you see just now, this CCD
actually has a very packed
array or matrix
of sensor, which will then
convert the light into
some electric charges.
Okay. So afterwards you have
an analog to digital converter
to convert all these electric
charges into the pixel value.
Right. So for this pixel value,
you can decide to, for example,
store as a raw image.
For those of you who play with
photography, sometimes you
may prefer to keep the image
in the raw format. Because
if you keep it in the raw format, then you can
have access to the original data
and you can do different types of
manipulation to
adjust the photo quality.
But for most people,
we'll let the
onboard processor in
the camera to do the processing.
So the processor, the image
processing engine on the camera
will typically do the following.
So first of all, you will do the
demossacking or the image reconstruction.
So you try to recover
three channels
of color images.
So this particular process is known as
reconstruction or demossacking.
And afterwards,
adjust the brightness, make sure that the
image looks bright,
and then doing the white balancing.
So white balancing is that you make sure that
white color, white
object will actually appear
as if it's white color. Because
white color is very sensitive to
the light sources. When you capture an
image, whether it will appear to be
white or not depends on what kind of
light sources you are getting.
So this white balancing step will
make sure that the white component
will appear to be white.
And afterwards, improve the sharpness,
you'll improve the contrast of the
image. So these are actually the
kind of processor,
the onboard processing
performed by the
camera. And afterwards,
next you can then proceed to do the compression.
Because typically the image, if you don't
compress it, it's latched. So you need
to perform the compression,
but some common compression technique that you
can use is, for example, the JPEG
compression. Then you can compress it
and store it into your memory
card. Or in some application,
for example, if you are trying to do
some publishing application, then
the quality of the image is very important.
Then you may store it uncompressed,
for example using the TIFF format
and store it into your memory card.
So this is the typical signal flow.
So when we want to talk
about a camera, what is the
important criteria to determine
whether the quality of
the camera, there's a few key factors.
So the first one is lens.
This lens here.
So when you buy
a camera, for those of you who are into
photography, you'll know
that lens is very important and
it's very expensive.
The role of the lens is that it's trying to
collect the light from the
imaging source. So therefore, whether a
camera is good or not, the quality
of the lens is a very important factor.
So the next one is CCD.
This particular part here, the sensor.
So this particular
sensor, typically, if
the sensor has a higher resolution,
we consider it to be better.
For example, 10 megapixel
sensor, usually we consider
it to be better than, for example, 3 megapixel
sensor. But more
importantly is whether this sensor
is very sensitive to noise or not.
When you take the photo, for example, in a
very dark environment,
whether the sensor is very sensitive to
noise. So the quality of
the sensor therefore is also an important factor.
And then finally
is this particular image processing engine
here. How well
the
camera performs all these tasks here.
So depending on different companies, for example,
whether you are
Canon or whether you are Nikson,
so different companies
have their own algorithm
to perform these tasks here. So
they are a little bit different. So that the
performance of this particular image
processing engine will also determine
the quality of your camera and
the captured images of video.
So therefore the digital image quality is
actually determined by these
three factors here, which is shown.
So it depends on the lens performance,
CCD, image sensor,
pixel count and performance, as
well as the image processing
engine performance. So these are
the factors that will determine
the quality of the image.
Right, so what are the
some common cameras?
So this particular slide
shows some of the common
cameras that are available out there.
So the one that we have seen just now is
the normal RGB kind of
cameras. But in addition to that,
there are many other different cameras that are
out there. For example, one of the
other common cameras
that we have is the RGBD.
So RGBD camera,
for example this Kinect camera.
So in addition to the RGB
information, it can also capture
the depth information.
It can also capture the depth information.
Another common
types of camera that we have is
the near-infrared.
This type of cameras here.
Another common one is
the thermal camera. For example,
when you, during the
many years ago,
during the SARS period, I'm not sure
whether you heard about SARS.
Do you know about SARS?
Okay, SARS, I think
occurred around
2003, around that time.
And afterwards, the most recent one
of us is COVID. So for those
you can use, for example, this kind of
thermal camera to detect
the body temperature. So it's
types of camera as well.
And then another types of camera that we
have is event-based camera.
So event-based camera
means that only when there's a change
of the brightness,
okay, of
the imaging scene,
then it will be able, it will capture
the information. So most of the time
it will not capture the information.
But when there's change of brightness, then it will
capture. So the reason why
event-based camera is used in some
applications is because it's
very power
efficient. Yeah, it can save
lots of energy. So therefore you can see
there's many different types of camera
that can be used in different kind
of application.
Yeah.
Okay, so
we have very briefly explained
about image already. So next,
let's move on to video. So what's
video? Video is nothing but a sequence
of frame or images
or pictures with audio
signal. So essentially all of us
should know that video is nothing but a
sequence of frame.
Okay, and when you play this sequence
of frame very quickly, and
due to the human persistence
of vision, then you start to get the
impression of smooth movement.
So that's essentially what a video
is. Okay, and it also
has the audio component.
So the different frame that we have, sometimes
we call it frame, sometimes we call it
images, sometimes we call it pictures,
they refer to the same thing.
Right, so as mentioned earlier on, we
play this video at a very high speed
that gives the impression of the
movement, a very smooth movement.
Okay, due to the human persistence
of vision. So this is the characteristics
of the human vision system.
So some popular video format
include MPAC, Moving Picture
Expert Group,
AVI, which is Intel, and then
WMV, which is Microsoft.
So this is some of the
common video format.
So next I will play you
a short video so I couldn't resist
because we are talking about video. So I
will just play you a video of one of my
popular songs.
So
yeah, so bear with me.
So this particular song is actually
an example of a video.
So
Ah, someday, someone will take this road
I will go, with my face turned to blue
I will go, farewell, I will be closed
So these are known as 480i
And this particular i refers to interlace scanning
That we will explain a bit later here
And then for the PEL, for example, it says that it's 576i
That means the number of rows is 720
The width is 720 and the height of the number of rows is 576 here
So therefore this number actually indicates the resolution
So the standard resolution is used in very early years
That's why you can see the resolution actually is very small
And then afterwards we moved on to the high definition
High definition is called HD
So under HD there's a few different variations
The first one is 720p
So 720p refers to, this number here usually refers to the number of rows
So 720p means 1280 by 720
And this p here refers to progressive
Later on we'll see what's the difference between interlace and progressive
So the next one is 1080i
So 1080i refers to 1920 by 1080
And then i refers to interlace
And then finally 1080p is this resolution
And p is progressive
So when you have this 1080p it also has a very unique name known as a full HD
So maybe 10, 15 years ago when your parents go out and buy a TV from an electronic shop
And on the shop you see this full HD
Actually it refers to this particular resolution with this scanning
And of course in recent years nowadays the TV that we have is the ultra high definition or UHD here
So we typically see things like 4K or 8K
So 4K resolution is about four times the size of a full HD
And the 8K resolution is four times the resolution of 4K
So all this number if you look at it, you may not have a good intuition of how it looks like
So if you look at this particular image it gives you an impression
About how over time the number of pixels that you can squeeze into a single frame, how it has progressed
So we start off with this SD and afterwards HD
4K, so most of our TV nowadays is using this 4K resolution
And then 8K resolution is about this big
So in the previous slide we introduced these terms about interlace scanning, I, and the progressive scanning, P
So what's the difference between these two types of scan type?
So interlace scanning refers to, given a particular, for example, image frame, if it's a video
So first of all we scan the odd line first and afterwards we scan the even line
So sometimes we also call it top or bottom field
So we scan the top field first, followed by the bottom field
So if you do that, then this kind of scanning is known as interlace scanning
So it consists of two fields, odd or even line, or sometimes it's known as top and bottom field
So it's scanned alternately
So this is an example of the interlace scanning
You can see it scans the odd line first, the blue line
And afterwards it scans the red line here
So this is the interlace scanning
So as opposed to that, you have the next one which is the progressive scanning
So the progressive scanning is all the lines are scanned in sequence, so you scan it line by line
So if you spare one moment to think about it, why do we want to do this interlace scan?
Why do we want to do interlace scanning? Especially in the early years
A lot of these standards were developed in the early years of video compression and transmission
So for example, interlace scanning was developed during the time
So why do you want to do interlace scanning?
Anyone?
So if you think about it, the reason why we want to do this interlace scanning
Is that each time when you're doing interlace scanning, we only scan half of the line
For example, we only scan the odd line for one frame, and afterwards we scan the even line
So therefore what it means is that when you only scan the odd line and you transmit it
The bandwidth that you use is only half
Because during the early days, bandwidth is very limited, it's very expensive
So if you can reduce the number of bits that can be transmitted, you try to do that
So therefore people think of one way is that you only scan the top line first
And you transmit this particular frame
So the bandwidth is reduced by half
But there's also problems that you have
So when you do that, as you can see, since you're only scanning half of the line
You're a little bit like cheating or cutting the corner
Because it's trying to trick our eye into trying to refresh
So even though there's some movement, it will trick your eye to interpret
This frame has been refreshed already, there's a certain movement
So that is actually the trick
The objective of interlace scanning is you reduce the number of lines
And hence you reduce the bandwidth that you need to retransmit
By trying to trick our brain into thinking that it's already updated some of the content
But the problem of this kind of interlace scanning is that for some images
Especially lines like this, when you have some imaging scene that has lots of edges and lines
Some parts of the line are updated, other lines are not updated
Then you are going to get this kind of jittering effect
So these are the jittering effects
So therefore, if you're using interlace scanning, the advantage is that you reduce the bandwidth
But the price you have to pay is that sometimes you'll get some content jittering
Like this, this is a very well-known example of jittering
So as opposed to that, you can use this progressive scanning
You scan all the lines
So the price you pay is that you transmit more bandwidth, but the quality is better
So that is during the early days
But nowadays because the bandwidth has actually increased a lot
And the compression technique has improved a lot
So therefore nowadays we hardly use this interlace scanning anymore
Most of them will be based on progressive scanning
So earlier on we also mentioned about frame rate
So frame rate is referred to how many frames is played per second
So it's given in terms of frames per second here
So depending on different countries and different standards
For example, in Singapore and Australia, we use the PALS system
Which is the video is played at 25 frames per second
And in the US and Japan, they use the NTSC standard
So the video is played at 30 frames per second
So next we are going to very quickly look at some video signal processing and application
So what is video signal processing?
So this is a very broad term as I mentioned
So video signal processing can deal with different aspects of video
So it can include things like representation
So how do you present the video?
Compression, how do you compress it into a small file size or low bit rate?
And afterwards, how do you store it?
How do you transmit it?
How do you process it?
Analyze the content and understand what the content is
So there's actually many different aspects of video
But for this particular course, we'll be focusing on these two topics
That I mentioned a few times already
So we'll be focusing on compression
And then we'll be focusing on analytics and understanding
So next let's look at some of the sample signal processing applications
So there are many, many different applications nowadays that are centered on video
So for example, we can have a business streaming e-commerce
This is particularly popular in China
Almost every year
Very, very popular in China
And then entertainment, for example, video streaming, video on demand
Some typical examples would be Netflix
Any movie that you want to watch, you can just stream it
Technology, technology enabled learning online lecture
So a few years back during COVID, it was quite serious
So we have to actually conduct most of our lectures online
So other things like, for example, in smart cities transportation
The autonomous vehicles that you have
The video analytics
So for example, the autonomous vehicles
I just read, I think a few weeks ago or last month in Wuhan
There's actually a new service, right?
It's a Luo Bo Kuai Pao
So for those applications, you need to be able to see the surroundings
And be able to perform tasks like segmentation, detection and so on
Okay, so next I'm just going to
I think for Chinese students definitely you know what this
So I'm just going to, I'm not going to do that here
Even though I'm tempted to show my QR code
And then you can also use some
, or whatever
But okay, I'm not doing here
I'm just trying to show you some of the possible applications of video processing
So this is live streaming in China
Okay, so I'll just play a short segment of it
Because the video is a bit long, so I'll just play a short segment
Sorry, because I don't pay for the Google subscription
So they always show me the advertisement
This is live stream shopping
One of the hottest trends in China
Every night, tens of millions of people watch live shows
Hosted by influencers like VIA and by the products they recommend
Or on e-commerce and social apps like Taobao and Douyin
The sister app of TikTok
It's not about only shopping
It's about the experience, it's about having fun
You got to see 3D, you got to see in some kind of action
It's almost like a theatre act
The internet craze has taken over China
By the end of 2020, the country had almost 400 million live stream shopping users
China's live stream e-commerce market has also grown dramatically
With an estimated value of 161 billion dollars in 2020
It's becoming popular outside China as well
So is live streaming the future of shopping?
Live streaming is not a new thing
In China, it started in 2015 with the rollout of 4G
And it was first used for entertainment and socializing
Many live streamers perform for their followers or chat it to them
Making money by receiving virtual currency and gifts
In the West, live streaming is mainly the doming of avid gamers
In China, it's broken into e-commerce
China actually has a very big e-commerce empire
So it uses these super apps, what we call
That you have payment, you have search of information
You have recommendation system
And you have huge amount of goods available on the platform
And as well as a lot of consumers
So with this advantage, they merge these features of live streaming
To make the influencers actually sell goods
Here is a perfect choice
Nice neutrals, beautiful prints, nothing overwhelming
And the warmth and comfort of flannel
Traditional TV shopping involves a one-way direction
Whereby a host introduces a product, demonstrates certain things
And say call this number or something
But live stream shopping is live
That in itself is a very, very big difference
That causes different psychology
And live stream shopping is a very entertaining way of engaging someone else
When you shop, actually this live streaming video will continue
It will minimize into a corner
And you can buy the items and pay all on the same app
After that, the live streaming screen will just enlarge by itself
And the promoter will come back to screen
So it's like very convenient
Taobao, one of China's biggest e-commerce platforms
Owned by tech giant Alibaba
Added a live streaming function in early 2016
In the following years, other e-commerce and social platforms
Like JD and Douyin also integrated this feature
But in the past few years, it's been difficult to make a breakthrough
People were in lockdown and many retailers were pushed online
OK, so it's a long video. So I'm not going to...
long video so I'm not going to yeah I'm not going to play the whole video but you can see now yeah
in the past this Alibaba Jingdong is very big but I heard nowadays actually people don't buy so much
from it anymore usually what people nowadays is using Pingdol right that's that's why I heard
from my wife yeah so nowadays people tend to buy very cheap stuff from Pingdol but recently I
think last year or a few months ago there's also this event ZhaDian right you are you aware of it
okay if you do not know you can go and find out later anyway yeah so okay so this is actually
therefore like video streaming right so one of the very important criteria is in order to support
applications such as video streaming you must have a very powerful video compression and
streaming technology to support it so that's what we are going to study later on for this course
which is how do we perform very efficient video compression and streaming and transmission
okay
okay another application just as video on demand so video on demand okay so this again is one of
my very favorite animation right so I'll also would like to share with you so that you can
relax a bit more
from master filmmaker Hayao Miyazaki the director of the academy award-winning
spirited away that is ancient sorcery quite powerful too
this summer experience the epic tale of a young woman transformed by a mysterious curse
oh that's really me isn't it an enchanted moving castle this is a magic house
and the one wizard powerful enough to set her free this charm will guarantee your safe return
Walt Disney Studios presents a studio jiggly production of a Hayao Miyazaki film
hold on
this June journey to amazing new worlds
aboard Howl's moving castle
okay so this animation is also my daughter's favorite
okay so the next short video that I'm going to show is about video analytics so right nowadays
you know that when together with AI and video you can do many tasks right so this particular
video is mainly going to be focusing from the surveillance and analytics perspective
so just to demonstrate some of the potential use cases
so
okay so just now from the particular video you can see that there's actually many kind of
tasks that can be achieved it turned out that actually currently I do have a project with an
industrial partner a lots of the tasks that's being described in the video actually we are also
doing it so we are quite familiar with some of those topics so pretty much for the particular
industrial project for example from the safety perspective we need to be able to detect smoke
fire know whether persons are wearing the know the mask especially during the covid
period whether they are wearing the protective here PPE personal protective equipment okay
also things like we try to you know track the movements of different objects
know count the person know perform action recognition human object interaction and so on
so these are some of the things that we can do to analyze the video application
okay let me see all right let me probably just quickly cover the next
uh two slides and then we'll you know take a short break so what are the current trends in
no video signal processing so right of course in recent years we see that there's new
ai and deep learning algorithm and models right okay so this is particularly used in the context
of video analytics and understanding okay and also progressively we have more and more
data that's being collected so therefore a new train will be the big data okay from the
processing perspective we have a better processor larger storage devices and also there's a new
emerging consumer behavior that supports some of the application for example the video that
just now we show about the you know the e-commerce live streaming e-commerce these are some of the
emerging or new consumer behaviors that require the underlying technology to support it okay and
of course over the years we have a better and better compression algorithm so this is what
we are going to study as our next topic and then we have a better video analytics uh techniques
so in terms of the technical challenges so for this particular course as i mentioned we are
be focusing on two things number one is the compression or coding yeah number two is on
the content analysis and understanding so from the perspective of compression and coding some of the
challenges is that we want our video always to have a better quality lower bit rate okay and also you
need to uh offer a certain quality of services for example just now in the live streaming we need to
make sure that you know the delay the latency the video is smooth and so on right so from the context
of uh no video content analysis and understanding so some of the challenges that we have is that
robust performance for example just now in the video that you see you do counting right you try
to detect uh no ppe right you try to detect for example uh post estimation you try to estimate
you try to analyze the whether when the worker is performing certain tasks whether it's uh no help
no kind of harmful to their uh posture and so on those we need to have a robust performance
so therefore robust performance is one of the key challenge so another common challenge that we have
is the domain gap or shift or generalization so for example if you train on this data set right
you train on this data set but later on when you want to deploy to a new environment
are you able to still achieve good performance right so this is the domain gap or shift or
generalization problem okay so other issues uh very well known in ai uh domain is no annotation
data collections and annotations are always expensive right so how do we address those
problems that's why you have things like no nowadays uh pre-trained model followed by
fine tuning or adaptation is becoming very uh popular it's because the data annotation is very
expensive but there's also other techniques like no training with a small number of data such as
few short learning and even training without no training data right which is for example known
as a zero short learning so these are some active research direction and challenge in this space here
right okay so with that i think we'll take a short break let's come back at say uh 8 15
let's come back 8 15
you
okay so let's continue so just now during the break there are some students asking some questions
regarding the exam so just now i just probably want to add on her which is uh this particular
course right so in the past actually there are two lecturers who are teaching so uh last for example okay
this course is offered in both semester semester one as well as semester two so the previous semester
there's actually a guest lecturer okay and then uh the semester before actually there's a second
lecture so therefore uh that means what what i'm trying to say is that no uh usually i would suggest
students can actually if they are not too sure about the exam question they can go to the uh library
and then download past year exam question for you know a few years like two years or so then roughly
you have a certain feel about what kind of questions you will come out already but it's just that for
this particular course because for the past semesters there's always a second lecture so therefore uh
what i'm trying to say is that i would still encourage you to know go to the library download
the past year exam question but only look at for example the first two questions yeah because the
first two questions are uh set by me the last two questions depending on which year sometimes is set
by another lecture so therefore with that then you have a better appreciation or feeling about how
the question will look like so that's one suggestion the second suggestion the second point is actually
for a lot of the uh past year exam question for my lecture notes i'll try to include them into the
lecture notes and then we'll go through those uh exercises and questions together so in even if
you do not go and download those uh exam past year exam question but you by going through the lecture
exercises you would still have a certain feeling or familiarity with what kind of question they'll
be asked okay so therefore you don't have to worry too much so it's up to you if you want to
download the question from the library okay just be a bit aware that some of the question is set by
the second lecture so it may not be relevant okay so yeah and second is that you can also refer to
our you know lecture exercise you know as far as possible i'll usually at least include some past
year exam question in the exercise okay in the lectures so that's the first point i just want to
clarify uh the second point actually early on i already mentioned early on so uh for this year
in terms of the dissertation right um yeah because we received really many many applications
so unfortunately we don't have time to be able to reply each individual email so that's why you know
we want to ask for know your understanding that we will not be able to reply every single email
because there are just too many of them and also when we or at least for myself usually because
there are so many applications so usually when i look at a student if i feel that he's a good
student i'll assign the projects to him or her already and then afterwards i'll finish the
assignment of all my projects but subsequently actually there are a lot other strong students
so therefore please don't feel that you know because i do not choose your you know choose you
is because you are not a good student it's just that there are too many and some of they are
actually some very strong students but somehow at the end i only uh kind of notice them later
okay sometimes it's a the area may not match so well but sometimes it's just the way you know we
just assign the projects so yeah i just want to clarify that so at least some of you have a
certain understanding why i did not reply to some of your email okay
so
all right okay so the next thing we are going to talk about is a few image and video standards
here right so this slides give a quick summary of some of the image and video standards right
so if you have a quick look there's a few different entities or organizations that develop
standards so in early years we have this organization known as itut so itut they develop
the standards they they develop is called h.26x series so you can see a 261 okay 262 263 264 so
these are the standards that's developed by itut okay and then there's another organization which
is impact also known as iso so for iso the standard that they develop they call impact series so you
have impact one impact two impact four all right and so on and so forth right they are also sometimes
when this itut and iso they try to develop the standard together right so some of the well-known
one is actually this impact two actually this impact two by right they should draw it here
because it's jointly developed by them okay h.264 is also jointly developed by them and then h.265
so some of the standards are jointly developed by them so on top of that you also have some other
organization for example this uh society of moving picture and television engineer they develop vc1
standard and google they also develop their own sets of standards as well so these are a few
different organizations that develop the video standard so when they talk about video standard
what it means is a video compression okay or coding standard so let's quickly go through some
of these well-known standards so the first standard that we have is the jpeg standard so jpeg i think
most some of you probably have heard about it before it's a very popular image compression
standard so it's used to compress image so jpeg is also known as iso iec international standard
10918 or itut recommendation t.81 so of course you don't have to memorize this number
you know it's just kind of for your information right so officially jpeg is known as these two
standards so if any of you are interested you can go and download this particular
jpeg standard it's the size of a book right so there's no need to go and spend too much time
reading it up okay and it's developed by a particular body known as joint photographic
expert group or jpeg so that's why this particular image compression standard
afterwards you know take over the name of this body that developed the standard
right okay so next we are going to look at the families of mpeg standards here so mpeg standard
started in 92 right so the first standard that was developed is called mpeg one right so mpeg one
is a standard that contain video compression and it also perform audio compression right so at the
time is trying to target the application which is like you know for cd-rom okay for cd-rom right so
i'm not even too sure for your generation whether you know what cd-rom right so cd-rom is something
like this that is like the music cd that you listen to right so but it's for computer so that's
cd-rom so at the time is targeting for cd-rom and the bit rate is 1.5 megabits per second so that's
the target bit rate so arising from this particular mpeg one standard there's a particular commercial
product arising from it which is known as the vcd so any one of you have watched vcd before
right it's probably two you are still too young so at the time i still remember i was in i can
remember in in high school or in university if you want to watch a standard movie 60 minute
a movie you need two of this vcd this okay right so this is uh during the early years
right okay and afterwards uh things of course start to progress then we move on to mpeg two
standard so mpeg two standard is also known as the h.262 right so it was developed in 94 many
years ago so one of the key characteristics of this mpeg two standard is that it's a video and
audio coding with different profile okay so this different profile means that is trying to target
for different use cases in application right okay so in different applications sometimes there's a
different uh you know kind of image quality requirement some of them can be smaller some
of them the the size can be bigger and also their quality uh quality expectation is different okay
some is probably for lower end kind of use cases some is for some higher quality video so because
of that you have a wider range of the bit rate okay so for mpeg two it can cover a wider range
of bit rate from two to 80 megabits per second so the relevant products okay so the product arising
from this mpeg two is a dvd i think dvd very likely you probably heard about it if not at
least your parents you know should still have some uh dvds from the older days okay and then
things start to uh move on then we have the mpeg four so mpeg four is actually a content based video
coding that means you try to contain uh perform video compression by looking at the content of
the video right so some of the very unique features of mpeg four is that uh it provide
uh coding coding actually also means compression so coding or compressions of natural or synthetic
media objects so either the object is natural occurring or whether it's for example some
animation the kind of generated content or synthetic content so mpeg four is used to target
to compress those kinds of uh content right okay then afterwards we move on to the h.26x series of
the standards okay so this is another important family of the standards here so it started in
many years ago it started off with a h.261 so it's developed in uh 90s right by this particular
organization known as the ccitt so ccitt again the name you don't have to memorize it's just
for your information so ccitt stand for international telegraph and telephone consultative committee
right but this uh body later on was renamed as itut right if you look at the full name is international
telecom nation union international telecom nations standardization sector right so you don't have to
worry too much about it because it's quite a lot but probably what you need to know is that
right this standard was uh developed by itut okay so uh this particular standard is uh based on dct
based video compression uh scheme so dct is a discrete cosine transform so it's the types of
uh transform that we are going to study later on so therefore for this particular standard h.261
right is used to perform video compression and is using this particular dct transform
discrete cosine transform okay and it has many similarity with mpeg-1 okay its original target
application is for video conferencing so originally when uh no the body developed this h.261
is mainly for uh tele video or teleconferencing so that means no when i call you right you'll
be able to talk to me in uh real time so because it's used for video conferencing therefore their
bit rate requirement is very low yeah because it's for video conferencing that means you need to be
able to perform the compression very quickly yeah so you need to be fast you need to compress it
very quickly and you need to transmit this particular video right very quickly that means
the bit rate need to be very low so therefore for this h.261 their bit rate is a multiple of
64 kilobits per second right so first 64 kilobits per second is very low okay so yeah whereas the p
can run from uh values of 1 to 30 so it's actually very low bit rate so therefore you can kind of
recognize in the early days right h.26 series of standard initially is mainly used for you know
video conferencing therefore the requirement is that it has to be low bit rate the compression
need to be fast yeah because you are using it for video conferencing okay and then afterwards uh no
the next major standard right there's actually a h.262 right okay if you see this one now there's
a h.263 already what happened to h.262
right you can see it's a h.261 usually 261 you expect 262 263 and so on right so what happened
there's a missing h.262
so it turned out that right if you remember this uh iso and itut sometimes they work together they
collaborate so it turned out that this h.262 is also known as impact 2 that we covered early on
so therefore h.262 is also uh impact 2 yeah so 262 is also known as impact 2 they are the same
right so it was uh because it was jointly developed by these two uh organizations okay so
because it's covered in impact 2 already so we will not touch it here so uh the objective of
today's lecture is more for uh overview or quick introduction so we are not going to go into the
detail in subsequent lecture we will learn more about it okay so this h.263 right is um okay
there's actually a few different versions of it so the first version v1 is developed in 95
okay so of course you expect the performance is better than the previous uh 261 okay so it's also
mainly for video conferencing therefore you expect it to be fast you expect the bit rate to be low
okay yeah and afterwards there's a new improvement version 2 and version 3 so for version 2 and version
3 we call also called uh 263 plus and plus plus okay so these are different versions or improvement
right okay and then afterwards things uh continue on then we move on to h.264 so h.264 again there's
a few common name that's being used right we can call it h.264 sometimes we also call it advanced
video coding or avc okay sometimes they also call it mpeg for part 10 so all this refer to the same
thing okay so it was standardized in 2003 right uh of course you expect since it was a later standard
right it's going to perform better than uh the previous version h.263 all right so it has a
wide range of application like internet video computer no hd tv uh blu-ray and so on and so
so nowadays right if you go to the internet right and if you download a video very likely the standard
that you are going to get is the h.264 or mp4 right if all some of you have downloaded some
video nowadays right this is currently the most popular and dominant uh video standard at the
moment okay h.264 right okay and then afterwards things continue you know i mean the body continue
to improve the standard so the next one is the h.265 all right so it's also known as a high
evision video coding or gvc here so uh it's basic structure right in terms of the algorithm is very
similar to 264 okay but it has a few uh feature it can support higher resolution now 8k resolution
and up to 120 frame per second right okay and also uh it's more efficient in terms of a bit
rate quality trade-off right uh because typically right for a good video you want the bit rate to be
low and you want the quality to be high but usually if your bit rate is low your quality
will not be so good and vice versa so as a whole h.265 can actually achieve this trade-off better
than 264
right okay so the mpeg and the h.26x series are two dominant important video compression standards
but there are also some other standards uh out there so the first one is vc1 so vc1 is uh developed
by this uh society known as society of motion picture and tv television engineers right it was
supported by a microsoft uh window media video so these are more like no factual information
because if you are studying this course and people ask you know you are studying about
video compression can you at least tell us some of the standard at least you'll be aware you know
these are currently some of the you know standards that's out there okay so another uh recent popular
one is uh this vp8 so vp8 is target for a web video right the video that's embedded in the
internet right okay so it support this web video format and it can support up to 4k resolution
okay and vp9 is also developed by google right so it's an improvement to vp8 so you can see
its structure is actually similar to vp8 so it's an improvement but in terms of resolution now
it's better it can support up to 8k and 120 uh frame per second so yeah so these are some of the
popular and current major standards out there right okay so the next topic we want to very
quickly touch on is on the video analysis and understanding so uh early on as i mentioned for
this course right there's the compression there's a video analytics and actually uh there's also
going to be on the emerging direction but the part i have not finalized it so these are the a few key
expect for this particular course so under the video analysis and understanding so what we'll
do is that we'll try to you know uh for this course these are some of the tasks we'll be studying
because even for video content and analysis now there's many many many different topics that you
can uh talk about so that's why we are going to select some no use case right on an application
and try to you know explain them or cover in this lecture so in this lecture some of the important
tasks that we'll cover including uh object detections and tracking okay uh post estimation for
example how do you detect uh different poles of the human right just now you can also see from the
video that we have no for post estimation one very common things is that you can use to
you know study for example the ergonomics right you can use do uh jayshir recognition for example
recognize different hand jayshir you can use to uh once you estimate different poles on the body
you can also use it to perform action recognition trying to find out whether they are no drinking
water or walking or playing balls and things like that so those are the post estimation but okay we
also will be covering some action recognition so you'll try to analyze different actions in
the video human actions in the video so these are some of the selected uh topics we'll cover under
this video analysis right okay so next i'm going to play you a few short video to explain
right some of those tasks that object detection
yeah so next i'll try to play you a short a few short video to explain some of the
tasks that we have uh mentioned in case because i know that for your group your background is
very diverse you have some students which has a bit more experience in you know this AI computer
vision but there's also a large percentage of a student who doesn't have this background so i'll
play you a few short video just to give you some sense about some of the tasks that we are going
to cover in the later part of lecture so that you have a certain idea so the first task that we are
going to do is about object detection so i'll play you this video it's about two minutes plus
to explain what object detection is a pinnacle in artificial intelligence but it co-exists with us
in our lives hiding in plain sight we often fail to notice simple applications of object
detection around us have you ever wondered how a face unlock works on your smartphone or how a
self-driving car operates on its own the answer is object detection so what is object detection
technically object detection is a technology that includes computer vision and image processing
used to detect objects in images or videos sounds interesting let's break it down for you
using a simple example self-driving cars make use of the moving object detection technology
where computer vision and image processing are used to determine the distance between the car
and the moving objects to create alerts and guide the self-driving cars you must be wondering what
is the technology behind it well artificial intelligence is the basic principle that drives
object detection the idea is simple the data is collected through computer vision the data is then
fed into the model and using machine learning algorithms or deep learning algorithms inclusions
are made the camera collects the image from different angles and sends it to the image
processing unit now based on how the model was trained and what the training data was the results
are laid out to the system in the form of alerts or instructions like how far the object is if the
object is moving or if the object has stopped object detection has also been paving a glorious
path for the surveillance industry traffic tracking systems activity recognition even sentiment
analysis through object detection are all possible now surveillance has picked up a lot of pace with
object detection with increasing efficiency in object detection technology it is evident that
artificial intelligence is on the rise and it will eventually create a lot of job opportunities
in the coming years as well at eureka's postgraduate program in ai ml in collaboration
with nid varangal will help you in mastering such advanced ai concepts with the help of experience
okay so therefore you can see from this video the objective of object detection is to try to
detect different instances of objects in the scene so there's actually object detection even though
it's a more fundamental task but it actually also have various challenges for example you need to
be able to handle different imaging condition yeah different viewpoint now the size whether it's big
object or small object sometimes different lighting condition for example currently i have one
particular project with a company so for this particular project we are trying to put some
camera in the car cabin and try to you know analyze the you know the actions and the behaviors of the
drivers as well as the passengers as well as detect different objects in the car so this could be used
for example in application for example the one that we mentioned in wuhan the
low ball quite power right so if you go into the car you know if you try to scratch their car they
will see that you're doing something that you're not supposed to be or you live behind something
they will actually alert you so yeah for example in car environment one of the challenge that you
have is the lighting condition yeah sometimes no it can be a bit too dark in the car environment
so therefore you need to investigate different issues like using different
sensing modality for example just now the camera that we talked about using the rgb camera as well
as the no infrared okay near infrared capture this information and then try to fuse them
to help you to perform object detection as well as action recognition so therefore
there are actually still quite a lot of uh no challenges in problems such as object detection
okay so the next uh video that we are going to show is the object tracking so what's the meaning
of object tracking so we can yeah pretty much as the name suggests is that once you detect the object
you want to track the movement of the object okay you want to track the movement so there's many
uh cases why you may want to do that for example for separate security application and so on yeah
yeah so let me just play you this short video on object tracking
so
okay yeah so for example now you can see from the video quite clearly what's the objective of the
object tracking is that you want to track the movement of the person so what are some common
challenges in this object tracking one common one is the occlusion if you're for example the
person you are trying to track they go you know behind a particular structure okay say this
building so part of my body now is obscured so when i move out and reappear can you still track
that it's the same person so these are some challenge other things include for example if
you're a two person you know walking in opposite direction right and afterwards say suppose they
cross over would you somehow switch the id the track number you would think that is now different
person or if these two person they meet here and afterwards they move separate in a separate way
if you just follow the trajectory path you will thought that you know this person is becoming here
and this person is becoming here but actually sometimes they could just meet and then they're
separate so therefore id switch the switch of different id is also a challenge in this object
tracking right so let's continue to look at some of the other right okay so this video shows you
post estimation so post estimation pretty much means that you want to estimate the key point
or the key important joint of the body so it can be a full body post estimation or it can be for
example your facial post estimation some of the key point on your face or some of the key point on
your head so these are some a few different possible variations of the post estimation
so let me just play for you this short video
so
you can see it's trying to estimate all the important key points right
so once you estimate this important key point you can use to analyze the actions of the
you know the person actually in gyms is a very natural no use case of post estimation
I used to have one research staff right he he used to work in a project in uh Korea yeah and
they're actually doing exactly this which is using the post estimation to analyze the movement of the
of the person who do the workout in a gym yeah
so
they should bring a mattress then he can fold up a bit faster
oh
yeah so in the past I still remember there was a project which is they're using a post estimation
to do the uh Parkinson disease progression you know what's a Parkinson disease right
no Parkinson disease is characterized by no uh we start when you walk especially for old older
person when you walk actually your swing of the hand is asymmetric one hand swing normally the
other hand doesn't swing a lot actually I also notice sometimes when I walk that's how I walk
so actually it can be used to analyze for example whether your Parkinson disease has deteriorated
over time okay so the next one is actually on uh action recognition so action recognition for
this video is mainly focusing on sports video but it can be a lot more for example in the context of
a factory uh kind of assembly task you can analyze whether this particular worker is performing what
task whether it's tightening tightening a nuts no applying some screw and so on so currently we are
also uh no discussing with a uh a company right to know uh try to perform this action recognition
for worker who is trying to perform some assembly tasks yeah so uh but for this video is for a sports video
right so there are different action whether it's like you know dribbling the balls
no whether it's like no trying to block no and and so on so there's a different actions
for this particular sports video okay but in general case of course it can be a lot broader
okay like the one that I mentioned trying to analyze different actions in assembly tasks
or in a more generous setting to try out find out whether you are drinking water you're walking
no or you are smoking and so on
okay so the next uh video this one is called egocentric human object interactions so egocentric
means that is no the viewpoint is like the human viewpoint the first person perspective viewpoint
and human object interaction as the name suggests the interaction between human and objects so in
many of the tasks are when the worker is trying to learn something at the form certain tasks
you know we need to understand what the worker is doing right how does it manipulate the objects
and so on so this is also one topic which is known as an egocentric human object interaction
okay
it's from interactions between hands with objects
audio can be a prime discriminator for actions such as washing or frying
it can also differentiate between objects within actions such as
putting a plate versus putting a bag
okay audio captures sounds of actions out of the camera's field of view such as eating
but can also capture irrelevant background music
we propose mid-level fusion of three modalities rgb flow and audio for audio we extract the raw
waveform from the sound stream of the video which we transform into a spectrogram
convolutional features are pooled and mid-level fusion is learned through feature concatenation
we learn the action as multitask verb and noun classifiers importantly we train using
asynchronous fusion we fuse modalities with a range of temporal offsets within a temporal
binding window evidence in neuroscience points to the presence of such temporal
binding windows across sensory input in humans within each binding window modality samples are
randomly selected tbw's are sparsely sampled within the action and could be overlapping
predictions are temporally aggregated by averaging to obtain video level multimodal predictions
importantly we first bind and fuse modalities within windows before temporal aggregation of
different windows tbn is trained end to end where all modalities are trained simultaneously
and the weights are shared over time we next present qualitative results of tbn on the epic
kitchens data set
so
okay yeah so this is one of the earlier works that was done to perform human object interaction
actually this human object interaction is very difficult to do it's still very challenging
because there's a lot of challenges for example you need to perform action detection or temporal
video segmentation right from what you see that actually no a lot of the earlier for example action
recognitions are usually the video we chop it into small segments okay and then for each of the video
segment we try to you know classify what kind of action it is but for a continuous video like this
given a particular video you need to divide into different segments so that different
segments actually correspond to different action so that particular task is known as a temporal
video segmentation so that one even to do that to nicely cut it into different video segment
in itself is already a challenge and also from just now you can see the video when the person
is doing some tasks there's lots of noise sometimes he will just move around and then go and do
something else and we come back so how do we recognize those actions are not of interest to
us and they are noise yeah so there's also for example when you're dealing with this object in
real life there's lots of background clutters and you know different objects that is not interested
that you are not interested in so it's in short this is still a very difficult and challenging problem
okay so next I'll just very briefly talk about some of the emerging topics right so in
recent years of course generative AI is becoming very you know important so I think many of you
probably have seen like chat gbt whereas you can generate the new content it can become a chat box
it can become an assistant you can interact with them in a very natural way other things like
them in a very natural way other things like you know for example image generation so how many of
you have used some image generation tools like you know mid-journey or stable diffusion
yeah I can see a few person raising their hand so you can see no reason in recent year right if
you want to generate text generate image this is actually a very hot topic in uh in recent year
because in the past in the past for AI it tends to be discriminative right in other words for
example in the past AI tends to try to classify an image or video into this category or that
category so they cannot generate new content but in recent year right no uh this in I think year
2018 forwards this generative AI is becoming very important because it can generate new content
so generative AI is a class of model that can generate new content such as a text image audio
okay and so on so if you are referring to for example text generation one very popular model is
the gbt generative pre-trained transformer okay so for this course we will also touch on this a
little bit later okay and then for image generation uh no a well-known technique is a stable diffusion
okay so it support various types of application like chat box you ask question they will answer
you okay content uh generation for example you can use the transformer to ask them to write a novel
write a story okay and virtual assistant for those of you who have watched uh this interaction the
recent uh chat gb this gbt 4o you will know that no you can actually interact with them in a very
natural way right so another kind of a very important emerging direction in recent year
is the idea of this foundation model so what's the foundation model so foundation model is a
class of model that are trained on large scale broad data that can be adapted or fine-tuned to
wide range of downstream tasks or application so in a more traditional way you know in the past
when people want to say suppose they want to solve a particular problem what they need to do
for example if you want to recognize different plants in singapore right so suppose if you join
a company and the company asks you to develop a mobile app that can recognize different plants
in singapore what do you have to do so if you think about it so what it means likely is that
you have to go and collect some you know images your plant images in singapore and then you have
to employ an expert to tell you what this different you know categories of plants it is and afterwards
you need to spend lots of money to do that collection annotation and afterwards you need
to train this model from the scratch to develop your uh plan recognition or classification algorithm
so that's in the past that means for each problems that you have you need to collect the data set
you need to train a AI model and then afterwards then you can deploy it so different use case you
need to collect different data set and you need to train a new model so this of course you can see
it's very expensive because data collection you know is very expensive and annotation is very
expensive so this foundation model is basically based on this idea is that you're going to train
on a very large scale data so this large scale data can be billions of images right it's broad
data that means you try to train over a wide range of different types of data okay and afterwards
once you have fully trained it you can then use it to adapt or do it some fine tuning so that you can
then use it to deploy for your specific application yeah so that's the high level idea so you can see
this is the high level idea you have lots of data right it's a large scale broad data you use it to
train a very big foundation model so this foundation model is very big you have seen many different
things already so afterwards once you have this foundation model depending on what is your
downstream application you can then use it to do some adaptation or simple fine tuning right
so that you can then use it to address some specific problem so therefore this foundation
model in recent years is actually past one or two years is becoming very important okay and many
people are trying to spend time to develop this different way for example to adapt your big
foundation model so some examples of foundation models are large language model for example gpt
that we have seen and vision language model model that combine the vision and the language
so a very well known example is the clip model
okay so next we have a short video actually the video is long but i'm not going to play the
whole video i just play a short segment right just to give you a feel know how is the current
train right as well as some background in generative ai and foundation model so let me just play this
particular video for you
ever since computers were invented they've really just been glorified calculators machines that
execute the exact instructions given to them by the programmers but something incredible is
happening now computers have started gaining the ability to learn and think and communicate
just like we do they can do creative intellectual work that previously only humans could do we call
this technology generative ai and you may have encountered it already through products like chat
gpt basically intelligence is now available as a service kind of like a giant
sky that anyone can talk to it's not perfect but it is surprisingly capable and it is improving
at an exponential rate this is a big deal it's going to affect just about every person and company
on the planet positively or negatively this video is here to help you understand what generative ai
is all about in practical terms beyond the hype the better you understand this technology as a
person team or company the better equipped you will be to survive and thrive in the age of ai
so here's the silly but useful mental model for this you have einstein in your basement in
fact everyone does and by einstein i really mean the combination of every smart person who ever
lived you can talk to einstein whenever you want he has instant access to the sum of all human
knowledge and will answer anything you want within seconds never running out of patience he can also
take on any role you want a comedian poet doctor coach and will be an expert within that field
he has some human-like limitations though he can make mistakes he can jump to conclusions he can
misunderstand you but the biggest limitation is actually your imagination and your ability to
communicate effectively with him this skill is known as prompt engineering and in the age of ai
this is as essential as reading and writing most people vastly underestimate what this einstein
in your basement can do it's like going to the real einstein and asking him to proofread a high
school report or hiring a world-class five-star chef and having him chop onions the more you
interact with einstein the more you will discover surprising and powerful ways for him to help you
or your company okay enough fluffy metaphors let's clarify some terms ai as you probably know stands
for artificial intelligence ai is not new feels like machine learning and computer vision have
been around for decades whenever you see a youtube recommendation or a web search result or whenever
you get a credit card transaction approved that's traditional ai in action generative ai is ai that
generates new original content rather than just finding or classifying existing content that's the
g and gpt for example large language models or lms are a type of generative ai that can communicate
using normal human language chat gpt is a product by the company open ai it started as an lm
essentially an advanced chat bot using a new architecture called the transformer architecture
which by the way is the t and gpt it is so fluent at human language that anyone can use it you don't
need to be an ai expert or programmer and that's kind of what triggered the whole revolution
so how does it actually work well a large language model is an artificial neural network basically a
bunch of numbers or parameters connected to each other similar to how our brain is a bunch of
neurons or brain cells connected to each other neural networks only deal with numbers you send
in numbers and depending on how the parameters are set all the numbers come out but any kind of
content such as text or images can be represented as numbers so let's say i write dogs are when i
send that to a large language model that gets converted to numbers processed by the neural
network and then the resulting numbers are converted back into text in this case the word
animals dogs are animals so yeah this is basically a guess the next word machine the interesting part
is if we take that output and combine it with input and send it through the model again then
it will continue adding new words that's what's going on behind the scenes when you type something
in chat gpt in this case for example it generated a whole story and i can continue this indefinitely
by adding more prompts a large language model may have billions or even trillions of parameters
that's why they're called large so how are all these numbers set well not through manual
programming that would be impossible but through training just like babies learning to speak a
baby isn't told how to speak she doesn't get an instruction manual instead she listens to people
speaking around her and when she's heard enough she starts seeing the pattern she speaks a few
words at first to the delight of her parents and then later on full sentences similarly during a
training period the language model is fed a mind-boggling amount of text to learn from mostly
from internet sources it then plays guess the next word with all of this over and over again
and the parameters are automatically tweaked until it starts getting really good at predicting the
next word this is called backpropagation which is a fancy term for oh i guessed wrong i better change
something however to become truly useful a model also needs to undergo human training this is called
reinforcement learning with human feedback and it involves thousands of hours of humans painstakingly
testing and evaluating output from the model and giving feedback kind of like training a dog with
a clicker to reinforce good behavior that's why a model like gpt won't tell you how to rob a bank
it knows very well how to rob a bank but through human training it has learned that it shouldn't
help people commit crimes when training is done the model is mostly frozen other than some fine
tuning that can happen later that's what the p stands for in gpt pre-trained although in the
future we will probably have models that can learn continuously rather than just during training and
fine tuning now although chat gpt kind of got the ball rolling gpt isn't the only model out there
in fact new models are sprouting like mushrooms they vary a lot in terms of speed capability and
cost some can be downloaded and run locally others are only online some are free or open source
others are commercial products some are super easy to use while others require complicated
technical setup some are specialized for certain use cases others are more general and can be used
for almost anything and some are baked into products in the form of co-pilots or chat windows
it's it's the wild west just keep in mind that you generally get what you pay for so with a free
model you may just be getting a smart high school student in your basement rather than einstein
the difference between for example gpt 3.5 and gpt 4 is massive note that there are different
types of generative ai models that generate different types of content text-to-text models
like gpt4 take text as input and generate text as output the text can be natural language but it can
also be structured information like code and json or html i use this a lot myself to generate
code when programming it saves an incredible amount of time and
yeah so yeah i guess i'll probably stop here because i can see some students starting to
prepare to leave right okay so anyway it's quite an interesting video right you can actually go
and i provide the link you have go and i've looked uh just give me a few more seconds i'm
trying to finish this okay so in this lecture we cover the following topic okay see you
next week
you