Good evening, welcome back.
Welcome back.
So just before we start the lecture, there's a number of announcements.
So number one is that today you'll notice that the lecture, there's lots of flowers.
Not for today's lecture, it's actually tomorrow there's some VIP who's going to use this
banning.
So I was asked to inform you all not to touch the flowers and the decoration in front.
Okay.
All right.
So that's our first announcement.
Number one is regarding the makeup lecture.
So I think in week seven, actually I informed you that next week I'll be attending a conference
overseas.
So therefore we need to arrange a makeup.
So therefore for the makeup lecture is going to be on this coming Saturday.
So 12th of October.
The time will be from 9am to 12 noon.
So it's actually an online Zoom lecture.
So I'll try to record the lecture and afterwards I'll make it available online.
But of course you should try to attend it if you're available.
And then because there's this makeup lecture, so on week nine, okay, 17th of October, which
is the regular Thursday lecture, there will be no lecture on week nine.
So it'll be replaced by this coming Saturday makeup lecture.
Right.
So that's for the makeup lecture one.
So for makeup lecture two, once it's a bit closer, I'll remind you again.
Okay.
So okay, I have also sent out this particular announcement.
So all of you should have received an announcement regarding this makeup lecture for week nine.
So there's this announcement.
So what you need to do is just go to your email.
You'll see that there's actually a link.
You just click on the link and you'll be able to join the Zoom lecture.
So there's arrangement for this coming Saturday makeup lecture.
So that's the first thing.
So the second thing I want to remind you is also regarding the crease.
Right.
So because, okay, so this week eight, right, we have today's lecture.
Saturday is makeup of week nine.
So that means after Saturday, I won't be seeing you in week nine, but week 10 itself is already
the crease.
So I also want to take the opportunity to remind you regarding the crease.
Right.
So the crease just to remind you.
Okay.
So it'll be on week 10, 24th of October, nine, sorry, eight to eight, 40 PM.
So in the first one hour or so, we'll still conduct a short kind of lecture.
And afterwards I'll give you a break and then we'll start the crease at 8 PM.
Right.
So the venue is the same venue as this LT.
So it's a Likong Shin LT.
So topic cover is part three and part four.
Right.
Okay.
Once on the day, try to sit alternately.
In the LT.
So arrive 10 minutes early, bring along your matriculation card for attendance taking.
Right.
And for whatever reason, if you are absent, please send me an email with some reason,
for example, MC and so on.
So that I can arrange a makeup for you.
Right.
So that's the announcement that I shared with you last time.
Okay.
So then the next thing is regarding the class list.
Yeah.
Okay.
So as I mentioned before, please check your serial number.
So especially for those students with the same name, please make sure that which check your
serial number carefully because later on on the question booklet, the question booklet,
you're supposed to write down this serial number.
Okay.
So this is to make it a lot more easier for us to check who, who is present and who is
absent and also for our mark entering purpose.
Okay.
So if you have not done that, please try to scan through the name list and found what
is your sit number or serial number.
Okay.
All these documents are actually available in the course site under the crease.
So you can also read it up.
Okay.
And then for the crease, this is the question booklet.
This how it's going to be.
Right.
So on the top left corner, there's a serial number.
So this is the one that just now you should found what's the number and then you should
fill in here.
Okay.
And the creases 40 minutes, right?
Make sure you write down your full name and your methylation number.
Right.
So, uh, you, the question, there'll be a few questions, right?
There'll be some space for you to write your answer or calculation.
And at the bottom, usually there are some, uh, designated place for you to write down
your answer.
So please try to write down your final answer in this, uh, designated, uh, no places.
Usually when I do the marking, if there are some calculation marking, I'll just, uh,
if there's some calculation problem, I'll just check your answer at the bottom.
If your answer agree with what I have, usually I'll think, no, you, you answer it correctly.
So I wouldn't check too much detail.
But on the other hand, if you, for example, your numerical answer is not correct, then
I'll probably go back to check where other steps they make mistake.
Okay.
Uh, anyway, make sure that you write down your answer at the, uh, no, the bottom.
So there's going to be a few, uh, pages.
Yeah.
And then, uh, yeah.
So this is just the cover page.
So that's for the quiz.
Right.
One more thing.
Um, okay.
There's one more thing which is regarding this, uh, sitting arrangement because the
class is really big.
Yeah.
On that day, right, we need to get some student helper to help me to take attendance.
And also when we collect it, we need to tell you, right, whether, uh, no, attendance.
So therefore, instead of letting your sit randomly, which will make it very hard for
us to, you know, uh, to tell you, right.
So we think that the, okay, probably one of the most efficient way is try to sit according
to this sitting arrangement.
So just now for those students, you check your serial number here.
So for those students whose serial number is between one to 100, please sit at this,
uh, section here.
So which is the top, right?
Uh, a bit.
Okay.
So this three sections is one to 100.
And then the central three sections is, uh, 100 to one to 200.
And then this section here is, uh, 200 and one to 300.
Okay.
And then vice versa.
So you can see, uh, this sitting arrangement.
Please try your best to sit according to this arrangement so that when we conduct, uh, your
quiz paper, we can file the attendance very quickly.
All right.
Any questions so far regarding the crease?
Okay.
So I hope it's clear.
Huh?
Right.
So this is the announcement regarding the crease, right?
Then, uh, next we should be ready to, uh, continue with the lecture.
Right.
Okay.
So, so we are going to continue on with the CNN as I mentioned, right?
Some of you probably have already studied this before, but they are some students have
not, uh, studied this right.
So if you have, uh, no studied this before, just bear with me, right?
Probably you can also get some, uh, new insight, but I'll probably try to, you know, increase
the pace a little bit when we cover this section.
So in, uh, the lecture before the break, we look at this, uh, CNN architecture.
So we mainly mentioned that this CNN actually has a number of different layer.
Okay.
You have the input, you have the convolution and ReLU layer.
Which is used to extract some, um, high level cover extract some features in a hierarchical
manner.
Okay.
But pretty much the first few layers mainly is for feature learning, right?
So which is the one to extract some feature that can represent the image.
And then the next few layers use the classification, right?
Which consists of the FC layer as the, as well as the soft max layer is to classify this,
right?
Feature or this embedding or this factor into one of the classes.
Right.
So this is the high level overview.
So next we're going to look at each of the layer in CNN a bit more in details.
Right.
Okay.
So the basic architecture of CNN is as follow.
So we have the convolutional layer.
Okay.
Activation function layer, pulling layer.
FC layer.
FC layer is also the linear layer that we have studied in previous lecture.
And then finally the soft max layer.
Right.
So what's a convolutional layer?
So the name CNN actually takes after this convolution process here.
So convolution layer, the goal is that is try to extract some features in a hierarchical
manner.
So early layers extract simple features.
Later layers extract more complicated features.
So we can see early layer extract simple feature like low level feature like point edge and
so on.
And later layers extract high level feature.
Right.
So one of the important properties of this convolutional layer is that it reduce the
number of parameter by weight sharing through this filter or also known as a kernel.
Right.
So you're going to apply the train filter or kernel across all the positions in the image.
So the same filter is going to be applied across all the positions.
So therefore you reduce the number of parameter quite significantly.
Okay.
So this is known as the, you know, this which sharing through the same kernel or filter
across all different spatial position in the image.
Right.
Okay.
So this slide shows the visualizations.
Right.
Suppose you have an image.
You have a few different layers.
So you can see early layer tends to extract some low level feature, very simple feature.
Okay.
Higher level tends to extract a lot more complicated features ready because it's progressively
trying to extract combinations of, no, from low level to become combinations of mid level
feature combinations of mid level feature that will obtain some more complex high level
feature.
Okay.
So, and then finally you have the classifier that will perform the classification, which
usually consists of the FC as well as the softmax layers.
Right.
Okay.
So next we are going to go through how do we perform the convolution so you can take
this as a revision if you have studied before.
So suppose you have an image, which is 32 by 32 by three.
So 32 by 32 and is three is three channel RGB image here.
So when you want to apply a filter to perform the convolution, right.
So this particular filter, the spatial dimension is five by five.
Okay.
So you can see it's five by five here.
And then the last dimension three is actually the depth.
So this three here, this number here three need to be consistent with the input, no volume,
the depth or the number of channel for the input volume.
Right.
Okay.
So that when you superimpose on each other, the filter that dimension and the input volume
channel is consistent.
Right.
Okay.
So this thing is, this that dimension is kind of understood.
Sometimes when we talk about a convolution, very often sometimes when we talk about filter,
we ignore this number, we just simply say it's five by five filter, for example, but
it's understood that, okay, there's still a depth channel and this num, the depth channel
right need to be consistent with the number of channel for your input volume.
Right.
Okay.
So that's just for your information.
Right.
So how do we perform convolution?
So when perform convolution, what we do is that we take one of these particular filter,
for example, five by five by three filter, we put it at the top left corner.
Okay.
So you superimpose and then you perform a sum of product operation.
Some of product operation means that you multiply the corresponding value.
Okay.
And then you sum it up.
So when you do that, you generate a single output value.
So this single output value would then be written as here.
And then next you will take this particular filter, you shift to the, no, to the right
by the amount shift.
For example, if the amount shift is one position, okay, so this filter now is located at this
position here.
You perform this sum of product operation or the filtering operation or roughly speaking
the convolution operation, then you'll be able to obtain the second value, which is
located here.
So therefore you slides this particular corner or filter across all the position.
Your output will be what is known as the activation map or feature map.
Okay.
Activation map or feature map.
Right.
So you can see that in this case here, the dimension is 28 by 28.
So if you pause one moment and think about why is the output dimension 28 by 28?
So if you think about it, right, you have this five by five filter.
When this five by five filter is put at the top left corner here, the center of this particular
filter here with respect to the coordinate for this particular input volume here is actually
at three.
Yeah.
And as you shift it to the extreme right direction, okay, the center of this particular
filter now will be located at 30.
So it's known from position three all the way to 30 is 30 minus three, which is 27,
but you also need to add in a boundary condition.
So add up with one that will give you the dimensions of 28.
All right.
So therefore if you slice it, every time you perform this convolution or the filtering or
the sum of product, you're all referred to the same thing, then you are going to get
one slice or one channel of your activation map, which looks like this 28 by 28 by one.
Okay.
So therefore by using one particular filter, you have extract certain information.
Maybe this filter is good at extracting, for example, vertical edge information.
Yeah.
But in order for you to be able to extract different types of information from your input
volume, you need different filter.
So that's why you need additional filter.
So now, okay, so we need an addition, we need other filters.
So suppose now let's consider a second filter here now.
So this is the second filter is also five by five by three.
So now if you repeat the same process of moving through all this position, performing the convolution
or filtering operation, then the output is you are going to get another channel or another
slice of the activation map here, which is 28 by 28 by one.
So when you have two feature map or two activation map now, so we call activation maps now.
So now it becomes a prurer.
So therefore you can actually use as many filter as you want.
And then you'll be actually generating different layers of this particular activation map.
So this activation map sometimes is also known as the output volume, okay, because
now it has that information.
Right.
Okay.
So now if you do that, if you put everything together, let's look at this example here.
Suppose your input image is 32 by 32 by three, right?
And then if you use a six, five by five by three filter.
So for each of the five by five by three filter, you can see just now from the previous example,
you're going to get one slice of 28 by 28 by one.
Okay.
Activation map.
But because you're using six filter, so now your output volume is going to have six channel.
Right.
So your output volume now you can see because they're using six filter now.
So your output volume will have six channel.
Right.
Okay.
So next suppose now in the next layer, we use 10, five by five by six filter here.
So now the filter is five by five, but the depth has to be six now.
This number six need to be consistent with the input volume as we have mentioned.
So each of these five by five by six is going to generate a channel, right?
A slice of 24 by 24 by one activation map.
But since they're using 10 filter, so your output volume now is 24 by 24 by 10.
Right.
So now you're able to extract features, no layer by layer by using no different filters.
So that's the basic operations of the convolution.
Right.
Okay.
So when we perform convolution, very often we also combine with this padding process.
So the idea of padding is quite simple.
Suppose if you have a particular input image just now, which is a 32 by 32 by three, 32
by 32, right by three.
It's the depth, but for this visualization, we do not show the depth information.
We only show the spatial information here.
So from the earlier example, you can see that if we use a five by five by three filter,
the size of your output volume is going to be reduced to 28 by 28.
Right.
But at times you may want to retain the size of this output volume.
You want your output volume spatial dimension to be consistent with your input volume, no
spatial dimension.
Right.
No, sometimes you just want to do it for consistency purpose or for other consideration.
So if you want to do that, then one easy trick that you can do is to try to pack some layers
of zero next to your input volume.
Okay.
So we add some zeros next to it.
For example, in this case, we add two layers of zero at each side here.
So if you add two layer now, this particular input volume now will have the have the dimension
of 36 by 36 by three.
Right.
You have that.
No, the depth is still three, but we ignore the depth information for this visualization.
We just focus on the spatial information.
So now after padding the dimension 36 by 36, suppose now if we use a five by five by three
filter, you put it at this top positions here, you can see respect to the index image index
of this enlarged image.
Okay.
So if you coordinate here is actually, we recall this one, two, three.
This is three.
Okay.
And then afterwards, all the way when you come to here, right, you'll be 34.
Right.
So it's 34 minus three, which give you 31, but you need to add up with one for the boundary
condition.
So therefore your output is actually 32 by 32 again.
So then you can see that you can preserve the dimensions of your input volume spatial
dimension and your output volume spatial dimension is the same.
So this is one simple trick to do that.
Right.
So you can see this is the basic explanation here.
So if we have this initially, this 32 by 32 by three volume, if we pat two borders of
zero, it becomes 36 by 36 by three, 36 by 36 by three.
Okay.
And if we apply just now the same filter of five by five by three, okay, we can see that
our output volume now is 32 by 32 by three.
So we retain the dimension spatial dimension of your input volume and output volume is
the same now by simply doing some padding operation.
Right.
Okay.
So this simple animation just show how do we perform the, you know, the convolution
process.
So you have some input.
Okay.
Volume.
Right.
So we ignore the debt information.
We just focus on the spatial information.
So we have the input volume.
You pet up with some zero.
Okay.
Suppose if your filter in this case happened to be a four by four filter.
So you just slide through every time at a certain position, you will generate an output
and then you just slice it through.
Okay.
And then you perform this filtering or some of product operation.
Then you'll be generating this particular output.
Okay.
Or this activation map or activation feature.
Right.
So next, right.
So this particular example, just try to show suppose now, okay, you have a particular input
image now.
Okay.
So this is the RGB image here.
Right.
So you can see it.
You have a RGB image that has three channel.
This is the red channel.
Okay.
This corresponds to the green channel of image.
This corresponds to the blue channel of image.
Right.
Suppose we are only looking at the top left corner.
So we have one layers of zero padding.
Okay.
We introduced one layer of zero padding.
Suppose our current filter now is, you can see it's three by three.
Right.
So the spatial dimension is three by three, but the depth is actually three as well because
you have one for red, one for green and one for blue channel.
So the filter that we have is three by three by three.
Okay.
So if you want to perform the filtering operation, yeah, it says that, you know, you're just
superimposed this particular filter into, you know, current positions of the image.
Yeah.
For example, I'm not sure whether I can stop it, but anyway, suppose it's at the top left
corner, you just know, superimposed, you multiply their corresponding value.
You sum it up.
Okay.
That will give, for example, this value.
So you repeat that for the green channel.
Suppose at this position, you multiply their corresponding value and you add them up.
That will give you this value.
So anyway, you add up the output due to the green, red, red, green and blue channel.
And if you also use bias, this bias is optional.
If you choose to use the bias, then you add it up.
This will be output.
So at each position, right?
So you generate output and then as you slide through this filter, then you'll be filling
all those entry.
So pretty much this is just an animation to again explain what we have mentioned, right?
There's nothing too new about this.
Okay.
So the next concept that we need to introduce very quickly is a strike.
So as the name suggests, strike is a mouth.
You know, when you move your filter from one position to the next position, how much you
have to move.
So strike is like, you know, the human, right?
Strike means that when you walk, how big is your step size?
So that's a meaning of strike.
So in the context of CNN, that means how much as you move from the filter from one position
to the other position, how much you move.
So suppose if you take this example here, you have input volume, which is like this.
Okay.
Again, we ignore the depth dimension.
If this is the input volume, right?
Suppose we use a three by three filter, right?
So at this top left position, after you perform the convolution operation, you generate this
output.
So the next position you move, if it's a strike of one, that means you only move to the next
position with a step size of one away.
Okay.
So now with this filter and the underlying image, you perform the filtering process or
you multiply their corresponding value.
You sum it up.
That would give you the green value, right?
And afterwards, if you repeat, when you come to here, next, if you move down, right, if
you do not indicate otherwise, then you also move down with a strike of one.
Okay.
Then you'll be generating the output at the next row.
And then afterwards, you repeat the whole process.
This is how you're going to obtain your output volume.
Okay.
So the next example is if you again use a three by three filter, but now with a strike
of two, so what I mean is initially it's at this position, performing the convolution
of filtering operation, you'll get generate this rate output.
Next, when you shift, you shift by a position of two, you move right by a position of two
to this green position, performing filtering or convolution, you'll get this value.
And the next one is here.
You get this value.
Next, when you move it down, you also move down by a position of two.
Right.
So if you perform filtering, this is your blue output.
Okay.
So that's pretty much what strike is about.
Right.
So this animation shows the very simple examples of the strike of two.
We can see initially it's here.
Okay.
You move to, when you move to a side is by a strike of two, when you move down is also
with a strike of two.
Okay.
So the next thing after the convolution, right, the next layer that we have is the activation
layer.
Right.
So for this activation layer, what it does is that once you get the output of this convolution,
you immediately let it pass through an activation.
So activation is an element by element nonlinear activation function.
You simply get the output.
You let it pass through a nonlinear function to generate the output.
So why do you want to let it go through a nonlinear function?
It's because nonlinear function provide a more dynamic modeling capability.
It can model the value in a more powerful manner.
Right.
So therefore, yeah.
So we are going to let the output of the convolution to let it through a nonlinear activation function.
So among them, value is one of the most popular activation functions.
Some of you probably have seen it.
Right.
So this activation layer is commonly closely coupled with the convolution together.
Yeah.
Usually as soon as you get the convolution output, you just let it go through this activation
layer immediately.
So therefore they are very often written as con plus, no, for example, activation or con
plus rellu right away.
So this slide shows some of the sample activation function in the activation layer.
So some of the well known one, for example, is risk rellu function.
So this rellu function horizontal axis is the input, vertical axis is the output.
So you can see when the input is positive or zero, your output is the same.
No distortion.
But when your input is actually a negative value, your output will be kept at zero.
So this particular modeling can be shown by this equations here, the maximum between
zero or X.
So when X is positive, right, you just take the X value.
But when your X is negative, you'll be taking the zero value.
So this is a very popular activation function.
There are also some other popular functions such as, for example, this sigmoid function
here, which map your input value to an output value between zero and one and 10 H, which
map your input value to output value between minus one and one.
So these are some popular activation function.
So if we now put convolution and rellu together, so pretty much is that assuming that we have
an input volume, which is 2 to 4 by 2 to 4 by 3, for example, in VGG network, this is
the dimensions of an input image.
2 to 4 by 2 to 4 by 3.
We use a filter of 3 by 3 by 3 filter.
So we know that we are going to go through each of these particular positions to perform
the convolution.
Suppose this is the current position it's operating on.
So you take this particular filter at this particular position, you superimpose, you
multiply their corresponding term, and you sum it up.
So that will give you the output.
So this output would then immediately go through the activation function.
For example, in this case, it's a sigmoid activation function, and then you generate
this output directly.
So afterwards, you actually repeat it for all the positions.
That means you'll be generating the output directly.
So we combine, in this case, convolution and activation together.
So we have covered two of the layers already.
So the next layer that we have is the pooling layer.
So the objective of the pooling layer is that you want to reduce the size of your activation
map.
Because if you have a very large activation map, there's a lot of computation you need
to perform.
There's also a lot of storage.
So therefore, sometimes you want to reduce the number of the size of the activation map.
So therefore, the goals of this pooling layer is to reduce the activation map dimension or
size.
By reducing it, you can reduce a number of downstream or subsequent computation, as
well as the storage.
So there's a few common pooling operations, such as max pooling, average pooling, that
we'll show later.
So for the pooling operation, each of the channel, each channel in the feature map or
the activation map, we perform it independently.
So let's look at this diagram to show how do we perform the pooling.
Suppose this is the current channel or the current slice that you want to perform the
pooling.
And if you are performing as max pooling with a 2 by 2 filter and with a strut of 2, so
2 by 2 filter means that we partition this particular, first of all, we examine this
2 by 2 block here.
And then because it's max pooling, means that you choose the largest value in this 2 by
2 block here.
So in this example, the largest value is 6, so you write down the 6.
Next what's the strut?
You have to examine what strut you're using.
If you're using a strut of 2, that means now you are going to move this particular filter
to this new position now.
So within this 2 by 2 block, you are trying to find what's the largest value.
In this example, it's 8.
So we just write it down as 8.
And afterwards, when you move it down, you move by a strut of 2.
Again, you repeat the exercise.
You see this is 3 and this block is 4.
So this is how you perform the max pooling.
So you can see in this example here, after you perform the max pooling, the dimensions
of the vertical and the horizontal dimension has been half from 4 to 4 to 2 by 2 dimension
now.
So therefore, you reduce the size of your output volume and hence, for your subsequent
layer, you need less computation and storage.
So early on, we also mentioned that for this pooling layer, for example, this is our current
volume, which is 224 by 224 by 64 channel here.
So when you perform pooling, we consider each of this particular channel or slice independently.
Suppose this is our current channel.
When we perform just now the 2 by 2 max pooling, you can see the size have you reduced to
112 by 112 and then you put it back here.
And each of the channels you operate independently.
So now the size of your output volume now will be 112 by 112 by 64.
So now we have actually introduced quite a number of layers already.
So let's see where we are now.
So we have the input.
We say that first we have a convolutional layer.
And then, the coloristic couple with it is the activation layer.
So it's not shown here, but there's an activation layer.
And afterwards, we'll do the pooling layer to reduce the dimension.
So this convolution, activation, and pooling, typically we repeat a few times.
So for example, in this illustration, you show it, you just do it once and you do it
twice.
So once you reach this particular junctures here, this is the output volume at this juncture
here.
So what we are going to do is that we are going to convert this particular output into
a vector.
So we are going to convert this into a particular vector here.
So this particular process is known as a flattening.
So you flatten it into a vector.
So how do we perform the flattening is actually quite simple.
We just scan channel by channel.
For example, first row, second row, third row of the first channel.
Each row you scan you write as part of the vector.
So you have vector 1, vector 2, vector 3, vector 4.
So after you scan the first channel, then you move on to the next channel.
So therefore, by performing this scanning operation or the flattening operation, you
can convert it into a vector now.
So this particular vector now, then subsequently will be passed through the FC layer, fully
connected layer.
So if you recall this fully connected layer, it's just like the linear layer that you
have studied before, the linear classifier.
And then finally, if the particular, this application is for the task of classification,
then often you will be following by a softmax layer to convert the output into the probability.
So next, let's look at the FC layer now.
So for FC layer, all the nodes in one layer are connected to all the nodes in the next
layer.
So for example, if you have this is one FC layer here, you have 1000 nodes here.
Suppose you have the next FC layer, also 1000.
So all the nodes in one FC layer is fully connected to all the nodes in the next layer.
So because they are fully connected, so therefore, for FC layer is usually very expensive.
It's very expensive because all the nodes are fully connected.
So you need to store lots of parameters.
So for example, if this particular FC layer, if this dimension is 1000, and the next layer
dimension is 1000, then all together you need 1000 times 1000, which is one million parameters,
which is a lot.
You can see all the nodes in one layer are connected to all the nodes in the next layer.
So this particular FC layer feature vector can also be interpreted as a feature or embedding
to represent the image.
So one very useful way to interpret this FC layer is that at any of this particular FC
layer, you can interpret this is actually a vector, or sometimes you call it a feature,
or sometimes you call it an embedding that is used to represent this image here.
So each of these vector representations here at different layer can be interpreted as extracting
some useful information from your input image.
So we either call embedding, we call it a vector, or we call it feature.
So FC layer just behaves like the linear layer for classification, like what I've explained
to you.
So this is the diagram that we have shown before when we study about the linear classifier.
So suppose input, right, initially your input image is 32 by 32 by 3.
We use a lexical graphical ordering, we can convert it into a long vector.
So this is our long vector here, 3072.
So this is a vector 3072.
So if we use this FC layer, so FC layer is just like the linear layer that you can model
using this linear operation.
Wx plus b, the b is optional.
So in this illustration here, it doesn't consider the bias.
So pretty much you have this long input vector, and you have this particular weight matrix
W that need to be trained or estimated.
So you can see that when you want to calculate each of the output layer, each of the output
nodes here, to calculate each of the output nodes involved taking a row vector in W, multiply
with this column vector x.
So therefore each of this particular output here will be examining or will be taking input
from each of the points in this vector x here.
So anyway this is what we have studied before.
We'll talk about FC layer.
Suppose if your input vector is 3072 by 1, if you want to classify into 10 category,
then your size of your matrix W will be 3072 times 10.
Sorry, it's 10 times 3072.
So you can see which is lots of parameter.
So now we have explained about the FC layer.
So the FC layer you can interpret is as like a general purpose transformation.
It's a general purpose transformation to transform one vector to the next vector.
It's a general purpose transformation.
So which generally speaking is good, except there's one price that you have to pay.
What's the price you have to pay?
Now if you want to learn any, you can actually always use many FC layer because each FC layer
is just like a general purpose transformation.
It can even sufficient training data.
You can always map your input factor into another output vector which is more, which
further extract the feature and so on and so forth.
But in practice it's very difficult to do that.
What's the reason?
So the reason why in practice we do not use many FC layer or we only use it sparingly
is because of the reason that we mentioned before.
Because each node is connected to other nodes.
So you require a large number of parameter.
That means you need to store.
Your storage becomes very large.
The second thing is when you have lots of weight, that means you need a lot of training
data to train it.
So birth unknown ideal.
So that's why we only use FC layer quite sparingly.
Usually at the end of the layer, once you have already extract most of the feature, you
just want to do some final car mapping to boost up the performance a bit.
So next anyway, suppose now you have the last FC layer already.
Assuming that if our application is to perform classification, then your output, you need
to map it into the probability.
If for the classification problem, then the last layer that we have typically will be
the softmax layer.
So if you remember in our previous lecture, the objective of softmax is to convert output
into probability so that you can perform classification.
So therefore the softmax layer what it does is you take the output from the last FC layer.
So the output from the last FC layer has a unique name we call logit.
So we take this logit value and we convert it into probability for the purpose of training
and classification later.
So how do we take the output from the last FC layer and convert it into a probability?
We use the softmax normalization that we have studied in the last lecture.
So if you take these particular examples here, suppose this is the input to the last layer.
So for your last layer, so you can kind of think about it as input multiplied with W
matrix.
Then you generate this particular output for the last FC layer.
So this is called the logit.
So this logit next we need to let it go through the softmax normalization to convert it into
the probability.
So if you recall, the process to convert this output into the probability is using this
equation.
Either a power of the logit, the current logit divided by the denominator.
This denominator is either a power of the output is summed up over all the possible
nodes here, all the possible classes.
So by doing that, then you will convert this into the probability now.
So in this illustration, it's trying to show, for example, if you want to classify into
different types of probability.
So now we have almost studied all the basic structures of a vanilla CNN.
So let's just take one particular code to see whether you can put everything together.
So we are going to look at a simple PyTorch CNN implementation.
So in order to implement this simple vanilla CNN, so first of all, we'll define a particular
new class called net.
And this net is extending its parent class call module.
So it has a lot of the properties from the parent class.
And then next, when you want to define this network, you need to have these constructor
methods here.
This particular method is a constructor method here.
So we need to define all the layers for this current CNN.
So in order to do that, we call this superclass, initialization of this superclass.
And then afterwards, the next thing is that this is the first layer here.
So the first layer that we are going to have is the 2D convolutional layer.
So it's implemented using this particular command nn.con2d.
And then there have some input argument.
The first one is one here corresponding to the input channel.
So the second parameter corresponds to the output channel, which is 6.
And then finally, this last parameter is actually the size of a filter.
So therefore, if you look at the first line of the command, what it says is that you are
going to construct your first convolutional layer.
Input is actually one channel.
Output is six channel.
And then the filter you're using is 3 by 3 filter.
So if you look at the first line of this command here, what kind of image are we dealing with?
Are we dealing with a grayscale image?
Or are we dealing with a colored image?
We are dealing with a grayscale image because it says that the input volume is one.
That means input is only one channel.
So if it's a colored image, what do you think this number would be?
It would be 3.
So therefore, from this particular structure, you have some sense about what kind of data
you'll be handling.
So the next convolutional layer you can see is nn.con2d.
Output volume is 6.
Output volume is 16.
And then again, we're using 3 by 3 filter.
So now you can see this six here need to agree with this six here.
Because after the first layer, you have six channel.
So this will then serve as an input to the next conv layer.
So this is also six here.
So you have defined two convolutional layer.
And then afterwards, you continue to define the FC layer now, fully connected layer.
So the FC layer is defined using nn.linear, using this PyTorch.
It's defined using this function nn.linear.
So this nn.linear, the first parameter here is actually the number, the input dimensions
of your input vector.
Dimensions of your input vector.
The second parameter is the output dimension vector.
So you can see that in this particular case here.
So input dimension vector is 16 multiplied by 6 by 6.
This is because for this particular example, people already know the input image is actually
32 by 32 by 3.
32 by 32.
So they already know the input image.
Therefore they also know the structure.
So after some going through a few different layers, they know what is the dimensions of
your output volume.
Therefore they do a bit of a hard coding.
It's probably not the best way, but they do a bit of hard coding.
If they already know the input dimension, they do some calculation and found that the
output volume is 16 by 6 by 6.
So you can visualise this a little bit like this.
They already know the size of the input image after and they also know the structure.
So therefore they can pre-compute and know that the output now is...
What's that?
Anyway they know the spatial dimension as well as the number of this output channel.
So that is assuming that they already know the structure.
They do some pre-computation and they know that this is the dimensions of your output
volume after the last layer before the FC layer.
So that's why they hard-coded it here.
So the FC layer is this number by this number here.
And afterwards the second FC layer now is mapping from 120 to 84.
The last FC layer is mapping from 84 to 10.
So for this particular problem, suppose it's for the purpose of classification, how many
classes do you think you will classify into?
How many classes do you think you will try to classify this particular...
I mean this code is for classification of how many categories of objects.
10 classes.
So you can see at the last layer it's going to map from a vector dimensions of 84 to 10.
So these 10 usually correspond to 10 different categories because these 10 classes later
on you're going to perform the four softmax.
You're going to let it pass through the softmax layer to convert it into probability.
So therefore from this code you can more or less tell that you're trying to classify
into 10 categories here.
So now we have defined the structure.
Next we are going to define how the signal flow looks like.
So the signal flow is actually based on our understanding.
So we have our input image.
You go through a first convolutional layer and afterwards go through the ReLU layer,
which is our activation layer, and then afterwards go through a max pooling layer.
So this max pooling layer is 2x2.
2x2 max pooling.
You get your output.
So this output now will then go through your second convolutional layer, activation layer,
max pooling layer to get the output.
So this output now, afterwards we are going to use this particular function to calculate
what is the dimensions of this final output volume.
So we use this particular function to calculate what's the dimension.
Then we use this X view to do the flattening to convert this volume into a vector.
So this line will do the flattening process.
So after this line here, your volume, feature volume will become a vector, just like what
we described.
So this vector now will then go through your first FC layer followed by ReLU to get your
output.
Your output from the first FC layer go through your second FC layer, ReLU and the output.
So the output from the last FC layer will go through your last FC layer to get the output.
And then finally this output is returned.
So for this particular illustration here, it does not perform the normalization, the
softmax normalization, because the softmax normalization will be handled elsewhere later.
So all right, I actually have one question for you.
You can see that for this FC layer here, after each FC layer it will go through activation
function, ReLU and ReLU here.
Is it okay if I remove this two ReLU layer?
No, someone may say, okay, no, can I just remove this two ReLU layer and just simply
put X go through the first FC layer to obtain the output.
Go through the second FC layer to obtain the output.
And then this output then go through the last FC layer to obtain your final output.
Can you remove the activation layer?
Okay, if you cannot remove the activation layer, why?
Yeah, okay, yeah, I think I heard someone mention.
Because if you remove this activation layer, then this particular mathematical operation
is more or less modeled by a matrix, for example, W1.
Afterwards, this one is modeled by W2, this one is modeled by W3.
So the operation is actually X multiplied with W1, later on multiplied with W2, later
on multiplied with W3.
So multiplications of three matrices is still a matrix.
Then this has been reduced to simply one FC layer.
So therefore you cannot remove this.
We need to have an activation in between to enrich its dynamic modeling capability.
Right, okay, so now we have covered most of the basic concepts about the CNN already.
So I think it's time that we try up your understanding now.
So we have one exercise.
Actually this is one pass here exam question.
So you can give a try to see your understanding.
Okay, so in this question it says that a simple CNN, in a simple CNN, an input image A pass
through a convolution layer, activation layer and max pooling.
And then the output from the max pooling is then used for further subsequent processing.
So first of all, you are given an input image A that looks like this.
And the convolution layer has the following setting.
So the current filter that you have is given here.
So this is our current filter.
And the amount of zero padding at each side is one.
The strike both horizontally and vertically is two.
And the activation layer that we, activation function that we use in the activation layer is given by this sigmoid function.
Right, okay, the pooling that we use is the two by two max pooling with a strike of two.
Right, so afterwards there's a series of questions.
So I'll give you some time to go through this question and then we'll go through the answer together.
But one thing at a time, let's look at question one.
So question one is it asks you to find the output after the convolution layer.
So I'll give you a bit of time to try it out and then we'll go through the answer together.
At the end of this exercise, if you can get all the steps correct, pretty much that means you have a pretty good understanding of all the operations in this CNN process already.
Okay.
So at least we have some time to think about it.
, so any suggestions.
How do we solve this problem?
Any suggestion?
So first of all, we take our input image
and then what's the layers of padding that you have to do?
One layer, right?
So you pad up with one layer,
so zero surrounding it.
And afterwards, you simply take this particular filter,
put on top, right?
You perform the filtering
or multiply the corresponding entry and sum it up.
That will generate the first value.
And afterwards, you do the shifting.
The strike here is two, right?
So just be careful.
You need to move by a step size of two.
So then afterwards, you repeat the operation.
You should be able to generate your output.
Okay, so let's show, go through the answer together.
Right, okay, so...
Right, okay.
I think this one we can just show it.
Right, okay, so this is actually our given image.
So we use one padding of zero on both sides of the image.
And now this is a given filter.
So you put your filter initially at this top left corner.
You perform the filtering operation.
That means you multiply their corresponding value.
You sum it up, right?
So for example, I'll just go through one.
So the first one, when you put it here,
so it turned out we multiply together, everything is zero.
So let's just look at, okay, so you position here,
you perform the filtering, you get zero.
Next, because you're told the strike is two,
so you move, okay, to this position,
you perform the filtering, your C is zero.
So next, you move down to this position here.
If you move down to this position here,
if you move down to this position,
you can see this multiply with this will be zero.
Four multiply is zero, okay,
so it's zero multiply with one,
zero multiply with two, zero multiply with one,
all is zero, okay, and then this one multiply also zero.
So the only non-zero value is when you have two
multiply with minus two, that will give you minus four.
So therefore the value here is minus four, right?
So anyway, this is a very simple calculation
because I don't want it to be too complicated,
especially at early stage.
So if you go through this process,
your output after the convolution will be this value, okay?
So this is the output after the,
after the convolution.
Right, so let's look at the,
okay, so we managed to obtain the first one already.
So part two, it asks you to briefly describe
the effect of this particular filter F,
where it's applied to the input image, okay?
So you look at this particular filter F here.
What can you observe from this filter F?
What is the objective of this particular filter F?
Is trying to,
sorry, quite stuff, I can't.
Okay, actually there's a specific goal
is trying to achieve here, right?
Actually, I can't really fully hear you very clearly,
but in this particular case here,
for those of you who have studied
some image processing before,
you know that there's some basic filter operation
that you can do.
For example, this one is a well-known filter
that will extract gradient in the horizontal direction.
Right, so you try to extract gradient
in the horizontal direction,
or some edge information in the vertical direction.
So this is actually, you can see, right?
This is two, this minus two,
this is one, this minus one,
this is one, this minus one.
So you are trying to find the difference, okay,
the gradient in the horizontal direction, okay?
So therefore, this particular filter is objective,
is to extract the gradient information
in the horizontal direction.
Okay, so this objective of this particular,
the effect of it, right?
The effect of this particular filter here.
Okay, right, so next,
later on I'll show you the answer for this.
The next one is that I ask you to find
the output after the activation layer.
Yeah, so I give you a bit of time, right?
To try to find the output after the activation layer.
Okay, at this particular point,
I also probably want to highlight to you.
So in this particular course,
there'll be, sometimes you may need to use,
for example, sigmoid function, or 10-H function.
So make sure that you familiarize yourself, right?
Or lone function, okay?
Lock, and, right, this is a lone function.
So make sure that you familiarize yourself
with your calculator, right?
So in the event you come out in the exam,
you can just simply, you know how to calculate, yeah?
Okay, so anyway, I'll give you some time to quickly calculate
the output after the activation layer.
Right, and also the output after the max pooling layer.
These are relatively calculation-wise,
relatively straightforward,
so we'll go through the answers together.
Okay.
Right.
In case some of you have not got the answer before,
right, so early on,
the output after the convolution is this one, okay?
So we know after convolution,
you need to let it go through the activation, right?
So you step to try to find...
Okay.
Okay, so I think this part should be quite straightforward
because I actually provide you
with the activation functionality.
And activation function is the element
by element operation.
So that means you put zero into this,
you'll be able to get your output,
and afterwards you put each of the element
right into this function.
You'll be able to get the output of the activation function.
So that part is quite straightforward.
And then the next layer is actually a two by two max pooling.
So in this example, you only have a two by two
because of block, right?
So you just write down the largest value, okay?
So the reason is because in the context of exam,
sometimes I don't want to make it too complicated,
otherwise you'll be spending a lot of time
doing all the calculation, yeah?
So anyway, right?
So if you look at the...
Yeah, so just now we say the if our filter F
is to compute the horizontal gradient, okay?
Which in a sense that means you will capture
or reflect some of the edge information.
Okay, and then, right?
So for part three, if you just now apply
the activation function element by element,
you'll see that this is the output, okay?
You can go and check later.
And then the next thing is actually doing
the two by two max pooling.
That means within this two by two pixel block,
you choose the largest value, which is this 0.982.
So therefore, this is the output after your max pooling.
So let's continue to the last part of the question.
So last part of the question is says that
a student would like to make the following changes
to the input image and the convolutional layer, right?
So he changed this grayscale image A to now
and RGB image B.
And the dimensions of this RGB image is 100 by 100, okay?
And then he changed the channel number
of the output feature map to six now, okay?
All right?
And then afterwards, no, assume that the spatial dimensions
of the filter remain the same, right?
Spatial dimension in this case is three by three, okay?
So it asks you to find what's the number
of trainable parameter, okay?
For the new convolutional layer after these changes,
assuming no biases use, yeah?
Okay, I'll give you a bit of time to think about it
and then we'll go through the answer together.
Okay.
Right, okay, so I think this question is quite,
yeah, it's either you get it or you don't get it.
There's no point thinking too much about it.
So what do you think is the answer?
The calculation is,
so what is the number of parameter?
The number of parameter is the number of coefficient
or weight that you have for the filter, right?
So first of all, what's the spatial dimensions of,
suppose if you just assume one filter first.
So if you have one filter, now,
so now your new image now, you can see it's RGB image,
that means the input volume is three channel, right?
Okay, so if you want to apply this filter here,
what is the, suppose if it's just one filter,
you want to apply on it,
what is the dimensions of this one filter is?
We want to modify initially, in this example here,
initially this filter is three by three, right?
And the number of channel is one
because this is the grayscale image.
Now we say we want to change this grayscale image
to color image now.
That means now your input volume now has three channel, right?
So this filter now initially is three by three
for grayscale, three by three by one for grayscale.
Now your input now is from one channel,
grayscale image to three channel RGB image.
So your filter now need to be three by three by,
three by three by three, right?
Because you need to make sure now
this particular filter dimension
need to be consistent with your input volume.
That means if you are using only one filter,
it'll be three by three by three.
But the question also tell you now,
your output now, your output,
you want to increase it to the number of channel now is six.
That means your output volume dimension
in terms of the number of channel is six.
How do you generate six channel?
You need to use six different filter, right?
So therefore the total number of parameter now
for one filter is three by three by three.
So that's one filter.
And because now you're going to generate six channel,
so it's three by three by three times a six.
That would be the answer.
So now,
okay, so therefore the number of channel parameter
for this new convolutional layer is three by three by three
by six, yeah?
So just now going through the explanation.
So it's one, six, two.
So that is the answer to that particular question.
Right, okay, so perhaps let's try to go through one more
exercise before I give you a break.
Okay, so the next exercise is this, yeah?
Okay, the FC, we're going to focus on FC and softmax layer.
It says that the input feature X will pass through
a FC layer of a CNN, right?
Okay, so this is an input feature.
This is actually your weight matrix and this is the bias.
So it says that this softmax function is then applied
to the output of this FC layer.
Right, number one, you're asked to find what's the output
of the FC layer.
Number two is try to find the output of this softmax layer.
Right, okay, so it's not that difficult,
but it's a process that you need to finalize yourself
on how to convert this softmax normalization, yeah?
So I'll give you a bit of time to try it out
and then we'll go through the answers together.
Okay.
Okay, so for step one, how do we calculate the output
after the FC layer?
Right, so if you remember, the equation for FC layer
is nothing but WX plus B, right?
So you just go through the motion, yeah?
You should be able to find the output.
Right, okay, so the output after FC layer is WX plus B,
so you plug in the value, you do some calculation,
you'll see that this is your output.
Okay, so next, this output will go through a softmax layer.
So the softmax layers involve the softmax normalization,
which is given by this equations here.
So this equation, Pj, refer to the probability
for the category, for node J or category J, right?
So it's either a power of the output
for the particular category J, right?
Over either a power of, no, either a power of ZK,
you sum up over all the category, okay?
So in this case here, what it means is that
for this denominator, right, is either a power of 1.2
plus either a power of 1.3 plus either a power of 2.2, right?
If you calculate, you see this is the value.
So now, the first probability after normalization
is either a power of 1.2 divided by this value
that we have evaluated earlier, your C is 0.207.
Okay, and then for P2, it's either a power of 1.3
divided by the common denominator.
But so if you do that, your C is 0.229, right?
You repeat that for the third category,
the C is 0.56636.
So therefore, the output after the softmax layer
would be this value here.
So you can see that this particular value
after the softmax is actually a probability.
When you sum it up, it should be equal to one.
So therefore, this particular output
after softmax normalization,
you can compare to the ground truth.
The ground truth is usually in the form of one hot modeling.
But for the category, the ground truth category is one,
the rest is zero.
That's why now, these two factor,
their distance is comparable.
And then you can use it to calculate the loss.
And this loss is the cross entropy
of the softmax loss that we have studied before.
Okay, right?
So that's pretty much for this exercise.
Right, okay, so before, I think we can take a short break
before we go to the next part.
So now it's 750, let's come back, 805, okay?
Okay.
Okay, so let's continue with the training of the CNN.
So how do we train a CNN?
So training a CNN essentially means
that you want to estimate the parameters in your,
just in the convolutional layer, you have the filter, right?
And also in the FC layer, you have the big W matrix.
So when we say train a CNN,
that means we want to train those parameters in the network,
okay, including the weight matrix in the FC layer,
as well as a filter or kernel in the convolutional layer.
Right, okay, so what's the high level objective
of this training is that we want to minimize
the loss function.
So for example, in our case of classification,
the loss function would be the softmax loss
or the cross-entrophy loss.
So the idea is based on what is known
as a stochastic gradient descent, okay?
So the idea of stochastic gradient descent is like this.
Right, suppose if you look at this particular graph,
for Wang-Men-Wen, let's assume that for this network,
we only have two parameters we need to optimize.
Right, let's call this thing X1 and X2, right?
For action network, you may have millions of parameters,
okay, that you need to optimize.
But let's start with something simple
that we can visualize and then afterwards,
we can extend to something more complicated.
Suppose for this simple network,
we only have two parameters we need to optimize.
We call X1 and X2, okay?
So with respect to different values of X1 and X2,
you have different value of loss.
So this loss value now will look like actually,
the landscape, the mountain and valley, okay?
So our objective is that initially,
because we do not know what is the best parameter of weight,
so initially we may start off with some position here,
okay, somewhere that correspond to below
a non-ideal X1 and X2 value.
Our goal is that we want to reach the minima,
okay, this point here.
So what do we do?
What do we do is that at this position,
we look around, we find the direction of the steepest descent
and then we walk a certain steps in the direction.
So once you reach the direction, you look around,
you find the direction of steepest descent
and you continue to walk in the direction.
So you repeat the process a number of times
until hopefully you reach a good local minima.
So that means at this point, you look around,
you find this direction is the direction
of the steepest descent.
So you walk in a certain percentage until you reach here.
So next, at this point, you look around, okay?
You see this is the direction of the steepest descent,
so you walk in this direction here
and afterwards you repeatedly doing that
until you reach a local minima.
How much you need to walk is controlled
by a parameter known as the learning rate, okay?
So that's the basic ideas of stochastic gradient descent.
So in order to do that, you typically need
to construct a computational graph
to help you to find out what is the gradient, okay?
And how to update the parameter.
So now if you look at this particular training here,
so in order to look at this particular,
just now we talked about the learning rate here.
So let's look at this equation.
So this equation is actually the loss function
or the error function for I training data.
So suppose our current training data is called XI,
our current label is called YI, the ground truth is YI,
and the view is your current parameter
or weight that you need to learn,
which can include all the convolutional layer kernel
plus all the FC weight matrix.
So it's modeled by this big W here, right?
So even input, even this W matrix,
this weight parameter W, you can get your predicted output.
Once you get your predicted output,
you can compare with your ground truth, right?
Then you'll get your current loss for I training sample.
So when we want to find the total loss,
we need to add up all the training sample,
and then we divide it by N.
So this, therefore, is our loss function now.
Our loss function is the functions of W.
So this W is a parameter that we want to optimize or learn.
So now we have this loss function.
So when we want to learn this parameter,
that means we need to take this loss function
and differentiate with respect to this W parameter.
So we differentiate with respect to this W parameter.
So mathematically, what it means is that
you also take this particular loss function
and you perform partial, no,
kind of a differentiation with respect
to this W parameter here, okay?
Right, so this particular term here can be interpreted
as trying to find the steepest gradient, okay?
Steepest gradient up works.
So now when you want to do the training of the network,
essentially what it means is that
you have a current set of the parameter already, okay?
So you have the current set of the parameter here, okay?
You look at the directions of the steepest ascent, okay?
And then after works, you have a negative sign in front,
which means that you are now trying to find the direction
of the steepest ascent now, okay?
And then this parameter alpha is the learning rate.
So this alpha means how much you want to walk
in the direction.
So therefore, when you want to learn it,
it's actually quite easy.
That means our next step learning,
our next step parameter, next iteration parameter,
is your current parameter, okay?
You walk in the directions of the steepest ascent
and how much you want to walk is controlled
by this learning rate alpha, okay?
So that's the high level interpretation.
So now if you look at this particular graph,
if you try to plot the loss function versus the epoch,
so epoch is the number of training,
okay, all the training data that you have,
if you use all your training data to train it once,
we call it one epoch, right?
So horizontal axis is the number of epochs that you have,
vertical axis is the loss.
So suppose initially you start off with some parameter W,
so the loss is quite high.
If you choose a good learning rate,
then your loss will decrease nicely.
That means your W will become better and better
and your loss will start to decrease.
So on the other hand, if you choose a low learning rate,
then your loss is going to reduce slowly, okay?
If you choose a large learning rate, okay,
then the ideal one,
then your loss is going to decrease quickly,
but you'll reach an optimal or steady state,
which is not as good as a good learning rate.
And finally, if you choose a very large learning rate,
sometimes it may not converge, yeah?
Because it may overshoot.
So therefore, a lot of the time,
this choosing a good learning rate involves trying error.
In your data set, you have to try different range
of the learning rate, right?
There's some strategy to do that, okay?
So next, we are going to look at some well-known
CNN architecture, right?
So this particular timeline shows some
of the CNN architecture.
So what we have studied so far is a vanilla CNN, yeah?
But over time, actually people start to improve
and propose better and better CNN network here, right?
Okay, so this diagram just shows you
some of the well-known network.
So the conf net, just now we see a number of layers
of convolutional layer.
The net is by Yang Li-kun,
early layers to recognize character.
Alex net, okay, some of them we'll explain later, right?
I will not go through some of them,
all of them are just highlighted, okay, Alex net, right?
This is the network that indicate,
really first time demonstrate if you train using a CNN,
using a large data set, is really going to outperform
traditional handcrafted methods.
So this is considered as a turning point.
Okay, VGG is an important network
that shows the elegance of the network.
Resnet is also a very important network.
There's lots of a network which is currently
still using Resnet.
For example, the transformer that probably some
of you heard about is still leveraging
some of the ideas in Resnet, okay?
Right, so let's try to very quickly go through
some of this network here.
So the first one that we have is Alex net, right?
So it was the first neural network that is applied
on large scale image data set, right?
Which is actually image net by their group,
is Feifei Li's group, right?
Okay, and then it had make use of a classical structure
for image classification, consisting of convolutional layer
and FC layer.
So this is the Alex net.
At first glance, it looks a little bit different,
but actually essentially, right?
The basic layers are very similar to the vanilla CNN
that you have studied, okay?
So it make use of convolutional layer and FC layer.
So it's actually the champion in 2012
in this image net large scale visual recognition
championship, right?
Or competition.
So this one, the objective is,
given the image you want to classify into 1000 category.
Okay, so this is also known as an image net challenge in 2012.
So this particular year 2012,
commonly is interpreted as a turning point, yeah?
Right, so this is the first time that people actually
more conveniently show that deep learning
or this kind of network can outperform many classical
approach.
So if you count today, yeah, I mean now it's 2014.
So pretty much we only have like 12 years of AI,
which really demonstrates just within 12 years
how things has changed from this year.
Right, okay, so the next network is called VGG network.
So some basic information about VGG is a runner up
to this particular image net challenge in 2014.
Right, so why VGG is very important
is because it has a very elegant network architecture.
The network architecture it uses is very elegant,
is very similar to the vanilla CNN that we have studied.
Okay, so it make use a deep network
with three by three kernel.
So the filter size is actually three by three kernel,
filter size, and at the time is, right,
usually the number of layers that you have,
there's a few different variants,
like you have 11 layers, 16 layer, 19 layers.
So at this, at our current time we consider 16 to 19 layer,
it's not a lot, but you have to remember during that time,
right, like 19 layer is considered as quite deep already.
So at that time it's considered as a deep network, right.
But one of the problem of VGG is that it requires
a large number of parameters, okay.
So shortly we'll see why that's the case, yeah.
Okay, so there are a few variants for this VGG among them
is the VGG 16 and 19,
which indicate the number of layers, yeah.
So, right, so this is actually the network structures
of a VGG network, right.
So it takes the input image of 224 by 224 by three RGB image,
right, so you can see this early channels here
are actually the convolutional plus value layer, okay.
For example, this two layer, the dimension is 224
by 224 by 64 channel, okay.
And afterwards it let go through the max pooling, okay.
And then two convolutional, max pooling,
convolutional, max pooling,
convolutional, max pooling, convolutional, max pooling.
And then finally you have this FC layer.
So the FC layer that we've seen in the previous example
is indicated as a vertical vector,
but in this again they redraw it,
no as if it's like a no lying down,
but it's actually the same as a vertical
kind of a vectors here.
So you have this FC layers here, right.
You can see it's 4096, 4096 dimension, right.
And then this one is 1000 and this one is 1000, okay.
So this is the structures of the VCC VGG networks here.
So early on we mentioned that, right,
one of the shortcomings of VGG is that it requires a large,
no, it requires a large number of parameters.
Where do you think this large number of parameters
is coming from?
VGG requires a large number of parameters.
And where does this large number of parameters comes from?
It comes from, from our earlier discussion,
we say that which part of the network,
which part of CNN requires the largest number of parameters?
FC layer, huh.
So actually the reason why this particular VGG network
requires such a number of parameters
is because you can see the dimensions of the FC layer
is very large.
For example, 4096, 4096, 1000, 1000.
That means there's lots of connection in between
and hence it's very, it requires lots of parameters.
So therefore one of the shortcomings of VGG is,
no, it requires a large number of parameters.
So it's not so commonly used in some network
that cannot afford so many parameters.
Right, so the next network that we have,
very well known one is called ResNet.
So ResNet is the winner of this ImageNet challenge in 2015.
It has a very deep structure.
So this deep structure at the time correspond to about,
like, 50 layers, 101 layers, 15 something layers.
So it's about 100 plus layer.
So at the time, even now, yeah,
it's considered reasonably deep already.
So it's a very deep structure.
And then it makes use of what is known as a residue block
and a highway or skip connection
for better gradient back propagation.
So what is the meaning of this residue block
and, no, skip and highway connection
and how does it facilitate gradient back propagation?
So let's look at this particular diagram here.
So this is the one of the smallest versions
of the ResNet here.
So you can see in this ResNet here,
some of the key building block is like these structures here.
So it consists of many of this kind of block
which is known as a residue block here.
So if you take out one of these residue blocks,
this is how it looks like.
Okay, so this residue block,
you can see you have the X input
and then you have these particular connections here.
So this connection here is known as a highway
or skip connection.
Okay, and then afterwards you have a small network here.
So this small network here,
we can interpret it as like a function FX.
You take this input X
and it's going to learn something FX.
Okay, and then the output at this particular junction here,
you can see it's nothing but FX.
Okay, what this network is learning FX plus
because this is just a cable or highway connection,
it's always X.
So the output at this particular junction
is actually FX plus X.
Okay, so output at this junction.
So now, okay, so in early years,
when people start to design CNN,
they find that, okay,
if I start to increase the number of layers of CNN,
the performance start to increase.
But now, if you continue to add in more and more layers
of CNN, do you think that the performance
will continue to increase all the time?
The answer is no.
So if you keep adding many different layers
to the vanilla CNN,
actually the performance after it will increase a while
and then it will start to come down.
So what is the problem with this?
What is the issue if you keep adding
many different layers of this to your CNN?
So this particular problem is a well-known problem
known as a vanishing gradient problem.
So vanishing gradient problem is that,
but suppose if you're a network with many different layers,
so when you want to compute,
when you want to perform, train your network,
first of all, you have an input image or input.
You'll go through many different layers,
to get your predicted output.
You compare your predicted output with your ground truth
to get the error.
And then this error will then start to back propagate.
And this error, back propagate,
we then be used to adjust the parameter for the network.
Some of them is FC layer, some of them is convolutional layer.
But one of the problems when you have many different layers
is that this gradient, right,
initially this gradient is large,
but after you propagate more and more,
the gradient becomes smaller and smaller and smaller.
Until you reach the earlier layers,
the gradient is almost zero.
So when the gradient is almost zero,
then you have no way of updating your parameter
in the earlier layer.
So therefore, this is a well-known problem
known as a vanishing gradient problem.
So if you stack your gradient, many, many different layers,
your earlier layers cannot be updated effectively.
So that's the problem.
So how does RESTED address this problem?
So RESTED address this problem
by having this particular connection known as the skip
or highway connection.
So the skip and highway connection is that
suppose you have the predicted output
and your ground truth, you get some error already.
So this error now can go through this highway connection.
Yeah, this gradient can then use this particular path
as a highway connection to back propagate
this gradient more effectively.
So that's the high level reasoning.
Why for RESTED, even when you have many different layer,
the gradient can still be back propagated effectively
and hence, even earlier layer,
you can still train it effectively.
So that's one of the important reasoning.
Okay, another kind of a high level hypothesis
that people think about it is like this.
Okay, why RESTED is performing better is that,
okay, so RESTED consists of many of this small network here.
Each of this network here is,
it can be interpreted as,
your input is X, your output is X plus FX here.
So this FX is actually only learning some small tasks,
a very simple task.
So the example is like, for example,
if you want to take this course here,
so you learn every week, you learn some basic concepts.
So week one, you learn a basic concept,
week two, you learn a basic concept.
So every week, you learn a basic concept
so that when you put all these weeks together,
you turn out that you can learn the final outcome
for this goal more effectively.
So each week can then be interpreted like this.
So each week, you are learning a simple task, FX.
So this is as compared to,
if I just give you a very complicated networks,
I say, this is the input,
this is the output you need to learn at the end.
So if you just simply say,
input, output, this is a big network you want,
you need to learn a lot of the time,
the network are not able to learn effectively.
So you need to learn a little bit followed by a little bit.
So this is another common analogy
to explain why RESTnet usually perform well.
So this slide shows some of the performance comparison.
So for this of different networks,
so the vertical axis is the arrow rate,
top five arrow rate, so for this ImageNet challenge.
So that means so long as your predictor output
is in any of the top five category,
you consider it to be correct.
So horizontal axis is actually the number of years
this network was produced.
So you can see all these are the winner.
So what you notice is that number one
is the arrow rate start to decrease.
Over here, the arrow start to decrease as you expect.
Number two is that you notice
that the number of layers start to increase.
So over the time, the number of networks start to increase
and the arrow start to decrease.
Okay, so this particular diagram shows the performance
comparison for different network for the ImageNet challenge.
So ImageNet challenge as you recall,
is given an image you want to classify into 1000 category.
So if we look at this diagram here,
vertical axis is the top one accuracy.
Okay, so horizontal axis is,
flop means this number of calculation,
floating point operation like addition,
subtraction and so on.
So for a good network, we want the accuracy to be high.
We want the number of calculation,
number of addition, subtraction required
to perform a full pass to be small.
So therefore a good network should be in this region here.
Large accuracy, low number of parameters.
So it's in this region here.
And then what's the size of this bubble here?
So the size of this particular bubble here
means the number of parameter that is required
for this network.
So therefore a good network, CNN network,
should be in this corner
and the size of bubble should be small.
So you can see these are some of the top choices.
Among them, right, you can see these are the VGG network here.
One thing you recognize right away is VGG,
the bubble is very big.
Why?
Why the VGG bubble is so big?
I think we just explained a few minutes ago
because, yeah, FC layer,
it's got a lot of parameters.
So therefore VGG is so big.
So therefore for applications such as edge computation,
no rest, no number of storage is limited,
and so on, you usually don't want to go for VGG.
Yeah, VGG is elegant,
but actually nowadays is a little bit obsolete already.
Right, so, okay, when we talk about network,
what are some key performance matrix here?
So when we measure how good a network is,
one of the important one is accuracy,
whether you can achieve high accuracy,
whether you can classify it correctly.
The second thing to consider is the memory footprint.
So how much parameter you need to store
to train the network?
What is the activation map
or the feature map that you need to store?
So this is also an important consideration,
how much memory you'll occupy.
The next one is a speed or computational complexity
or flock, right?
When you have a forward,
when you have doing the testing,
when you have an image,
how many operation do you need to compute
before you can get the output, right?
So this is a flock.
So generally speaking, the flock,
the smaller, the better,
or the speed, the higher, the better, right?
So often, why is the most important matrix
need not necessarily be accuracy or this?
It depends on application, right?
Some application, some factors is more important
than the others.
For other application,
other factors would be more important.
For example, if you have an edge computing devices,
so some device that you put somewhere else,
and then it doesn't have the cable to power,
it power using the battery.
So for those cases, then you know that,
it need to be very efficient.
So this flock computational complexity
then could be very important consideration
because otherwise your model will run out,
the battery will run flat very quickly.
So in those cases,
probably the computational complexity
is one of the key consideration.
The accuracy probably is not the most important one.
Often it's a compromise, yeah?
But it would depends on what application
you are referring to,
see which is a good choice.
Not necessarily that accuracy is the most important thing.
Right, so next, let's very quickly look at
some of the potential application.
So for CNN, there's many, many, many different applications.
So here I'm just going to share with you
some of the potential application.
So one of the potential applications
is person re-identification.
So the idea of person re-identification
is that suppose in, for example, in university,
where many different camera networks, yeah?
So even but the image that appear in one camera,
we want to find where this person appear
across other camera, okay?
So this is known as the person re-identification.
Given a query image,
you want to find, okay,
where this person appear in different cameras, yeah?
So I remember, I think last year or yeah,
in China there was this news that
an old lady actually went missing in China
and then they managed to find out
where this person has walked, right?
So they're using this kind of technology
because in, I think just like in Singapore, in China,
there's lots of surveillance camera.
So maybe much when you walk, then they will know.
They can find out where you have walked, yeah?
And then they can identify the missing person very quickly.
Right, okay, so for this particular method here,
the idea is using,
I'm not going to go into the detail by stat.
Given an image, you use a rest net, right?
To extract some feature.
So this feature then will be divided into three parts.
One is the global feature.
The other is the park feature.
And then finally is attribute feature.
So the global feature means that you look at a feature
for your whole image, a whole person.
Park feature means that you probably divide your body
into different parts.
And then the attribute feature is you look at things
like whether the person is wearing some backpack,
wearing some hats and so on.
And then you use some attention map
to highlight those attributes.
And afterwards you combine these three laws
to train your network, okay?
So this is an example so you can extend your basic CNN
to something which can fit into this kind of application.
So anyway, this is one of the work of my earlier student,
a couple of years back already.
Right, okay, so another potential application
is a visual food recognition.
So the idea is quite similar, simple.
So we want to develop a mobile app
such that you can take pictures of the food images
and recognize what it is.
So once you can recognize it, right,
for individual person, you can understand
his dietary habits, right?
But if you look at the community, then you will know, right?
What is the dietary habit of a community or a certain country?
So this particular project, actually,
we used to work with a beta, right?
So this is one of the projects that we worked
with beta before.
Okay, so the approach that we propose here is that, right,
we use a technique known as a knowledge distillation, yep?
So given an image, we train a large teacher network,
but because this large teacher network
requires a lot of the parameters and so on.
So because this network need to be later on deployed
on your mobile devices, so it need to be lightweight.
But at the same time, we want it to be able
to extract the information that is learned
by a large teacher network.
So therefore, the technique that was used
is actually knowledge distillation.
So this image here, right, we use it to train
a large teacher network, and this large teacher network
would then distill the knowledge
to a smaller student network.
Then later on, once this student network is fully trained,
we use this student network, we pluck it out,
and then we deploy it on some devices such as mobile phone
so that it require less storage and computation.
So there's a high level principle of this particular work.
Okay, so in short, in section one, right,
we cover the following.
So introduction, linear classifier.
So today we cover CNN training, right,
and then just now we just very briefly explain
some well-known CNN architecture,
and also we just take one or two applications
to very quickly highlight it.
Right, okay, so because for the Cree's on week 10,
it includes this part four, that's why I need to go,
just touch faster to make sure that we can finish
this part four of the lecture.
So the second section we're going to look at it
is the recurrent neural network and LSTM, right?
Right, so under this section,
we'll be looking at the following.
First we'll be looking at the introduction,
and afterwards we'll look at recurrent neural network,
RNN, what this, how do we train it, okay,
and afterwards we'll be looking at variants of RNN,
which we call LSTM, long shutter memory,
and then finally we'll be looking
at some selected application.
Okay, so first of all, before we look at,
why do we want to study RNN,
let's look at the AI model that we've studied before.
So far we've studied linear classifier, MLP, CNN, right?
So this type of network is actually a fit forward network,
a simple fit forward network,
whereas you have some input,
it goes through some network
and you generate some output here, right?
But those networks that we have studied before,
like CNN, linear classifier and so on,
one of the problem for this type of network is that
when it comes to sequential data,
a data that can be modeled by a sequence of values,
such as time sequence data, share price,
or state series data, such as languages,
they have different works.
So models that we have studied before,
like CNN, cannot handle this sequential model very well, okay?
So these are the limitations of earlier model
that we have studied when they tried
to handle sequential data.
So therefore for sequential data,
the model that we've studied before for CNN,
it cannot handle sequential data
because it only consider the current input,
for example, for CNN is good at certain tasks
like classification,
but it can only handle the current data, okay?
One of the reasons is because it does not have the memory,
it does not have the memory element to remember
what is the data that has encountered before.
So these are the shortcomings of the previous model
if you want to use it on sequential data.
So now, so that is the motivation,
why do we want to study this recurrent neural network here?
So a short form for this recurrent neural network,
the simple recurrent network can be shown here.
So the network actually has input,
X is actually your input,
H is known as a hidden state,
H, I, D, D, E, N, hidden.
So H is a hidden state.
Hidden state is also the memory, okay?
So you have this memory here, so H is the memory,
and Y is the output, right?
So if you look at this particular diagram here,
what it means is that your memory,
your current memory depends on your current input,
and also this loop here means
it depends on your past input.
So this current memory depends on your current input
as well as the past memory.
So therefore it has this hidden state of memory
that's able to handle sequential data.
We'll see a bit more about it later.
And then once you have updated this current memory,
you can use it to generate some output, okay?
So these types of neural network
is known as a recurrent neural network.
So its advantage is that you can handle sequential data
like time series data or state series data
such as sentences, languages, okay?
You can consider the current input
and also the previous received input.
You can see that this hidden state,
this current hidden state or memory
depends on your current input,
and it also depends on the previous hidden state.
And the previous hidden state in turn
depends on the previous input
and the previous memory.
So in other words, that means your current memory
depends on your current input
as well as all the past input.
Therefore your current memory actually is a function
of your current input as well as all the past input.
So theoretically that means it has certain memory capability
to remember all your current input
as well as the past input.
So therefore you can see it can memorize the previous input
due to this internal memory.
So what are some common applications for RNN?
So it can be used in time series prediction or forecasting.
For example, you want to predict the share price,
the sales of a certain product.
It can be used to perform speech recognition,
recognizing different works that has been spoken.
It can be used to perform some tasks
in natural language processing or NLP,
such as a language translation.
Given a French, you can translate into English.
It can perform sentiment, text sentiment analysis.
For example, given a sentence,
you tell them whether this is a positive sentiment
or negative sentiment.
It can also do things like image captioning.
Given an image, you want to generate a sentence
or a caption to describe this image.
So these are all some possible applications
that you can perform under RNN.
Right, okay, so before we go into that,
let's look at some sequence modeling
for this type of a sequential data.
So for the sequential data,
there are quite a number of different way we can model it.
So the first type is known as a one-to-many mapping.
So as the name suggests, one-to-many mapping
means that you have one input, but many output here.
So many output can also mean sequence or output.
Right, so this one-to-many mapping
you can see from this diagram here.
Your input, so this red color is your input.
So your input is a card, one single input.
Your green component here is your RNN or the memory,
or the hidden state.
Your blue box is actually your output.
So you have one input and you have multiple outputs.
So hence is one-to-many mapping.
So among this one-to-many mapping,
one of the application is image captioning.
So for image captioning, it can be achieved using this.
So this is the older model to perform image captioning.
So you have a given image, right?
You let it go through the CNN that we have studied early on.
And then, okay, you actually extract a feature vector,
one of the FC vector that you have.
That is actually our feature vectors here.
So that means we can get a feature vector
that represents this particular image here.
So we have this FC vector.
So this FC vector then go through LSTM.
So LSTM currently, you can just think about each of these
is like a memory, this is like memory here.
Okay, so at this stage, you do need to know the detail.
Just have some high-level understanding.
This LSTM here is just like this memory that you have here.
So you get your single input of your feature vector.
First, you will try to generate the first token,
which is like spot, indicate the spot of the caption.
So these spots here will then be used
to generate your next work.
For example, giraffe, this giraffe, you move it down,
use to generate the next work, and so on and so forth.
So the detail, you don't have to understand, right?
Maybe in the later part we'll explain a bit more.
But the high-level intuition I'm trying to tell you
in this case is you can see your input is a single image,
but your output is a sentence or a caption,
which consists of many different works.
So therefore it can be interpreted as a single
to many mapping.
So you can see input is a single image,
output is a sequence of works.
Right, so okay.
So the next type of mapping that we have
is a many to one mapping here.
So many to one mapping as name suggests,
input is many, right?
So many input, a sequence of input, output is one.
Okay, so from this visualization you can see,
you have many input, right?
So this is your memory or on end, okay?
And then this is your output, single output.
So what are some use cases that fall under this category?
For example, one of them is a video classification.
So for video classifications here,
this can be interpreted as different frame in the video,
right, and then your output is a single decision, right?
Whether it's actually a comedy, a horror movie, and so on.
Okay, so this is a many to one mapping.
Right, it can also be sentiment classification.
For example, your input can be a sentence,
a sequence of work or sentence, right, different works.
And your output is a single sentiment,
whether it's positive, negative, or neutral, for example.
So therefore it can be a many to one mapping.
Right, okay, so there are also others like many to many mapping.
So by now you should know many to many means
that you have many input, right,
and your output is also many output here.
Right, okay, so, right, there's two different variants here.
So one of them is this many to many mapping.
So your input here, okay, this is a memory and this is output.
What you notice is for this particular case here,
there's a delay, right?
When your input is generated here,
there's a delay before your output is being generated.
So this kind of use case is commonly used,
and for example, in machine translation, okay?
So your input is a sequence of, for example, a French work.
Your output is a sequence of English works, yeah?
So usually you have a delay.
So why is the reason why you usually have a head for a delay?
Why usually you have a delay
in the context of machine translation?
Now to answer this question,
you just have to think of your friend.
Some of your friend actually shit from the mouth
before thinking right away,
people say something, you just, right away,
you just say something, and then later you regret,
oh, I should not have said that.
Right, sometimes it happened to me as well.
So usually what it means is that for translation,
you need to understand, you need to, first of all,
take in some work first to have a good understanding
of the context before you start to do the translation.
So therefore you need to take in some works here
to digest and understand what's the context first
before you start to generate the translation.
So it makes sense, right?
You cannot just simply, the first work you handle is here,
then right away you say something.
That's what sometimes my wife say about me, right?
Whatever she say, I just reflect,
kind of fight back right away, so she should avoid that.
Okay, anyway, so this is what you have here.
For translation, you need to understand the context first
before you start to do the translation.
Okay, so that's why for translation,
it can be modeled into this.
So this one can be interpreted as a frame video classification.
So each of this input here is different frame in a video.
So this is actually your memory, okay?
And then this could be, for example,
you want to detect at each frame
whether, for example, a certain object appear or not.
So therefore actually you don't have to wait,
you can generate the output right away.
So therefore depends on cases,
your modeling can be a little bit different.
Right, okay, so this diagrams here shows a well-known
encoder and decoder modeling here.
So in this butter diagrams here,
is illustrating these ideas of the language translation.
Okay, so first of all, the goal is that you have,
for example, in this case, an English sentence,
you want to translate into, I think this is German,
the Germans here.
So what we do is that typically we take this particular work,
we'll convert it into some vectors,
because you cannot represent works,
you have to convert it into some vectors here.
This is known as the work embedding.
Right, and then afterwards we have this particular element
here, each of this is actually a memory,
such as an RNN or LSTM here.
Right, so what it does is that,
okay, at each of the time steps here,
it takes the previous memory from the previous time step,
it takes its current input,
and then you will try to extract some information.
Right, so this information would then be passed
to the next element.
So it would just kind of extract information
from the first work, okay, and afterwards go in,
combine with the second work,
combine with the third work, and so on and so forth.
So at the end of this particular,
so this module here is known as encoder,
this is known as encoder.
So the encoder, the objective of the encoder is input,
okay, it can use, for example, a network such as RNN,
at the end to extract a vector.
So this particular vector, S here,
is typically known as a context vector.
So this context vector will actually contain
some good information of all the works
that it has encountered, okay?
So this is a context vector.
So once you have, so this is the encoder,
you take a sentence, you encode the information
into a context vector.
So next, this part is known as a decoder.
So the goal of the decoder is given this context.
Now you want to translate into your target language
such as German, right?
So you start off with a start token, yeah?
Okay, with the context that you have extracted previously,
what you start to generate, what is the most likely works?
Okay, and then based on this translated work,
you bring it down, right?
You then try to generate what is the most likely next work
and so on and so forth, okay?
Right, so that is the high level structures
of encoder and decoder.
Again, details you will study a bit more later on
as we move on from RNN, LSTM to transformer.
But these ideas of transformer,
this encoder and decoder is that the objective
of the encoder is you take your input
and you try to extract some feature
that can extract some meaningful information
from your input.
And then the objective of this decoder
is that given this particular context information,
you try to generate your target output, okay?
Yeah, so one is encode, one is to decode, right?
Right, okay, yeah, so we still have a bit of time.
Let me just go through some of the basic
about this recurrent neural network or RNN, right?
So what are RNN?
So RNN are actually a class of network
which can handle sequential data, right?
So RNN are typical AI model
which is used to handle sequential data.
So sequential data are data which have kind of a sequence,
appear in sequence.
So some very common one are including time series data,
right, or state series data.
So it could be, for example, share price or languages.
So it's commonly used in analyzing sequential data
or temporal data, right?
So it can be used in applications such as NLP,
natural language processing,
because NLP usually is sentence
and sentence have different works.
So this is ideal, right?
You handle using RNN, right?
Other things like translation, image captioning.
So these are common application
that we can use RNN to solve the problem.
Right, let's look at the basic structures of an RNN.
So the basic structures of an RNN is like this, right?
It has two forms, so this is a folded form.
Okay, this is known as a folded or a roll form.
This is known as unfolded or unroll form.
You roll it up, okay?
So if we look at this particular form here,
what it means is that, okay?
You'll have this X is our input,
H is our hidden state of memory.
This, in this case here, O is the output.
So you can see your current memory
depends on your current input and your past memory.
And after once you've updated your memory,
you can then use to generate the output.
So how this particular hidden state output and memory
is affected is through the matrix, okay?
U, V, and W, right?
So that's high level.
Later on, we are going to make it more concrete
and give some example.
So this particular compact form,
you can unroll it to become this.
So if you unroll it, it's actually easier
for you to see.
For example, right?
So this is your input at different time step,
T minus one, T and T plus one.
This is your hidden state of memory
at time step T minus one, T and T plus one.
This is your output at time step T minus one,
T and T plus one.
So if you look at this current memory
at time step T plus one,
this current memory depends on your current input
and also depends on your past memory.
And your past memory depends on,
your past memory, HT depends on your input XT
and your previous memory, HT minus one.
And HT minus one depends on the input at XT minus one
and so forth and so forth.
So therefore you can see that this particular memory here,
HT minus one, is a function of X of all the input.
So in other words, if it's a function
of all the input, that means it has memory.
It has a memory capability of all the previous input
in theory.
So once you have this particular memory,
then you can use it to generate the output.
Right?
So at high level, that's pretty much that.
So we have the input, we have the output,
we have the hidden state of the memory
and this memory is called RNN.
So this RNN have what is known as an internal state.
So we can call it RNN, we can call it internal state,
we can call it memory, we can call it hidden state.
They're all more or less referred to the same thing.
So next we are going to make it more concrete, right?
And then see whether we're going to make it
more concrete mathematically.
So let's look at this particular modeling now.
So okay, X is the input.
RNN is your hidden state or internal memory
or hidden state, this is your output Y here.
So you can see that, right?
Your current hidden state, okay?
Right, your current hidden state or current memory
is actually a function of your previous hidden state
or previous memory and also the current input, okay?
So your current memory at time step T
is a function of previous memory at time step T minus one
and your current input at time step T, right?
It goes through some mathematical kind of mapping.
So this mathematical mapping is a function of the view, right?
Some weight parameter.
So this is some high level understanding.
Later on, as I mentioned, over time we're going to start
to make it more and more concrete.
So once you have updated your memory,
suppose just now we updated our memory,
if you want to generate the output,
it's actually very simple.
We take our current memory now,
we let it go through a mapping
to generate our current output
and this particular mapping is a function
of this matrix W, HY, yeah?
So later on we're going to see
what's this particular matrix W, HY.
So next, this slide, we are going to make it more concrete now.
So we can see that, okay?
So early on we say that, right?
Our current memory will depends on the past memory
and your current input.
Go through some mathematical operation
to obtain your current memory.
But how exactly is this?
Because you can see that the current memory
is a function of the current input.
But how exactly is this being done here?
So how is being done more concretely for the vanilla?
There are many different versions of INN, yeah?
So the first thing we are going to study
is the vanilla INN on the most basic INN,
which is also known as the Elmman INN here.
Right, so for vanilla INN or Elmman INN,
what we need to do is that HT, what is HT?
HT is your current memory, okay?
Current memory at time step T.
So your current memory is equal to your previous memory,
HT minus what is previous memory,
you multiply with this particular update matrix,
WHH.
So you can see it's hidden state to hidden state, all right?
So previous memory, you multiply with this WHH, right?
Okay, and then afterwards you add up with your current input,
which is your XT, input at time step T, right?
And you multiply with this update matrix, WHHX.
So from memory to hidden state, right?
So afterwards you add them up,
then you let it go through a nonlinear activation function,
which is 10H.
So once you let it go through a 10H,
you will map it to a function between minus one to one.
That is your new memory, okay?
So therefore you can see your new memory
can be obtained from your previous memory
and create current input through this formula.
And these are the matrix that need to be trained, okay?
These are the matrix that need to be trained.
When you say train and INN,
these are the matrix that need to be trained, okay?
And then once you obtain your memory,
if you want to generate your output,
you just take your updated current memory,
multiply with this matrix, it will generate your output.
So you can see this matrix notation
is hidden state to output, why is output?
So hidden state to output.
So therefore you can see pretty much for vanilla INN,
it can be simply reduced into this two simple equation, okay?
So we can see now right from this equation,
if you want to find the hidden state at time step one,
you simply take your previous memory H naught,
your current input X1.
So this mathematical operation is defined
by this equation here, you generate your next memory.
So your memory at time step two
is depending on previous time step H1
plus the current input X2 going through this mapping here.
This mapping is this equation here.
Then you generate your memory at time step two
and then the process just continue.
So one thing to take note of is that
for all this process here, you're using the,
for all the time step,
you're always using the same weight matrix, okay?
Right, okay, so with that basic understanding,
I think it's time that I can kind of share with you
this particular exercise.
So for this exercise here, it says that you have a vanilla
INN that has a flowing starting.
This is the initial hidden state, right?
So the initial hidden state.
So this is the hidden state weight matrix WHH, okay?
So this is the input weight matrix WXH
and this is the output weight matrix WHY, okay?
And then assume no bias is used in the calculation.
So you are told that you have a two-step input, right?
So for this input, it only consists of simple two time step,
right, X1 and X2.
X1 is this factor and X2 is this factor.
So number one, it asks you to find the hidden state H1
at time step, he is equal to one, right?
Okay, so I know this is the, today,
if you have not studied before,
this is only the first time you see
and right away you're asked to solve this problem already.
But this is also a good exercise for you to see
whether you fully understand this equation.
Because if you can solve this problem,
that means you understand it, yeah?
Okay, so I'll give you a few minutes to think about
how to solve this part one
and then we can go through the answers together.
Okay.
So actually it's just trying to apply this formula.
And actually I already make all these decisions
so straight forward,
he's hasn't let the map,
put it in and you will know.
Okay.
Okay, so yeah, in view of the time, right?
Because I know that many of you once is after nine,
your mind start to go somewhere else already.
So let's quickly just look at this particular
question seat.
So essentially for this particular problem,
it's nothing but applying the formula, right?
So if I can memorize this, sorry, enlarge this.
Right, so this is the first question.
And enlarge this, right?
So this is the equation.
So it says that your memory at time step T
is equal to your previous memory at time step T minus one,
multiply with WXX,
WHH matrix plus your current input at time step T.
Okay, multiply with the update matrix WXH.
And the whole thing you add it up,
you let it go through a 10H function
to obtain your current memory.
And once you obtain your current memory,
you can use it to generate your current output.
So it's pretty much that, it's just this formula.
So therefore the first thing you need to do
is that when you want to find out the memory at time step one,
that means we let T be equal to one.
So anyway, I think let's try to maximize this.
Yeah, so this formula is given
from just now the lecture notes.
Yeah, so at time step T is equal to one,
H1, memory at time step one,
is equal to memory at time step zero,
multiply with WHH matrix,
input at time steps one, multiply with this WHH matrix.
So actually these informations are all given.
So this X1 is the input at the first time step.
Just plug it in, you'll get this.
So this is the point you must remember, 10H function.
If you do not know how to use a calculator
to calculate this, please go back and thermize yourself.
Almost all the calculator can calculate,
but just some of you may not know.
Try to thermize yourself to how to calculate
this 10H function, because in the exam,
if I ask this question, I will not provide you
with the formula.
So, okay, please try to do that.
So suppose after you know how to calculate
this 10H function, you see this is the output.
We might as well just go through the next two parts.
Actually it's not tricky, it's just,
you just need to thermize yourself with the formula.
So the next part is that,
it asks you to find now the output at time step Y1.
So the output at time step Y1 is,
just now you already get X1.
So X1 multiplied with W,
HY will give you output already.
So therefore, to calculate output at time step one,
we simply use this formula.
Memory at time step one,
multiply with this output matrix,
which is given from the fault.
The question, you do some calculation,
you get your output at time step one.
Okay, so next part of the question,
it asks you to find what is the output at time step two.
So in order to find the output at time step two,
you need to know the memory at time step two.
In order to find the memory at time step two,
you need the input from time step two,
and the memory from time step one,
that you have already obtained.
So therefore, that means you can calculate
your memory at time step two,
and then afterwards, you can use to generate
output at time step two.
So it's just that.
Okay, so let's do it.
So therefore, same formula early on,
if you want to find the memory at time step two,
so memory at time step two is actually memory
at time step one, multiply with WHH,
plus input at time step two, multiply with WXH.
Holding, go through 10H function.
So these two are given from the question,
the second time step input is also given from the question.
H one is the memory that you obtain
from earlier times, earlier part.
Plug it in, go through 10H function, you get the result.
So this is your memory at time step two.
So if you want to find the output at time step two,
just apply this formula to some calculation,
you'll see this is the output.
All right, so.
Yeah, so anyway, as usual,
this, the solution I will share,
upload to the course slide shortly.
Okay, I think this is the last slide.
Okay, so for INN, what's the advantages and disadvantages?
So the advantages of INN is that theoretically,
you can handle sequence of any length.
It can be as long as you want.
But theoretically, the computation for time step T
can in theory make use of information
from earlier times that.
This thing I've already mentioned quite a number of times.
Your memory at time step T,
would depends on your current input and previous memory.
Previous memory depends on previous input.
Previous memory, okay, so I probably said too many times.
That means your current input,
current memory would actually theoretically
depends on many, all the inputs in the past.
Okay, another thing is this model size does not change.
So you can see from the formula, right?
For this INN model, the only parameter you need to compute
is WHH, WXH, and WHY, right?
No matter how long your model is, it's only this parameter.
So the model size does not change for longer sequence, right?
The same weight is applied at every time step.
So there's consistency and input how it's being processed.
Just now from the calculation, you can see,
we use the same matrix repeatedly, yeah?
So what is the disadvantage?
The disadvantage is recurrent computation is slow.
Suppose if your sequence is very long,
if you want to calculate the output
after a sequence of 1,000 time steps,
you need to start from the beginning,
do all the calculation to find the memory at time step 1,000
before you can generate output,
and this obviously is very slow.
So therefore it's slow.
And in practice, it's difficult to leverage information
from any time step back.
Even though we say that current memory,
it will depends on current input as well as the pass input.
But in practice, those input in the pass,
you can hardly leverage them, right?
So therefore it's very difficult to make use of information
from many times step back, right?
Okay, so probably just one last slide.
Don't worry, it's not a music or video,
some of you are...
Yeah, so some of you probably already heard about
this year's Nobel Prize, if you still do not know, right?
Probably I will just share this information with you.
So this year's Nobel Prize for Physics
is awarded to someone in AI.
I think Jeff Hinton, I'm not sure whether I mentioned to him,
mentioned his name.
When I was a student, we studied about this Hopfield.
Hopfield Network, we studied a lot when I was a student.
And we do not know Jeff Hinton.
Jeff Hinton is after when we studied in recent years, right?
After the, just now we talked about AlexNet.
So he's actually a pioneer now.
Actually, he has been working for this for a long time.
So anyway, both of them has been awarded
the Nobel Prize in Physics.
So what it means is that now the opportunity is open
to you all in AI area.
If you try hard, maybe you'll be the Nobel Prize winner.
Okay, all right, so we'll see you.
Okay, so last reminder, our next lecture is this Saturday,
right, Zoom lecture.
Next week, there's no lecture because I'll be away.
Okay, I'll see you.
Thank you.